<?xml-model href="../schemas/ddhi.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Transcript of an Interview with Paul Patton Winkel, Jr.</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>
          <orgName>Vietnam Center and Sam Johnson Vietnam Archive</orgName>
        </authority>
        <date>
          <!--  Date of publication, e.g. for citation purposes  -->
        </date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <recordingStmt>
          <recording xml:id="primary_recording" type="video" dur-iso="00:51:47">
            <!-- https://www.digi.com/resources/documentation/digidocs/90001437-13/reference/r_iso_8601_duration_format.htm -->
            <media url="https://vva.vietnam.ttu.edu/images.php?img=/OH/OH0451/OH0451.mp4" mimeType="video/mp4"/>
          </recording>
        </recordingStmt>
        <bibl xml:id="primary_transcription">
          <respStmt>
            <persName>Mark Varela</persName>
            <orgName>Vietnam Center and Sam Johnson Vietnam Archive</orgName>
            <resp ref="http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/trc.html">Transcriber</resp>
          </respStmt>
          <ref target="path_to_file">https://vva.vietnam.ttu.edu/images.php?img=/OH/OH0451/OH0451.pdf</ref>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The Oral History Project of the Vietnam Center and Sam Johnson Vietnam Archive</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application ident="DDHIEncoder" version="1.0">
          <desc>Conversion from Word docx to TEI xml.</desc>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en-us">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <particDesc>
        <person xml:id="VERRONE"/>
        <person xml:id="WINKEL"/>
      </particDesc>
      <settingDesc>
        <setting>
          <date when-iso="2005-11-10"/>
          <locale/>
        </setting>
      </settingDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <u who="VERRONE"><persName>Patton Winkel Jr</persName>, today is <date when="2005-11-10">November 10th, 2005</date>, and we are in <placeName>Washington DC</placeName>, in the <placeName>Crystal City Hilton</placeName> for the 40th anniversary reunion of the <name type="event">Ia Drang-Pleiku campaigns</name>. <persName>Colonel Winkel</persName>, thank you so much for doing this with us. We want to talk about <date when="1965">1965</date> and that, but I want—if you can give us a little background of yourself and what got you into aviation, and then into the unit that support everything going on at <placeName>X-Ray</placeName>. So how did that begin? You have some family experience in warfare.</u>
      <u who="WINKEL">Well, I’ve been army ever since I was three, I think. I just did some ancestral research, I found a great-great that was in the provisional army of the <placeName>colonies</placeName> in <date when="1725">1725</date>, and then I had a great-grandfather who was with <persName>Washington</persName> in the <name type="event">Revolution War</name>—great-great-grandfather. Then a great-grandfather who was a sergeant in the <orgName>Calvary</orgName> with <persName>Sherman</persName> for four years. Two uncles in <name type="event">World War I</name>, my dad and another uncle in <name type="event">World War II</name>. So I enlisted in being <orgName>army</orgName>, graduated from high school in <placeName>Vienna, Austria</placeName>, when my dad was assigned over there, and became interested in the military academy. Graduated in <date when="1956">’56</date> and having been a private prior to going to military academy for a year and a half, army prep school. Went into <orgName>Army Rangers</orgName>, parachute, airborne, army aviation. Then went to <placeName>Fort Bragg</placeName>, and <placeName>Fort Bragg</placeName> in the late 50s when <persName>General Howe</persName> came down and he and <persName>Gavin</persName> had been looking at air assault business, and he sort of used our <orgName>82nd aviation company</orgName> as a test vehicle. I would, after coming back from helicopter school, fix wing helicopters and instruments. Sort of toyed around with us, hopping over trees in our H13, shooting tanks by turning on our landing lights, and then moving troops from place to place, sort of investigating this sort of thing. Then I got another assignment, went to <placeName>Korea</placeName>, and then came back and went to advanced course.  Transferred to the <orgName>Transportation Corps</orgName> because that’s where aviation was. Ended up real quickly down at <persName>General Kinnard</persName>’s organization in <date when="1964">’64</date> and we got involved in the air assault business there. I was a helicopter Platoon Commander Operations Officer—Company Platoon Commander and then <orgName>Operations Officer</orgName>. Then, because I rode a lot, I got to be a PIO (Public Information Officer) for the battalion during the selling of the air assault stuff. Then within the same year, was a gunship Platoon Commander, went to the <placeName>Dominican Republic</placeName> and was the Assistant Operation Officer down with our aviation detention there and came back and got into—they put me into the gunship come in and when we got to <placeName>‘Nam</placeName>, they put me into the troop with a Bravo Company. So that’s sort of—just had no choice, all of the sudden there we were and <placeName>Benning</placeName>, at Benning <persName>General Kinnard</persName> had us—he was our initiative, that became probably because we using our initiative during the air assault test enabled us to do this sort of thing in the <placeName>Ia Drang</placeName>. One example of using an initiative we went to the Carolinas and had practicing the air assault test in the middle of a hurricane. One of our platoon leaders said, “We can’t fly anymore, were going to stop, were going to land our ships at the Howard Johnson’s.” They put them in the parking lot and they spent the night at the Howard Johnsons. So that was one example of initiative, in support of the whole thing.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Right. Tell me a little bit about getting over to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> and getting situated with <orgName>229th</orgName>.</u>
      <u who="WINKEL">Well, I was with the <orgName>229th</orgName> for two years, in the <orgName>11th Air Assault</orgName> through the <orgName>229th</orgName>. We did a lot of testing down in the air assault test and got—had to go to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. Got on board this ship, jeep carrier. Went to <placeName>Panama</placeName>, two other ships followed us, other ships went through the <placeName>Suez</placeName>. Our ship had to refit at <placeName>Long Beach</placeName>. Our aircraft carrier with all the helicopters landed first and the officers went to the officer’s club and the EM (Enlisted Men) went to EM club. We ate all the steaks, cleaned out the class six door. They brought the EM back in borrowed buses and the port commander says, “Anybody else from the cav, they’ll stay at the dock.” Then we went off with our carrier and went adrift in the Pacific about four times and went through a typhoon. Then we landed at (??) and they put the blades on our helicopters and we all test flew the helicopters off the ship two miles inland, and if they worked, they worked. If it didn’t work, well we—but that’s my boat ride.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Wow. That’s quite an adventure—</u>
      <u who="WINKEL"><placeName>Panama Canal</placeName> was pretty interesting.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">I can imagine, I can imagine. You were attached to <persName>Bruce Crandall</persName>’s task force once you were there—is that correct?</u>
      <u who="WINKEL">No, no. No, <persName>Bruce Crandall</persName> went over early and he became the company commander of <orgName>A Company</orgName>. At that time, we had different names because the companies weren’t A, B, and C. They were, I think, <persName>Bruce</persName> had <orgName>7th Special Forces—Aviation Company 7th Special Forces</orgName>. <orgName>B Company</orgName> under <persName>Dick Rodgers</persName> was <orgName>A Company the 5th Infantry</orgName>. <orgName>C Company</orgName> under <persName>Willard Bennet</persName> was <orgName>194th Aviation Company</orgName> and the <orgName>Delta Company</orgName> under <persName>Major Raydu Cornel</persName>, <persName>Raydu</persName> was the <orgName>110th Aviation Company</orgName>. We had to take names of units already on the rolls until this became finalized as A, B, C, D. So <persName>Bruce</persName> had <orgName>A company</orgName>, <persName>Rodgers</persName> had <orgName>B company</orgName>, <persName>Bennet</persName> had <orgName>C company</orgName>, and <persName>Raydu</persName> had <orgName>D company</orgName>, the gunship company. Each company had 2 platoons, I was in the second platoon of <orgName>B company</orgName> of captain Bob Stunet, <persName>Captain Bob Stunet</persName>. That was all-year around. We come up to the <placeName>Ia Drang</placeName>—we move up to the <placeName>Ia Drang</placeName>, <persName>Bruce</persName> sent his <orgName>A company</orgName> up there, <persName>Willard Bennet</persName> had his <orgName>C company</orgName> up there and second platoon of <orgName>B company</orgName> also went up to <placeName>Pleiku</placeName> under <persName>Stunet</persName>. These three organizations operated under the S3 forward. <persName>Dick Rodgers</persName> and the first platoon of <orgName>D company</orgName> stayed back in <placeName>An Khê</placeName> until they came up end of the month in <date when="1965-11">November</date> and we swap. He commanded <orgName>229th</orgName>, and that contention back there. The battalion commander, <persName>Colonel Bob Keller</persName>, had gone home on emergency leave and signed over the <orgName>battalion</orgName> to his second officer, <persName>Major David Carol</persName> who was brand new to the division, a fixed-wing aviator, and not too—had not experience he should’ve have as air assault yet. He was the de facto, he was de jour of company commander—battalion commander forward in <placeName>Pleiku</placeName> under him. Strange as it may seem, during the <name type="event">battle</name> <persName>Vince Panzita</persName>, <persName>Captain Panzita</persName>, was one of the most experienced assaulters that we had. He had been at <placeName>Bragg</placeName> when I was there under <persName>Howsburg</persName>. <persName>Major Carol</persName> because of his inexperience deferred to <persName>Captain Panzita</persName>, so throughout all of <name type="event">Ia Drang battle</name>, you see the actual battalion commander de facto was <persName>Captain Panzita</persName>.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Is that a good thing or bad thing?</u>
      <u who="WINKEL">This is—it really didn’t matter because we were all using our own initiative to do what we had to do and whoever gave us the orders to do something we did something, and <persName>Panzita</persName> was the goal between the forward S3 operations and <persName>Bruce</persName>’s <orgName>A company</orgName>, <persName>Stunet</persName>’s <orgName>B company</orgName>, and <persName>Willard Bennet</persName>’s <orgName>C company</orgName>. You asked about <persName>Bruce Crandall</persName>’s command. He had sixteen aircraft on the troop lift on the <date when="1965-11-14">fourteenth</date>. We joined—(Interviewer speaks to third party)</u>
      <u who="WINKEL">On the morning of the <date when="1965-11-14">fourteen</date>, <persName>Bruce</persName> was in charge of sixteen aircraft. His twelve aircraft and attachment from second <orgName>B Company</orgName> which is my flight. His yellow flight, he commanded a sixteen aircraft, a yellow flight of four. His right flight was commanded by <persName>Ed Freeman</persName>, his flight of four. The third flight, was green flight, commanded by Wall, <persName>Jim Wall</persName> also of <orgName>A Company</orgName>. The fourth flight was commanded by me, in the attached aircraft. That—the balloon went up and <persName>General Moore</persName> closed the LZ (Landing Zone). Many things happened; few people know about until we researched over the 90s to find out what exactly happened. When <persName>Bruce</persName> went off on his two ship volunteer flights, he did fourteen into <placeName>X-Ray</placeName> along with <persName>Ed Freeman</persName> as his wingman, he had turned over the command of the troop lift over to subordinate. <persName>Emroy Gilson</persName> also <orgName>B Company</orgName>. So <persName>Emroy Gilson</persName> was really the troop commander of the troop lift ships the rest of the day, with <persName>Bruce</persName> doing his volunteer flights. Of course, they were communicating. All under the auspices of <persName>Vince Panzita</persName>, the de jour Battalion Commander, who got it because the <persName>Major Carol</persName> had handed it over to him.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">This is a very—almost twisted command chain here.</u>
      <u who="WINKEL">Well, it’s fractioned because the way <persName>General Kinnard</persName> had taught us how to do this in the air assault concept. All for the best interest of the battle we were able to do this. It’s a shame that in April of ’64—excuse me, <date when="1966-04">April of ’66</date> when we started defusing, new people coming in and old people going out, that this air assault concept dissipated that we had trained on for a couple of years. <persName>Dick Rodgers</persName>, the <orgName>B Company</orgName> Commander,  was sent down to <placeName>Saigon</placeName> and when he told him the things we were doing, the formation, flying at night, tree tops, suppressive fire, landing forward at a time in the heat of the time, lifting troops up, and meeting them on the battlefield. The <placeName>Saigon</placeName> people said, “You are crazy, you don’t know what you’re talking about, you’re going to another organization.” And ignored him. </u>
      <u who="VERRONE">But did this work?</u>
      <u who="WINKEL">I have a letter. I have a couple of letters from <persName>Dick Rodgers</persName> telling me about how people just didn’t know what we were they doing.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Why didn’t they trust you at all? Why—</u>
      <u who="WINKEL">Well, that’s a good question! That’s a good question. I don’t know. But some of the research that’s come up, one Vietnamese has said that , “Had we been able to sit this down at the <placeName>Ho Chi Minh Trail</placeName> at that time, it’s a high probability that the war would’ve ended a lot sooner than it did.” But the politicians back then were afraid of—I assume, were afraid Chinese coming across the border. The <placeName>Thailand</placeName> folks didn’t want any more airplanes over there because he was afraid of what might’ve happened, it was just a bad situation and people didn’t want to experiment.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Tell me about the <date when="1965-11-14">fourteen</date>, and how that went down?</u>
      <u who="WINKEL">Okay. Got up at six o’clock in the morning—I’ll tell you about my aspect of it. </u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Yes, please. </u>
      <u who="WINKEL">Got up at six o’clock in the morning. I had been briefed the night before, that I would have a flag of four and I was to meet and join up with <persName>Bruce Crandall</persName>’s <orgName>A company</orgName> at <placeName>Plei Me</placeName> at ten o’clock. We spent most of the morning—I flew 9.8 hours that day and my flight record says I landed fifty-five times. I do know nine of them were at <placeName>X-Ray</placeName> and I do know that four were during the time <persName>General Moore</persName> said, “This is the most dangerous period.” From 1430 to approximately 1630.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">He just repeated that in here actually. </u>
      <u who="WINKEL">Yeah, I do know that. But anyway, from six o’clock to ten o’clock, we were shuttling troops between plantation or in the field, and moving the troops and marshalling the assault troops which was <orgName>Bravo Company</orgName>, <persName>Herren</persName>’s Company of <orgName>first and the seventh</orgName>, at <placeName>Plei Me</placeName>. So at ten o’clock, threw my four aircraft down and joined <persName>Crandall</persName>’s fourth lift ship. We proceeded to make our assault, we went off eight at a time and then it was four at a time. Then we got separated by minutes, we had to refuel. <orgName>A Company</orgName> told me that <orgName>A Company 1st through the 7th</orgName> we were in different locations and we had to go pick them up on one or two ship pickups, and bring them back to <placeName>Plei Me</placeName> for his launch and took a lot of time and we got—about 12:30 <persName>General Moore</persName> was in with <persName>Herren</persName>’s <orgName>B Company</orgName> and Summit of the <orgName>Dulles company</orgName>, the book will tell you what the time before the first rounds went off. Then some more rounds went off. I remember on my fourth lift, <persName>Bruce</persName> was in his yellow, <persName>Freeman</persName> in his white. They had gone in and I was coming up green and I don’t know what happened to green, I think he was behind me, we were told by <persName>General Moore</persName>, “Don’t come in, we’re on short approach. Don’t come in, we have a little problem here.” Later on, I found out the little problem was they were being mortared in-field. So I orbited, and with his green we orbited and then <persName>Moore</persName> said, “Come on in, but when you come on in—."</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Is this your first time in?</u>
      <u who="WINKEL">This is the fourth time.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">This is your fourth lift in.</u>
      <u who="WINKEL">The first one, two and three were no problem. So <persName>Moore</persName> said, “When you come in on your fourth lift, I want you to go back out the same way you came in. Because we’re firing direct fire with artillery. This is with 105s. I read later in the Camp After Action report, that the 105s were kind of erratic in the jungle. Lord knows whether—but they were going up on the hill and around the perimeter. So we came in and we landed the four and so I had my ships rotate, and I said, “Orange four, lead us out.” When we came in, I noticed that the lift before had drop pods of troops as if they were in the same four helicopters, they hadn’t moved! They were all pinned down to the ground. I said, “This is strange, why are they pinned down to the ground?” But I heard this popcorn sound, it sounded like we were in the middle of a popcorn popper and that was bullets. So we turned around and <persName>Dallas Harper</persName> was in orange four, he let us out. We went out in formation, that was the four ship, and then I came around and took the lead and on the way back, <persName>Bruce</persName> said, “Orange, I want you to send two ships for ammunition.”  So I send <persName>Lee Commege</persName> in orange three and <persName>Dallas Harper</persName> in orange four, as soon as they drop the troops off, you go back and get ammo and then come on back. So we sat down, we refueled and I took my other two ships which kind of diked us, it was <persName>Neil Parker</persName>, they were here before. They landed at the far eastern end because the fuel bags were in the western end and the other ships had to refuel. So I shut down and the mechanic came over to me and said, “You know, my engine is been all shot up, I got to get maintenance and we can’t go anywhere because its been shot, lost a breather tube or something.” So I called back from maintenance and probably called <persName>Panzita</persName> and we had a <orgName>B Company</orgName> maintenance ship come out later and repair it. So we’re sitting there and I go over across the strip to where I think it was <orgName>D company 1st or 7th</orgName> was still waiting to go out. We had a PRC (Portable Radio Communication) twenty-five and a two-niner-six antenna hooked together so we hear the battle. So we were listening to the battle in the battlefield.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">What was that like?</u>
      <u who="WINKEL">Well, it was like you listening to <persName>John Wayne</persName>. You know, I remember <persName>Moore</persName> saying, “Okay, we’re going to fire artillery! I want you to come back as we’re going to ease up on artillery. March back with the artillery and we’ll get you back that way!” So the artillery explodes, and explodes here, and explodes here, and the troops would come this way. I said, “Boy, this is just like combat!” Then I got a call, “We’re coming back with the ammo. What do you want us to do with it?” I said—I picked up, change frequencies, I had my own radio and I called the flight <persName>Crandell</persName> was in and said, “<persName>Ammos</persName>, what do you want to do with it?” He said, “<placeName>X-Ray</placeName>.” He didn’t say who was going to take it, he didn’t say where it was going to go. So I call <persName>Commege</persName> back, “Come back in and land.” We sat down, I went over and unloaded one of the guys who got in and said, “Okay, we’re going to <placeName>X-Ray</placeName>, take off.” So two ships went off to <placeName>X-Ray</placeName>. This is a little bit before three o’clock. We got—at that time <persName>Vince Panzita</persName> was in the airborne Charlie-Charlie and said— whatever the book says, “I want you to proceed towards the down A1E.” An aircraft A1E had exploded and the big pillars like an A-bomb had gone. They said, “When you get there, turn left and about ten seconds later turn right and you’ll be right on the final for <placeName>X-Ray</placeName>.” Of course, we’re doing this at treetop level.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Right.</u>
      <u who="WINKEL">With the bushes. I really didn’t need him because I had been in and out of there all day, I had my finger on the map, I was a watching the contours I said, “Okay, there’s this hill, there’s that thing, there’s that mountain, there’s that thing and <persName>Lee</persName> is on the controls.” Had I sneezed and taken my finger off where we were, we’d been up a crate. So we did end up—and <persName>Panzita</persName> says, “After you turn on the shorter approach, you’ll probably pick up fire.” I said “Hmm!” (Laughs). So we did that and we were coming. I just saw trees, as we turned, I just saw trees. I said, “God, I hope the thing is there, I don’t see the mountain.” We were so low, that the trees were going by just like this. (Editor’s Note: The interviewee is most likely expressing how fast they were going with his hands) I think we were about three feet into the trees. The skids weren’t catching on anything. I said—I told Trojan, I said “We’re about three out.”</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Trojan for?</u>
      <u who="WINKEL">Trojan six. It’s <persName>Moore</persName>. Then I heard him say, “Get that panel out there, wave it around, you won’t get shot!” So we came up, and there that thing was, there was this guy waving this panel and we’re doing about 80 knots, and <persName>Commege</persName> takes the chopper, and puts it up like this, like a big fan, and slices down a line. He’s an expert instructor pilot. They chose the right guy to fly with. But we were doing this (Editor’s Note: Interviewee most likely showing gestures to interviewer) and the other ship came along. Harper went up into the <placeName>X-Ray</placeName> a little bit further and <persName>Moore</persName> said to him, “Come back! Come back! You’re going get hit, you’re going get hit!” Well he got hit and came back. During research, I never found out who was first in until maybe about two or three years ago. <persName>Candyke</persName> was in here, he had the ship that he was fixing us in. He said he was watching us go at the same time the rest of the aviators were in a meeting. When—had we landed in X-Ray and somebody else had been there before, we would’ve heard it on the radio. I heard no aircraft traffic. That panel would probably have been stuck to the ground instead of being waved around. I kept asking people, asking people, asking people, and then there’s the story about when <persName>Bruce</persName> came in with <persName>Freeman</persName> and pulled <persName>Metzger</persName> out and <persName>Metzger</persName> got shot getting on the airplane. <persName>Taboada, Raul Taboada</persName>, got onboard that aircraft, he was wounded, had been setting up a CP (Command Post). I saw that in the book and I finally got in touch with <persName>Taboada</persName>, I said, “Do you remember seeing anything happening before you left?” He said, “Yes, I saw a helicopter come in, take off, and go down immediately smoking heavily and then another aircraft coming back in to make the rescue.” That was my two ships. We were the first in, whether that means anything at all is in the term because as <persName>General Kinnard</persName> says, “A hot LZ (Landing Zone), is a hot LZ, is a hot LZ.”</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Let me ask you this, what did <placeName>X-Ray</placeName> looked like? At this point when you come in onto the new LZ?</u>
      <u who="WINKEL">Ashtray. It looked like an ashtray. It was an area with few little scrub trees and trees all the way around it, and a big hill of which the enemy was coming, pouring down of it. Smoke was everywhere, but it was a clearing.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Did you see the troopers on the ground quite easily?</u>
      <u who="WINKEL">Yeah, we saw them on the ground, they were on the ground. We had landed at—<persName>Commege</persName> had landed us just off to the west of the CP (Command Post) area and the other ship had gone along. When we took off, my crew chief says, “After you unloaded the ammo, let’s get the hell out of here!” I said, “Fine.” I remember sitting there waiting for this ammo to come off, it seemed to me to be about twelve years. It had sort of tunnel vision. An absurd gray, a green gray. I was thinking, I looked at Commege and Commege was sitting there like that too and I said, “I wonder how long, how soon the bullets will come in and I wonder how long it will hurt before I die.” I will never forget that. Then the crew chief brought me back by saying, “Let’s get the hell out of here.”</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">What did Commege say?</u>
      <u who="WINKEL">Nothing. I didn’t say that, I was thinking that. So we picked up in tandem, that time <persName>Smithy</persName> immediately said, “<persName>Mr. Harper</persName> is on fire!” I turn around, looked over here and there was spurts of jet, stuff coming out of his engine. Supposed to come out backwards, not supposed to come out of the side. So whether he was on fire or not, I don’t know, I said “<persName>Harper</persName>, set her down, you’re on fire.” At that time, <persName>Commege</persName> starts bending us around and <persName>Moore</persName> comes up on the horn and says, “Orange one, what are your intentions?” I said, “We’re coming back in, we’re going to pick up my crew and pick up your wounded.” Prior to the party, <persName>Harper</persName> had picked up some wounded and we had two POWs (Prisoner of War). <persName>Moore</persName> asked me “Can you take out two POWs?” And I said, “Sure.” We had two POWs; we were told we couldn’t put wounded onboard the same ship with POWs flying infantrymen. So we came back in and circled around and sadistically, I guess, I saw I had not made a bad decision, because <persName>Harper</persName>’s ship looked like a boiling black smoke coming up like that. I said, “God he must be on fire.” But <persName>Commege</persName> kept on moving us. Right next to the airplane, I was thinking to myself, “Any closer and if that thing blows up, we’ve had it.” But it was oil. It received eleven shots! Maintenance officer told me it received eleven shots in its engine and had it flown another five minutes, all the oil would’ve gone out and of course they would have had to land somewhere in the jungle and the wounded, and the airship might not have made it. We pulled him on, popcorn sounding like all get out. One of the wounded started running off to the woods, he had red blood all over his back. I told him, “Go get that guy, we’re not leaving until we get him.” Smithy and Newlander ran out about seventy-five yards and dragged him back, got on board our aircraft. Harper got on board our aircraft; another guy got on board our aircraft. It was an infantryman, I called him the “strap hanger” and I’ll tell you why in a minute. I guess he chickened out and wanted to get out of the battle.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">He was not wounded?</u>
      <u who="WINKEL">No, no! No, he wasn’t. I’ll tell you who he is in a minute. We had those four on his ship, we had our four and the strap hanger, and we had two, three, or four other wounded people, the POWs had been taken off. We had anywhere thirteen, fourteen, fifteen people onboard on that aircraft. Fortunately, <persName>Commege</persName> had not refueled. We had about twenty more minutes, thirty more minutes of fuel left. He picks it up, flutters around and off we go over the treetops and fortunately we were able to carry out thirteen, fourteen, fifteen total—fifteen sounds awful large, but that’s souls onboard. On the way back, I heard over the radio an aviation signal coming in and that was the <persName>Gilson</persName> lift of the rest of the <orgName>1st and the 7th</orgName>. I heard no more all day long from <persName>Bruce</persName>. I did not know to take wounded to <placeName>Falcon</placeName>. I took my wounded back to <placeName>Holloway</placeName>. But I heard nothing from yellow line all day. So there I was sort of reusing my own initiative to support the battle. I heard <persName>Moore</persName> say, “Don’t come in four at a time, I told you that would happen!” Later I learned that four ships had come in and one had a tree strike and had to sit down in the battlefield. We got back to <placeName>Holloway</placeName>, dropped off our wounded and <persName>Commege</persName> says, “Well, let’s get some more ammo” I said, “Sure! <placeName>X-Ray</placeName> here we go!” So we loaded up on some—we got refueled on some fuel homestead, pumped a lot faster than the pumps they had in <placeName>Pleiku</placeName>, so we got fuel real quickly. We went over to this ammo dump and the strap hanger was still with us, and we started piling ammo on both of our ships and some major comes from a tent, “You can’t do that! You can’t do that! We got to keep that! Take that off!” I said, “Full pitch!” and we left him in a cloud of dust. We were loaded all the way up to the ceiling, both ships with ammo and the strap hanger was still with us. I said, “What’s wrong with this guy? Does he want to get killed or what?” We’re flying back with this one ship and I reported over our S3 to let them know I didn’t hear from my flight leader, I didn’t hear from <persName>Moore</persName>. At least I wanted to tell somebody where we were, we were going back with more ammo. I said, “We need another ship.” About five minutes out, I call on the aviation channel and said, “We need a chase ship to come with us.” I thought we heard white one will go with us, which is an error. For years I thought white one was Freeman. I thought it was <persName>Ed Freeman</persName>, but it was not. Later on, and I’ll come back to this, after the battle was over and gone to the officer’s club to get my warm beer and <persName>Bruce</persName> was there and he walks up with a big glass of booze and says, “That took balls.” I figured he knew what I did, I don’t know if he did or not.  But <persName>Ed</persName> comes in and I said, “<persName>Ed</persName>, thanks for being my chase ship” He says, “I’ve been with you.” What I thought he said was, “I was with you all day.” But he never said that. I learned he had a southern accent and what he had really said was, “I was with <persName>Bruce</persName> all day.” But later on, during research, I found that the chase ship was not white one, it was red one. The guy who said red one also had a southern accent, so white and red sounded like the same thing. Red one was <persName>Dwyane Denton</persName> from <orgName>B Company</orgName>. I further checked that out and I found out the two ships he had, <persName>Dwyane Denton</persName>, red one and red two, were assigned to the <orgName>1st and 7th</orgName> S4, for bringing in C-rations and this sort, and had been attached to <orgName>1st and 7th</orgName>, those two ships. The second ship which was <persName>Bob Kies</persName>, he said, “I don’t know where <persName>Bruce</persName> went, but for about an hour and a half he was gone.” <persName>Ergo</persName>, the guy who was my chase was not <persName>Freeman</persName>, it was <persName>Denton</persName>. The two ships under the S4 were going back and forth getting ammo and C-rations, and the supply officer was going with them. When my two ships went back to get ammo, the Supply Officer got on board. The strap hanger! That was <persName>Rozanski</persName>! I learned about that when I they talked to <persName>Rozanski</persName> in <date when="1990">’90</date>, <date when="1992">’92</date> we had a reunion in <placeName>Montana</placeName>, <persName>General Moore</persName> and <persName>Joe Galloway</persName> brought this fellow over, <persName>Rozanski</persName>, and he said, “Here’s your strap hanger!” I’ll be damned! I didn’t know until <date>’92</date> that that guy was not a strap hanger, it was S4 and he had thought he had gotten on his own two long ships, and he didn’t, he had gotten on my two combat ships. He stayed with me until we dropped him off at 1700 back in X-Ray, but anyway, as we’re coming in with the chase ship, our chase ship joined us, which is <persName>Denton</persName>, there’s this big cloud of dust and dirt and stuff, he says, “Where’s the battlefield? Where’s the battlefield?” I said, “I can’t find any place to land!” I came along and I told <persName>Moore</persName>, “We’re going around, we can’t find you” <persName>Moore</persName> says, “Stay away from the mountain!” So we make a right turn, and we go in between the battlefield and the mountain, which is not smart. But we’re down to treetop and my indicator says we’re doing a hundred and twenty. Whether we’re doing a hundred and twenty or not, I don’t know. We were doing up until the red line. Both of us we’re going around to the right. The wind had blown the smoke from the northeast towards the southeast a little bit and I saw the battlefield then I saw the northeast corner, where <persName>Moore</persName> had set up the small little area we can land. Inside we’re going to land. So they gave it to <persName>Commege</persName> and said, “You land this thing.” So we landed, dropped off more ammo from our ships. Both our ships then picked up wounded. We took off and went back to <placeName>Holloway</placeName>. I still had not heard that I was supposed to take them to <placeName>Falcon</placeName>. I heard nothing from my flight leader, <persName>Crandall</persName>. I figured we were doing our initiative thing and we went back and dropped off wounded. We loaded up with more ammo, strap hanger is with us and then we’re on our way back again. It’s about twenty after four. We tell <persName>Moore</persName> that we’re coming back in, and he said, “No, no, don’t bring anymore in, we got too much now, it’ll be a burden to us taking it back when we end this thing, taking it over the <placeName>Falcon</placeName>.” <persName>Commege</persName> and I we’re sort of teed off because we’re willing to come back and get killed and you’re telling us to save your life and you’re telling us to don’t come in we have too much, so we got a little peeved. So we dropped it off at <placeName>Falcon</placeName>, which is about four miles from our artillery base. We sat down and I saw guns going, that’s where the artillery were firing. I saw a big pile of cannisters, it must’ve been ten feet tall, I’ve never seen that many in my life. I got out of my ship, as we were unloading my ammo, I walked over to the artilleryman, I said, “Wow, some shooting!” He said, “Yeah it is, we’ve broken one gun and hydraulics on two other guns or vice versa. We’ve been firing fire for effect for three hours without leveling the bubbles. You need to level the bubbles in an artillery piece to keep it accurate.” But having read in the cav after action report, those 105s in the jungle are not as accurate as they ought to be. So they didn’t level the bubbles, they’re not as accurate, and we’re flying under all the artillery stuff going off. It’s amazing we’re here. About that time, out from the tent two of the fifth, <persName>Bob Tully</persName>’s <orgName>two of fifth</orgName> was CP (Command Post) was in <placeName>Falcon</placeName>. <persName>Bob Stunet</persName>, my platoon leader, was supporting him with two ships. He’d been shuttling troops back and forth out of the jungle area over to a place called <placeName>Victor</placeName>, which was three clicks from <placeName>X-Ray</placeName> as a blocking position. But he got with those two ships he got a hundred—I don’t know how many troops he got in from the battalion. A hundred and seventy-one troops I think research says by those two ships alone. He had to wait because <persName>Tully</persName>’s <orgName>C Company</orgName> was buried deeply in many places in the jungle, and they had to blow out trees so they can make some space for the chopper to come in and land. He had nothing to do. He says, “I’m going in with water to <placeName>X-Ray</placeName>, you coming?” I said, “Shit.” (Laughs) I could go back to colors. I said, "Crank her up.” So they loaded her up with water. Now, <persName>Stunet</persName> is leading me, I’m his second ship and I’m thinking to myself,  “I’ve been in and out of X-<placeName>Ray</placeName> all day, it’s a hectic place, and I’m going in with some—even my leader hadn’t been in there, I don’t feel very comfortable about that.” But we went in and we dropped off the—even though <persName>Stunet</persName> wasn’t supposed to be with the <orgName>1st and 7th</orgName>, he was the <orgName>2nd and the 5th</orgName>, but he had nothing to do. There you go again, with <persName>Kinnard</persName>’s initiative, we’re going to do it, the battle needs it. We took in water and we brought wounded and then they called for all the ships to go take in <orgName>Bravo company 2nd and the 7th</orgName>, with the movie people, and we helped on one lift on that and the movie people got out. I’d forgotten, when <persName>Stunet</persName> let us in, the pathfinders—<persName>Bruce</persName> had brought the pathfinders at about 1630 and this is about 1640 or something like that, pathfinders had just gotten setup. <persName>Stunet</persName> is coming in, and <persName>Stunet</persName> says, “They went off the air.” I learned from the pathfinders later what had happened. <persName>Tift</persName>, who is deceased today, <persName>Bear Tift</persName> who, was the lead pathfinders, had said in a meeting <placeName>Fort Hood</placeName> base later, that he was bringing two ships, just after he got there. He got his radio that was on his back, shot. So we had to find another radio to bring in the other two ships which was <persName>Stunet</persName> and myself. He came back on the air and he says, “Sorry about that!” <persName>Bob</persName> said, “Glad you’re there!” and landed us. But that proves that <persName>Stunet</persName> did go in at that time and we’re still within the end of <persName>Moore</persName>’s two-hour period of heroic action.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Let me ask you, was there some doubt that <persName>Stunet</persName> did not go in that time?</u>
      <u who="WINKEL">Well, you can listen to people and have them tell you something, then you got to find some other research to validate that. Otherwise you’ll just hearsay. So you find other research to validate this, and once you get it validated then it’s more likely to be true. This is in the research. I’ve done that with all the research. Having of course research methods along the way.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Let me ask you this <persName>Colonel</persName> before you continue, how tired are you now? What are you feeling? I mean, you’re doing multiple lifts, are you thinking about that? Or are you just going?</u>
      <u who="WINKEL">You’re just going. You’re just going. You go. You sometimes—in a book I read about <persName>Geronimo</persName>, you put on a shirt. If you get through a battle, then you’re not going to get shot again because your wearing your shirt. I felt invincible. I said, “No problem at all.”</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">You’ve done it this many times, let’s go.</u>
      <u who="WINKEL">Yeah, it’s a strange adrenaline, the feeling of adrenaline. There’s no fear anymore. I got rid of that fear that first time staring down that tube, wondering how long—from then on, it was just business as usual and get the hell out of my way. We’re going to get those guys; we’re going to keep those guys alive. But that’s the feeling.</u>
        <u who="VERRONE">Where was <persName>Crandall</persName>? I mean, why the silence?</u>
        <u who="WINKEL">I have no idea. I have no idea. I don’t know.</u>
        <u who="VERRONE">Was he—</u>
        <u who="WINKEL">I do know from research where he was, what he was doing. But at the time I only knew this other ship, who I didn’t know was Red one. I only knew <persName>Stunet</persName>’s ship and I knew my ship. I knew <persName>Harper</persName>, we dropped him off back there because his ship got destroyed and my other two orange people had joined and stayed with the <orgName>Gilson A Company</orgName> Troop lift. But we’re there sort of like we were doing our thing and a lot of people saw a lot of airplanes doing a lot things. Airplanes crews saw a lot of airplanes doing a lot of things, but to put names on those airplanes, it couldn’t be done until we found out who was in the battle thirty years later! Then based on that, a lot of recommendations have been made, <orgName>Congress</orgName> has allowed the department of the army to do this sort of thing.</u>
        <u who="VERRONE">Where was <persName>Crandall</persName>? Now that you know.</u>
        <u who="WINKEL">He was flying his own missions from <placeName>Falcon</placeName> to <placeName>X-Ray</placeName>, to <placeName>Falcon</placeName> to <placeName>X-Ray</placeName>. Taking ammo, bringing wounded back, taking ammo, bringing wounded back, he continued, continued, and continued. We had one more lift to make after—no we did not. The <orgName>2nd of the 7th</orgName>, <persName>Stunet</persName> and I and the chase ship helped with that. But then we went off back to the <orgName>2nd of the 5th</orgName> because my platoon leader told me, “You’re now with me.” I said, “Yes sir.” So I stayed with him and we delivered the rest of the <orgName>2nd and 5th</orgName> out of those jungle positions, <orgName>C Company two of the 5th</orgName> has made space for us over to <placeName>Victor</placeName>. Which was unprotected place, but it was three clicks away from <placeName>X-Ray</placeName> from where <persName>Tully</persName> would walk the next day and reinforce <persName>General Moore</persName>. From my research, <persName>Bruce</persName> and the rest of his task force had been released at 1800 and that’s when <persName>Rozanski</persName> went back, we dropped <persName>Rozanski</persName> off in that water run. He was still with me, the strap hanger was still with me and got off and then he stayed—he was the S4 of the <orgName>1st and 7th</orgName>. Then he went back with the 1800 release. But <persName>Bruce</persName> and <persName>Ed</persName> had stayed on. They made two—or three more—night flights and the last flight was when they brought <persName>Dillon</persName>, the S3N and <persName>Galloway</persName> on the C-rations. They could see lights all over them. Then <persName>Bruce</persName> after that, it was about 9:30, he broke off and he came home. I got home after the <placeName>Victor</placeName> sortie with my platoon leader. Closed out my flight and stopped off. I was going over to get my warm beer and I stopped off at the chaplain tent for about fifteen minutes to talk to a big guy about what was going on today and kind of how wild it is.</u>
        <u who="VERRONE">That’s important for you to do?</u>
      <u who="WINKEL">I felt like it was. I mean there was a tent with this little table, had a cross on it and I went to talk to the old man. Then I went to the office to get my warm beer. I walked in, and there was <persName>Bruce</persName> with a drink in his hand he came over and said, “That took balls.” And as I said before, <persName>Ed</persName> came in and said, “Thanks for being with me all day!” He came back with what I thought he had said, I’m repeating myself here, “I was with you all day!” I said, “You weren’t with me all day, you were just there for about an hour.” But he had actually said, “I was with <persName>Bruce</persName> all day!” So later on in research—well if it wasn’t him, who the hell was it? Then I found out later that it was red flight. Why did—red two was <persName>Bob Kies</persName>, his radios went defuncted during the day, so he had no communication with red one. So <persName>Bob Kies</persName> stayed with the <persName>Gilson</persName> contention to let the troops in. Then went home at 1800.</u>
        <u who="VERRONE">Why did <persName>Crandall</persName>, even in the movie it’s depicted, he gets some hot water there with his I guess his CO (Commanding Officer)—</u>
        <u who="WINKEL"><persName>Bruce Crandall</persName>’s CO?</u>
        <u who="VERRONE">Do you remember this in the movie? When he comes back the first night, he has made numerous night flights and he’s getting grief about doing this—</u>
        <u who="WINKEL">Doing what?</u>
        <u who="VERRONE">Making the night flights.</u>
        <u who="WINKEL">You mean the medevac people?</u>
        <u who="VERRONE">Yes.</u>
        <u who="WINKEL">The medevacs, <persName>General Kinnard</persName> says the medivacs weren’t trained yet to do what they were—they were new people on board. They had—we had no guns. We had no guns. The guns we had were M16s for suppressive fire. We did not have machine guns yet. We did have some machine guns hanging on bungee cords. But I mean it had no chest protectors yet and the medivacs were unused to air assaulting. When they came in, they really got close to another aircraft. <persName>Bruce</persName> brought the medevacs in one time and they aborted, and they never came back in again. We weren’t really too pleased with the medevacs. But the medevacs later on became marvelous, wonderful people to have around.</u>
        <u who="VERRONE">Can you describe <persName>General Moore</persName> briefly for me?</u>
        <u who="WINKEL">Yeah, yeah. Man is ten foot tall. Big boots and follow him anywhere. When he came on and talked on the radio, he doesn’t come like—he came on like John Wayne. He didn’t come on like (Makes mumbled-yelling noises) he says, “Okay guys, just hang in there.” That taught me a lesson my entire life. Whenever you get into a bind, slow down! Just get back to normal—happens on a volleyball court. You get in a volleyball court; the game is going really hectic. Slow down and get back to the basics. Then you begin to use your skills again. So the man is ten foot tall, gets you calmed down and able to remember the basics, remember the professionalism, and it works.</u>
        <u who="VERRONE">Okay. We have a few more minutes before we have to end, we have gone for an hour almost.</u>
        <u who="WINKEL">Oh god.</u>
        <u who="VERRONE">Tell me a little bit more, the next day and what happened?</u>
        <u who="WINKEL">Well, the <date when="1965-11-15">15th</date> there was log missions. <date when="1965-11-16">16th</date> we extracted the <orgName>1st of the 7th</orgName>. Then the <date when="1965-11-17">17th</date> was <name type="event">Albany</name>, I was in <placeName>Albany</placeName> in the <date when="1965-11-18">18th</date> but not that night, well that’s another story.</u>
        <u who="VERRONE">Tell me about <name type="event">Albany</name>, briefly tell me about that experience on the <date when="1965-11-18">18th</date>.</u>
        <u who="WINKEL">Well the <date when="1965-11-18">18th</date> is when we had to go bring the troops out and take them over to <placeName>LZ (Landing Zone) Crooks</placeName> and the guys we were picking up in the morning from <placeName>Albany</placeName> looked like death warmed over. The ten-mile stare, the “Why am I here” sort of thing. Then we dropped them off at <placeName>LZ Crooks</placeName> in another little battle. But it wasn’t anything going on too much around <placeName>LZ Crooks</placeName> except artillery.</u>
        <u who="VERRONE">How does it affect you as a pilot to see these men over and over and over?</u>
        <u who="WINKEL">How did it affect me? Later on, I started logging in troops and when we brought wounded out, I logged this cargo. I did not log troops coming out. Which in <date when="1983">1983</date>, I was diagnosed with PTSD (Post-Traumatic Stress Disorder), went to six years counseling. First wife went mentally ill because of the kids and <name type="event">Vietnam</name>. Second wife and my kids didn’t work out too well. Finally, after counseling, I met my wife at a volleyball court, and we’ve been great. But ix years of counseling.</u>
        <u who="VERRONE">What’s it like now forty years after the fact, for you to be here?</u>
        <u who="WINKEL">I’m writing a book. I’m writing a book about—</u>
        <u who="VERRONE">Is that cathartic for you and getting this out?</u>
        <u who="WINKEL">Yeah, yeah. Writing a book about the chopper guys, which is taking about seventeen years to find out who did what to whom and when.</u>
        <u who="VERRONE">What’s it like being around the men again forty years later? I know you all had previous reunions, but on this 40th anniversary what’s it like seeing them?</u>
        <u who="WINKEL">Like brothers.</u>
        <u who="VERRONE">Well, thank you very much <persName>Colonel</persName>. I know we need to talk more, and I hope we will in the future, but for now, we will have to end the interview. Thank you very much.</u>
       <u who="WINKEL">Thank you.(End of interview)</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
