<?xml-model href="../schemas/ddhi.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Transcript of an Interview with Gordon Paul Rozanski</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>
          <orgName>Vietnam Center and Sam Johnson Vietnam Archive</orgName>
        </authority>
        <date>
          <!--  Date of publication, e.g. for citation purposes  -->
        </date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <recordingStmt>
          <recording xml:id="primary_recording" type="video" dur-iso="00:33:04">
            <!-- https://www.digi.com/resources/documentation/digidocs/90001437-13/reference/r_iso_8601_duration_format.htm -->
            <media url="https://vva.vietnam.ttu.edu/images.php?img=/OH/OH0452/OH0452.mp4" mimeType="video/mp4"/>
          </recording>
        </recordingStmt>
        <bibl xml:id="primary_transcription">
          <respStmt>
            <persName>Mark Steven Varela</persName>
            <orgName>Vietnam Center and Sam Johnson Vietnam Archive</orgName>
            <resp ref="http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/trc.html">Transcriber</resp>
          </respStmt>
          <ref target="path_to_file">https://vva.vietnam.ttu.edu/images.php?img=/OH/OH0452/OH0452.pdf</ref>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The Oral History Project of the Vietnam Center and Sam Johnson Vietnam Archive</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application ident="DDHIEncoder" version="1.0">
          <desc>Conversion from Word docx to TEI xml.</desc>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en-us">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <particDesc>
        <person xml:id="ROZANSKI"/>
        <person xml:id="VERRONE"/>
      </particDesc>
      <settingDesc>
        <setting>
          <date when-iso="2005-11-10"/>
          <locale/>
        </setting>
      </settingDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <u who="VERRONE">This is <persName>Dr. Richard Verrone</persName>, I’m conducting a video oral history with <persName>Gordon Paul Rozanski</persName>, better known as <persName>Rozy</persName>. Today is <date when="2005-11-10">11/10/05</date> and we are in <placeName>Washington, DC</placeName>, at the <placeName>Crystal City Hilton</placeName> and we’re here for the 40th anniversary reunion of the <name type="event">Pleiku-Ia Drang Valley campaign</name>. Sir, what I would like for you to do is we can concentrate and look at these days in <date when="1965-11">November</date> and I like to get you to describe maybe that weekend before Sunday the <date when= "1965-11-14">14th</date>. What were you doing, what was your position, then what were you doing to prepare for this?</u>
      <u who="ROZANSKI">The battalion at the time had been working in the <placeName>Plei Me</placeName> area there because of the attack of the on the Special Forces camp. When the battalion had moved up in there, I was the S4 for <orgName>1st and the 7th</orgName> and in charge of supplies. So I set up a supply agency there or attempted. Then, a couple of people at <placeName>Pleiku</placeName>, <persName>Holloway</persName> and then also put some other people up on the tea plantation to help and supply. We—at the time we’ve been supplying daily rations for the troops as they been on their other operations and then it was just a matter of support all the way through for—we had some guys who were troops ready to head on home and in a lot of cases decided to stick it out until they came back in from the field. So it was a matter of supply and taking care of the troops, making sure they had what they needed.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">How difficult of a job was that in that terrain? In that atmosphere and its—you’re right at the crux of what the public saw as the real first time the <orgName>Americans</orgName> were on the ground, which we know is not true. But tell me about working supply there in <date when="1965">1965</date>.</u>
        <u who="ROZANSKI">Well, really the weapons we had were basically new. They were the M16s. Getting the people used to the M16s and the problems of maintenance and trying to keep them from wrapping them around a tree after their little frustration. We had the rations, you know, were no problem. Still eating C-rations at the time, but we tried if possible, to make sure they got a hot meal or hot something. Usually every day or whatever if you’re not in contact. It wasn’t bad. The one problem we had from the get-go over there was the water. What we had for brining water out to the troops besides their own canteens, were plastic—they looked like collapsible milk jugs. Probably four and five gallons. They worked fine. They’d fold up, but when they were full of water and sloshed around, the first stick punctured them. So you always had a problem with water. I think that was probably one of the biggest headaches. Ammunition, we had a great supply of ammunition. Rations. Anything we need was right stone’s throw from the tent. The medical unit was supporting me and the <name type="event">Pleiku operation</name> was right in my backdoor.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Sounded like you had what you needed.</u>
      <u who="ROZANSKI">We had everything we needed right there.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Sunday the <date when="1965-11-14">14th</date>. Tell me about that day.</u>
      <u who="ROZANSKI">The troops had moved basically back into the <placeName>Plei Me</placeName> area. The old <placeName>Special Forces camp</placeName> there, at <placeName>Plei Me</placeName>. They had trouble—they had all come in from the operations they’d been running We served them I think a hot meal that day. And as we’re sitting there, the general says, “Let’s go for a ride.” I’d say it was <persName>General Moore</persName>, <persName>Matt Dillon</persName>, myself, <persName>Crandall</persName>, and <persName>Freeman</persName>. As I recall.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE"><persName>Crandall</persName>, <persName>Freeman</persName> had already left?</u>
      <u who="ROZANSKI">They’re pilot and co-pilot. We took off, flew out. I guess you could call it an aerial reconnaissance. It was—I think we figured it was going be a walk in the park. We had no real, I think, intel of anything being in that area. Even though the <placeName>Special Forces camp</placeName> had been hit, they had run an operation at the camp to go back a little bit before that. The team that had been out on the ground came back in from the south to the camp. Crossed the airstrip. Saw nothing all the while they were out there. They got into back into the camp, they had just barley put their gear down. The whole south-side of the airstrip rose up and moved on. They got hit pretty good. So us not being able to see anything in there I think was just—we knew there were troops there. I don’t—I really don’t know if we had any idea there were <orgName>North Vietnamese</orgName> troops there. In my own mind. But we decided after making the fly by that we would go in and I would get two ships for supplying the first, because the first group going in, they would take just a very small amount of ammunition for their mortars and machine guns, and cruiser weapons. So the deal in what we had done in the past was that after the first lift goes in, I get two ships, they’re mine. I’d learned through all the training that when you get them, you keep a foot on them or they have a tendency to run all away like children. So the first lift went in, when they came back, I got my two ships loaded the crew served extra ammunition and parts for the mortars of the gear that they needed. We followed the second lift in and I always, while I was ES4, did the supplies so I could see what was going on down on the ground. As we went in and kind of trailing the second lift in, first bunch had already been pretty well towed. I’m sitting in the door of the chopper and the one that I was in had gotten—I didn’t find out until we were out on the ground, supposedly had been dinged going in. But as we went over going into the Ia Drang, there was the ridge line here. As I looked down, I could see them shooting at us and I figured, not a walk in the park. So we got in, I unloaded the ammunition close to the—there were a couple of First Sergeants there and they had a bunch of wounded already. I’m carrying stuff for <persName>Crawston</persName> and taking fire. The First Sergeant and the troops that were there helping load the wounded and offload the stuff, while the pilot decided the ship couldn’t fly for what reason. I guess it had been hit, but it’s his decision. So we loaded on to the second and just as we lifted off, it either got hit again, or it had been hit before. So we started to smoke, went a short ways away heading down and the crew bailed. They had already called, and I don’t know—<persName>Winkel</persName> says he was the one that came in, I don’t know for sure. At that time, I wasn’t looking at name tags or asking for resumes it was, you know, “Give me some support!” We had the troops that needed to get some of these guys out. I had one part of the side of his face, his ear was gone. Another one through the neck, one in the chest, one in the stomach, several others. The ship came in and I pealed everybody off that I could and stuffed them in the back of the chopper. We went on back into <placeName>Pleiku</placeName> instead of going into any of others because the guys who were wounded at that time, they had battle bandages on, but they hadn’t been treated by <persName>Sergeant Keating</persName>, the medical sergeant or the doc hadn’t been at them yet. These guys had just been—they were fresh.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Right. They didn’t get—</u>
      <u who="ROZANSKI">That’s it, so I took them right back there, we landed. The guys met us, I mean, they were there in a heartbeat. They refueled, we reloaded. I had my S4 Sergeant, I think <persName>Sergeant Freiburger</persName> at the time, called my two NCOs (Non-Commissioned Officers) who were out at the tea plantation and told them to give them whatever assistance they could.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Are you calling <persName>Moore</persName> and asking, “What do you want now?” Or are you kind of just following your instinct?</u>
      <u who="ROZANSKI">The thing there is, I dealt with the people who needed it and what I figured they were needing. One of the things that did happen during this time, and just kind of a sideline here is that <persName>Crandall</persName> and them did haul a lot of ammunition in. Problem being, it was a good idea to a point. But you don’t need a lot of machine gun ammunition. We destroyed a lot of ammunition when we left. We had ammunition, but it wasn’t what we needed. In fact, in some of the cases, instead of the ammunition, five gallons of water would’ve been better. It’s neither here nor there, it happened and it’s just the way it is. I talked to the people on the ground and—</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">You told the company commander?</u>
      <u who="ROZANSKI">The company commanders and also the troops. The mortar people, the first sergeants they were there, they knew what they needed. I didn’t think that going to Moore, I talked with the General and at that time, we were getting into the things that we figured we needed. We needed water, and we really didn’t get any large amounts of water and supplies. The water came—got in the next day. They had brought in—we had tried to make a deal to bring in a couple of big bladders. However, when supplies they like to keep a foot on things, they took them in and they forgot the pumps. So there’s trouble getting water out of those things. Those two Chinooks they were there, they were the ones that Moore and I walked around and reloaded with the dead that we had. But other than—I haven’t really thought that much about, you know, the things that happened. I just know that I kept moving as much as I could, in bringing things in that they needed and taking people out, trying to treat people. When I did take the dead back into <placeName>Pleiku</placeName>, I took the dead and one wounded <orgName>NVA (North Vietnamese Army)</orgName>.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">What do you do with that, in the midst of this day? How do you handle the dead and the wounded? Do you put that aside so you can go forward?</u>
      <u who="ROZANSKI">My wife says that I’m probably the most together person about this. It was bad, however, in later times in my tour over there I saw things that were a little, I think, worse than what had gone there. The dead bothered me to the point—these young guys, I was commanding headquarters coming in, the <orgName>2nd of the 23rd</orgName>, which later became the <orgName>1st</orgName>. When a lot of these shiny faces got off the buses in front, they came right to me for mama.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">And you saw these faces?</u>
      <u who="ROZANSKI">I did, and I watched them throughout their training at <placeName>Benning</placeName>, at <placeName>Carolinas</placeName>. My first Sergeant didn’t go over with us because he had a medical problem. But I’d go and bail them out of jail! It happened more than once. I could talk to them; I wasn’t an enlisted man to begin with. When these guys, a lot of them that did get killed, that didn’t have to be there. But they went through the training. Everybody that was there, they were a family. You knew what the next guy was going and that’s really what turned the tide there. You knew you could rely on the guy next to you because you knew what he was up to.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Tell me about <persName>General Moore</persName>. What kind of man is he? Who was he to you then? And who is he to you now?</u>
      <u who="ROZANSKI">Well, we haven’t talked that much in recent years, but when he reported and took over the battalion, I was very close to <persName>General Moore</persName>’s wife. It was sort of like, “<persName>Rozy</persName> you’re the old dude around here.” You know, we were going to have a party, “<persName>Rozy</persName>, you set this up.” I was <persName>Harold Moore</persName>’s dog robber. If there was something that was needed, I could get it.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">It’s a great skill.</u>
      <u who="ROZANSKI">When we went over, I had moved units overseas before, I knew that you’re not going to have what you need. You order a bunch of extra CONEX containers and then you go, they issue you plywood, so you could box off these containers. Well, no. I keep the plywood and all of this, and put it in one because you’re going to need it later. Then I go and Fort Benning was a great place that had a lot research and development. They were doing at that time the dehydrated rations and our friend said, “Gosh, I had this stuff.” I said, “Fine, I’ll have it pick up.” So I took many containers, dehydrated rations. We ate porkchops when the division headquarters was eating C-rations.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">So tell me about your time there at <placeName>X-Ra</placeName>y. That first day you were busy loading, unloading.</u>
      <u who="ROZANSKI">Loading, unloading. Usually, to get the supplies, the guys who were in the choppers, they wouldn’t budge. If they did anything, they’d push something off, but that was about it. It was a matter of getting over to the supplies to who need it and taking out the wounded as according to <persName>Sergeant Keating</persName>. They all had worked for me when I had commanded headquarters company. They really made sure that these guys need out of here. They need attention right now and I did what I could.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Did you stay at <placeName>X-Ray</placeName> in any of those nights? Or did you—</u>
      <u who="ROZANSKI">I didn’t. I was usually in the back trying to make sure—because first of all, I’m not knowing just exactly how long we’re going to be on because the amount of supply that had been at <placeName>Holloway</placeName> was actually we were about running out time. So I wanted to make sure we had enough mortar, ammunition, any of the ration that we needed or if I needed to have stuff brought up from <placeName>An Khê</placeName>. Then try to deal with and coordinate with the people out at the Tea Plantation. Which several people, I think, tried to get involved more than—they may have slowed things down. We were able to supply—my section was able to supply anything my battalion could do and had the best team, and as far as the helicopters saying, “Well, we had to do this, we had to do that.” It’s a helicopter, they were attached to us. Taking ammunition back into the landing zone was their job. You know, you can’t fight a war on sailboat fuel. Empty helicopters don’t do anything. Same way coming out, you have wounded, they got to be out. Bringing in the medevac choppers, I think would’ve been a mistake. The medevac choppers at that time I think the, as I recall, the policy was for that to come in as a slick, they had to have gunships to support it. The troops, they didn’t have gunners on them then. The troops that did have guns, they were in the back were also the medics. It would’ve been, in my opinion, and at that time I was a captain and my opinion, it may have been listened to but probably not, it would’ve been a waste of a great asset that the division needed. Coming in and hauling a couple of people off and possibly losing because of not having the gunners.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Tell me about <persName>Bruce Crandall</persName>. He plays such a significant role in the book and in the movie. Tell me about <persName>Crandall</persName> in those three days.</u>
      <u who="ROZANSKI">I wasn’t that close with—in touch with him at that time because it seemed that every time, he may have been flying some of the time I was there. He always (Imitates Crandall’s voice) “If I’d known you’d be there, you’d have had a helmet.” Well, we always had a flight helmet, so we’d have contact. Whenever I went, I had a war flight helmet, so I had contact and I could tell them where I wanted to land. After forty years of the story being told and retold, sanitized or whatever, I think he did a great job. If anyone could do a video game, I’d like to see that they for those three days to see how the helicopters didn’t eat themselves up based on you’re hearing of this. I didn’t see as many helicopters as I’ve heard they were but.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Tell me about <persName>Ed Freeman</persName>.</u>
      <u who="ROZANSKI">Top notch. Top notch. Not much to say. He’s business, professional. Deserves what he got.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Tell me about yourself, and what you took away from those three days. Your busyness, your lessons learned. Where are you now?</u>
      <u who="ROZANSKI">I learned a lot, I learned that everything is going to change and you’re training people, it doesn’t make a difference how well you train them. They’re going to get killed. War is not a pleasant thing and we don’t do it just for the fun of it. I really support all the troops. To me, that’s it. Like I tell all the young guys that I see today, that really us old dudes, we can’t hold a candle to them. They’re so far above us and what they can do. The guys that we had, I think, were the finest trained people. Most settled bunch that I have ever had the privilege of working with. </u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Would you attribute that to <persName>Plumley</persName> and <persName>Moore</persName>?</u>
      <u who="ROZANSKI"><persName>General Moore</persName> was a SOB. He was a stickler. Now <persName>Moore</persName>, it was from the reveille calls, to the retreat ceremonies, he was a stickler for detail. And I like to cut corners, so right there I'm usually on the hot seat somewhere along the line.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">What’s it like being here forty years later and seeing the men? There’d been reunions in the past, but this is a special 40th commemorative reunion for you all. </u>
      <u who="ROZANSKI">This one here and just looking at the people I’ve seen today, I could run into <persName>Matt Dillon</persName> on the street like I did today. <persName>Matt</persName> and I live sixty miles apart and I’ve seen him once.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Since <name type="event">Ia Drang</name>?</u>
      <u who="ROZANSKI">Since <name type="event">Ia Drang</name>. (Laughs) We’re both the same. It’s like so-so. In <date when="2005-06">June</date>, we had a reunion down in <placeName>Fort Hood</placeName>. A bunch of the guys—I took over <orgName>B Company</orgName> as we came out of the <placeName>Ia Drang</placeName>. And all of these guys were there, they wanted me there so I went down. They all had the pictures. Really that was the hardest thing for me. I’m looking at these guys, they’re all grown and you’ve had good careers or not. Then when you look at the picture, you think, “You know, you really treated these young dudes wrong.” There’s one Frenchy, he looked just like he’s ought to be with a peachcello out on the beach and now he’s an old grizzled. But at time I’m thinking, this kid, he held off people and he helped a couple of the guys who were wounded. That was his baptism. Not so much do the fire thing, into life. For all of us, we had kind of wondered around in the An Khê area. You get shot at once and while.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">You were wounded, a little bit, four times. Is that correct? </u>
      <u who="ROZANSKI">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">When was this?</u>
      <u who="ROZANSKI">In <placeName>Bồng Sơn</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Next year? In <date when="1966">’66</date>?</u>
      <u who="ROZANSKI">Yes. I have mechanical elbows.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Let me ask this, we need to wrap this up. When you picture <placeName>LZ (Landing Zone) X-Ray</placeName>, when you picture those three days in <date when="1965-11">November 1965</date>, what do you see in your mind? What stands out? What is it that you remember?</u>
      <u who="ROZANSKI">I’ll tell you, that’s one thing that I really thought about when I was back there, I was in <orgName>Special Forces</orgName> because that was my area. I went in with several operations and I walked. Like I told <persName>Moore</persName>, “I heard the guys talk.” It was just like walking through the cemetery. Not a sound, not a bird, nothing. But as it got dark, in your mind you could hear the voices. That’s about as closest I’ve got to, really.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Well, why don’t we go ahead end the interview now? Thank you very much Mr. <persName>Rozanski</persName>, appreciate it.</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
