<?xml-model href="../schemas/ddhi.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ttu_453">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Transcript of an Interview with Barbara Ann Weathers Geoghegan Johns</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>
          <orgName>Sam Johnson Vietnam Center and Archive</orgName>
        </authority>
        <date>
          <!--  Date of publication, e.g. for citation purposes  -->
        </date>
        <idno type="DDHI">ttu_453</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <recordingStmt>
          <recording xml:id="primary_recording" type="video" dur-iso="02:27:51">
            <!-- https://www.digi.com/resources/documentation/digidocs/90001437-13/reference/r_iso_8601_duration_format.htm -->
            <media url="https://vva.vietnam.ttu.edu/images.php?img=/OH/OH0507/OH0507.mp3" mimeType="video/mp4"/>
          </recording>
        </recordingStmt>
        <bibl xml:id="primary_transcription">
          <respStmt>
            <persName>Mindy Moser</persName>
            <orgName>Sam Johnson Vietnam Center and Archive</orgName>
            <resp ref="http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/trc.html">Transcriber</resp>
          </respStmt>
          <ref target="https://vva.vietnam.ttu.edu/images.php?img=/OH/OH0507/OH0507.pdf">Primary transcription</ref>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The Oral History Project of the Sam Johnson Vietnam Center and Archive</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application ident="DDHIEncoder" version="1.0">
          <desc>Conversion from Word docx to TEI xml.</desc>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en-us">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <particDesc>
        <person xml:id="VERRONE"/>
        <person xml:id="JOHNS"/>
      </particDesc>
      <settingDesc>
        <setting>
          <date when-iso="2005-11-10"/>
          <locale/>
        </setting>
      </settingDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <u who="VERRONE">This is Dr. <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_0">Richard Verrone</persName>, I’m conducting a video-oral history with Mrs. <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_1">Barbara Ann Weathers Geoghegan Johns</persName>. <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_2">Barbara</persName> and I are at the <placeName ref="#ttu_453_place_0">Hilton Crystal City</placeName> at <placeName ref="#ttu_453_place_1">Washington D.C.</placeName>, for the 40th anniversary reunion of the <name type="event" ref="#ttu_453_event_0">Ia Drang-Pleiku Battles</name> in <date when="1965-11">November 1965</date>. It is <date when="2005-10-11">November 10th, 2005</date> and <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_3">Barbara</persName>, I’d like to start with some general questions about yourself. You’re here for a number of reasons. I want to talk about you. I want to talk about who you are and meeting <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_4">Jack</persName>, and your earlier history with that before we talk about anything beyond. Can you tell me a little bit about yourself?</u>
      <u who="JOHNS">About myself?</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Yes.</u>
      <u who="JOHNS">I’ve lived in <placeName ref="#ttu_453_place_2">Annandale, Virginia</placeName>, for twenty-eight years, my husband and I. My husband and I have been married for thirty-six and a half years. I actually met <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_5">John</persName> in <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_6">Jack</persName>’s parents’ home in <date when="1968-12">December of 1968</date> and we were we married in <date when="1969-04">April of 1969</date>. <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_7">John</persName> was in the <orgName ref="#ttu_453_org_0">army</orgName>, he was a Lieutenant Colonel at the time, so we moved around a bit and eventually ended up in <placeName ref="#ttu_453_place_3">Washington D.C.</placeName> area.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Tell me about before 1965, state the full year in the context of what we’re doing here this weekend. Tell me about <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_8">Jack</persName>, your husband <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_9">Jack Geoghegan</persName>, your then husband. What was he like? What were you all like as a young couple?</u>
      <u who="JOHNS">Well, he was an amazing person. I was a junior in college. I went to <placeName ref="#ttu_453_place_4">Beaver College</placeName> outside of <placeName ref="#ttu_453_place_5">Philadelphia</placeName>, which is now <orgName ref="#ttu_453_org_1">Arcadian University</orgName>. I was a junior there and he was a senior at <orgName ref="#ttu_453_org_2">PMC</orgName>, <orgName ref="#ttu_453_org_3">Pennsylvania Military College</orgName>. We met—it was quite a fluke how me meet because he called me on the telephone. I had been to a mixer, we used             to have those things those days, between colleges and I didn’t meet him at the time, but I met some people who knew him. It was a couple of years later and they said they remembered having met me, and I’ve never gone out with any of them. They dared him to call me, and he did. I was shocked to—for one thing I knew a <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_10">Jack Geoghegan</persName> in my high school class, and I knew it wasn’t him and he sounded very nice, very gentlemanly. But I didn’t want to go out on a date with somebody who had just called me on the phone like that. But at the same time, I was interested. Well, he called another time and asked me to go to a parade at <placeName ref="#ttu_453_place_6">Pennsylvania Military College</placeName>, on a Sunday afternoon and I thought, “That’s harmless enough.” So I decided to do that.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">What year is this?</u>
      <u who="JOHNS">That was <date when="1963">1963</date>—<date when="1962">1962</date>. He graduated in <date when="1963">1963</date>, <date when="1962-10">October of ’62</date>. So he had me seated in the stands. I was watching the parade and somebody next to me said, “That’s your guy out there leading the parade!” I said, “What?” I was looking through all these corps cadets and I couldn’t find him, and somebody said that. It turned out he was the brigade commander. He hadn’t mentioned that earlier, even though he had all these things on his sleeve. He was a very modest person. We started to date and dated through the rest of that year, and then he graduated from <orgName ref="#ttu_453_org_4">PMC</orgName> (<orgName ref="#ttu_453_org_5">Pennsylvania Military College</orgName>) and then I went into my senior year of college. He went to <orgName ref="#ttu_453_org_6">University of Pennsylvania</orgName> to get a master’s degree in international relations, while I was in my senior year.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">And you knew, I guess, going in that he would be the <orgName ref="#ttu_453_org_7">army</orgName>, you all would move around. Were you okay with that?</u>
      <u who="JOHNS">I was, but he was only intending to be in <orgName ref="#ttu_453_org_8">army</orgName> for two years at that point, after he got his master’s degree. Actually, he had two years to get that and, in the meantime, I graduated from college and he had a year leftover. What he said to me was, “I would like to spend that year doing something for somebody else.” He started looking at different programs and that’s how we ended up with the <orgName ref="#ttu_453_org_9">Catholic Relief Services</orgName>, and how we ended up going to Africa for ten months after we were married.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Tell me about that experience, what was it like? When were you married?</u>
      <u who="JOHNS"><date when="1964-06-13">June 13th, 1964</date>. A week after I graduated from college.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Tell me about Africa, it’s a very unique experience.</u>
      <u who="JOHNS">It certainly was. </u>
      <u who="VERRONE">It stands out in a lot of people’s minds as something mentioned in movies, mentioned in the book, and people are remembering it now forty years later. Tell me about the experience.</u>
      <u who="JOHNS">It was an incredible experience. I had never been out of <placeName ref="#ttu_453_place_7">New Jersey</placeName> except for family trips and <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_11">Jack</persName> said, “I’ve lifted you out of the swamps of <placeName ref="#ttu_453_place_8">South Jersey</placeName> and dropped you into the jungles of Africa.”</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Where in Africa were you?</u>
      <u who="JOHNS">In <placeName ref="#ttu_453_place_9">Tanzania</placeName>. <placeName ref="#ttu_453_place_10">Dar es Salaam, Tanzania</placeName>. We lived in the outskirts.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">What did you do there for ten months?</u>
      <u who="JOHNS">Well, he worked, as I said, in the <orgName ref="#ttu_453_org_10">Catholic Relief Services</orgName> and his job was distributing <placeName ref="#ttu_453_place_11">United States</placeName> surplus food throughout the country to schools, and we used to travel around the country to make sure that the schools were receiving what they were supposed to. Then when we were back in home base, I taught school. Salvadoran convent school outside of <placeName ref="#ttu_453_place_12">Dar es Salaam</placeName>. I actually taught President <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_12">Nyerere</persName>’s children. Which was an interesting experience while they were in school.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">You all were Catholic, is that right?</u>
      <u who="JOHNS">Yes. </u>
      <u who="VERRONE">So you come back from Africa. Tell me what happens to the two of you then?</u>
      <u who="JOHNS">Well, by that time, I was pregnant. We came back in late <date when="1965-04">April of ’65</date> and there was a short time maybe three weeks where we spent time with our family, and then went on to <placeName ref="#ttu_453_place_13">Fort Benning, Georgia</placeName>, because he had to report there in <date when="1965-05">May of ’65</date> and he was going to infantry officer basic course. Then <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_13">Cami</persName> was born in <date when="1965-06">June</date>. June 13th—I mean, <date when="1965-06-08">June 8th</date>. Our anniversary is <date when="1965-06-13">June 13th</date>, it was almost on our anniversary.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">I can imagine the reactions of the newborn, your first child. Tell me about <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_14">Jack Geoghegan</persName>. </u>
      <u who="JOHNS">Oh, he was so thrilled, he just adored her. She was premature, she was only four pounds when she was born. She was so tiny; she was in the hospital for a whole month before we could bring her home. We brought her home on the <date when="1965-07-04">4th of July</date>, I remember that. I had pictures of him holding her very gingerly. He couldn’t keep his eyes off of her, he just adored her. She looked like him even then, she still looks like him.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">As a new mother and your husband going to this training at infantry school, and this war heating up in Southeast Asia. What were your thoughts about your future and your future with <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_15">Jack</persName>? And were you all—if you had an inclination that he would be deployed to <placeName ref="#ttu_453_place_14">Vietnam</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="JOHNS">I don’t remember thinking a lot about it because it wasn’t until, sometime in July that it was announced that there would be a big troop buildup. I was focusing on the fact that he was really only intending to be in the <orgName ref="#ttu_453_org_11">army</orgName> for two years and then he wanted to go back to Africa. That period in Africa to go back just a bit, I wish everyone could see that it was really the fulfillment of his spirit. He loved it there and he was just so focused on doing that, that was what he wanted to go back to. But he also was glad to be doing the <orgName ref="#ttu_453_org_12">army</orgName>.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">What was <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_16">Jack</persName>’s spirit like? You said it fulfilled his spirit.</u>
      <u who="JOHNS">He was always a giving person. Always looking for ways to help other people or just to do little thoughtful things, and somewhere I talked about when I was in college and I guess it was a prom or something, and as we were going out, <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_17">Jack</persName> said to the house mother-—they did have house mothers, <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_18">Jack</persName> said, “I’m going to get you a sundae to enjoy this evening.” He went across the street to <placeName ref="#ttu_453_place_15">Howard Johnson’s</placeName> and brought back a hot fudge sundae for her. Just a little thoughtful thing, he would do things like that for people often. When he was at <orgName ref="#ttu_453_org_13">PMC</orgName>, he learned of a student who couldn’t pay his next semester’s tuition. So <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_19">Jack</persName> formed a committee and throughout the entire night had many of the <orgName ref="#ttu_453_org_14">Corps Candidates</orgName> collect money to pay for this young man’s tuition.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">He sounds pretty selfless.</u>
      <u who="JOHNS">He was. He was. It was the kind of thing he did.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">So when you did hear the news, that his unit would be deployed and in the calvary, and he’s been training in this as a young lieutenant, what were your reactions to that?</u>
      <u who="JOHNS">I was in shock really, I remember that. I just couldn’t believe it. I kept telling myself—I kept thinking that the war wouldn’t last very long. Little did I know.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">I think a lot of people did not foresee the next eight years, ten years. What was <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_20">Jack</persName>’s reaction to that?</u>
      <u who="JOHNS">That he was going?</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Yes.</u>
      <u who="JOHNS">Well, he felt like that it was his duty to go. From that standpoint, he wasn’t happy to leave home because, who would be? But he was actually glad to have had the opportunity to serve his country. Very strong man.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">What do you remember about the then Lieutenant Colonel <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_21">Hal Moore</persName>, in <date when="1965">1965</date>, before he was deployed?</u>
      <u who="JOHNS">Well, I only met him a time or two. I met his wife <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_22">Julie</persName>, who was a wonderful person, and they became very good friends through the years, my husband now worked for <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_23">General Moore</persName>. They were very good friends. They were very warm and welcoming. I remember going to a luncheon at <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_24">Julie Moore</persName>’s house for the battalion wives and I was on the phone with people, “Should we wear a hat and gloves?” (Laughs)</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">What was the dress? Do you remember?</u>
      <u who="JOHNS">It was a dress, but I don’t think it was a dress and hat and gloves, but I don’t remember actually doing it. May or may not have. But that was what were afraid of, that we were expected to. But then within a second, all of that feeling melted away because <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_25">Julie Moore</persName> was just the warmest and most wonderful person you can meet.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">A lot of people have an image of <orgName ref="#ttu_453_org_15">General Moore</orgName>, based on the book and certainly the movie, tell me about <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_26">Julie Moore</persName>. She’s also mentioned in the book and of course portrayed very much in the movie by <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_27">Madeline Stowe</persName>. Tell me about her, her character, and just your experience with her.</u>
      <u who="JOHNS">I didn’t have a lot of experience with her before <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_28">Jack</persName> went to <placeName ref="#ttu_453_place_16">Vietnam</placeName>. Just that one meeting really, that told me everything I needed to know about her. She was just such a delightful person. It was only years later that I got to know her much, much better and I’m extremely fond of her.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Tell me about the days before <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_29">Jack</persName> leaves and if you can, if you would like to, how you all functioned together knowing he was going off to war and probably, most likely, would see combat and would be one of the leaders within that system. What was that like? And leaving a baby daughter behind. Tell me about that.</u>
      <u who="JOHNS">That was—it was very difficult. I knew that I would be staying near <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_30">Jack</persName>’s parents, actually with them for a while. That was helpful to be with them and close to them for each other’s support. We went to <placeName ref="#ttu_453_place_17">Connecticut</placeName>, to be with them before he went to <placeName ref="#ttu_453_place_18">Vietnam</placeName>. I was so grateful for that. I remember that very clearly.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Before he went to <placeName ref="#ttu_453_place_19">Connecticut</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="JOHNS">Yes, with his parents and that was a very difficult time, and I vividly remember his father looking out the window and just shaking his head and saying something about “I’ll never see him again.”</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">This is when he left?</u>
      <u who="JOHNS">Right before he left. He just felt that he was going off to war and—but they also worried when we went to Africa. They were afraid then; <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_31">Jack</persName>’s parents were, that something would happen in Africa. So it just multiplied that effect in many, many times over when he was going to <placeName ref="#ttu_453_place_20">Vietnam</placeName>. And he was an only child too. They were married twelve years before he was born.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Yes, he was a late baby if you will.</u>
      <u who="JOHNS">That’s right, they were thirty-six.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Tell me about <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_32">Jack</persName>’s parents.</u>
      <u who="JOHNS">They were fabulous people, I loved them dearly. They were just wonderful. They were like parents to me; Another set of parents and I was like a daughter to them I think, and they adored <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_33">Cami</persName>. It was really wonderful to be with them and then when <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_34">Jack</persName> left, they were very supportive. But they had built a house there in <placeName ref="#ttu_453_place_21">Connecticut</placeName> and they—I lived there, it was a little house, I always referred to it as a little house. They lived there for a year and then built a larger house on the same property. That house was ready about a month after <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_35">Jack</persName> left to <placeName ref="#ttu_453_place_22">Vietnam</placeName>. Even though he saw that house and walked through it, he never actually lived in it and it was probably a good thing for them that they were changing their associations, and their lives so much that if they had stayed in <placeName ref="#ttu_453_place_23">Pelham, New York</placeName>, where they had lived, they would have been constantly surrounded with memories. But as it was, it was very hard.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">What about his mother?</u>
      <u who="JOHNS">She was a saint. She was such a wonderful person. She died in <date when="1979">1979</date> and I still miss her. I still think about her every day. In some context or another I think, “Oh, I wonder what she would think of that?” Or she would probably say this about that and was—</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">That’s a real tribute to her.</u>
      <u who="JOHNS">Yes. She was just—really, a great guiding force in my life and I feel she still is. I think a lot of <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_36">Jack</persName>, a lot of her, and his father too. But she was a very strong person and really, I think she had to be strong for her husband who was—he was just shattered when <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_37">Jack</persName> died. He got the news on his birthday. It was his 62nd birthday. We were planning a birthday party for him.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">What about your mother and father, and who they were and also their relationship with <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_38">Jack</persName>.</u>
      <u who="JOHNS">Well they lived in <placeName ref="#ttu_453_place_24">New Jersey</placeName>, about five miles east of <placeName ref="#ttu_453_place_25">Philadelphia</placeName>. They thought the world of <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_39">Jack</persName> and were very, very proud of him. Loved him dearly. They were—my mother had been Catholic, then she left Catholic church. I actually converted to Catholicism, which didn’t thrill my mother a lot. (Laughs) But they still thought the world of him. She was fearful since she had left the <orgName ref="#ttu_453_org_16">church</orgName>, but that was another issue.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">When <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_40">Jack</persName> left to <placeName ref="#ttu_453_place_26">Vietnam</placeName>, what did you all said to each other and how did that happen?</u>
      <u who="JOHNS">Well, I remember going in night and in the morning. I dropped him off at the army—at <placeName ref="#ttu_453_place_27">Fort Benning</placeName>. That was—we had spent the last couple nights at—we left our home at the <placeName ref="#ttu_453_place_28">Camilia Apartments</placeName>. <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_41">Cami</persName> was not named after the <placeName ref="#ttu_453_place_29">Camila Apartments</placeName> by the way. (Laughs) We stayed a couple of nights at a hotel there in <placeName ref="#ttu_453_place_30">Columbus, Georgia</placeName>. We spent a lot of time talking and talking.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">What did you talk about?</u>
      <u who="JOHNS">Well <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_42">Jack</persName>, he really did not think anything would happen to him, but he would talk about our future together. Talked about coming back and maybe going to another country in Africa or South America. He wanted to go back to the same life we had in Africa.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">How did you feel about that?</u>
      <u who="JOHNS">I wasn’t so sure about that because even though I came to really love where we were in Africa, I went through a couple of months of really bad homesickness and it was very strange. I remember walking out the backdoor and seeing a lizard about four feet long. I’d never seen such a thing before. (Laughs)</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Did <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_43">Jack</persName> kill the lizard, like a cockroach or spider? (Laughs) Well, so there was no—unlike a spot, there was no authority in that?</u>
      <u who="JOHNS">No there wasn’t. He did not. I have no memory of him—except that night when he left and when he said to me, “<persName ref="#ttu_453_person_44">Barbara</persName>, nothing is going to happen to me. But if it does, I want you to married <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_45">Bill</persName>.” I remember him saying that.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">The night he left?</u>
      <u who="JOHNS">The night he left he said that. Then he said, “<persName ref="#ttu_453_person_46">Cami</persName> needs a father.” I remember that so vividly and years, and years later I’m so glad he said that. But many years later, it was as if he had given me a blessing to say that.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">He was being selfless.</u>
      <u who="JOHNS">Exactly. His parents after—I guess it was two years after <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_47">Jack</persName> died and my mother-in-law said to me one day, “You know, we are very, very close. But I don’t want you to feel like we don’t want you to marry again, because we are so close. We want you to marry again. You’re young at that point, twenty-five, twenty-six.” They just wanted me to know that they wanted me to marry again. At that point I didn’t decide at all to marry again, I never thought I would.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">What do you remember <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_48">Jack</persName> saying about <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_49">Lieutenant Colonel Moore</persName>?</u>
      <u who="JOHNS">Oh, he thought very, very highly of him. It seemed to be a lot like him because G<persName ref="#ttu_453_person_50">eneral Moore</persName> is a tough solider. He’s a very kind and good person. He was—he thought very highly of him and was very proud to be in his unit, to be part of the 7th.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">So when he leaves, did you—maybe it’s not a question, did you talk to <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_51">Camille</persName>? What did you tell her as a baby? </u>
      <u who="JOHNS">I hadn’t thought of that in many years, but I would talk to her about him and tell her that he was away, but he would be back. I would read his letters to her; I’d pray with her.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Tell me about his letters and the contact you all had.</u>
      <u who="JOHNS">Well we wrote to each other every day. Unfortunately, when I remarried, my mother-in-law said to me, “You really should destroy <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_52">Jack</persName>’s letters. You are starting a whole new live and it wouldn’t be a good idea to have these letters.” Foolishly, I followed what she said. I wish I hadn’t. I wish I had gone through them and even just saved some of them. I do remember that I was on letter number ninety-three to him, when the phone rang. I was writing the night I learned of his death.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">I would like to talk about that. What did <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_53">Jack</persName> say in his letters to you about the war and about his experiences there?</u>
      <u who="JOHNS">Since I don’t have them, I don’t really remember.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">I know it’s been a long time; Do you remember the tone and the spirit of his letters?</u>
      <u who="JOHNS">Well, he was very concerned about his men. That was a primary. That may have been his last letter to me. He said he would bring all of his men home safely. All but three of them died with him. One of his men had drowned in an accident, maybe a month before that. That was very hard on him, very difficult.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">How responsible <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_54">Jack</persName> felt, how bad he felt and how to deal with that.</u>
      <u who="JOHNS">It was very hard.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">If we could, could we talk about the day that you found out about his death and that experience?</u>
      <u who="JOHNS">Well, I was in—I was not actually at home that night. I had gone to <placeName ref="#ttu_453_place_31">New Rochelle, New York</placeName>, about an hour from <placeName ref="#ttu_453_place_32">Redding, Connecticut</placeName>, to be with <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_55">Jack</persName>’s aunt, his mother’s sister, whose husband had died on the 15th of November, two years before and I didn’t want her to be alone on the anniversary of his death. So I was with her. I didn’t actually hear anything he said. I think it was two days later, we went back up to <placeName ref="#ttu_453_place_33">Connecticut</placeName> and that was when <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_56">Jack</persName>’s father’s birthday. The 17th of November was his father’s birthday, the 62nd birthday. Now I was wrong about that because I was still at <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_57">Aunt Pat</persName>’s house when my mother-in-law called me and told me.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">So they called there looking for you, I guess.</u>
      <u who="JOHNS">My mother-in-law called me. The cab driver had gone to their house. Since I wasn’t home, he delivered the telegram to <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_58">Jack</persName>’s parents and then she called me.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Do you remember that phone call?</u>
      <u who="JOHNS">I remember as if I was back there in the kitchen because I was writing a letter to <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_59">Jack</persName>. I guess <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_60">Aunt Pat</persName> had answered the phone and I think she knew something was amidst because she called me over, and I took the phone and <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_61">Jack</persName>’s mother, I could tell by her voice, she said, “It’s about <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_62">Jack</persName>.” My first thought was that he was alright, maybe he was hurt. Then, the next thing she said was that he was killed. I remember I just sank to the floor. I wasn’t sitting at the time. I was next to a cabinet or something and just slid down to the floor. It was like being thrusted into another world. It was just a stunning shock. Then, the next thing she said to me was, “I’m so glad he married you.” And that was how much of his mother was—the fact that she would think to say that. It was a beautiful, beautiful thing. So we talked a while.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Did she tell you how? Was there news of what had happened?</u>
      <u who="JOHNS">It was in the telegram that he had been killed in battle. Gun shots to the back of his head. It’s interesting, I don’t have that telegram. I’d always wondered that everything else—of course it went to them and I guess they probably still—I don’t remember, I probably had it at some point but it’s something that I would not have destroyed. I don’t know whatever happened to it.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">What did you tell <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_63">Camille</persName>?</u>
      <u who="JOHNS">Then? Well, I remember she was asleep upstairs at <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_64">Pat</persName>’s house, and I went up and I went to her crib where she was, and I just picked her up. She was still very little at that point, just five months old and I just held her. I remember just holding her. I went to the window and I could remember thinking, that I noticed cars driving by and I thought, “The world is still going, and it had stopped.” It was such a strange feeling to be noticing cars going by and thinking, “Why are they still out there.” I held <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_65">Cami</persName> and just hugged her, and I remember telling her, “It’s just the two of us now.” That was very hard. That was what I remember. I remember she didn’t wake up, I just held her.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Tell me about <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_66">Camille</persName> and her development with who she is today. </u>
      <u who="JOHNS">Well, she just had her 40th birthday. (Laughs) Made it a little traumatic for her. That was funny because she said she was dreading it so much and thinking it was terrible turning forty. Then she said, “I’m at the happiest point in my life, I’m happily married, I have two beautiful children, why should I be miserable about turning forty? It’s part of life.” But growing up, she was a wonderful child. Always a very good child. She was almost four, <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_67">John</persName> and I were married in <date when="1969-04">April ’69</date>. She was four then. </u>
      <u who="VERRONE">She doesn’t remember <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_68">Jack</persName> most likely.</u>
      <u who="JOHNS">No, because she was only five months old.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">What did you tell her about her father? How did you handle that when she was old enough to understand?</u>
      <u who="JOHNS">I never hid it from her. Never. I was more matter of fact about it than anything. Her parents, we were always very close to <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_69">Jack</persName>’s parents. After <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_70">John</persName> and I married, we’d visit them once or twice a year, they’d come visit us for Christmas. So we were very close to them. <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_71">Cami</persName> knew that they were her father’s parents and occasionally they might say something about their father, I can’t even remember an example. But not often because they were very conscience of. They didn’t want to intrude at all in our lives, that was very—I use to argue with my mother-in-law about that because at first they didn’t want to go to our wedding, because they felt like they were casting a shadow or a dark cloud over our wedding. We insisted that they be there and they did come. So we very—just had a very small wedding. My parents, <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_72">Jack</persName>’s parents and few other people. My sister.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Well, we don’t have a lot of time, I know there’s a lot more we can talk about. I did want to talk to you about how the book and the movie has changed your life. I mean, the book is in the early 90s it comes out, the movie a couple of years ago. Tell me about that experience.</u>
      <u who="JOHNS">Well, that came about, I guess, in <date when="1990">1990</date>. Somewhere around there. <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_73">Joe Galloway</persName> called me, and it was <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_74">Tony Nadal</persName> who had known <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_75">Jack</persName> and had suggested to <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_76">Joe</persName> that he called me to interview me for his chapter on the families left behind. So <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_77">Joe</persName> did call me. It was interesting because <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_78">Tony</persName>, <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_79">Tony</persName> knew where to find me because we were all in <placeName ref="#ttu_453_place_34">Washington</placeName> together. We knew <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_80">Tony</persName> and <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_81">Billy</persName> at <placeName ref="#ttu_453_place_35">West Point</placeName>. In fact, <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_82">Tony</persName> and <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_83">General Moore</persName> I think were the only two people who knew both <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_84">Jack</persName> and <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_85">John</persName>. So it’s all these little interconnective things that were interesting about that. But that—there was an article in <orgName ref="#ttu_453_org_17">US News</orgName>, in World Report that was done in <date when="1990">1990</date> and I think the book followed that, and <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_86">Joe</persName> asked me to write my story for his chapter and that was—it took me back all those years and I felt like as if I was in a time warp to write that, but I was very happy to do that because I always wanted to tell the world about <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_87">Jack</persName>, he was such an unusual person.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Because of?</u>
      <u who="JOHNS">Because of the kind of person he was. Not that they aren’t wonderful people like he was, but he was—all that he wanted to do for the world and for other people, it was such a giving. Almost like, I don’t want to say saintly, no he wasn’t saintly. He was such a good person.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Do you think that—what do you think about his death today? I mean given who he was, that’s a huge question. </u>
      <u who="JOHNS">That’s interesting you’re asking me about his death and today would’ve been his birthday. Today he would’ve been sixty-four. Instead he died at twenty-four.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">How do you feel about that? </u>
      <u who="JOHNS">Well, it’s still makes me very sad to think that he—especially as I'm getting older too, that he didn’t have the opportunity to live a normal life, to have known <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_88">Cami</persName> and we probably would’ve had other children. But it’s odd though, how my children from my present marriage honor <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_89">Jack</persName>. They’ve read the book, they saw the movie, they’ve asked me about him. My daughter in <placeName ref="#ttu_453_place_36">California</placeName>, who’s a struggling screenwriter, even wants to write a story about <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_90">Jack</persName>. They also knew <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_91">Jack</persName>’s parents. So there’s that connection too. It’s just life is so very strange.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">What about the movie? I mean, your story plays a huge role in what really happens there with <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_92">Jack</persName> and also mainly the fact that the stakes and the spouses left behind and your character, <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_93">Keri Russel</persName>, who played your character, who is very prominently featured. Tell me about that experience, in the last couple of years.</u>
      <u who="JOHNS">That was—I still can’t believe it. I have the poster of the movie hanging on the wall and every time I look at it, I just—as if it’s the first time. I’ll look at <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_94">Keri Russel</persName> and think, she actually played me? She’s very sweet person. Very lovely person. Very, very nice. When we were at <placeName ref="#ttu_453_place_37">Fort Benning</placeName>, we met her. Very good, very kind person. I’ve had a little contact with her through email. I don’t try to maintain any kind of correspondence, but once and a while I hear of something she’s doing, I will—I mean in the movies, I will write to her, and just write a couple of sentences of how happy I am that she’s doing this and to know what’s going on. Once in a while she’ll write back and we ended very nice.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">How has the movie touched you and <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_95">Camille</persName>?</u>
      <u who="JOHNS">It’s been incredible because what I can’t believe is the number of people I have heard from, over the last three years, three and a half, four years. That people who have seen the movie and were touched by <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_96">Jack</persName>’s part in it. I’ve also heard from people that knew <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_97">Jack</persName>. But the ones that really touched me even more are those who didn’t know him. People whose lives were actually changed by that experience of watching that movie. What it makes me think of is <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_98">Jack</persName>’s mother said to me. I said she died in <date when="1969">1969</date> but she said to me one time, “I believe with all my soul, that great spiritual things will come to people through <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_99">Jack</persName>. This is a conviction with me, not just wishful thinking.”</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">It has come to past?</u>
      <u who="JOHNS">It has come to past. After all of these years. I told <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_100">Randall Wallace</persName> about that and we went to the premiere of the movie, and those words were on a plaque on a wall at the premiere, at the little party there was after the premiere. But he’s quite an astonishing person too, <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_101">Randall Wallace</persName>.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">What about <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_102">Chris Klein</persName>?</u>
      <u who="JOHNS">Oh, he’s very nice. Really fun person. We met him and his parents. He’s from <placeName ref="#ttu_453_place_38">Omaha</placeName>, I believe.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">What has it been like going to reunions and seeing, being a part of this family of veterans of this battle, but really the whole <orgName ref="#ttu_453_org_18">1st Cav</orgName>? What is here now? The 40th anniversary of these battles that happened in <placeName ref="#ttu_453_place_39">X-Ray</placeName> and <placeName ref="#ttu_453_place_40">Albany</placeName>. Tell me about what this experience has been like. I know this is only the first day I believe you’re in. But what about this commemorative reunion?</u>
      <u who="JOHNS">You mean because this is the 40th or? We’ve been at each one, each year and it’s quite amazing, wonderful to be with these people. But I’ve just—it’s like <orgName ref="#ttu_453_org_19">Cami</orgName> turning forty. I can’t believe it’s been forty years. Forty years. It’s just almost feels like <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_103">Rip Van Winkle</persName>. (Laughs) I miss so many years, going so fast.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">This interview will be made available to the public and then housed <orgName ref="#ttu_453_org_20">Vietnam Archive</orgName> for multiple generations into the future. What would you like to tell people about yourself, about <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_104">Jack</persName>, about <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_105">Camille</persName>, this experience, <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_106">Jack</persName>’s experience a hundred years from now, two hundred years from now? What would you what them to know?</u>
      <u who="JOHNS">Oh. </u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Sorry to put you on the spot.</u>
      <u who="JOHNS">I wish I knew in advance; I would think about that.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">We could do another interview and we can talk about that in more detail. What comes into your mind now?</u>
      <u who="JOHNS">That’s of interest to me because I like history and I like to think of people. I just watched this <name type="event" ref="#ttu_453_event_1">Civil War</name> series and read and heard that letter of <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_107">Major Ballou</persName> to his wife and isn’t it wonderful that we—I can’t read it or hear it without crying, but I thought, that was a hundred years ago. This would be, say like you’re asking me, a hundred years from now. How I would want people to know about that. I would want the fact that <placeName ref="#ttu_453_place_41">Vietnam</placeName> was such a controversial war that took place, that maybe we shouldn’t have been, maybe it was a mistake. But our men went there because they were asked to go, because it was their duty. Like <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_108">Jack</persName>, he didn’t question the war. He in fact—he felt like it was definitely the thing to do back in <date when="1965">1965</date>. So that would certainly be one thing. They wanted to serve the country. I need to think about that more and we can talk about it more because that was an interesting question.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Well, we’ll go ahead and end the interview now. Thank you very much <persName ref="#ttu_453_person_109">Barbara</persName>, for your time.</u>
      <u who="JOHNS">Thank you very much, I appreciate it.(End of interview)</u>
    </body>
  </text>
  <standOff>
    <listPlace>
      <place xml:id="ttu_453_place_0">
        <placeName>Hilton Crystal City</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_453_place_1">
        <placeName>Washington D.C.</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_453_place_2">
        <placeName>Annandale, Virginia</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_453_place_3">
        <placeName>Washington D.C.</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_453_place_4">
        <placeName>Beaver College</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_453_place_5">
        <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_453_place_6">
        <placeName>Pennsylvania Military College</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_453_place_7">
        <placeName>New Jersey</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_453_place_8">
        <placeName>South Jersey</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_453_place_9">
        <placeName>Tanzania</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_453_place_10">
        <placeName>Dar es Salaam, Tanzania</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_453_place_11">
        <placeName>United States</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_453_place_12">
        <placeName>Dar es Salaam</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_453_place_13">
        <placeName>Fort Benning, Georgia</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_453_place_14">
        <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_453_place_15">
        <placeName>Howard Johnson’s</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_453_place_16">
        <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_453_place_17">
        <placeName>Connecticut</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_453_place_18">
        <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_453_place_19">
        <placeName>Connecticut</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_453_place_20">
        <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_453_place_21">
        <placeName>Connecticut</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_453_place_22">
        <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_453_place_23">
        <placeName>Pelham, New York</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_453_place_24">
        <placeName>New Jersey</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_453_place_25">
        <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_453_place_26">
        <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_453_place_27">
        <placeName>Fort Benning</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_453_place_28">
        <placeName>Camilia Apartments</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_453_place_29">
        <placeName>Camila Apartments</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_453_place_30">
        <placeName>Columbus, Georgia</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_453_place_31">
        <placeName>New Rochelle, New York</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_453_place_32">
        <placeName>Redding, Connecticut</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_453_place_33">
        <placeName>Connecticut</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_453_place_34">
        <placeName>Washington</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_453_place_35">
        <placeName>West Point</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_453_place_36">
        <placeName>California</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_453_place_37">
        <placeName>Fort Benning</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_453_place_38">
        <placeName>Omaha</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_453_place_39">
        <placeName>X-Ray</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_453_place_40">
        <placeName>Albany</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_453_place_41">
        <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>
      </place>
    </listPlace>
    <listEvent>
      <event xml:id="ttu_453_event_0">
        <desc>Ia Drang-Pleiku Battles</desc>
      </event>
      <event xml:id="ttu_453_event_1">
        <desc>Civil War</desc>
      </event>
    </listEvent>
    <listPerson>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_0">
        <persName>Richard Verrone</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_1">
        <persName>Barbara Ann Weathers Geoghegan Johns</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_2">
        <persName>Barbara</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_3">
        <persName>Barbara</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_4">
        <persName>Jack</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_5">
        <persName>John</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_6">
        <persName>Jack</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_7">
        <persName>John</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_8">
        <persName>Jack</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_9">
        <persName>Jack Geoghegan</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_10">
        <persName>Jack Geoghegan</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_11">
        <persName>Jack</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_12">
        <persName>Nyerere</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_13">
        <persName>Cami</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_14">
        <persName>Jack Geoghegan</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_15">
        <persName>Jack</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_16">
        <persName>Jack</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_17">
        <persName>Jack</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_18">
        <persName>Jack</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_19">
        <persName>Jack</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_20">
        <persName>Jack</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_21">
        <persName>Hal Moore</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_22">
        <persName>Julie</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_23">
        <persName>General Moore</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_24">
        <persName>Julie Moore</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_25">
        <persName>Julie Moore</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_26">
        <persName>Julie Moore</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_27">
        <persName>Madeline Stowe</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_28">
        <persName>Jack</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_29">
        <persName>Jack</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_30">
        <persName>Jack</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_31">
        <persName>Jack</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_32">
        <persName>Jack</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_33">
        <persName>Cami</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_34">
        <persName>Jack</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_35">
        <persName>Jack</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_36">
        <persName>Jack</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_37">
        <persName>Jack</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_38">
        <persName>Jack</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_39">
        <persName>Jack</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_40">
        <persName>Jack</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_41">
        <persName>Cami</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_42">
        <persName>Jack</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_43">
        <persName>Jack</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_44">
        <persName>Barbara</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_45">
        <persName>Bill</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_46">
        <persName>Cami</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_47">
        <persName>Jack</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_48">
        <persName>Jack</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_49">
        <persName>Lieutenant Colonel Moore</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_50">
        <persName>eneral Moore</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_51">
        <persName>Camille</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_52">
        <persName>Jack</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_53">
        <persName>Jack</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_54">
        <persName>Jack</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_55">
        <persName>Jack</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_56">
        <persName>Jack</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_57">
        <persName>Aunt Pat</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_58">
        <persName>Jack</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_59">
        <persName>Jack</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_60">
        <persName>Aunt Pat</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_61">
        <persName>Jack</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_62">
        <persName>Jack</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_63">
        <persName>Camille</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_64">
        <persName>Pat</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_65">
        <persName>Cami</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_66">
        <persName>Camille</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_67">
        <persName>John</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_68">
        <persName>Jack</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_69">
        <persName>Jack</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_70">
        <persName>John</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_71">
        <persName>Cami</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_72">
        <persName>Jack</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_73">
        <persName>Joe Galloway</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_74">
        <persName>Tony Nadal</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_75">
        <persName>Jack</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_76">
        <persName>Joe</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_77">
        <persName>Joe</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_78">
        <persName>Tony</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_79">
        <persName>Tony</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_80">
        <persName>Tony</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_81">
        <persName>Billy</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_82">
        <persName>Tony</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_83">
        <persName>General Moore</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_84">
        <persName>Jack</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_85">
        <persName>John</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_86">
        <persName>Joe</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_87">
        <persName>Jack</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_88">
        <persName>Cami</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_89">
        <persName>Jack</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_90">
        <persName>Jack</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_91">
        <persName>Jack</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_92">
        <persName>Jack</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_93">
        <persName>Keri Russel</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_94">
        <persName>Keri Russel</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_95">
        <persName>Camille</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_96">
        <persName>Jack</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_97">
        <persName>Jack</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_98">
        <persName>Jack</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_99">
        <persName>Jack</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_100">
        <persName>Randall Wallace</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_101">
        <persName>Randall Wallace</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_102">
        <persName>Chris Klein</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_103">
        <persName>Rip Van Winkle</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_104">
        <persName>Jack</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_105">
        <persName>Camille</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_106">
        <persName>Jack</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_107">
        <persName>Major Ballou</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_108">
        <persName>Jack</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_453_person_109">
        <persName>Barbara</persName>
      </person>
    </listPerson>
    <listOrg>
      <org xml:id="ttu_453_org_0">
        <orgName>army</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="ttu_453_org_1">
        <orgName>Arcadian University</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="ttu_453_org_2">
        <orgName>PMC</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="ttu_453_org_3">
        <orgName>Pennsylvania Military College</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="ttu_453_org_4">
        <orgName>PMC</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="ttu_453_org_5">
        <orgName>Pennsylvania Military College</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="ttu_453_org_6">
        <orgName>University of Pennsylvania</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="ttu_453_org_7">
        <orgName>army</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="ttu_453_org_8">
        <orgName>army</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="ttu_453_org_9">
        <orgName>Catholic Relief Services</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="ttu_453_org_10">
        <orgName>Catholic Relief Services</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="ttu_453_org_11">
        <orgName>army</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="ttu_453_org_12">
        <orgName>army</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="ttu_453_org_13">
        <orgName>PMC</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="ttu_453_org_14">
        <orgName>Corps Candidates</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="ttu_453_org_15">
        <orgName>General Moore</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="ttu_453_org_16">
        <orgName>church</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="ttu_453_org_17">
        <orgName>US News</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="ttu_453_org_18">
        <orgName>1st Cav</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="ttu_453_org_19">
        <orgName>Cami</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="ttu_453_org_20">
        <orgName>Vietnam Archive</orgName>
      </org>
    </listOrg>
  </standOff>
</TEI>
