<?xml-model href="../schemas/ddhi.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ttu_461">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Transcript of an Interview with a Edward Charles Robinson</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>
          <orgName>Sam Johnson Vietnam Center and Archive</orgName>
        </authority>
        <date>
          <!--  Date of publication, e.g. for citation purposes  -->
        </date>
        <idno type="DDHI">ttu_461</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <recordingStmt>
          <recording xml:id="primary_recording" type="video" dur-iso="01:00:34">
            <!-- https://www.digi.com/resources/documentation/digidocs/90001437-13/reference/r_iso_8601_duration_format.htm -->
            <media url="https://vva.vietnam.ttu.edu/images.php?img=/OH/OH0461/OH0461.mp4" mimeType="MIMEvideo/mp4"/>
          </recording>
        </recordingStmt>
        <bibl xml:id="primary_transcription">
          <respStmt>
            <persName>Mark Steven Varela</persName>
            <orgName>Sam Johnson Vietnam Center and Archive</orgName>
            <resp ref="http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/trc.html">Transcriber</resp>
          </respStmt>
          <ref target="https://vva.vietnam.ttu.edu/images.php?img=/OH/OH0461/OH0461.pdf">Primary transcription</ref>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The Oral History Project of the Sam Johnson Vietnam Center and Archive</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application ident="DDHIEncoder" version="1.0">
          <desc>Conversion from Word docx to TEI xml.</desc>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en-us">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <particDesc>
        <person xml:id="ROBINSON"/>
        <person xml:id="MILAM"/>
      </particDesc>
      <settingDesc>
        <setting>
          <date when-iso="2005-11-10"/>
          <locale/>
        </setting>
      </settingDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <u who="ROBINSON"><orgName ref="#ttu_461_org_0">9th Assault Helicopter Battalion</orgName>, I was assigned with a group of aircraft that were to support the mission and to—what became known as <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_0">LZ (Landing Zone) X-Ray</placeName>. I was a UH-1D helicopter pilot, flight section leader.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">So you’re chopper pilot was scheduled to go into <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_1">X-Ray</placeName>, let’s back up a bit then. Tell me, first of all what was your commissioning source?</u>
      <u who="ROBINSON">My commissioning source was the <orgName ref="#ttu_461_org_1">United States Military Academy at West Point</orgName>, in <date when="1959-06">June of 1959</date>.</u>
      <u who="MILAM"><orgName ref="#ttu_461_org_2">Class of ’59</orgName>?</u>
      <u who="ROBINSON"><orgName ref="#ttu_461_org_3">Class of ’59</orgName>.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">Between <date when="1959">1959</date> and <date when="1965">1965</date>, six years in the military, when did you arrive at <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_2">Benning</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="ROBINSON">I arrived at <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_3">Benning</placeName> about the middle of <date when="1964">1964</date>, which wasn’t the assault unit at that time in training. I’d come back not long before from <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_4">Germany</placeName>, from a tour in <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_5">Germany</placeName> where I was a fixed wing aviator and an artillery battery commander. I went to school en route and wound up being assigned to <orgName ref="#ttu_461_org_4">11th Air Assault</orgName>, to the <orgName ref="#ttu_461_org_5">10th Air Transport Brigade</orgName>, which primarily consisted of the CB-2 Caribous and CH-47, the heavy lift aircraft at that time.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">So you were fixed wing qualified, and then you went to rotary school after <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_6">Germany</placeName>, on your way to <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_7">Benning</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="ROBINSON">No, I was fixed wing qualified and then while I was part of the <orgName ref="#ttu_461_org_6">10th Air Transport Brigade</orgName>, I went to rotary wing qualification course at <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_8">Fort Wolters</placeName>, to get qualify in the H-23 and ultimately the UH-1D, shortly before the unit deployed as the <orgName ref="#ttu_461_org_7">1st Cav</orgName>.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">So you came to <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_9">Benning</placeName>, in mid-summer, <date when="1964-08">August</date> or so of ’64.</u>
      <u who="ROBINSON">That’s correct.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">That’s about the time that—the <orgName ref="#ttu_461_org_8">1st Air Cav</orgName> had formed earlier than that but you were one year away from deployment with the cav. Were you involved in the training exercises for that next year, until <date when="1965-07">July of ’65</date>?</u>
      <u who="ROBINSON">No, I was in the <orgName ref="#ttu_461_org_9">270th Aircraft Maintenance Battalion</orgName>, which was supporting the CB-2 Caribous and I was in charge at one point putting the reverse pitch props on the Caribous aircraft, and I was not part of the UH-1 assault training that was going on at the time. That went on until about mid <date when="1965">’65</date>, and I went home on leave for a couple of weeks and mid <date when="1965">’65</date> while I was at home, I got a call that <persName ref="#ttu_461_person_0">President Johnson</persName> had converted the <orgName ref="#ttu_461_org_10">11th Air Assault</orgName> to the <orgName ref="#ttu_461_org_11">1st Air Cavalry Division</orgName> and that we would be deploying to <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_10">Vietnam</placeName>. They asked me if I was UH-1D qualified, and I said “Yes, I was.” I had, just before that, been qualified in the UH-1D. So it wasn’t an urgent matter for me to come right back. So I finished my leave, I went back to <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_11">Fort Benning</placeName> with my family and then I deployed with the division when they shipped out, I think it was in <date when="1965-08">August of ’65</date>, if I remember correctly. We deployed in the middle of the night in combat gear, loaded onto buses. My family was there ready to part—my family did not stay because they’d anticipated possibly some things that were going on in the area. There were a lot of causalities being reported in the <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_12">Fort Benning</placeName> area, even before the <orgName ref="#ttu_461_org_12">1st Cav</orgName> deployed, including neighbors around. One of our neighbors had lost a husband with special forces over there. My family decided that they wanted to go back to <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_13">New York</placeName> State, where my wife’s parents and my parents were located. So they decided they wanted to go home, so we sold our house and—we shipped out in the middle of the night, and they shortly left after, to go to <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_14">New York</placeName> State. We took the bus to <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_15">Charleston, South Carolina</placeName>, with the division—pretty much what was depicted in the movie, leaving in the middle of the night. We arrived at <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_16">Charleston</placeName>, we got on board the ship, I was on the Darby. We left on the Darby, went down the East Coast, through the <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_17">Panama Canal</placeName>, up the West Coast to <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_18">Long Beach</placeName>, where we docked and provisioned for <date>a few days</date>. Then, we sailed across the Pacific. I was with the—on the Darby at that time was the 1st of the <orgName ref="#ttu_461_org_13">9th Cavalry</orgName>, primarily. There was a few of us aviators mixed in with them. So I deployed basically with the 1st of the 9th. When we landed in the <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_19">Qui Nhon Harbor</placeName>, ultimately—it was a thirty-day voyage as I can recall, we did a lot of training on board the Darby.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">What kind?</u>
      <u who="ROBINSON">Firing off of the fan tail, that type of thing. Not training such as an air cav, but there was some training and classes, and things going on board. We landed in <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_20">Qui Nhon Harbor</placeName>. Deployed onto the landing craft where—the landing craft then landed on the beach at <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_21">Qui Nhon</placeName>. Standing on the beach was <persName ref="#ttu_461_person_1">General Westmoreland</persName>, to greet us as we came on shore. Then, some other people from the battalion deployed with the aircraft, in aircraft carriers, but we did not so we were picked up by helicopters and we landed far from <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_22">Qui Nhon</placeName>, inland through the central highlands and landed in <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_23">An Khe</placeName>, what became our basecamp. At that time it was pretty much—</u>
      <u who="MILAM">You had to build it, you had to build it.</u>
      <u who="ROBINSON">You had to build it, yes. We landed at what was an old French PSP runway, as a matter of fact. There was no basecamp as such, so we did a lot of cutting down trees, digging out terminate mounds and doing the trenching around the areas where we would put up tents. We actually slept in “pup” tents there, for—I think it was one or two months, whatever it was. It was a short period of time. Then we got general purpose tents, GP tents, and we moved into those. We had—then we were offered the opportunity for those who wanted to build their own structure, to put up a more substantially space, which I did with a couple of others as we had some free time from flying, or when we weren’t assigned to a mission, we would work on a Hooch, as we called it and a more substantial place to sleep.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">You had not trained in the <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_24">United States</placeName> with these <orgName ref="#ttu_461_org_14">1st Air Cav</orgName> troops, that you were going to be expected to take into combat, going before you left. How much training, once you got into <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_25">Vietnam</placeName>, did you have with troops before you went into combat?</u>
      <u who="ROBINSON">(Chuckles) Very little, I would say. We went out onto operational combat missions almost immediately, around the <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_26">Happy Valley</placeName> area. I learned very quickly over the first couple of weeks the procedures. I had quite a bit of fixed wing time, I probably had about fifteen-hundred hours of fixed wing time. Not specifically operating with rotary wing, but the people that were flying and had been with the <orgName ref="#ttu_461_org_15">11th Air Assault</orgName> were very well trained and qualified, and then they transferred that very quickly.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">You were captain at this time?</u>
      <u who="ROBINSON">I was captain, yeah.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">What would you say was the biggest challenge from, not so much because of combat, but what was the biggest challenge to go from what you had been doing prior to being deployed, to what you were expected to do? Was it mechanical with the aircraft? Was it procedural? Or was it flying in formation? What were—</u>
      <u who="ROBINSON">I think it was something of all of those. The formation, we learned quickly that the formation was changing from one to the other. Some of the terminology that they used, but I found it came very quickly, it wasn’t really a problem. I would say within the three or four weeks, I felt very comfortable. Of course, we hadn’t really been in any big combat at that time.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">What about night flying? Had you done any training in night flying, as far as with troops?</u>
      <u who="ROBINSON">No—well, we did do some night lifts in <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_27">Happy Valley</placeName>, over in <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_28">Mang Yang Pass</placeName> area, up around. We flew up around <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_29">Phu Cat</placeName>, which became a major air force base. At that time, it was a special forces camp, we did a lot of operations up around <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_30">Highway 1</placeName>. Let’s see, it was August, September, October, we had probably two or three months before the big operation, over in the <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_31">Ia Drang Valley</placeName>.MILAM: So, you’ve come into this country where <orgName ref="#ttu_461_org_16">America</orgName> has not really experienced any large battles, even though the 173rd has been there for a while, the <orgName ref="#ttu_461_org_17">marines</orgName> had been there for a while. We hadn’t experienced—as a nation we hadn’t experienced a very large operation, at least speaking—doesn’t mean we weren’t suffering casualties and those kinds of things. What was your anticipation about operations? Did you anticipate that you would have the kind of operations the <name type="event" ref="#ttu_461_event_0">Ia Drang</name> becomes? Or were you believing war would be the kind of things we’d seen so far, which was smaller?</u>
      <u who="ROBINSON">Having come from studying military tactics and strategy and that type of thing, with a military background, I really kind of expected that we ultimately, would be what we got into although—so I guess I wasn’t really surprised that that happened because it happened in every other war, why wouldn’t it happen there? So I wouldn’t say that I was comfortable with going in there. Nobody really knows until you’ve flown into combat, what your reactions are going to be. But I wouldn’t say I was surprised by what happened, other than what I learned later on to the extent of the commitment of the <orgName ref="#ttu_461_org_18">North Vietnamese</orgName> and the type of attitude that they brought into the <name type="event" ref="#ttu_461_event_1">Ia Drang</name>, that was probably stronger than what I expected that we would encounter. I think that was brought out in the book too. I think everybody was kind of surprised by that.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">Well, I think, you kind of hit on it with your background at the academy, you would’ve known some military history. So, we come into this war. We have this new delivery system placing men into combat from the air. So I was wondering if maybe you saw it differently because of your being at the <orgName ref="#ttu_461_org_19">academy</orgName> background versus someone that would say, “A warrant officer was flying an aircraft.”</u>
      <u who="ROBINSON">I would suspect, I thought it was a very powerful tool, the air cavalry concept. I thought it was a very formable force. Certainly, it has certain vulnerabilities which I came to be known and associate later on in the aircraft survivability program manager later in my career, the vulnerabilities of the aircraft. We were picking up bullet heads rounds and bullet heads in the aircraft. Matter of fact, I think I got the first one in our company. Through my tail rotor drive shaft, when we were over by the <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_32">Phu Cat</placeName> area, right shortly after we got there. But it didn’t seem to be anything that caused you have to go down. It didn’t destroy the aircraft. It was small rounds, AK-47 type of rounds.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">So the experience at <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_33">Phu Cat</placeName> that you had, was one of the first times that American helicopters had come into smaller fire and was affected by it, but not shot down?</u>
      <u who="ROBINSON">I think I was the first aircraft in <orgName ref="#ttu_461_org_20">B Company two-two-nine</orgName> (Editor’s note: 229th) that suffered a bullet wound, certain milestone our first bullet wound. We removed it, later on removed the drive shaft, replaced the drive shaft. But while we were operating up and down on Highway 1, we would go through a pass in <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_34">highway one</placeName> and typically every time we went through that pass, there were clouds. So you kind of low through the path. But you’d come out of there with two or three out of the four aircraft in the fight, with some kind of bullet wound in them. So there was somebody operating them obviously. But it didn’t affect the operation.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">Yeah, it could’ve been just a <orgName ref="#ttu_461_org_21">VC (Viet Cong)</orgName> out in a rice patty with an AK, takes a couple shots at you. But it wasn’t .50 cal and it wasn’t heavy aircraft. It wasn’t the kinds of things you experienced.</u>
      <u who="ROBINSON">Later on in my second tour of <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_35">Vietnam</placeName>, I was an aircraft maintenance  commander over there. We would fix those things overnight very quickly. We often put temporary patches on things, even with three-hundred mile an hour, five-hundred miles an hour, we would put tape on it. You could fix proxy bullet holes or fix bullet holes in rotor blades, heat them up overnight and you would have a lot of your aircraft reported down for damage and the next morning we’d have them all back up again. So we worked at night fixing them. That was my second experience. </u>
      <u who="MILAM">Your second term. So you’re in-country now. You got a base that you had to build in <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_36">An Khe</placeName>. For a couple of months, you had an operation going on in <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_37">Happy Valley</placeName>. No battalion sized operations I don’t believe.</u>
      <u who="ROBINSON">I really can’t recall the size of the operations were but they were involved probably a couple platoons from each company. They would mix up. We had <orgName ref="#ttu_461_org_22">A</orgName>, <orgName ref="#ttu_461_org_23">B</orgName>, <orgName ref="#ttu_461_org_24">C</orgName> lift Companies and <orgName ref="#ttu_461_org_25">229th</orgName> and <orgName ref="#ttu_461_org_26">D Company</orgName> was the gunship company. Gunship company always had a few aircraft out there, four aircraft. They put two on each side of a platoon basically. We had a couple of platoons out there, maybe a company sized one once in a while.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">Sure. Enemy contact wise, nothing big? Anything you can recall?</u>
      <u who="ROBINSON">No, not before <name type="event" ref="#ttu_461_event_2">LZ X-Ray</name>, after <name type="event" ref="#ttu_461_event_3">LZ X-Ray</name>.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">Understanding that any contact for the person involved is a big contact, but at least as far as looking at the size of the ends and everything, there was nothing that came along until <name type="event" ref="#ttu_461_event_4">X-Ray</name> and your units that would—what about, did you get any—what was going on in <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_38">Vietnam</placeName>, as far as other units were concerned. Did you start to get through the <orgName ref="#ttu_461_org_27">Stars and Stripes</orgName> or through any other kinds of intelligence to know what was going on in the rest of the country?</u>
      <u who="ROBINSON">Well, the <orgName ref="#ttu_461_org_28">marines</orgName> had some units operating over there and they had been there flying CH-34s, and of course there were some units over there as part of navigation units, part of special forces that were flying the old CH-41 bananas, before that. Shortly before we arrived, the <orgName ref="#ttu_461_org_29">101st</orgName> had an element. I think a brigade over there and they helped protect the area to some extent that we were going into there. One of the first things that happened when we arrived there was the <orgName ref="#ttu_461_org_30">101st</orgName> had gotten all their aircrafts shot down and they landed in an NVA, North Vietnamese basecamp area, so it was said. They had all of their aircraft shot down. The <orgName ref="#ttu_461_org_31">1st Cav</orgName> was asked to send the unit down there to help get them out of there, which they did. That was shortly after we arrived there. It was one of the first times. That went off of the PSP landing at the ol’ French strip there, where they formed up a pickup force to go down there and help relive that <orgName ref="#ttu_461_org_32">101st</orgName>, before <orgName ref="#ttu_461_org_33">the 1st Cav</orgName> got to even operating. So it was said to be of <orgName ref="#ttu_461_org_34">North Vietnamese</orgName>, where the <orgName ref="#ttu_461_org_35">101st</orgName> was operating.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">So let’s talk about <date when="1964-11-13">November 13th</date> and <date when="1964-11-14">14th</date>. I want to know about <date when="1964-11-13">November 13th</date> first, with the assumption that <date when="1964-11-14">November 14th</date> kicks off. What was your day like on <date when="1964-11-13">13th</date>? Had you already moved to <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_39">Pleiku</placeName>? Moved your chopper to, I guess, Holloway?</u>
      <u who="ROBINSON">As I recall, we had deployed to <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_40">Holloway</placeName>. Certain elements of the company that were—some units and crews of A, B, C, D were operating off the runway at <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_41">Holloway</placeName> there. They had a runway that could carry large fixed wing aircraft and we were often sleeping in the aircraft and we would kick the doors off of the aircraft and use them as shelters to sleep on the ground in the aircraft, right there in <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_42">Holloway</placeName>. We were operating down around, in the <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_43">Plei Me</placeName> area, as I recall. I’ve got pictures of it; I took in black and white that could have been taken on the 13th or at least the 14th. I remember one incident going into <name type="event" ref="#ttu_461_event_5">LZ X-Ray</name>, I know we were at <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_44">Plei Me</placeName> because I remember taking off out of there and out of <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_45">Plei Me</placeName>, and landing nap-of-the-earth, into this small LZ they had set up and that was recounted in the book, I think, where they structured a small LZ where it could handle two aircraft. I know we went out of <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_46">Plei Me</placeName> and went nap-of-the-earth, wall to wall. Two aircraft at a time were landing into some trips in <name type="event" ref="#ttu_461_event_6">LZ X-Ray</name>. I remember that specifically on <date when="1964-11-14">the 14th</date>.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">I see. Okay, what word do you get about the extent of this operation on <date when="1964-11-14">the 14th</date>?</u>
      <u who="ROBINSON">It was a hot LZ, I know that. They had run into some big trouble, none of the details I didn’t know at the time. I know that there was no feedback coming, it was a hot LZ. We were waiting for permissions from assignments to go in there. But I didn’t really know much about what was going on in the ground initially there. Although I did become aware of it because we started flying around, and I have another photo I took from the air while we were flying around in <name type="event" ref="#ttu_461_event_7">LZ X-Ray</name>. We were heading toward <name type="event" ref="#ttu_461_event_8">LZ X-Ray</name> and there must been at least two platoons because I have a silhouette against smoke on the ground in <name type="event" ref="#ttu_461_event_9">LZ X-Ray</name> of four helicopters, and in the background on the <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_47">Chu Prong Mountain</placeName>, I can see a stick of smoke, from a stick bomb is being dropped from a B-52 Arc Light strike, which I think it may have been the first Arc Light strike they ever conducted in <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_48">Vietnam</placeName>. I can see both the smoke and the <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_49">Chu Prong Mountain</placeName> in my photo. Which I provided, and four helicopters silhouetted against the smoke in the LZ, which the fire was coming out of the <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_50">LZ Falcon</placeName>. Two of my classmates, by the way,  were in charge of the artillery there. Captain <persName ref="#ttu_461_person_2">Don Davis</persName>, the battery commander, was classmate of mine. Captain <persName ref="#ttu_461_person_3">Holly Langford</persName> was the fire direction officer I found out later on, he also was a classmate. Another classmate, Captain <persName ref="#ttu_461_person_4">Buse Tully</persName>, was later killed in <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_51">Vietnam</placeName> in his second tour, was also part of the elements that came to relieve them at <name type="event" ref="#ttu_461_event_10">X-Ray</name> and <name type="event" ref="#ttu_461_event_11">Albany</name>.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">Just as a side, you were <orgName ref="#ttu_461_org_36">class of ’59</orgName>. How many helicopter pilots were there in the <orgName ref="#ttu_461_org_37">class of ’59</orgName>?</u>
      <u who="ROBINSON">I don’t know—well I know we had fixed wing and rotary wing. We all went to rotary wing first because commissioner officers went to fixed-wing. They didn’t go into rotary wing. Warrant officers went to rotary wing, very few went to fixed wing. Then, you would transition later on to the other one. While I was in <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_52">Germany</placeName>, we had about fifteen classmates flying fixed wing over there in aviation unit. How many ultimately ended up in rotary wing, I don’t know. Some of them were flying Caribous in the <orgName ref="#ttu_461_org_38">10th Air Transport Brigade</orgName> and ultimately transitioned for their second tour. I know several did that.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">Well certainly in <date when="1959">1959</date>, <orgName ref="#ttu_461_org_39">United States</orgName> involvement in <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_53">Vietnam</placeName> was virtually non-existent, a handful of advisors. But when you went to fixed wing aircraft school in <date when="1959">1959</date>, or shortly thereafter, there was probably not an anticipation on your part that you’d  become a helicopter pilot.</u>
      <u who="ROBINSON">Well, I think there was. Although I didn’t give it much thought, I wasn’t— when I first went there, I wasn’t too familiar with what aviator’s career patterns ultimately became. Most of the fixed-wing pilots converted, were transitioned to rotary wing at some point in time.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">So back to <name type="event" ref="#ttu_461_event_12">X-Ray</name>. The morning, the first—I think there were four lifts that go out in the morning and what I know about the operation, there was little enemy contact for the first couple of lifts and about lifts three and four there they started getting shot at, and then all hell breaks loose. Where did your involvement start with that operation?</u>
      <u who="ROBINSON">Well, I don’t know exactly. But I know that—because we did so many of these things, so many different units and they were all very similar. I mean as far as what we did to support the ground units. I never kept track of a timeline or anything like that on these specific units. Supporting one unit was pretty much like supporting any other unit. We changed all the time, we changed crews, we change crew chiefs, we changed aircrafts. It’s hard to keep track unless you were really focusing on that. But I know at one point during the day there, while we were loitering with the other aircraft and I have some photos of the group there, couple of the aircraft anyway, we were called on to go into the LZ into the two ship landing zone, which became a particular issue for me because there was a citation written later on that causes me to remember that. As I said, we went onto treetop level because it was a hot LZ, and as we approached the LZ, in two ship increments, there were two aircrafts in front of me, I started receiving groundfire vertically right in front of the aircraft, I can see the tracers going up right in front of the feet to the extent that it caused me to jerk my feet off at one point in time. Anyways, we went high speed through that. They got a quick shot at you vertically through the trees, because it was all trees there. We landed in the LZ, dropped off the troops and I looked over to my co-pilot, Chief Warrant Officer <persName ref="#ttu_461_person_5">Jimmy Johnson</persName> noticed an aircraft down in the trees, to my right. So I picked up to hover and hovered over there, sat down and told my wingman, who was behind me, to clear the LZ to take off, so he did. I noticed in the aircraft that the crew was still there in the aircraft. So I sent my crew chief gunner, that day was <persName ref="#ttu_461_person_6">Sergeant Pavlovich</persName>, told him to get the crew out of the aircraft and help them get over. So he went over and the crew got out of the aircraft, they took the guns and radios and loaded them on my aircraft, and then the infantry brought over some wounded and loaded them on my aircraft. I took off, climbed out and at some point, I think it was right after coming out of the LZ, I heard a voice from an A1-E pilot calling for help, begging someone to come help his wingman who had gone down and was burning down on the ground, not too far from the LZ. I could see the smoke for it. Then I heard a voice, who I think was warrant officer <persName ref="#ttu_461_person_7">Bob Kies</persName>, who was the man behind me I believe, also at that point in time, my wingman. He said he was going over there and landing by the A1-E. I kind of over flew the area and heard, I think it was <persName ref="#ttu_461_person_8">Kies</persName>, saying it was on fire and rounds were popping off. I overflew the area and he was going to the aircraft. So I had wounded on board and the crew and took them up to <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_54">Pleiku</placeName> and I brought them up into the <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_55">MASH (Mobile Army Surgical Hospital)</placeName> station, the wounded into the station in <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_56">Pleiku</placeName>. Every time we would go in there, the flight crews while we were on final, I think he called on the radio he was coming in there. They come out running of their MASH program and meet the aircraft, and they’d always bring a big bucket of water because they had to wash the blood out of the aircraft. At that time there didn’t seem to be anybody bags. They brought in KIA (Killed in Action), they were often wrapped in ponchos and you would get a lot of blood in the aircraft, and they would come out running with water and take the wounded off and everything. I dropped the crew off there at the <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_57">MASH</placeName> station also, because it was not too far off from the air facility there where we were operating out of. </u>
      <u who="MILAM">So this timing was—did you think it was <date when="1964-11-14">the 14th</date>? Or was it the next day?</u>
      <u who="ROBINSON">It seems to me that it was that time when I was coming out of <name type="event" ref="#ttu_461_event_13">LZ X-Ray</name>, after having picked up that crew. I couldn’t swear to that, but that’s the recollection I had. Voice that I had heard, associated with <persName ref="#ttu_461_person_9">Kies</persName>. I read later on or saw something that he did land near the A1-E.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">The A1-E that went down, was the only fixed wing that was shot down in this?</u>
      <u who="ROBINSON">That’s all I know of. I think what happened, what I heard later on, was that the pilot—they dropped bombs with devices on them and got underneath him and I think he went down with his own bomb. They blew up because they would come in low and drop, and if you got close to an explosion or if it was over when it exploded, I think that’s what happened but I can’t say that from any personal knowledge.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">So you came in, either later that day or next day, how many trips did you make back into it?</u>
      <u who="ROBINSON">Actually, I don’t know. I can’t say.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">A bunch?</u>
      <u who="ROBINSON">I really don’t know.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">Now, there was a—let me talk a little about this. You did a lot of medevac, I assume. Not official medevac, but you were bringing in supplies and they were putting troops on that were wounded.</u>
      <u who="ROBINSON">Not only that, but we would get calls to go in often, to go pick up people because the medevac people often would not go in. They had a policy that if it was a hot LZ and they didn’t have guns, which they didn’t, they wouldn’t go in. I think <persName ref="#ttu_461_person_10">Bruce Crandall</persName> mentioned this in the book and I remember that very vividly too, we had to do medevacs because the medevacs wouldn’t go in. At least in that stage of the operation over there. They were probably as new to this as we were, you know?</u>
      <u who="MILAM">Were the medevacs, at that time they were not armed, I assumed. </u>
      <u who="ROBINSON">No.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">They weren’t supposed to be armed. They had a big red cross on the front. The army did not have Cobra gunships, but it had the Huey B model?</u>
      <u who="ROBINSON">B models and some C models. The B models had a little bit more vertical lift, they were designed to hover, while the C models were designed with a little bit different rotor system, for a little bit different speed and they didn’t have as good hover capabilities. But the B and C models which were still the short cockpit, not the longer cockpit, the UH-1D and later the UH-NH had an extended cockpit to carry more troops. The A, B, and C models were short cockpits and Bs and Cs essentially were the gunships. They mounted guns, rockets, and machine guns. Ultimately miniguns.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">They did put miniguns on those?</u>
      <u who="ROBINSON">I can’t remember if there were miniguns at first, when we were starting off over there, later on they got miniguns, I believe. Nor did we, as lift ships going into LZ. For example, when we went into <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_58">X-Ray</placeName>, we did not have the X23 thirty caliber machine guns, on the outside doors. We had some aircrafts that had the thirty caliber machine guns, the M30 machine guns extended from bungie cords. Some just had M16s on the doors. We did not have the guns yet. Those were added as mod-kits a few months later, the mod-kits came out and they had to be mounted on hardpoints on the side of the aircraft.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">So, you’re saying that at <name type="event" ref="#ttu_461_event_14">LZ X-Ray</name> and <name type="event" ref="#ttu_461_event_15">Albany</name> and this operation begun, the Hueys did not have M16s. Was there an MOS  (Military Occupational Specialty Code) door-gunner at that time?</u>
      <u who="ROBINSON">I don’t know. There was a door-gunner, assigned usually from an infantry unit. He was tasked from an infantry unit. I guess they were tasked to provide so many people for door gunners, so these guys come over from the infantry units and served as door-gunners.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">So, it came later that there was an actual crew of door-gunners on your Huey?</u>
      <u who="ROBINSON">We didn’t have the XO23 gun-mounted machine guns mounted on the doors. Most people did not have breast plates at the time. We didn’t have a lot of breast plates at the time. We didn’t have a lot of breast plates for the pilots or the crew chiefs. Those did not come in quantities until later on. At least, first two or three months there were very few of them. Matter of fact, we had a shipment of machine guns over at <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_59">Happy Valley</placeName>, before <name type="event" ref="#ttu_461_event_16">LZ X-Ray</name>. A shipment of machine guns and load of breast plates that were going to be carted out onto a field at <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_60">Happy Valley</placeName> and an aircraft took off out of <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_61">An Khe</placeName>, went through the <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_62">Mang Yang Pass</placeName>. When they arrived, we were out in the field. They took off before dawn and there was clouds down in the pass, and they couldn’t get through the pass. They were bringing out coffee, breakfast, machine guns, and breast plates. They took off and they had to go climb up into the clouds, and nothing was ever heard from that aircraft ever again. One of the sisters of one of the crew chiefs from that mission comes regularly to the calvary reunions. I’ve met with her several times. I can’t think of her name right off hand, but she has never heard anything from her brother. The aircraft went down somewhere in the trees, well I don’t know where it went down. What the practice was at that point of time, since there weren’t really any navigation facilities, was you had to go to IFR (Instrument Flight Rules), instrument rules. You climbed up into the clouds and you headed for the coast, normally the clouds clear over the coast and you would come back in underneath it. They never had any radio calls either, so it seems it wasn’t the situation with them. It must’ve gone down somewhere, in that deep jungle over there, a lot of it was triple canopy. As matter of fact, after that aircraft didn’t arrive and they couldn’t find the aircraft for about two or three weeks after that, every time we didn’t have a mission to fly or we were loitering around, we were out flying around, hovering, looking at any holes in the trees in the area, trying to find this aircraft and that went on for two, three weeks maybe a month and they never found it. To the best of my knowledge, it never was found. The sister of the crew member still doesn’t know what happened to her—</u>
      <u who="MILAM">Is he still listed as missing?</u>
      <u who="ROBINSON">He is still listed as missing.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">Hopefully, someday well do some—you mentioned doors. Did you take the doors off for this operation?</u>
      <u who="ROBINSON">The doors were slid back and pinned with a safety wire on, it was put in and the doors were back. Never used the doors because of the urgency of getting people in and out. The procedure was—and they saw procedure was, they climbed in, they took the seats out too. They sat on the floor and when we touched down, they were out the door as soon as we touched, they we were gone, normally. It was a very quick precision type of operation normally, you’re in and out to minimize exposure to the aircraft and the crews on the ground as much as possible. It didn’t seem to affect the dynamics of the aircraft at all.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">Yeah, we have a Huey out on display out in the <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_63">Angel Fire, New Mexico</placeName>, memorial out there and we had a big celebration. We had put it there and we had several thousand <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_64">Vietnam</placeName> veterans and so many of them were looking at it and saying, “Geez, I didn’t know they had doors!” Because it came with the doors shut.</u>
      <u who="ROBINSON">At some point, I think the doors may have been removed, I can’t recall.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">Well, as an infantry solider you wouldn’t even noticed it was back. You would know that wasn’t there when you went on the aircraft. So did you go into <name type="event" ref="#ttu_461_event_17">Albany</name>? Were you involved in that operation?</u>
      <u who="ROBINSON">I remember going into <name type="event" ref="#ttu_461_event_18">Albany</name>, I don’t remember the extent of the operation there. I remember, one night going out in operation, in the pitch-black night. Landing to a flashlight or beanbag light on the ground over unknown trees and dropping off troops and picking up wounded and flying out of there, I think that was <name type="event" ref="#ttu_461_event_19">Albany</name>, in a night operation. It was so pitch-black; you couldn’t really see anything except occasionally an aircraft would drop flares, which would just mess up your night vision out there. It was the scariest night I’d ever flown. We were flying formation with just those lights three lights on top of the aircraft, with no light at all outside. I mean, we had formation lights on top of the aircraft and they were masked off so you could only see them above, so the ground couldn’t see them. That was one of the early night missions that I flew and it was—I was flying co-pilot at the time; I wasn’t flying pilot. I can’t remember who I was flying with but I think it was one of the platoon leaders, I remember going in there and landing in the middle of the night and I think that was <name type="event" ref="#ttu_461_event_20">Albany</name>.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">Now, you served out your tour. You had gone there in essentially <date when="1966-08">August</date>, so your twelve months would’ve been up <date when="1966-08">August ’66</date> or so. Did you spend that whole twelve months attached to the <orgName ref="#ttu_461_org_40">1st Air Cav</orgName>?</u>
      <u who="ROBINSON">I was with—I flew the whole time I was there. I flew as a pilot section leader. Later on, flight section leader.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">And out of <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_65">An Khe</placeName> for that whole time?</u>
      <u who="ROBINSON">We went down—later on, most of the time we were operating out of <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_66">An Khe</placeName> under <persName ref="#ttu_461_person_11">General Kinnard</persName>. We were building the base camps, securing the base camps, securing the area around there and trying to clean out that area around <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_67">An Khe</placeName>. Later on, when the new division commander came in, and he came in a couple of months before I left, <persName ref="#ttu_461_person_12">General Kinnard</persName>, I think,  must’ve gone left about June, July—maybe <date when="1966-06">June</date> or <date when="1966-07">July</date>. <persName ref="#ttu_461_person_13">General Norton</persName> he started—we moved out, and went down to <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_68">Tan Son Nhut</placeName>—no, not Tan Son Nhut, along the coast, I can’t remember the name of the town.</u>
      <u who="MILAM"><placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_69">Tuy Hoa</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="ROBINSON">I think it was <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_70">Tuy Hoa</placeName>. We flew operations down there. Let’s talk about <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_71">Tuy Hoa</placeName>, I think that was the one I was thinking about. There was a big episode there, where we lost a couple of people and out of the battalion. One of them my hoochmate, Captain <persName ref="#ttu_461_person_14">Larry Woods</persName>, who came in at the sixth-month point after we had been there, he was one of the new guys. Very fine fellow, he had won a writing contest, a contest on patriotism for the <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_72">Valley</placeName> Forge something or other. Just a real fine fellow and he had the bunk next to mine in the hooch, and he was flying the same position behind me in my platoon. We made multiple landings into an LZ. He was in—I flew number three in the 1st platoon, he was flying number three in the 2nd platoon, I remember that because I always flew number three, which is the guy who is supposed to take over if the platoon leader goes down—second section leader or the company commander who was leading the flight. It was announced by the co-pilot and I’m trying to remember who it was at the time but I don’t remember if it was <persName ref="#ttu_461_person_15">Captain Woods</persName> that his pilot had been hit. We went back and dropped off the first lift and came back and dropped off another lift the second time he— the co-pilot announced that his pilot was dead. That was <persName ref="#ttu_461_person_16">Larry Woods</persName>. <persName ref="#ttu_461_person_17">Larry</persName> was hit and apparently opted to go on and finish the lift and essentially died. I think he was struck right above the breast plate. He had a wife and some children. At the same time I think it was another aircraft, from <orgName ref="#ttu_461_org_41">Company C</orgName>, and I can’t remember the warrant officer’s name, was screaming that he was going down and he went down in a ball of flames and burned—everybody on the aircraft must’ve been killed. This was a couple of weeks before I left over there. So I never really did find out too much after that and my time came to rotate—we did operate and we span out after being there, and I think General <persName ref="#ttu_461_person_18">Kinnard</persName> secured the barrier around <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_73">An Khe</placeName> and as much as possible in <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_74">Pleiku</placeName> and fought after—we were kind of spread out, advanced out along the coast.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">So you came home around <date when="1966-08">August</date> or so, after your tour. What was your duty station when you first came back?</u>
      <u who="ROBINSON">I came back, I went to—I changed to transportation court, I was artillery battery commander. There was no aviation unit at that time, there was no aviation branch. Also, I was interested in going to graduate school. Having been an artillery battery commander and on ground duty and then a navigator, navigators were on short supply, the artillery was not interested in sending me to graduate school because I was already kind of loaned out to the navigation folk as it was. Whereas within the transportation branch, aviation was a part of your core functions or what could be a career path within transportation. So I came back and went to the transportation advance course, I came back from <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_75">Germany</placeName>, I was headed to the artillery advance course. I went through the advanced course and then I became an instructor in the air mobility branch there as well. I stayed there until my next tour, which—I went back shortly after the new year, right during the <name type="event" ref="#ttu_461_event_21">Tet Offensive</name>, I went back for my second tour. I went to <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_76">Phu Loi</placeName>, <orgName ref="#ttu_461_org_42">11th Combat Aviation Battalion</orgName>. I was detailed as the commander of the <orgName ref="#ttu_461_org_43">393rd Transportation Aircraft Maintenance</orgName> detachment, which was assigned to the <orgName ref="#ttu_461_org_44">128th Assault Helicopter Company</orgName>, part of the <orgName ref="#ttu_461_org_45">11th Combat Aviation Battalion</orgName> at <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_77">Phu Loi</placeName>. Then I commanded the <orgName ref="#ttu_461_org_46">393rd</orgName> to a unit for about six months and then I went battalion headquarters as a battalion S4. While I was in both of those jobs, I would go out and fly initiates with the UH-1, with the <orgName ref="#ttu_461_org_47">128th</orgName> and also with the black cats. I’m trying to think of the black cats, they were a Chinook unit, because I had gone to a Chinook transition just before I went over to my second tour, I had gone down to <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_78">Fort Rucker</placeName> and gone through the CH-47 transition. I expected the pilot will be flying the CH-47 in my second tour. So I would go and fly out missions with black cats and the Chinooks. They had big CH-47 C models, which were the most advanced lift Chinook at the time. I enjoyed flying with them.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">So, your second tour is, when did you go? You said—<name type="event" ref="#ttu_461_event_22">Tet</name> is <date when="1968-01-30">30th of January ’68</date>. Right before that? Or when did you go?</u>
      <u who="ROBINSON">I went to transition shortly before <date when="1968-12-25">Christmas</date>, because I remember finishing it right before <date when="1968-12-25">Christmas</date>. I came back from <date when="1968-12-25">Christmas</date> and I was going to deploy the first part of <date when="1968-01">January</date>, right after <date when="1968-12-31">New Year’s</date>. The <name type="event" ref="#ttu_461_event_23">Tet Offensive</name>, as I recall was—because we kept getting rocketed in <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_79">Phu Loi</placeName>, in the base camp area. The <name type="event" ref="#ttu_461_event_24">Tet Offensive</name> had been going on and was very hot item at the time. It was very well—everybody knows I think. So I was over there and it must have been from <date when="1968-01">January ’68</date> through <date when="1969-01">January ’69</date> I think, or <date when="1969-12">December of ’69</date>.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">Did you have another tour?</u>
      <u who="ROBINSON">No, I had two tours in <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_80">Vietnam</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">Now you had three, almost three years between your first tour and your second tour.</u>
      <u who="ROBINSON">No, I had about a year and a half. Less than a year and a half.</u>
      <u who="MILAM"><date when="1966">’66</date>—year and a half. Did you see—just thinking of it in from your own operations standpoint, your own helicopter business that you were in. Did you see much difference in the troops you were now commanding versus you were there before?</u>
      <u who="ROBINSON">Yes, yes, yes. When we went over there, everyone that you knew were dedicated, gung-ho, committed to the mission in the <orgName ref="#ttu_461_org_48">1st Cav</orgName>. The second time, at least in the base camp area where I was there, that was the <orgName ref="#ttu_461_org_49">1st Infantry Division</orgName> Area, they mostly operated around the <orgName ref="#ttu_461_org_50">Vietnamese</orgName> troops around there. You can tell there was a lot of marijuana. There was a lot of—there may have been a drug culture for all I know, but at that time guys were going off to R&amp;R (Rest and Recuperation), to <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_81">Thailand</placeName> and wherever, and getting influenced there or whatever. But in a year and a half between, I noticed a big difference in the attitude and moral of the troops.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">Of essentially the infantry troops?</u>
      <u who="ROBINSON">Yeah. The infantry troops that I dealt with there—there was not an infantry unit at <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_82">Phu Loi</placeName>. There were out of <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_83">Di An</placeName>, there were out of <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_84">Cu Chi</placeName>, and other areas around there. I didn’t have a lot of contact with the infantry troops, but we did have some infantry assigned, I think as part of the elements there, a lot of door gunners and that kind of thing. But going around and placing the barracks, I had people that were—It was a totally different thing. They did not have permeant barracks that were built. They had permeant mess halls and the conditions were much better. We were in the jungle essentially on our own, the first time, the second time they had <orgName ref="#ttu_461_org_51">PAE (Pacific Architects and Engineers)</orgName> that was brought in, under contract to build all of these facilities, put up electrical wiring and that type of thing. The base camp was totally different. They had a more or less a permeant base camp. The aircraft were revetted so that it wasn’t sitting out in the middle of where we were, they put up a PSP (Steel Planlink). It was much more stable and it wasn’t that far from <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_85">Saigon</placeName> either. You could drive down to <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_86">Saigon</placeName>, in a Jeep down there if you wanted to take the chance. So the troops had access to a lot of things of which we didn’t know about, but the disciplinary problems were much different the second time.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">Would you say at <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_87">An Khe</placeName>, when the <orgName ref="#ttu_461_org_52">1st Air Cav</orgName> arrived, you set up kind of a mini base camp, you had to do it yourself, were there—what would you think would be the ratio between infantry troops? That is ground, whatever you want to call them, and the support group at <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_88">An Khe</placeName>. Where am I going with this is, generally speaking in <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_89">Vietnam</placeName> for the whole time that we’re there, we think of ratios of about nine to one and that includes all of the people in <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_90">Saigon</placeName> that never got out of <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_91">Saigon</placeName> and stuff like that. But in the base camps even, a lot of times in <date when="1968">’68</date>, <date when="1969">’69</date>, and <date when="1970">’70</date> the numbers were much higher. They were in maybe the six to seven. I’m assuming that <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_92">An Khe</placeName> it wasn’t anything like that, that most of the people that came in there were grunts.</u>
      <u who="ROBINSON">That’s right, yeah. They had a, what was it? A maintenance battalion, <orgName ref="#ttu_461_org_53">270th</orgName>? I can’t remember. A maintenance battalion. Must have had a logistics battalion and then they had several infantry battalions. The ratio was very high on the infantry side, I don’t know specifically.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">It wasn’t necessarily like that in <date when="1968">’68</date>, <date when="1969">’69</date> as I understand it at least, in place like <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_93">Cu Chi</placeName>, where the 25th was, the <orgName ref="#ttu_461_org_54">1st Division</orgName>. The numbers had grown in support troops and it was to support the infrastructure. You have to have perimeter defenses and you have to do all of that. It was much different than when you were there the first time.</u>
      <u who="ROBINSON">Yeah, I would suspect. I don’t really know from firsthand what the situation was there but—</u>
      <u who="MILAM">When you look back on that time—you then stayed in the military for another—</u>
      <u who="ROBINSON">I retired in <date when="1983">’83</date>. I went on and ultimately I became the project engineer for the Cobra attack helicopter.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">Really?</u>
      <u who="ROBINSON">And I was the project engineer for the H-1S. I went to graduate school to aerospace engineering, after my second tour.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">Where did you go?</u>
      <u who="ROBINSON">I went to the <orgName ref="#ttu_461_org_55">University of Missouri Rolla</orgName>, which is the old <orgName ref="#ttu_461_org_56">Missouri School of Aerospace Engineering</orgName>.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">Then my assignment out of there was aviation systems command at <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_94">St. Louis</placeName>. I was assigned to the Cobra helicopter project office and I was the project engineer for what became the H-1S. We took the H-1Gs which had been put together basically by Bell helicopter, by reconstructing the fuel lodge of the old UH-1D or H, and we built a new program. At that time they were getting penetration of North Vietnamese tanks down at <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_95">Ho Chi Minh Trail</placeName>. They were also getting some SA7s that they were shooting at the aircraft and that type of thing. The objective was to build an aircraft with a tow-missile system that could engage these North Vietnamese tanks. We took the H-1G, which had been out there, which was basically a gunship and fired some rockets. We mounted—we built a fire control system for the aircraft before the AH-1 that could guide the tow missiles by the cockpit, by integrating the system into it. Also, a fire-control system that would enable you to accurately fire the two launch missiles or the rockets—the rocket systems. Also, to be able to guide the cannon. So we put a 20 millimeter cannon on the Cobra, the tow missile systems, fire control system for the rockets, and we designed a new rotor, which is an asymmetrical rotor designed to hover over the ground effect, carrying these missiles because it was basically hovering at a ground effect. So different rotor system. We built a new engine, took the T53 out 13 and upgraded it to a T53-L703 which had greater horsepower. I think the other one was 1300 horsepower and this one was upgraded to 1800 thermodynamic horsepower, which allowed it to operate at higher altitudes although it was flatline by engine transmission rating, at 1500 horsepower. Then we upgraded the transmission so you can again use more power through the transmission, we put on a bigger tail rotor system, a bigger drive shaft, bigger tail rotor gear mechanism. So we upgraded basically the whole aircraft. That became the H-1S, that was my program.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">I see. Now, you mentioned that the <orgName ref="#ttu_461_org_57">NVA</orgName> (North Vietnamese Army) were bringing tanks down. Was there any one thing though, that made the army say, “Hey we may need a Cobra? We need these.”? Was it for escort of Hueys into battle?</u>
      <u who="ROBINSON">It must have been. The Hueys, those old B and C models would often have to hop like the devil to keep up with the UH-1Ds and Hs. They were loaded down with external drag from the rockets and the machine guns out there. It didn’t have as big as engine, they didn’t have as big as rotor, they didn’t have the power. So you would often have to direct your flight path so that those people can come up and intercept you and not have to—because they really couldn’t catch you.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">There was also, my memory of being an infantry platoon leader was that you had—the Cobra gunship also gave you the close in tactical air support for troops on the ground. Did the Hueys do that early on?</u>
      <u who="ROBINSON">The Hueys, the aerial rocket version of the ARA (Aerial Rocket Artillery), they mounted forty-eight rockets, which was the equivalent of firing a battalion of artillery. Instead of carrying machine guns, we had separate gunship units which were always the D companies of the lift battalions. Then they had the ARA, the aerial rocket artillery battalion, which was our airborne artillery battalion. They would often prep the battle area before we went in, before the gunships. The infantry platoons went in, the gunships, we would slow down if the gunships would spread out as best as they could and fire on the flanks. The aerial rocket artillery, which were forty-eight rockets as I recall, would fire the equivalent of a battalion of artillery in the fire zone and the gunships would prep the flanks or fire at the flanks, guard the flanks if you will. Then they would fly a racetrack pattern so that—they usually the racetrack patterns were such a—you had one going forward and one of them coming backwards, so that they could protect their own flags. That was part of the tactics designed in the old 11th Air Assault and in the <orgName ref="#ttu_461_org_58">1st Cav</orgName>. Tactically, so the airborne aircraft attack ships could protect themselves. You see them now for example, getting shot down over in <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_96">Iraq</placeName> over there. You get hit from behind usually, you can’t see them. The gunships like the Apache, they can’t see behind them, they can’t see the ground. So often they get shot down from the rear. The tactics that we used in <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_97">Vietnam</placeName> was always somebody going forward, somebody was going backwards. One was covering the other one, when they’re flying racetrack patterns. Those gunships and the old soviet environment were designed to hover behind a revetted area or behind a mask and fire rockets or missiles. Tow missiles and later on hellfire missiles behind a mask, so that there was some protection for them. Later on, they added the mask mounted sights, where they could put a mask up above the aircraft and you could hover behind a mask, but the mask mounted sight would be up there and using a radar in the front or visual beams, they could engage the target and fire on the hill. Well in <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_98">Iraq</placeName> or <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_99">Afghanistan</placeName>, that situation is not what they’re faced with. So the tactics, I'm not sure what they’re using, but it’s often they have two ships operating so that one can protect the other. Later on I was the program manager for aircraft survivability, also where I was building the systems that were designed to protect the aircraft radar jam, radar infrared, electro-optical type of counter measure systems. But, hardening of the aircraft to the extent that you could, we learn to harden an aircraft to such that the critical components, were armor-protected and the others that could take a round best could be left unprotected. When these infrared guided missiles came on the scene and the sophisticated seekers that later came on the scene, we had a device that was made to reduce the signatures on the aircraft of the hot engine, for example on the back the infrared suppressor were added initially as a means to reducing the threat for all of those infrared seekers and then we came up with jammers, infrared jammers and flares that could be deployed to decoy the missiles, which we did not fool later on, some of the more advanced systems and we were even looking at laser. Of course, the biggest threat is the optical threat where they can look at you through a naked eye or a lens. Even those we had some counter measures systems.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">Well, I enjoyed visiting with you and we appreciated you very much for coming in. As I like to tell people, these are sort of what we call abbreviated quick interviews and we welcome you if you ever see fit or if you’re ever out in <placeName ref="#ttu_461_place_100">Lubbock, Texas</placeName>, or if you want to do telephonic interviews, we have over a thousand we have done now and we have a full oral history project that we are doing at the Vietnam center out there. So we encourage you to participate in one of those, if you ever see fit to do that or you’re out our way. I really appreciate you being out here today and participating in this project.</u>
      <u who="ROBINSON">ROBINSON: Thank you very much, I’ve enjoyed it.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">Thank you.(End of interview)</u>
    </body>
  </text>
  <standOff>
    <listPlace>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_0">
        <placeName>LZ (Landing Zone) X-Ray</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_1">
        <placeName>X-Ray</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_2">
        <placeName>Benning</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_3">
        <placeName>Benning</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_4">
        <placeName>Germany</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_5">
        <placeName>Germany</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_6">
        <placeName>Germany</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_7">
        <placeName>Benning</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_8">
        <placeName>Fort Wolters</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_9">
        <placeName>Benning</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_10">
        <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_11">
        <placeName>Fort Benning</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_12">
        <placeName>Fort Benning</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_13">
        <placeName>New York</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_14">
        <placeName>New York</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_15">
        <placeName>Charleston, South Carolina</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_16">
        <placeName>Charleston</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_17">
        <placeName>Panama Canal</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_18">
        <placeName>Long Beach</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_19">
        <placeName>Qui Nhon Harbor</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_20">
        <placeName>Qui Nhon Harbor</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_21">
        <placeName>Qui Nhon</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_22">
        <placeName>Qui Nhon</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_23">
        <placeName>An Khe</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_24">
        <placeName>United States</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_25">
        <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_26">
        <placeName>Happy Valley</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_27">
        <placeName>Happy Valley</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_28">
        <placeName>Mang Yang Pass</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_29">
        <placeName>Phu Cat</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_30">
        <placeName>Highway 1</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_31">
        <placeName>Ia Drang Valley</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_32">
        <placeName>Phu Cat</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_33">
        <placeName>Phu Cat</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_34">
        <placeName>highway one</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_35">
        <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_36">
        <placeName>An Khe</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_37">
        <placeName>Happy Valley</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_38">
        <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_39">
        <placeName>Pleiku</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_40">
        <placeName>Holloway</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_41">
        <placeName>Holloway</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_42">
        <placeName>Holloway</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_43">
        <placeName>Plei Me</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_44">
        <placeName>Plei Me</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_45">
        <placeName>Plei Me</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_46">
        <placeName>Plei Me</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_47">
        <placeName>Chu Prong Mountain</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_48">
        <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_49">
        <placeName>Chu Prong Mountain</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_50">
        <placeName>LZ Falcon</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_51">
        <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_52">
        <placeName>Germany</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_53">
        <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_54">
        <placeName>Pleiku</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_55">
        <placeName>MASH (Mobile Army Surgical Hospital)</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_56">
        <placeName>Pleiku</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_57">
        <placeName>MASH</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_58">
        <placeName>X-Ray</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_59">
        <placeName>Happy Valley</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_60">
        <placeName>Happy Valley</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_61">
        <placeName>An Khe</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_62">
        <placeName>Mang Yang Pass</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_63">
        <placeName>Angel Fire, New Mexico</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_64">
        <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_65">
        <placeName>An Khe</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_66">
        <placeName>An Khe</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_67">
        <placeName>An Khe</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_68">
        <placeName>Tan Son Nhut</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_69">
        <placeName>Tuy Hoa</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_70">
        <placeName>Tuy Hoa</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_71">
        <placeName>Tuy Hoa</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_72">
        <placeName>Valley</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_73">
        <placeName>An Khe</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_74">
        <placeName>Pleiku</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_75">
        <placeName>Germany</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_76">
        <placeName>Phu Loi</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_77">
        <placeName>Phu Loi</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_78">
        <placeName>Fort Rucker</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_79">
        <placeName>Phu Loi</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_80">
        <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_81">
        <placeName>Thailand</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_82">
        <placeName>Phu Loi</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_83">
        <placeName>Di An</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_84">
        <placeName>Cu Chi</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_85">
        <placeName>Saigon</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_86">
        <placeName>Saigon</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_87">
        <placeName>An Khe</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_88">
        <placeName>An Khe</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_89">
        <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_90">
        <placeName>Saigon</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_91">
        <placeName>Saigon</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_92">
        <placeName>An Khe</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_93">
        <placeName>Cu Chi</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_94">
        <placeName>St. Louis</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_95">
        <placeName>Ho Chi Minh Trail</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_96">
        <placeName>Iraq</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_97">
        <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_98">
        <placeName>Iraq</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_99">
        <placeName>Afghanistan</placeName>
      </place>
      <place xml:id="ttu_461_place_100">
        <placeName>Lubbock, Texas</placeName>
      </place>
    </listPlace>
    <listEvent>
      <event xml:id="ttu_461_event_0">
        <desc>Ia Drang</desc>
      </event>
      <event xml:id="ttu_461_event_1">
        <desc>Ia Drang</desc>
      </event>
      <event xml:id="ttu_461_event_2">
        <desc>LZ X-Ray</desc>
      </event>
      <event xml:id="ttu_461_event_3">
        <desc>LZ X-Ray</desc>
      </event>
      <event xml:id="ttu_461_event_4">
        <desc>X-Ray</desc>
      </event>
      <event xml:id="ttu_461_event_5">
        <desc>LZ X-Ray</desc>
      </event>
      <event xml:id="ttu_461_event_6">
        <desc>LZ X-Ray</desc>
      </event>
      <event xml:id="ttu_461_event_7">
        <desc>LZ X-Ray</desc>
      </event>
      <event xml:id="ttu_461_event_8">
        <desc>LZ X-Ray</desc>
      </event>
      <event xml:id="ttu_461_event_9">
        <desc>LZ X-Ray</desc>
      </event>
      <event xml:id="ttu_461_event_10">
        <desc>X-Ray</desc>
      </event>
      <event xml:id="ttu_461_event_11">
        <desc>Albany</desc>
      </event>
      <event xml:id="ttu_461_event_12">
        <desc>X-Ray</desc>
      </event>
      <event xml:id="ttu_461_event_13">
        <desc>LZ X-Ray</desc>
      </event>
      <event xml:id="ttu_461_event_14">
        <desc>LZ X-Ray</desc>
      </event>
      <event xml:id="ttu_461_event_15">
        <desc>Albany</desc>
      </event>
      <event xml:id="ttu_461_event_16">
        <desc>LZ X-Ray</desc>
      </event>
      <event xml:id="ttu_461_event_17">
        <desc>Albany</desc>
      </event>
      <event xml:id="ttu_461_event_18">
        <desc>Albany</desc>
      </event>
      <event xml:id="ttu_461_event_19">
        <desc>Albany</desc>
      </event>
      <event xml:id="ttu_461_event_20">
        <desc>Albany</desc>
      </event>
      <event xml:id="ttu_461_event_21">
        <desc>Tet Offensive</desc>
      </event>
      <event xml:id="ttu_461_event_22">
        <desc>Tet</desc>
      </event>
      <event xml:id="ttu_461_event_23">
        <desc>Tet Offensive</desc>
      </event>
      <event xml:id="ttu_461_event_24">
        <desc>Tet Offensive</desc>
      </event>
    </listEvent>
    <listPerson>
      <person xml:id="ttu_461_person_0">
        <persName>President Johnson</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_461_person_1">
        <persName>General Westmoreland</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_461_person_2">
        <persName>Don Davis</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_461_person_3">
        <persName>Holly Langford</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_461_person_4">
        <persName>Buse Tully</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_461_person_5">
        <persName>Jimmy Johnson</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_461_person_6">
        <persName>Sergeant Pavlovich</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_461_person_7">
        <persName>Bob Kies</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_461_person_8">
        <persName>Kies</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_461_person_9">
        <persName>Kies</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_461_person_10">
        <persName>Bruce Crandall</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_461_person_11">
        <persName>General Kinnard</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_461_person_12">
        <persName>General Kinnard</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_461_person_13">
        <persName>General Norton</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_461_person_14">
        <persName>Larry Woods</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_461_person_15">
        <persName>Captain Woods</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_461_person_16">
        <persName>Larry Woods</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_461_person_17">
        <persName>Larry</persName>
      </person>
      <person xml:id="ttu_461_person_18">
        <persName>Kinnard</persName>
      </person>
    </listPerson>
    <listOrg>
      <org xml:id="ttu_461_org_0">
        <orgName>9th Assault Helicopter Battalion</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="ttu_461_org_1">
        <orgName>United States Military Academy at West Point</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="ttu_461_org_2">
        <orgName>Class of ’59</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="ttu_461_org_3">
        <orgName>Class of ’59</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="ttu_461_org_4">
        <orgName>11th Air Assault</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="ttu_461_org_5">
        <orgName>10th Air Transport Brigade</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="ttu_461_org_6">
        <orgName>10th Air Transport Brigade</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="ttu_461_org_7">
        <orgName>1st Cav</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="ttu_461_org_8">
        <orgName>1st Air Cav</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="ttu_461_org_9">
        <orgName>270th Aircraft Maintenance Battalion</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="ttu_461_org_10">
        <orgName>11th Air Assault</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="ttu_461_org_11">
        <orgName>1st Air Cavalry Division</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="ttu_461_org_12">
        <orgName>1st Cav</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="ttu_461_org_13">
        <orgName>9th Cavalry</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="ttu_461_org_14">
        <orgName>1st Air Cav</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="ttu_461_org_15">
        <orgName>11th Air Assault</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="ttu_461_org_16">
        <orgName>America</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="ttu_461_org_17">
        <orgName>marines</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="ttu_461_org_18">
        <orgName>North Vietnamese</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="ttu_461_org_19">
        <orgName>academy</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="ttu_461_org_20">
        <orgName>B Company two-two-nine</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="ttu_461_org_21">
        <orgName>VC (Viet Cong)</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="ttu_461_org_22">
        <orgName>A</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="ttu_461_org_23">
        <orgName>B</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="ttu_461_org_24">
        <orgName>C</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="ttu_461_org_25">
        <orgName>229th</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="ttu_461_org_26">
        <orgName>D Company</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="ttu_461_org_27">
        <orgName>Stars and Stripes</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="ttu_461_org_28">
        <orgName>marines</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="ttu_461_org_29">
        <orgName>101st</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="ttu_461_org_30">
        <orgName>101st</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="ttu_461_org_31">
        <orgName>1st Cav</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="ttu_461_org_32">
        <orgName>101st</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="ttu_461_org_33">
        <orgName>the 1st Cav</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="ttu_461_org_34">
        <orgName>North Vietnamese</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="ttu_461_org_35">
        <orgName>101st</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="ttu_461_org_36">
        <orgName>class of ’59</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="ttu_461_org_37">
        <orgName>class of ’59</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="ttu_461_org_38">
        <orgName>10th Air Transport Brigade</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="ttu_461_org_39">
        <orgName>United States</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="ttu_461_org_40">
        <orgName>1st Air Cav</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="ttu_461_org_41">
        <orgName>Company C</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="ttu_461_org_42">
        <orgName>11th Combat Aviation Battalion</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="ttu_461_org_43">
        <orgName>393rd Transportation Aircraft Maintenance</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="ttu_461_org_44">
        <orgName>128th Assault Helicopter Company</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="ttu_461_org_45">
        <orgName>11th Combat Aviation Battalion</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="ttu_461_org_46">
        <orgName>393rd</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="ttu_461_org_47">
        <orgName>128th</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="ttu_461_org_48">
        <orgName>1st Cav</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="ttu_461_org_49">
        <orgName>1st Infantry Division</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="ttu_461_org_50">
        <orgName>Vietnamese</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="ttu_461_org_51">
        <orgName>PAE (Pacific Architects and Engineers)</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="ttu_461_org_52">
        <orgName>1st Air Cav</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="ttu_461_org_53">
        <orgName>270th</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="ttu_461_org_54">
        <orgName>1st Division</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="ttu_461_org_55">
        <orgName>University of Missouri Rolla</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="ttu_461_org_56">
        <orgName>Missouri School of Aerospace Engineering</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="ttu_461_org_57">
        <orgName>NVA</orgName>
      </org>
      <org xml:id="ttu_461_org_58">
        <orgName>1st Cav</orgName>
      </org>
    </listOrg>
  </standOff>
</TEI>
