<?xml-model href="../schemas/ddhi.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Transcript of an Interview with a Narrator</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>
          <orgName>Dartmouth Digital History Initiative</orgName>
        </authority>
        <date>
          <!--  Date of publication, e.g. for citation purposes  -->
        </date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <recordingStmt>
          <recording xml:id="primary_recording" type="audio" dur-iso="">
            <!-- https://www.digi.com/resources/documentation/digidocs/90001437-13/reference/r_iso_8601_duration_format.htm -->
            <media url="" mimeType="MIMEaudio/wav"/>
          </recording>
        </recordingStmt>
        <bibl xml:id="primary_transcription">
          <respStmt>
            <persName>Mimi Eisenberg</persName>
            <orgName>Wordcraft</orgName>
            <resp ref="http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/trc.html">Transcriber</resp>
          </respStmt>
          <ref target="path_to_file">Primary transcription</ref>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The Dartmouth Vietnam Project</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application ident="DDHIEncoder" version="1.0">
          <desc>Conversion from Word docx to TEI xml.</desc>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en-us">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <particDesc>
        <person xml:id="NAPOLI"/>
        <person xml:id="RANGEL"/>
      </particDesc>
      <settingDesc>
        <setting>
          <date when-iso=""/>
          <locale/>
        </setting>
      </settingDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <u who="NAPOLI">The very first question—I’d like for you to do is tell me your name, your age, and where you’re currently living.</u>
      <u who="RANGEL">My name is <persName>John Rangel</persName> RANGEL. I'm sixty-eight. Date of birth is <date when="1937-05-28">28th, May ’37</date>. I was born and raised in <placeName>California</placeName>. Upon completion of my high school, that same week, <date when="1956-05">June of ’56</date>, I joined the military. I retired in <date when="1980">1980</date>. I live now in <placeName>Augusta, Georgia</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">Tell me a little bit about the decision to join the military in <date when="1956">1956</date>.</u>
        <u who="RANGEL">All of my uncles were in the military and that impressed me a lot. Originally, I wanted to join <orgName>the Marine Corps</orgName> because I like their dress. But back then, they wanted guys six feet or better. Just coming out of high school, a puny little hundred-thirty pounds 5’6. I wasn’t fit for the <orgName>Marines</orgName>, what they were looking for. I went next door to my army recruiter. The first thing he says, “We need infantry soldiers. 11 Bravos.” I said, “That’s where I want to go.” I was an infantry sergeant all those years in my military career.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">I see. Tell me a little bit about your training and then we’ll move on.</u>
      <u who="RANGEL">We went to basic training for six months. That was the first group of soldiers that took that training for so long. They were actually training before us and thereafter for like eight weeks. But they were preparing us to go to <placeName>Europe</placeName> at the time, under <orgName>the 11th Mountain Division</orgName>. They were having a lot of uprisings in <placeName>the Middle East</placeName>, so they tapped us to go to <placeName>Europe</placeName> from basic training. From there, I went to different installations throughout the world, <placeName>the United States</placeName>, <placeName>Cornish</placeName>, <placeName>United States</placeName>, back to <placeName>Europe</placeName> and <placeName>Korea</placeName>. I think my biggest—I was in <placeName>Germany</placeName> in <date when="1960">1960</date> to <date when="1962">1962</date>. When I got a letter from <orgName>the Department of Defense</orgName>, that I was to go to <placeName>Fort Benning</placeName>, <placeName>Georgia</placeName>. I was going to be part of the <orgName>11th Air Assault</orgName> that they were going to take and escalate and train and that was going to be the new modern air warfare machine. Everybody then in <placeName>Germany</placeName> said, “Oh, you’re going to helicopters, air mobile! God!” I think that was the best move for us at that time because as it proceeded into the <orgName>11th Air Assault</orgName>, we got<persName> Colonel Moore</persName>, our battalion commander. <persName>Sergeant Major Plumley</persName>, and my company commander, <persName>Captain Nadal</persName>, <orgName>special forces</orgName> officer. I was one of the old sergeants they sent back then because we had <placeName>US</placeName> and lifted people, draftees. I was twenty-five years old at the time. I was a buck sergeant. I had all these young soldiers and we trained for almost a year and a half. <placeName>Fort Benning</placeName>, <placeName>South Carolinas</placeName>. <orgName>101st</orgName> were our enemy in <placeName>South Carolinas</placeName>. Finally, we left <placeName>South Carolina</placeName> headed back to Fort Benning and <orgName>the Department of Defense</orgName> said that we were ready. “We want you to be <orgName>the 1st Cavalry Division</orgName>.” So we had that big parade at <placeName>Doughboy Stadium</placeName> with all of us and that was very touching because here we were an elite outfit. First of its kind in a military organization to do what we did, as far as helicopters and training, the air lifting, the supporting elements, and the <persName>Hueys</persName> was the best thing we had for us, going over there to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. Because of the way the terrain was built in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, you couldn’t get in there with trucks, you couldn’t get in there—if we walked, you had to drop us off five, ten miles but it would take us days to get through the canopy and break through all that brush and shrubbery. So if they landed us real quick, like in an open space, we were good to go. I thought that was at that point—I was very proud of myself. I kept telling my troopers, “Don’t give up, there’s going to be better days and remember this. That you were the 1st <orgName>Air Assault</orgName> troops going into <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>.” The only thing that I regret, not really, that is when you say air assault now, it’s a helicopter with wings, but to us, that is not the air assault. (Editor’s Note: Interviewee takes out a badge to demonstrate it to interviewer) This badge right here. Which is lightning bolt and a rifle. That’s air assault. We were the first ones to wear that. No one else can have this pin and no one has that. The air assault is still in progress, but they give them the wings with the helicopter. So that, again there, made us a unique element that nobody can match, the firefight would tremendous—but most of all, we had the leadership.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">Talk to me about your officers.</u>
      <u who="RANGEL"><persName>Lieutenant Marm</persName>, he was a lieutenant then, a 2nd lieutenant. He was my platoon leader. Of course, you know he’s a Medal of Honor winner recipient. When I got hit, I landed in—I didn’t know where I was at. I woke up in <orgName>Qui Nhon Hospital</orgName> for surgery. But I thought about <persName>Lieutenant Marm</persName> and my people. I didn’t know if they had survived or if they’d died. Or whatever. I didn’t know nothing about them, and I cried, and I grieved for them because I wanted to be with them. My sole purpose in life as a leader down below is an NCO (Non-commissioned Officer). I know that they missed me. They missed getting orders from me, what to do and how to do it. I knew that they were going to get in trouble. As a result, they did because there was nobody there to move them around and shift them as leadership, that’s what we were trained for. I’m glad we <persName>Captain Nadal</persName> as our company commander. I think, <persName>Captain Nadal</persName> at that point, he was <orgName>special forces</orgName> before then he joined us. He was a big, big asset to our company.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">Talk to me about his character.</u>
      <u who="RANGEL">Down to earth. We know we were going to shot, we knew we were going to killed, but we had a mission to do and that’s why we were there in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. We were there to free these people from communism, and we were going to do all we could to help these folks out. He looked after his men. <persName>Captain Nadal</persName>, I think in my estimation, is a solider that I would follow today. I made a speech several years ago to a hospital, nurses and doctors at Eisenhower, and they wanted me to speak. One of the questions that they asked me was, “How do you feel about <persName>Sergeant Major Plumley</persName> and <persName>Colonel Moore</persName>?” Because I had my speech lined up, so I had to pause for that about a minute. I said—I think it was <date when="1965">’65</date> at the time, I said—put my notes aside, I paused for a little bit and I said, “If <persName>Sergeant Major Plumley</persName> called and made a phone called now, today, or tomorrow and said ‘<persName>General Moore</persName> wants you at <placeName>Fort</placeName> Benning.’ My answer to that was, ‘I’ll be there today.’” There was no hesitation whatsoever. Why, when, or who, that’s out of the question. That’s how I feel today. I feel lucky that I had good commanders in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> with me on this battle. Now, when I say, “Good commanders,” I was assigned to <orgName>the Americal Division</orgName>, before I went to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> the second time. When I got to <placeName>Hawaii</placeName>, I had a company commander. They’d been waiting for me because they knew I was coming. But I kept coming off for it. I didn’t want to go to <orgName>the Americal Division</orgName>, I wanted to go with a season group because we already went through all this training at <placeName>Fort Benning</placeName>. <orgName>Americal</orgName> was just started going through their routine training. What had happened was, I come in with my uniform and of course my big yellow pants. The first thing the captain says, “I am glad you are here <persName>Sergeant Rangel</persName>, because we are going to kick ass when we get to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>.” I didn’t say nothing. I didn’t say, “Yes sir, or no sir.” I just sort of nodded my head. But in my mind, that was the wrong words he used on me because I knew what was going to happen. I left <placeName>Hawaii</placeName> and I got assigned on my own from <orgName>the Department of Defense</orgName> and went over. That’s when I joined the <orgName>11th Armored Cav</orgName>. I was over there <date>three months</date>, <date>five months</date> with the <orgName>11th Cav</orgName> and guess what happened? <persName>Lieutenant Calley</persName> and his massacres,<name type="event"> My Lai</name>, took place and the whole battalion. I knew then that this captain, he wanted medals, but he was going to get medals the wrong way. He wasn’t going into <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> like <persName>Colonel Moore</persName>, <persName>Plumley</persName> and those people were. We were going in there for a cause. To relieve communism from those people and give them their freedom. That’s the difference between <name type="event">My Lai</name> and <name type="event">Ia Drang Valley</name> and our men. So I’d have to say that <persName>Captain Nadal</persName>, in my list stands pretty high. He’s always been the same today, tomorrow. He comes to meet me, or I meet him, I shake his hand and I tell him I love him; god bless him. Because he deserves that. He didn’t get wounded, but he led the men that he had to with all the resources that he had. We were outnumbered. We knew we weren’t going to make it. We knew that when they told us we were going in there. Three-hundred-fifty people. Against what? Four thousand? But we didn’t give up, we didn’t turn tail. Nobody cried, nobody went AWOL (Absent Without Official Leave). Nobody slid in the jungle to avoid the air lift that was going into the Ia Drang Valley.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">Tell me about that.</u>
      <u who="RANGEL">We landed—when we got the word, <orgName>A Company</orgName> was the first airlift with the headquarters, Colonel <persName>Moore</persName> and his people and elements of <orgName>B Company</orgName>. We landed right below <placeName>Chu Pong Mountain</placeName>. We scattered out naturally, that’s what we do automatically. The choppers—we’d been trained also to jump out the helicopters, don’t the choppers hit the ground because they are susceptible to firefight from the enemy. We flew out, choppers just moved on out. We were in good shape. We landed there and we got the word to go ahead and eat our meals. So we opened up our C-rations. This was about 12:30, quarter to one, because we were waiting for the direct order to come in. Supposedly, later about like 2:30, three o’clock, we got the word from <orgName>2nd Platoon</orgName>, from Lieutenant <persName>Marm</persName>, said we had to move out. As we were moving out, hell broke loose at that time at another flank. We started getting sniper fire a little bit on our side. We moved past the creek bed, we got our fifty yards and we got down. We waited and waited. It was about like ten, fifteen minutes. We got the word to withdrawal. So we pulled back behind the creek bed. Come to find out that we had artillery coming in, the aircraft F-100 was coming in. The gunship was coming in, they were going to pinpoint fire on <placeName>Chu Pong Mountain</placeName>, up for where we were supposed to attack. Again, that’s when the fire broke out loose. So as we proceed, we got the word from Captain <persName>Nadal</persName>, through Lieutenant <persName>Marm</persName> down the company, they came down the line to fix bayonets. So as we fixed bayonets, we crossed a creek bed, my first encounter with enemy was the bayonet, this <orgName>Vietnamese</orgName> solider. <persName>Bill Beck</persName> was there. <persName>Bill Beck</persName> describes it in the book. He gave me a sketch years ago and he says, “John, you were a hell of a dog-gone ground pounder. Bayonet this guy just like basic training.” Well, it was either him or me, the way I look at it. I had no choice, that was it right there, one on one. I did what I was trained to do and how to do it. So I bayoneted at the solider. As we proceed, looks like red ants. <orgName>NVA</orgName> (North Vietnamese Army). Khaki helmets. <orgName>North Vietnamese </orgName>and <persName>Viet Cong</persName>. It was overwhelming. It was just fire left and right. We kept moving to the right because we had a tight end with their platoon. About halfway, I couldn’t move with my <orgName>Alpha</orgName> team and <orgName>Bravo</orgName> team. We got fired right from the flanks, it was forty meters out. I didn’t know it at this time, <persName>Lieutenant Marm</persName> kept hounding, “Move it to the right! Move it to the right!” Well, we were pinned. Luckily, we had coverage there from logs. Barricade it was a little—Some troopers caught cover there, we still couldn’t move, we were getting intense fire. We couldn’t move. I kept yelling, “We can’t! We can’t move!” Everyone had four grenades on them when we went into <placeName>Ia Drang</placeName>. We had all four ammunitions pockets of ammo. Of course, our rucksacks were full of ammunition, we were still on the ground. I can’t move to my right, so here I am, what am I going to do? We’re getting shot, we need to move. So I thought, “I got two grenades here. I pulled a grenade out of my harness. I pull the grenades with my teeth, both of them, and I'm on my back, because I knew where the fire was coming from. Huge termite hill, I threw the grenade down there, on both of them. Those were the longest three, four seconds of my life. I said, “No, they can’t be duds.” About that time, they went (Makes explosion noises). We’d already been at 5th Bayonet, so I told my people “Cover my advance.” I zigzag to the bunker and I saw what the damage of my grenades had done to the four <orgName>Vietnamese</orgName> there. A machine gunner and three riflemen. They were still breathing. But I went with no mercy, I stabbed them with my bayonet. At the small of the back, on the spine, and I’d emptied out ten, fifteen magazines. I did that to four of those Vietnamese. Each one. I even had to change magazines, put them in there because they were still alive. I didn’t want to go back and maybe one guy would pick up a rifle, and on his last breath shot me going back. That’s what I did. As soon as I got back, I started running. My grenadier <persName>John Brennan</persName> got hit. He went berserk. I had to go tackle him to get him on the ground, had to fight him like a bull. I had to keep him down, I told him, “<persName>Brennan</persName>, if you don’t stay down, you’re going to get killed, you’re going to get killed!” So as I was ready to inject him with some morphine, my other hand was getting his first aid kit because that’s what we do, we don’t take our own first aid kit, we take theirs, the wounded, and that’s all I know. At that point, I’m at <placeName>Qui Nhon Hospital</placeName>. I'm looking at all these IVs in my feet and arms. I said, “What in the hell am I doing here?” I couldn’t speak. They told me the bullet went through my jaw, got a little speck right up in here, went through my neck, my jaw. Went through my neck, my esophagus and it came out right on my shoulder. It ripped my esophagus off, and that’s why I'm talking like I am today. But they didn’t conduct any surgery or cleaned out my shoulder because it was a huge open wound and it had to be healed. So from that point on, General <persName>Westmoreland</persName> was there at that time, lord god forbid why he was there that fast because he knew the casualties were in <placeName>Qui Nhon</placeName>. He came to me and just like I am seeing you today, he leaned over and whispered into my ears and hugged me and said, “<persName>Sergeant Rangel</persName> you are going home. You have the million-dollar wound.” His agent gave him a Purple Heart, pinned it on me. He gave me the Presidential Citation for <orgName>the 1st and the 7th</orgName> and pinned it on me. Gave me the Bronze Star medal with “V” device and pinned it on me. He says, “Good luck son.” And he went right on down the line. I wound up in in <placeName>San Francisco, Letterman General Hospital</placeName>. When I landed in <placeName>Travis</placeName>, they got me a bed in <placeName>San Francisco</placeName>, because my family from <placeName>Oakland, California</placeName>. I was scheduled to go to <placeName>Fort Walter</placeName>, with my wife and two children were in <placeName>Augusta</placeName>—<placeName>Fort Benning</placeName>, I’m sorry. My uncle, when he heard that he could get me transferred to <persName>Walter Reed</persName>, he made a call and put my wife and two children on a plane and flew them into <placeName>California</placeName>. When we got on a Medevac bus to go out, at <placeName>Travis</placeName>, the protestors were at the gate, they wouldn’t let us out because they knew that <placeName>Travis</placeName> was infiltrating people to <placeName>Letterman General Hospital</placeName>, from <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. The protestors wouldn’t let us get us out of <placeName>Travis</placeName>. I’m saying, “Oh my god—” I can’t talk yet, but I know what’s going on in my mind, I could see. I hear the rest of the soldiers that are with us, “Give us a machine gun, we’ll blow their asses away, what is wrong with these people? They’re fighting us!” They had to wait for the state troopers to come in and maintain and get order and shifted these people out of the way. They didn’t have no weapons or anything, they were just blocking and protesting “baby killers”, “women killers”, “baby killers”, spiting at us. Spitting at the buses as we went by. When we got to <placeName>Letterman Hospital</placeName>, it was the same thing. Protestors were waiting for when we got to the gates. That really made me very, very upset. About our American people taking those type of actions against our soldiers. <persName>John F. Kennedy</persName> said it right, that we were going to send our soldiers in there to help this country, no matter what and at what cost. It’s very sad to see that <persName>John Kennedy</persName> is laying up there and he hadn’t seen all those crosses that are up there, from veterans, us that came back. President <persName>Johnson</persName> was the one that put it on the newscast on television, that he is now sending the <orgName>1st Air Cav Division</orgName> over to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. Everybody was waiting for that day at <placeName>Fort Benning</placeName>. We were ready, we were ready. Nobody hightailed it. Nobody left and went AWOL. There were certain individuals that I know—I don’t know if I should say this to you or not. Can you cut that off for a minute?</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">You had a company commander?</u>
      <u who="RANGEL">When we got to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, when I left <placeName>Letterman Hospital</placeName>, I was out for recuperation finally. I could talk a little, but I was limited for duty at <placeName>Fort Benning</placeName>. I got a call from Lieutenant <persName>Marm</persName> one day. He says, “<persName>Sergeant Rangel</persName>—” I was still in the military. “<persName>Sergeant Rangel</persName>, I’m going to <placeName>Washington D.C.</placeName> to be presented the Medal of Honor and I want you to go with me. I hijack <persName>General York’s</persName> plane out of <placeName>Fort Benning</placeName>, and I want you to go with me.” I said, “Are you for real?” “<persName>Sergeant Rangel</persName>, I wouldn’t leave you behind. You’re part of why I got this award.” He’ll tell you today, that this award wasn’t for him, it was for his men. That’s how <persName>Lieutenant Marm</persName> is. I love the guy. A few months after that, we came back from <placeName>Washington D.C.</placeName>, I got a call from a sergeant that was in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> with us. He called me and he said, “<persName>Sergeant Rangel</persName>, do you remember so-and-so?” I said, “Yes, Sergeant.” “Well, he wants to meet you and a few others that was in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, that was in <orgName>Alpha Company</orgName> at the <placeName>NCO club</placeName> at <orgName>Sandhills</orgName>, at lunch perhaps 12:30, one o’clock. Can you make it?” I said, “Yes, I’ll be there.” And I hung up. For two days, I’m thinking, “How am I going to handle this after what I’d been through already with my men.” I got to go up there and shake hands and make it seem like nothing happened. But I couldn’t do that. I went to everybody talked—when one of the sergeants said this to him, he replied like, “Wow. If I knew it was going to be like that, I wish I would’ve gone with you guys.” And that’s it. I got up and I told him what I thought about, and my reason for saying what I did when I said that to him. “A lot of men died on that battlefield that are not here today. You should’ve been with us all the way because you started out with us in <date when="1963">’63</date> and you did the wrong thing.” And I left. I never had any more consultations or phone calls from other people in that group. Throughout the years, Captain <persName>Nadal</persName> had called me about nine years ago, I didn’t know they were having this reunion. Captain <persName>Nadal</persName> called me, and he says, “<persName>Sergeant Rangel</persName>,” We still address each other sergeant or colonel, just like General <persName>Moore</persName>. General <persName>Moore</persName>, “<persName>Sergeant Rangel</persName>, how are you doing?” I just met him up there, “Fine sir, I love you. I’m always thinking about you.” As <date>the years</date> go by, I get very emotional Veteran’s Day, Memorial Days. Veteran’s Day is the only time I come up here, but I didn’t know they were having a reunion except <orgName>the 1st and 7th</orgName>. When captain <persName>Nadal</persName> called me, he says—I think he said it, it was the fifth one going on. Then he said, “I didn’t know where you were at! I got a call from Becky. <persName>Becky Gill</persName>.” Oh okay, <persName>Becky Gill</persName>—<persName>Jack Gill</persName> was my neighbor, radio operator for Captain <persName>Nadal</persName>. He was my neighbor. He was my neighbor at Fort Benning. Let me say a little bit about <persName>Jack Gill</persName>. When we got on those ships, all E5s and above were given class captain class. All other soldiers were down on the bottom. They never did tell us why we had captain class, but we figured it out. We’re going to war, so they’re shipping us up and they are giving us some good royal treatment because we don’t know who’s coming back, we’re not all coming back. But it was wonderful. The butler would come through in the morning and (Interviewee makes bell noises). That was breakfast, dinner, and lunch, whatever and we would eat upstairs, in this dining area. We had waiters come to us and ask us what we want, and oh I couldn’t believe it. I enjoyed it, why not? <persName>Jack Gill</persName> was my roommate. We didn’t talk much about our families while we were at Fort Benning. Because we never thought about <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, we knew but we—you know, whatever. We might go individually but not as a whole group. The day before we got ready to embark that ship and get on that LSDs (Dock Landing Ships) to get to the beach, to get those Chinooks taken to <placeName>An Khe</placeName>, when we were on the deck, it was just like—it was just like—how do I want to say it? We knew it, we knew just by looking at each other through our eyes. We hugged each other and he said, “Take care of my children for me, look out after them if I don’t come back.” I told him the same thing. I said, “I love you <persName>Gill</persName>.” “I love you <persName>Sergeant Rangel</persName>.” He died. He got shot. Years after I got out. I did what I could to stay in touch with those families. I love them like they’re my kids, and they love me like their uncle. We had a reunion at <placeName>Fort Benning</placeName>, <orgName>1st of the 7th</orgName>. I made a plaque, <orgName>1st Cav</orgName> plaque. Out of wood, beautiful. I made it in my shop. I told my wife, “When we go to the reunion and we go to the cemetery.” because that was our next trip from the reunion, to the cemetery. I laid that wreath, that decal on his gravesite. His children were with me, the newspaper people were there. The television people were there. When I planted that plaque on there, I stood up in front of <persName>Gill</persName> and I saluted him. I said, “<persName>Sergeant Gill</persName>. Mission accomplished.” Seeing that the kids grew up, got married, had good jobs. I still look after them today. I still do. His wife moved to <placeName>Augusta, Georgia</placeName> last week and I'm glad because she has ties with my wife, because we used to go to <placeName>Charlotte</placeName> all the time, we were together. We meet up here and she’ll be here <date>Friday</date>. But it makes it better for my wife now. We’re old now and we need that come and go. I say her kids are wonderful children, and I love them dearly, but I think about their dad and a lot of the other soldiers that was <placeName>US</placeName> and draftees, eighteen and nineteen years old. They missed out on a lot of things. Coming home to girlfriends, new cars, going to school, getting an education, meeting somebody. I think of <persName>John Brennan</persName>. <persName>John Brennan</persName> and I used to share the same “pup” tent because he was my grenadier. He was the firepower on my squad, with a small 40 millimeters. That’s why he was right next to me, I kept him to me. I tell him, “You stay with me. Because I need your firepower.” “Okay serge! Okay, serge!” But it was many years later when I came to the wall, after Captain <persName>Nadal</persName> had call me. It had been now about maybe eight years. When I saw <persName>John Brenan’s</persName> name up there, I didn’t know then that he was dead or killed. I did not know until I saw his name on the wall. Every time I come back, that’s where I go to. <persName>John Brennan</persName>. <persName>John Brenan</persName>. I try to take all this one day at a time, since I’ve gotten out. I’m under the <orgName>VA</orgName> (Veteran’s Affairs) help now. Just think, it’s been forty years. The <orgName>VA</orgName> had been dragging their tails on soldiers like me that has a problem. They finally got me into this post-traumatic stress program. I finished it, August 15th. Hopefully now, the <orgName>VA</orgName> administration will look into my records and what the <orgName>VA</orgName> had done for me in <placeName>Augusta, Georgia</placeName> and why they put me in this program. To give me the entitlements that the government—I honestly believe, that is owed to the American soldiers. I would—I don’t hesitate to tell you that our government, I think in my opinion, our government is not doing enough for our veterans. There’s a lot of homeless people out there. I just left a stand down in <placeName>Augusta, Georgia.</placeName> For veterans and my god. I went there to the <orgName>DAV</orgName> (Disabled American Veterans) representative; we had our own little meets for these people. I cannot believe the conditions of these veterans. They are not retirees, they did three-four years, five years, whatever and they got out with no place to go. Hunger is there. Medical aid, no clothing for these folks. You might say, well, they took it upon themselves to go that way. But a lot of them came back and their families didn’t want them. They got divorces while they were over there, and they went hysterical. There was nothing for me, nothing to do. So why should I go further? That’s a bad—but I think the Veteran’s Administration, who is our only hope, I wish they wouldn’t cut budgets and cut budgets. Hospitals here, and clinics there. Just let and support these veterans that need help. I am the chapter president of <orgName>the 1st Cav Division Association</orgName> in <placeName>Augusta, Georgia</placeName>. I have a hundred and forty people on my roster that I get from Copper’s Cove. Let me tell you, I kick butt with these guys. I said, “Do it for the veterans, us. The new generation. The <orgName>Iraqi Soldiers</orgName> now. We need to go see them. We need to give them their stuff.” The <orgName>VA</orgName> doesn’t give clothing articles. It’s not in their budget. My chapter broke that charter, and we go to the hospitals and we get ditty bags, and we give them to these guys. Because they deserve that. They’re Iraqi soldiers, they’re doing something that they believe, like we did when we went in. They sent you in there—you were in there because our president told us to go. That’s who we supported. Doesn’t matter who the commander-in-chief is. The military, me like I am, infantry solider proud of the uniform, even though I'm a sergeant, not an officer. But I love the uniform, I love what every solider is doing today. But what’s hurting us is all of these protesters right now. Yes, they have a lot of soldiers killed over there, but war is hell. Somebody got to pay that price. Who’s going to pay that price? Civilians are not here—say, I'm going blow you an airplane, we’re going to take all these civilians out here and we’re going to fight a war in <placeName>Iraq</placeName>. That’s why we have the military. It was back in <date when="1776">1776</date>! <persName>George Washington</persName>, his troops! I believe honestly, that’s the way it should be in <placeName>America</placeName> today because in my speeches, when I go around, I sort of remind people, “How many people here seen the movie Red Dawn?” Do you know what I'm talking about?</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">Yes, I do.</u>
      <u who="RANGEL">“Do we need this in <placeName>Augusta, Georgia</placeName>? Or do we need this up there in <placeName>Decatur</placeName>? Do we need it up there in <placeName>Atlanta</placeName>? Do we need it in <placeName>Columbus</placeName>, <placeName>Georgia</placeName>?” And that’s what I tell them. “Think about it people. It could be right in your hometown! The possibility.”</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">The point is that the government then owes you if you’re going to make that bargain. To send your young body. To <placeName>Iraq</placeName> or <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="RANGEL">Exactly. The people in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, they say, “Well, that was an old lesson learned.” I can’t believe that old lesson learned, I read in papers and people talk this and say this. But let me tell you something that upsets me now that I'm here with you. I’m not going to mention any names. But there is a high visible individual here in this country when the war was going on in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, that individual’s son went to <placeName>Canada</placeName> to draft— draft dodger. When the war was over in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. I forget, ’<date when="1971">71</date>?</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">’<date when="1975">75</date>.</u>
      <u who="RANGEL">He came back to <placeName>the United States</placeName> and the rest of the drafters. They were given full amnesty.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">Right, like <persName>Carter</persName>.</u>
      <u who="RANGEL">Exactly. When <persName>Carter</persName> speaks on TV today, I turn it off. I turn it off. I feel that in my opinion him being our commander-in-chief did wrong. He pacified the enemy. The enemy is good for propaganda, and he did it again during that time. That’s sad for us. We have to cope with that, and we have to live with that. But I'm hoping that we’ll have some good days. I’m hoping for good days to come for all of our veterans.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">Me too. Me too.</u>
      <u who="RANGEL">I know that you people will do good on this. I am very proud of you guys.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">Listen, all we have to do is listen to you. That’s our privilege. I think we need to stop.</u>
      <u who="RANGEL">Yes, that’s the end of that. Thank you very much.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">Thank you.(End of interview)</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
