<?xml-model href="../schemas/ddhi.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Transcript of an Interview with a Narrator</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>
          <orgName>Dartmouth Digital History Initiative</orgName>
        </authority>
        <date>
          <!--  Date of publication, e.g. for citation purposes  -->
        </date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <recordingStmt>
          <recording xml:id="primary_recording" type="audio" dur-iso="">
            <!-- https://www.digi.com/resources/documentation/digidocs/90001437-13/reference/r_iso_8601_duration_format.htm -->
            <media url="" mimeType="MIMEaudio/wav"/>
          </recording>
        </recordingStmt>
        <bibl xml:id="primary_transcription">
          <respStmt>
            <persName>Mimi Eisenberg</persName>
            <orgName>Wordcraft</orgName>
            <resp ref="http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/trc.html">Transcriber</resp>
          </respStmt>
          <ref target="path_to_file">Primary transcription</ref>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The Dartmouth Vietnam Project</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application ident="DDHIEncoder" version="1.0">
          <desc>Conversion from Word docx to TEI xml.</desc>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en-us">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <particDesc>
        <person xml:id="MILAM"/>
        <person xml:id="PUJALS"/>
      </particDesc>
      <settingDesc>
        <setting>
          <date when-iso=""/>
          <locale/>
        </setting>
      </settingDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <u who="MILAM">This is Dr. <persName>Ron Milam</persName> with <orgName>Texas Tech University</orgName> and <orgName>the Vietnam Center</orgName>, and I'm interviewing today <orgName>Enrique Pujals</orgName>.</u>
      <u who="PUJALS">Yes, that’s it.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">Nice to have you here. I’d like to first start by asking you if you could tell me your MOS (Military Occupational Specialty) and your rank and your responsibilities on <date>November 14th, 1965</date>.</u>
      <u who="PUJALS">My <orgName>MOS</orgName> was <date>1542</date>, that’s an infantry small unit commander. I was a 2nd lieutenant platoon leader of the 3rd Platoon, <persName>Charlie Company</persName>, 2nd <name type="event">Battalion 7th Cav</name>.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">So you were in <date>the 2nd</date>?</u>
      <u who="PUJALS">Right.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">Okay. Let’s back up. You joined the 1st <name type="event">Cav in Benning</name>?</u>
      <u who="PUJALS">I joined the 1st Cav in <placeName>Fort Benning</placeName> as a volunteer officer. I was an extra officer. I was, at the time, with the infantry school of support troops <orgName>Alpha Company</orgName>, <date>1st of the 29th</date> infantry.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">Okay. When did you actually transfer over to the 1st <name type="event">Air Cav</name>?</u>
      <u who="PUJALS">On or <date>about the 28th of July</date>.</u>
      <u who="MILAM"><date>28th of July</date> of—</u>
      <u who="PUJALS"><date>’65</date>.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">Of ’65? So you were not involved with their training exercises from ’63 or ’64 on?</u>
      <u who="PUJALS">No, but I had been an escort officer to the high-ranking officers, colonels, generals, and foreign officers. As an escort officer doing the time, I forget the name of the fort, it’s the one that near <placeName>Macon</placeName>. As my duties, I learned a lot about my training from the theoretical part, which is from the literature. Sometimes my duties took me with a general colonel I was escorting to the sights and watch demonstrations and watch the troops maneuvering. But that was my involvement with the training of the 11th <orgName>Air Assault</orgName>.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">What was your source of commissioning? How did you get your—</u>
      <u who="PUJALS">I was commissioned through the ROTC (Reserve Officers’ Training Corps) program in <orgName>Pennsylvania Military College</orgName>, which was in <placeName>Chester</placeName>, <placeName>Pennsylvania</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">Okay, did you go to OBC (Officer Basic Course)? Officer Basic School, after ROTC?</u>
      <u who="PUJALS">No, I went through a special course they had for infantry officers at the time.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">Is this the U2 program?</u>
      <u who="PUJALS">Yeah, it’s the U2 program.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">Oh!</u>
      <u who="PUJALS">I got in a problem with one of the professors. He wouldn’t give me a make-up test because I went too early, <date>one day</date> early to my home for <date>Christmas</date>. He wouldn’t give me a make-up test and I had been in the top ten percent in the class, I was a distinguished military student. I was in line for RA (Regular Army) commission, but because of that, I flunked his course and I let slide all the other courses. I ended up with a very low C, or very high D. I don’t remember exactly. I was about to do the same thing in the on the second semester. I was a cadet officer, a cadet lieutenant, cadet platoon leader, in <orgName>Pennsylvania Military College</orgName>. But my second semester, before <date>the end of first semester</date>, I decided to buckle up and forget about what had happened and try to make the best grades I could. They offered me the U2 program and the U2 program was considered for the substandard officers. That hurt me in my career afterwards.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">You think it hurt you?</u>
      <u who="PUJALS">Yeah, I think it hurt me. I think they thought I was some sort of dud because the <orgName>S1</orgName> officer, when I was stationed in <placeName>Germany</placeName> in <date>1969</date> through ’71, he said, “Captain, I thought you were a dud, that’s what they told me to believe, but you're very sharp.” (Chuckles). So that’s where I get the impression from.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">How long did you stay in the army?</u>
      <u who="PUJALS">I stayed in the <orgName>Army</orgName> for <date>five and a half years</date>. Active duty.</u>
      <u who="MILAM"><date>Five and a half years</date>. Did you retire as a captain or left as a captain?</u>
      <u who="PUJALS">I left as a captain.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">One tour or two tours in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="PUJALS">I did two tours in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">You did two tours. Well, just for your information, I have—part of my research doctrinal dissertation was on junior officer leadership in training and everything during <name type="event">the Vietnam War</name>. I was not familiar with U2, I thought I knew most of everything that happened because I know how <orgName>OBC</orgName> was considered for a long time, that those who graduated from the <placeName>US</placeName> military academic didn’t have to go to <orgName>OBC</orgName> for a short period of time. Then they realized that <orgName>OBC</orgName>, <date>the eight weeks</date> of <orgName>OBC</orgName> was something that was necessary even for West Pointers. So this U2 program somehow kind of got snuck in there at a time, but I never found it in the literature, so it must have been a very short period of time.</u>
      <u who="PUJALS">Yes, that’s what they told us. It was an experiment to see—for the West Pointers, an experiment to see if we could do it, just a short—I think it was <date>two or three weeks</date> course then <orgName>OJT</orgName> (On the Job Training). One of our classmates, he asked, “What’s the real purpose of this, because if you look around, none of us here is in the top ten percent. We’re the C’s and B minuses.”</u>
      <u who="MILAM">To your credit, they cancelled the program after a while, obviously and the only people that didn’t have to go to OBC after that were <orgName>OCS</orgName> (<orgName>Officer Candidate School</orgName>) because they had been <date>six months</date> becoming officers and that’s the only way it—well, that’s interesting information right there. Go ahead.</u>
      <u who="PUJALS">I would like to add, we called him “the shepherd”, the 1st lieutenant who was in charge of our group at the <placeName>U2</placeName> and <placeName>Fort Benning</placeName>, was <persName>Joe Marm</persName>. He’s the one that won the Medal of Honor on the 14th, for his actions there.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">He was also in the U2 program?</u>
      <u who="PUJALS">No, he was OCS. He had been—he was first lieutenant, and he was in the 9th Infantry Division at the time. This was before they changed, this was <date>September of 1964</date>. He was in charge of our group; he was the one that was in charge of our group. We called him our shepherd. (Chuckles)</u>
      <u who="MILAM">Sure, well he did a good job, didn’t he? So you joined the 1st <name type="event">Air Cav</name> then, right before they leave?</u>
      <u who="PUJALS">Yes, because I was very despondent because the 1st Cav was going off to war and I was bored here as support troop, playing mighty aggressive forces and demonstrations that I had already done two or three times, showing how to maneuver against an ambush. Fire maneuver drills, anti-ambush drills, in charge of the details of our troops that were going to go over there, to show them how to use troops and how to use weapons and different types of weapons. I was getting bored because in the summer everybody just goes away. We had <date>thirteen 2nd</date> lieutenants in our company and I eventually got to meet them all, but we were there at the same time, all of us.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">I see.</u>
      <u who="PUJALS">I suddenly heard that the cav was still taking people. It was <date>the last day of July</date> so I—(Interviewee snaps his fingers.)Off I went. They told me that they wanted mortar officers.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">Mortar?</u>
      <u who="PUJALS">Yeah, mortar. That’s what they were looking for. I didn’t have any experiences with mortar, just rifle infantry. They said, “We can’t take you.” And my face went. (<orgName>Interviewee</orgName> shows interviewer facial expression)“But we’re authorized to take an extra ten percent personnel by regulations when we are about to make a landing on a hostile shore, and this qualifies as that.” So I said “I'm in!” So they took me as an extra officer at the time. I also told my—he was the acting company commander at the time, Lieutenant <persName>Raul Taboada</persName>. He was wounded, he ended up being the mortar officer in <orgName>Delta</orgName> company of <date>1st of the 7th</date>. He went over there and joined up. They wouldn’t let him go because he didn’t have secret clearance because he’s a Cuban officer, but he entered as a special program by President <persName>Kennedy</persName>. All these officers and NCOs (Non-Commissioned Officers) of the Cuban brigade that had been liberated they entered the armed forces of <placeName>the United States</placeName> with the same rank that they had in the brigade and they would work from that. So he had been a 2nd lieutenant as a mortar officer. He was the heavy mortar officer for the brigade.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">I see.</u>
      <u who="PUJALS">And he was my buddy over there.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">Now, when the <orgName>S1</orgName>, I guess it was the S1 you were talking to?</u>
      <u who="PUJALS">Yes, the S1, it was the Captain <persName>Johnson</persName>.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">When they said that they had a clause that they can take <date>an extra ten percent</date> when they launched an operation coming on shore, was that tongue and cheek? Or did he really believe we were going to—</u>
      <u who="PUJALS">No, no. We were going by ship. So we didn’t know exactly what was going on and what happened. When we got there, they didn’t know what to do with us. Whether we were going to go—I had two duffle bags and most of us had two duffle bags, whether we were going to go with our duffle bags and administrative landing, that’s what we called it, or if we were going to leave everything behind, issue us ammunition and send us in a hostile—you know, heed the beach. So they kept us a couple of hours until they finally decided to be an administrative landing. Everybody was going up and I said, “Just put my duffle bags down.” And I sat on them and I said, “I'm waiting for the last call.” Since I didn’t have any other troops in charge at the time, since I was an officer.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">So you are—which ship did you go on?</u>
      <u who="PUJALS"><persName>The Maurice Rose</persName>.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">The Rose.</u>
      <u who="PUJALS">I always forget the middle initial. </u>
      <u who="MILAM">Yeah, don’t worry about it. </u>
      <u who="PUJALS">You know, it was commissioned <date>the same month</date> I was born. It was commissioned in <date>August 1942</date>. I was born <date>August 6th, 1942</date>.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">You join up, you don’t really—at that moment, you don’t know what your duty station is going to be when you get there?</u>
      <u who="PUJALS">I didn’t know exactly where we were going to land, or what my actual duties were going to be, but at that time, I was labeled as a liaison officer. I knew we were going to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> and we were going to the camp that was being set up and already we know the name was the “Golf course”, it had already been called the “Golf Course”. All these things were coming back to us, all this information, in <date>those last few days</date> before we left.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">But you carried the designated title of liaison officer. So while you are onboard the ship, are you trying to find a job?</u>
      <u who="PUJALS">No, they gave me a job.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">Oh, they did. What they give you?</u>
      <u who="PUJALS">They made me work. They put me under the orders of Captain <persName>Koga</persName>. He looked like the captain in <placeName>Beetle Bailey</placeName>, you know. Fairly overweight. He was a Japanese American from <placeName>Hawaii</placeName>, at least he had some Japanese ancestors, his name was <persName>Koga</persName>. He made me deck police officer.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">Deck police officer?</u>
      <u who="PUJALS">Yeah, he told me I had to go out there and make sure they picked up all the papers and all the little bits and pieces of whatever, cigarettes buds. I had to do that. I went there the third time because he came down—if he caught me in the cabin, he’d put me up again. So after the third time I did it, I met up with these two guys who were there, sitting there on top of the hull, on top of the edge of the hull, I don’t know how you call it. One of them was Corporal <persName>John Setelin</persName> and the other one was not wearing a shirt, only a t-shirt. These two guys were wearing hats. The only ones that were wearing hats in the whole ship. So he calls me over and says, “Lieutenant, what are you doing?” I told him and he says, “That’s not your job.” I told him, “That’s my job. Captain <persName>Koga</persName> put me in charge of doing that.” He says, “That’s not your job, lieutenant. Men will get ill will against you because it’s considered harassment and if you go to combat with any of those guys, they’ll shoot you in the back. That’s our job. Next time they tell you to come up here and make sure the deck is policed, look for us and we’ll handle it.” And he did from then on. I asked him why he was wearing a hat and both of them took their hats off. <persName>John Setelin</persName> had one of those mohawk cuts, shaved head and just the mohawk. His buddy had two tufts and the other all shaved except for these two. Not the V but—and he said that Colonel <persName>White</persName>, the battalion commander, didn’t like that so he made them wear hats. I said, “These guys, I wish I had them in my platoon, when I get my platoon because these are the guys you can really rely on in combat. They are not garrison troopers.” I knew they weren’t—in the infantry, you had corporals at that time, they were only for the artillery. So long afterwards I asked him, in the first reunion when I met him again in <date>’91</date>, I asked him why was he a corporal at the time. He said he got busted for E6 for swinging at an officer.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">Oh, gosh. So they were out of regulation. Colonel didn’t like it; they were almost regulation probably because they had buzz cuts on the sides, right?</u>
      <u who="PUJALS">Oh no, they were very effusive young men. Loaded with piss and puck as we used to say, you know? </u>
      <u who="MILAM">Yeah. </u>
      <u who="PUJALS">That was their everyday core. They showed it that way, they weren’t the only ones. You know, you see in <name type="event">World War II</name> movies, the paratroopers when you see <persName>Eisenhower</persName> is interviewing them before they go. The ones that are not wearing helmets or anything? They got the mohawk cuts, most of them.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">So let’s talk about how you finally get a job!</u>
      <u who="PUJALS">Well I finally got a job <date>several weeks</date> after we arrived. I was made assistant S2. I was placed by the, I forget the captain’s name, Captain <persName>Lawrence</persName>, I think. No, no not <persName>Lawrence</persName>. He was the S2 and he was a new S2 because the previous S2 was captain <persName>Pritko</persName>. He was overweight and shipped off to some other place, I don’t know what happened to him. I think his name was <persName>Lawrence</persName>, Captain <persName>Lawrence</persName>, I'm pretty sure. He told me to work on the order of battle. I had to learn everything I could about the enemies. The designation of the units, the <orgName>TOE</orgName> (<orgName>Table of Organization and Equipment</orgName>), the weapons, the organization—the <orgName>TOE</orgName>, the table of organization and equipment. I remember a lot of that. One of the important things that I had not known was that the enemy used different designations for the same units, in order to confuse us. To confuse their enemy. </u>
      <u who="MILAM">You were looking at both PAVN (<orgName>People’s Army</orgName> of <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>) and the Viet Cong?</u>
      <u who="PUJALS">Both PAVN and <placeName>Vietcong</placeName>, but mostly PAVN because that’s the one we were hunting for.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">When did you—when were you made assistant S2?</u>
      <u who="PUJALS">I don’t remember the exact date, it was something <date>about three weeks</date>, something like <date>late September</date> or maybe—</u>
      <u who="MILAM"><date>Three weeks</date> after you got in country?</u>
      <u who="PUJALS">Yeah, <date>about three weeks</date> after I got in county.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">Okay, and <date>the first three weeks</date>, what did you do?</u>
      <u who="PUJALS">Go back and forth and pick up messages and whatever they were ready for in the distribution list for the 2nd Battalion, go there and poof around. Basically nothing. I’d get up early in the morning, work out and I did dynamic tension exercises and then I was free all day, except when I had to go and pick up the mail two or three times a day.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">At what point in, after you joined the cav, were you given a M16?</u>
      <u who="PUJALS">As soon as I got there.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">As soon as you got there, so you—</u>
      <u who="PUJALS">Not actually as soon as I got there. When I finished the interview with Captain <persName>Johnson</persName>, he passed on and I was accepted, and I had an interview with Colonel <persName>White</persName>. </u>
      <u who="MILAM">Yes. </u>
      <u who="PUJALS">And in the middle I had an interview with a sergeant major, which I didn’t remember. I never remembered seeing this sergeant major and he knew me. He remembered, he said a couple of reunions ago he says, “Of course, I had an interview with you, I talked to you.” And I didn’t remember, I said, “Sorry, sergeant major.” Well Captain <persName>Johnson</persName> said, “Take the time off, go take care of your personal business, get ready to leave and come back.” I took off <date>five-six days</date>. I finally came back. I came back and everything was closed down except for this sergeant there, he had a whole bunch of keys. He said, “Lieutenant Pujals!” I said, “That’s right, sergeant.” He said, “Come over here.” He opened up the armory, he gave me an <orgName>M16</orgName> rifle, fifteen magazines, the cleaning kit and a bipod. He issued me a weapons card right there, I signed it and left it with him. He said, “You have to go now to qualification fire.” He gave me the address to where the rifle range was and I took off, he locked up and took off too. I was the only one he was waiting for. (Chuckles) So I had it from the very beginning.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">Okay. So when you get to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, within <date>three weeks</date> or so they make you the battalion assistant S2 and they put you on this project to figure out what it is you’re there to do. Learn about this enemy. </u>
      <u who="PUJALS">You’re right.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">Did you participate in any of the operations? I think there was one called “Silver Bayonet”—</u>
      <u who="PUJALS">There was one we called that, they had these weird names for it, mostly it was bayonet. Silver Bayonet, Shiny Bayonet, <persName>Sticky Bayonet</persName>, something like that. It was in a place we called <placeName>Happy Valley</placeName>. Captain <persName>Lawrence</persName>, he went to the advanced CP (Command Post) and I stayed behind. With, as we used to say, the clerks and jerks, just dividing stuff. I had to stay behind. After <date>several days</date>, about two or three days after that, they move me forward to the advanced CP. When I got there, I was placed in charge—I was placed under supervision, a 2nd lieutenant, a whole bunch of—under supervision of a NCO. I think, a sergeant 1st class <orgName>E7</orgName> rank, <persName>Sergeant Bass</persName>. He was the assistant S3, the operation sergeant. I was the assistant S2 and there I was operations something, whatever. He said I had to dig my own foxhole and I dug a two-mile foxhole; you know a six foot by six feet by three feet wide. I did it. I only went as far as about five feet, just enough so it could cover, my head was up here not all the way down. I did it perfect, except I didn’t do the last foot. I decided not to sleep in it that night. I stayed up, it rained a little bit, not much and the next morning there was this huge scorpion there on the edge, just inside. (Chuckles) I was lucky not to sleep there. One of the things that they told me, as the assistant S2, look around and see if anybody left any trash that has value for the enemy. There was this huge wrapper from a care package from home with a name, rank, service number, address of the person, the whole unit designation, and the home address of the person that sent it to him. I picked it up and gave it to the S2. I said, “Look at this. What happened with it, I don’t know.”</u>
      <u who="MILAM">Interesting. Let’s talk a little bit about <date>November 14th</date>.</u>
      <u who="PUJALS"><date>November 14th</date>. <date>November 14th</date>, my battalion and my company was still running through the woods looking for the enemy, going up and down hills, crossing little streams, that’s what we were doing.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">And <orgName>1st battalion</orgName> had taken off to X-Ray <date>that day</date>?</u>
      <u who="PUJALS">We were slightly isolated. There was little information given to us. I tried to pick up as much information as I could in these orders and officer’s calls when we had—when the company commander had them. I took as many notes as I could and gave my men as much information because I learned that during <date>summer</date> camp. There was very little information that was given to us, who played the enlistment in <placeName>ROTC</placeName> summer camp. So I got as much as possible because I wanted to have my men—and that’s one of the things they tell you, always. Keep your men informed with all the information that you can. So that’s what I did. What information we had about what was going outside, we received mostly from the RTOs (<orgName>Radio Telephone Operator</orgName>) because you know, they heard half of the conversation and knew most of what was going on.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">Now on <date>the 14th</date>, at least just using <date>that day</date>, you had a platoon by then?</u>
      <u who="PUJALS">I had a platoon. I became a platoon leader just about two, maybe <date>three days</date> at the most before we set out on an operation. We set out on that operation on or about the 8th or 9th of <date>November</date>, my company, <persName>Charlie Company</persName> 2nd of the 7th.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">And in your operation, somewhere <date>between the 8th and 14th</date>, did you make enemy contact?</u>
      <u who="PUJALS">No, not us.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">Not your unit. Okay. Then you come back, and on <date>the 14th</date>, you are still out on the boonies conducting operations, and is it the generally vicinity of X-Ray? I'm trying to think of where.</u>
      <u who="PUJALS">I don’t know exactly where we were. We were in the general vicinity of <placeName>Pleiku</placeName>. That’s what I knew. We had our own maps, we had our maps taken around, I had a map, and I don’t remember very well but we were going up there. Actually, we were just going fast because I was at first a point platoon. Part of me wasn’t fast enough because I was doing what I learned from the book and what I learned in the U2 program. We’re out to contact the enemy, so we’re out searching, and we had to go not too fast, you know? Look, really look for them. Be careful for an ambush. I had out flanker people, the rear of security, I had the whole works in my platoon up front. I had a pacer; I double check the pace and I was the one—I had another man with a compass, who was a steer man and I also double checked with my compass. But they claimed I was too slow, and we were drifting slightly to the left. So when we stopped on <date>the first day</date>, that was the 8th or the 9th, when we stopped for one of the breaks—the last break in the afternoon, it was 4:30, when we stopped, the company commander said “Outside of the point, we’re going to stay there the night.” And I was out on the rear. So he put me back on the rear and the rear <date>the next day</date>, he was like a race. He would go up epsilon as we call it, you know you close up your coordinating effect. We were going up fast, I had to pull in my flankers, I didn’t want to lose anybody. I don’t know where the hell we were going because we didn’t know where the enemy was. I mean, if we knew where the enemy was and we were trying to get there as fast as possible I had no problem, you know. But if we were looking for the enemy, he could of just as easily be ready to ambush us at any point there because nobody was looking around the pacing.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">So around the 14th, you hear what’s going on at X-Ray but only through RTOs who have been monitoring the radios?</u>
      <u who="PUJALS">As I remember it was on <date>the 15th</date>. Apparently, this information didn’t get disseminated, at least in my platoon, in my company. On <date>the 15th</date>, all of the sudden we were told to halt and to move to a small hill where it was fairly clear and clear it. They had some saplings, some of them <date>three and a half inches</date> thick, and to clear it and make a landing zone to be picked up. Where we were going, they didn’t tell us, the RTOs. This information I had, that’s what I got from the company commander. That’s when information started dribbling in. The first battalion is in deep doo-doo. You know, a deep one. They had been fighting since <date>yesterday</date> and there’s a lot of causalities and we are going to reinforce them. But actually, what we did, we cleared it, and the first <persName>Chinook</persName> came in, two Chinooks. They just grabbed them, without any organizations, they just grabbed people and throw them out there and throw them back. You know, facing forward.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">On the <persName>Chinook</persName>?</u>
      <u who="PUJALS">Yeah, spread eagle, like that. (<orgName>Interviewee</orgName> demonstrates to the interviewer) The next one came here, all the way down. Two or three lines until we covered the hole and filled in the <persName>Chinook</persName> and took us off.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">How many people did you put on that <persName>Chinook</persName>, do have any idea?</u>
      <u who="PUJALS">I think you could put at least thirty, at least. I think it was <date>forty</date> you could put in a <persName>Chinook</persName>, I don’t remember right now, it was so long ago. We fill up completely and we got to the tea plantation and they had an air strip over there in a first mission after we got there, set up security with whatever people that were there on that ship. Some of them were in my platoon, some of them from other platoons. When the other <persName>Chinook</persName> came in, we got completely reorganized, set the people up divided by the platoon and set up the perimeter. Before that, I was amazed. Is this the way things are supposed to work? (Chuckles) Then we got our orders, I was told what we were going to do. We were going to stay there, set up security for the night because they had attacked that same place the night before. We were not going to reinforce the other battalion. The next morning, that’s when they told us come over and pick up the order, and that’s what the rumor was, you know the <orgName>RTO</orgName> started coming and said, “That’s where we are going. The information is ours. Here captain and lieutenant, were going to reinforce the first battalion.” But this came up <date>the next day</date>.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">So now were about the 16th?</u>
      <u who="PUJALS">This is <date>the 15th and now the 16th</date>.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">Now the 16th?</u>
      <u who="PUJALS">Yeah. We were going to go at dawn. They were going to pick us up at first daylight, but they kept postponing it, postponing it, and finally the information kept trickling down through them themselves, nothing from back channels. There was a heavy firefight going on in the early morning and that’s why we were being postponed. All of the sudden, I don’t remember what time it was, but it was already fairly early in the morning. They said, “Alright, saddle up, we’re going.” They picked us up, we went to the helicopters and we went to—we landed away from the LZ. We landed; I think it must’ve been in the other LZ that they cleared with the explosives. Must’ve been because we—they dropped us off there and we walked in. As we were walking into X-Ray, we were zapped by two helicopters.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">Two what?</u>
      <u who="PUJALS">We were attacked by two of our gunships.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">Two of our own?</u>
      <u who="PUJALS">Two of our own. Two men from the 1st platoon got wounded. What they did is they held the 1st platoon, take care of the wounded, and set up a perimeter around them and the 2nd and 3rd platoon, us, we moved in. We moved into X-Ray, it was quiet, there was an air strike going on. All of the sudden, a firefight broke out that lasted very few minutes. But most of the fire was ours, it was going out.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">So the attack that happened by our own helicopters, our own gunships, what was your—What did you think was going on there?</u>
      <u who="PUJALS">They thought we were coming in from the rear! We came in from the rear and when we came out, we were flanking. We hit right on the left <orgName>flank</orgName>.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">Did the attack by the gunships—were you able to call it off, or did it just stop?</u>
      <u who="PUJALS">Yeah, it was called off. Apparently, the people who were getting hit were the 1st platoon and they made several passes at us, several passes.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">Yeah, the reason I'm asking that is that I’ve talked to, over <date>the last couple days</date>, I’ve talked to several helicopter pilots and one of the questions that I ask is—I know later in the war, tactical support by helicopters with Cobra gunships became very ordinary. That’s how you got tactical air support when you were on the ground. But you didn’t have it then?</u>
      <u who="PUJALS">We didn’t have <persName>Cobras</persName> then. No, we had the <orgName>Hueys</orgName>.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">That’s what I'm wondering. No one called that in.</u>
      <u who="PUJALS">No, no, no.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">They had to have seen something and you think it was initiated on their own?</u>
      <u who="PUJALS">It must’ve been an air strike going on because they must’ve been circling around waiting for the F-100s, were the ones that were doing the airstrike from <orgName>the Air Force</orgName>. They were flying very slow, firing the Gatling gun, the 30 mm and dropping bombs.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">But you are sure it was helicopter fire rather than the A-1Es?</u>
      <u who="PUJALS">The thing is and the weird thing was, this is one of those things that they say was so confusing and disconcerting, the attack by the helicopter, because when they cut away, they go like this.(Makes helicopter dubs noises)Sounded like a machine gun! So everything time they made a pass, it sounded like they were strafing us, but they probably made one or two shooting passes. But they made several passes and these passes when they cut away, they sounded like machine gun.(Repeats helicopter noises)That’s why when I was looking around and finally, I saw the helicopter. Somebody said, “It’s the helicopter that’s shooting at us.” Because you know, we were deployed to both sides of the trail because we thought it was maybe an enemy coming in but it was actually a helicopter. I looked up and finally saw one of them coming around.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">And you said we had a couple of guys wounded?</u>
      <u who="PUJALS">Two guys wounded from the 1st platoon.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">Okay. So you’re out there working your way toward X-Ray and this is <date>the 3rd day</date> of X-Ray, so then what happens? Continue that day for me.</u>
      <u who="PUJALS">Well, we moved in. There was this cameraman, and he was dressed in fatigues, it turned out to be the two-man team from the army signal core. They were filming us. So I am walking in, they are filming us and my platoon and he started filming me for the close up and I was getting up close and all of the sudden that’s when the firefight broke out. He broke out like this, this way.(Interviewee demonstrates to the interviewer what direction the cameraman moved)He nearly smashed me in the face with the camera. He started running, he ran over a couple of boxes, C-rations, a couple boxes of ammunition and threw himself, landed on one knee and started panning. After a few more minutes, fire died out. We just kept on going. I heard all the fire, most of it going on our side, going over a few meters to our left. So, it’s going. I said, “It’s not going to hurt us.” We just kept on going. We finally ended, we cut to a place over there and the company commander halted us and told us where we were going to go, this is your platoon area. My platoon area took over for one of the platoons for <orgName>Alpha</orgName> company, Captain <persName>Tony Nadal</persName>’s company had been, inside the dried creek bed, partly outside. So I had two squads inside. One of them partly inside the dry creek, but the other completely inside. The third squad which was only about five men, on the outside. That’s how we broke out.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">Yeah, his company was decimated. They were down to forty-three killed or wounded so he was about less than fifty percent of what he started with which is already about sixty percent of <orgName>TOE</orgName>.</u>
      <u who="PUJALS">Yeah, that’s right. We were about fifty-five, sixty percent TOE. My platoon and I had twenty-five men, my platoon sergeant and myself. When we left, I had to leave two at the tea plantation, with fever of unknown origin which usually turned out to be <placeName>Malaria</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">Yeah, I know.</u>
      <u who="PUJALS">When I went to check on them, they told me my friend <placeName>Taboada</placeName>, <persName>Raul Taboada</persName>, who had been a mortarman, he had been wounded on <date>the 14th</date>. There was this— and I hope this sergeant, I hope somebody can find him. There was this sergeant and I thought he was with <date>the 1st of the 7th</date>, he was from <placeName>Ponce</placeName>, <placeName>Puerto Rico</placeName> and I’ve never been able to find out. I forgot his name. They gave him two different names. First something, Santiago. I couldn’t find any Santiago doctors. The other name they gave him was Ortiz-Suarez, those were the two last names. <persName>Ortiz-Suarez Humberto</persName>. I was never able to find anybody with those names either, nobody knows about him. I tried asking, the only—<date>the 1st of the 7th</date>, the battalion surgeon was Italian descent. I forget his name now. He said he had been there from before the battle. But this captain from <placeName>Puerto Rico</placeName> was onboard the ship, that’s where I met him. My name Pujals, there’s several Pujals families in <placeName>Ponce</placeName> where he lived. So he saw my name and came over and said, “Are you from <placeName>Puerto Rico</placeName>?” then we started chatting around.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">I see. So you’re there reinforcing <orgName>Alpha Company</orgName> of <date>1st of the 7th</date>.</u>
      <u who="PUJALS">Well, we started to reinforce them, but the battle was practically over. What we ended up doing was replacing them. The order was changed to “You will take over their positions instead of augmenting them.”</u>
      <u who="MILAM">And they pull out?</u>
      <u who="PUJALS">They pulled out. I met up with <persName>John Setelin</persName>, he was a sergeant then and his friend, <placeName>Lamont</placeName>. I forgot his first name—<persName>James Lamont</persName>. I met up with them, talked to them, they told me to pick up as much ammunition as I could. They had several people that got killed because they ran out of ammunition. So they tell me, “Pick up as much ammo, forget about food, forget about water. Ammunition, you need it.”</u>
      <u who="MILAM">Absolutely.</u>
      <u who="PUJALS">That’s what I did.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">Take me through <date>the next couple of days</date>, did you stay at <orgName>X-Ray</orgName>?</u>
      <u who="PUJALS">We stayed at X-Ray over the night, nothing had happened. There’s some firing and some of my men claimed that <persName>Drew McKinney</persName>, he was one of my fireteam leaders, he claims that he fired some snipers and he knocked out one. There’s some others that, I forget who he was, from another platoon, who claimed he shot with a M39 and wiped out a sniper in a tree. But as far as I remember, there's nothing. Firing, check the line. That was it.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">Yeah, and you stayed for how many more days?</u>
      <u who="PUJALS">All the night. The next morning, on <date>the 17th</date>, we were supposed to move out as soon as possible because the B-52s were going to blast the place. That kept being postponed and postponed until we finally left. We left, I forget what time, but it was very well into the morning also.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">They extracted you by chopper?</u>
      <u who="PUJALS">Oh no sir, we walked out. Not to a short space like when we came in, this was a long walk. We were to go to an LZ but before we got there, we were going to split. We were marching out with companies from two of the battalions of the 5th Cav. From <date>the 1st</date> of the 5th, and <date>the 2nd of the</date> 5th. The order I received from <orgName>Captain Fesmire</orgName>, he passed away <date>a few years ago</date>, the order was—we were marching out and our company was going to be the rear most company in the battalion, and I was going to be the rear most platoon. Nobody behind me. We were not going to have any artillery after we split out. The 2nd of the 5th I think it was, one of 5th battalions, they would move out to LZ <placeName>Columbus</placeName> and we would keep on going onto another LZ. I don’t remember if we had the name given at the time.</u>
      <u who="MILAM"><orgName>Falcon</orgName>? <placeName>Columbus</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="PUJALS">No, it turned out to be <placeName>Albany</placeName>. But at the time I don’t remember that they gave it a name. They had different letters for some of them. I don’t remember which one, but I remember distinctly LZ Albany I only learned that later as far as I am concerned. From that point on, we would have no artillery support and I was scared for that. You know, no more artillery. I had read several other books, at least two different books by <persName>Bernard</persName>. </u>
      <u who="MILAM"><persName>Bernard Fall</persName>?</u>
      <u who="PUJALS"><persName>Bernard Fall</persName>. One of the things that they had, that the French learned was to take their artillery with them. <persName>Halt</persName>, set up artillery and move.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">Hell in a very small place.</u>
      <u who="PUJALS">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">So you’re on the march to this place that we know now will be—</u>
      <u who="PUJALS">Turned out to be <placeName>Albany</placeName>. We weren’t told what was going to happened after. Some people say, some others have claimed in the book that we were going to be extracted. But from what I remember when they issued the order was, be prepared to continue the march. So we might have been extracted, we were going there to maybe be extradited, maybe to continue the operation, maybe to continue the march so—</u>
      <u who="MILAM">It wasn’t—you were going somewhere. You were not on operation to engage the enemy. </u>
      <u who="PUJALS">Right.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">Because you had a whole lot of administrative types that you were escorting, correct? The whole battalion. </u>
      <u who="PUJALS">Right. As far as—the attitude was that the battle was over. That was the attitude. It was not exactly said, the attitude was the power was forward, we beat the heck out of them, the other battalion did and we were moving out because—I tried to get information of why we weren’t getting extracted and all we got was some other people that the helicopters were down for maintenance because they had used them so much during <date>the three days</date> of battle. That was it. There’s no battle, there’s no search. <persName>Larry Gwin</persName> remembers it differently. He wrote a small monograph when he was in college. He says we were going to be extracted and continue in the operation and search for the enemy and they were going to move in a tactical formation, epsilon right I think it was. We were just moving in a column and we were moving as fast as possible.</u>
      <u who="MILAM">What was <persName>Larry Gwin’s</persName>—</u>
      <u who="PUJALS"><persName>Larry Gwin</persName> was <date>the 1st</date> lieutenant. He was the executive officer of <orgName>Alpha Company</orgName>, <date>2nd of the 7th</date>.</u>
      <u who="MILAM"><orgName>XO of Alpha Company</orgName>?</u>
      <u who="PUJALS">Yeah, <orgName>XO Alpha</orgName>. </u>
      <u who="MILAM">Okay. So tell me what happens when the firing starts. What was your platoon’s position?</u>
      <u who="PUJALS">Where we halted, at that time just before that, one of my men told me that we had people behind us. I was worried, I said, “Oh shit.” Because I was supposed to be the rear most. It turned out to be Captain <persName>Forrest</persName>’s Company. <date>1st</date> of the 5th, I think it was <date>the 1st</date>. He was <orgName>Alpha Company</orgName>, Captain <persName>George Forrest’s</persName> Company. So there was no problem there. That got me wondering, if I'm supposed to the last guy here, how come we got more people behind? Then we stopped—from the <orgName>RTO</orgName>, the information I got was that the conference for all company commanders has been called, our company commanders are going up forward. We’re halted, they found two enemy soldiers and they captured two enemy allegedly deserters, who say that there’s more deserters around but there’s a lot more who didn’t want to desert, waiting for us someplace and they were eager to kill Americans. What else? That’s basically what they said about the enemy. There were snipers also in the trees. After a while, the shooting started. You know, like a rifle range, you know? Not everybody starts at the same time, you hear,(Interviewee makes automatic gun noises)and it starts growing. In between it grows up, it grows down, and when it slows down, you get the explosions. Four, five, six, seven.(Interviewee makes gun noises and explosion noises)Then it picks up. Then goes up again and the explosion and it goes,(Interviewee repeats explosion noises)this is lasting a bit longer; I'm trying to get information of what’s going on. Nobody knows, so I say to my men, my squad leaders, “Get the men deployed. Be prepared for something here.” After a while of this going on, my <orgName>RTO</orgName> calls me, <orgName>CO1-CO</orgName>. I ask him what’s going on. He said, “Forget that. Get your men in line and maneuver right.” The classic anti-ambush. So that’s what I did. I’d done that in Fort Benning three or four times. So I tried to get my men in line, I am using hand and arm signals.(Interviewee shows interviewer hand and arm signals)Like this is get in line, nobody knew what the hell is going on. I'm moving forward, and I turn around and everybody is back there scratching themselves asking, “What’s going on? What, what, what?” I said, “Get on line! Get on line! Everybody get on line!” The <orgName>RTO</orgName> says, “CO wants you!” I call him and he says, “Hold your platoon where you are. Prepare to defend.” And that’s it. He didn’t say anything. He didn’t say, “Prepare to defend, defensive position.” Nothing. “Hold your platoon where you are.” That’s it. “Stop the maneuver.” So I try to get my men in a defensive position and the fighting just kept on going. Way up front. Then some of my men started firing at the trees. So I said, “Stop firing because our fire is going to get over there.” Some rounds started coming over this way. I tried to get the whole company commander to tell them, you know, “They’re shooting at us.” I couldn’t get him, I couldn’t get anybody on the horn and then I tried to get my squad leaders on the PRC6s, they didn’t work. I said, “Maybe it’s off.” So I turn it off, turn it on, turn it off. Doesn’t work. So I said, “Can I get somebody to turn the radios on?” Wait a couple of minutes, make sure the radios are on. Couldn’t work anything, no information I couldn’t(Editor’s Note: Audio file cuts here.)</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
