<?xml-model href="../schemas/ddhi.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Transcript of an Interview with Richard Robert Ackerman</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>
          <orgName>Vietnam Center and Sam Johnson Vietnam Archive</orgName>
        </authority>
        <date>
          <!--  Date of publication, e.g. for citation purposes  -->
        </date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <recordingStmt>
          <recording xml:id="primary_recording" type="video" dur-iso="00:48:24">
            <!-- https://www.digi.com/resources/documentation/digidocs/90001437-13/reference/r_iso_8601_duration_format.htm -->
            <media url="https://vva.vietnam.ttu.edu/images.php?img=/OH/OH0474/OH0474.mp4" mimeType="video/mp4"/>
          </recording>
        </recordingStmt>
        <bibl xml:id="primary_transcription">
          <respStmt>
            <persName>Mark Steven Varela</persName>
            <orgName>Vietnam Center and Sam Johnson Vietnam Archive</orgName>
            <resp ref="http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/trc.html">Transcriber</resp>
          </respStmt>
          <ref target="path_to_file">https://vva.vietnam.ttu.edu/images.php?img=/OH/OH0474/OH0474.pdf</ref>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The Oral History Project of the Vietnam Center and Sam Johnson Vietnam Archive</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application ident="DDHIEncoder" version="1.0">
          <desc>Conversion from Word docx to TEI xml.</desc>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en-us">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <particDesc>
        <person xml:id="ACKERMAN"/>
        <person xml:id="NAPOLI"/>
      </particDesc>
      <settingDesc>
        <setting>
          <date when-iso="2005-11-11"/>
          <locale/>
        </setting>
      </settingDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <u who="NAPOLI">This is Professor <persName>Philip F. Napoli</persName>, <date when="2005-11-11">today</date> is <date when="2005-11-11">the 11th of November 2005</date>. I'm with Mr. <persName>Ackerman</persName> at the <placeName>Crystal City Hilton</placeName>. (Editor’s Note: Interview speaks to a third party, not relevant to the interview.) Could you say your name and tell me what you had for breakfast <date when="2005-11-11">today</date>.</u>
      <u who="ACKERMAN"><persName>Dick Ackerman</persName>, I'm still waiting to go to breakfast. (Laughs)</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">So Mr. <persName>Ackerman</persName>, tell me your age and where you were born and grew up.</u>
      <u who="ACKERMAN">I am <persName>Richard R. Ackerman</persName>, but I go by “<persName>Dick</persName>.” I'm sixty-four, born in <placeName>Brooklyn, New York</placeName>. I was adopted out of there, I was raised by a career <orgName>Air Force</orgName> man, so I'm an <orgName>Air Force</orgName> brat. In fact, when I came back from <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, my dad went three months later and spent his year over there. It was kind of tough on my mom.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">Where were you raised? In <placeName>Brooklyn</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="ACKERMAN">No, mostly in <placeName>Rantoul, Illinois</placeName>, <placeName>Chanute Air Force Base</placeName>. We had three years in <placeName>England</placeName>, and couple of other places but that’s the main place, that’s what I call my hometown because I went to high school, graduated there. You know, friends from school and all that.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">Sure. So was joining the <orgName>military</orgName> kind of a natural thing for you?</u>
      <u who="ACKERMAN">No. (Chuckles)</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">Tell me that story then.</u>
      <u who="ACKERMAN">Well, back in <date when="1964">’64</date>, <date when="1963">’63</date> when the draft—if you were 1A it was very hard to get a job. Because they would have to hold your job for you until you got back, when you were drafted. So I was running around partying and having a goodtime, my mother thought I ought to settle down but couldn’t get a good job so she just wrote to the draft board and said, “Either draft him or change his status.” I was twenty-two years old! I could’ve probably made it through, but she got me drafted. It was a good thing, straighten me out a lot. (Laughs)</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">Alright, tell me a little bit about your training.</u>
      <u who="ACKERMAN"><placeName>Fort Knox, Kentucky</placeName> for basic. Then, <placeName>Fort Jackson, South Carolina</placeName> for AIT (Advanced Individual Training) and then <placeName>Fort Benning</placeName>. I was in the <orgName>29th Infantry</orgName>, which was a support battalion for <orgName>OCS (Officer Candidate School)</orgName> and ranger training. We were the aggressors whenever they went out to the field and simulated, we were the aggressors out there. That was when we went up to the <placeName>Dahlonega, Georgia</placeName> to mountain ranger camp. We went down to the <placeName>Air Force Base</placeName> for the swamp training and of course they had to hump the hills and we went on trucks, but that was okay. (Laughs) That was interesting. I ended up driving the company deuce and a half, so there wasn’t a lot of training. I never even saw my first M16 until I was issued it on the way to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. I wasn’t in the <orgName>1st Cavalry Division</orgName>. When they were preparing to go, they went around <placeName>Fort Benning</placeName>—well, first they determined who wasn’t going to go, the short-timers and the medical profiles and things like that. Then they just went around <placeName>Fort Benning</placeName>, I guess grabbing bodies to fill the slots. I got like two weeks’ notice I was going.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">Do you know why you got picked?</u>
      <u who="ACKERMAN">Infantry MOS (Military Occupational Specialty), I'm sure. (Laughs) There’s no doubt in my mind, because I was a short timer. When—I was supposed to get out <date when="1966-01-01">New Year’s Day</date> and they made the cut off somewhere in the middle of <date when="1965-10">October</date>, I think. If you were supposed to get out before that, you didn’t go. After that, you had to go. Then you got out when you’re over there, so I ended up going. I think they just went around and said, “We want you; we want you. Yeah, okay you come here.” Maybe I was at the wrong spot at the wrong time. (Laughs) I think that happens a lot in the <orgName>Army</orgName>. (Laughs)</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">Do you remember the trip to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="ACKERMAN">Yeah, we took the buses up to <placeName>Charleston, South Carolina</placeName>. I went over on the <orgName>General Maurice Rose</orgName>. We went down through the <placeName>Panama Canal</placeName>, up to <placeName>Long Beach</placeName>. Then, from <placeName>Long Beach</placeName> we were supposed to head over, but we got a guy with appendicitis on the ship. We had to go through the <placeName>Hawaii Islands</placeName>, they sent a ship out to pick him up and take him off, and then we went over. We had a typhoon outside of <placeName>Japan</placeName>, which was kind of rough in the ship because everybody had to stay below and guys getting sick all over in this troop ship with the bunks like this. You know, when you slept you roll inward because you never knew what was going to be coming down. (Laughs) That was quite interesting, but on calm days it was real nice. The ocean was like glass sometimes, we had movies up on the top deck and of course what they showed was combat guild TV series, which was what we wanted to see heading to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. (Laughs)</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">Spent time playing cards?</u>
      <u who="ACKERMAN">Oh yeah, lot of cards, lot of hearts. I spent a lot of time on deck. I didn’t get seasick, got queasy, but I didn’t get seasick. A lot of guys did get sick, of course they got the heads on the boats in the front and the back, where you get the most movement from. That doesn’t help either. Some guys were homestead on the toilets. You go in there and use one and— (Interviewee makes groaning noises) “This is mine!” (Laughs) That looks good on tape, doesn’t it?</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">It’s the truth!</u>
      <u who="ACKERMAN">Yeah, that’s exactly right.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">Tell me about arriving.</u>
      <u who="ACKERMAN">We arrived in <placeName>Qui Nhon</placeName>. We went—we got off the boat onto LSTs (Landing Ship Tanks), down cargo into LSTs. Then we got to the shore and they issued ammunition and everything, we don’t know what to expect, but we were carrying our duffle bags and everything else so I don’t know if they really thought of anything was going to happen or not. Then we got—after we got on shore, they took us to, I guess we went straight into the helicopters, went straight to <placeName>An Khe</placeName>. I do have some blanks from over there. We got there, they had little bit of a clearing there but we basically had to clear our base camp there and we put up pup tents and first couple of nights, we got guys being bit by centipedes and I mean the centipedes like this. (Interviewee shows length with hands) Huge and maybe as big around as your thumb. They bite you and they can poison you, they were poisonous. So they made us put cots in our pup tents and that didn’t work too well. We had some kind of plastic somewhere and we just made our own tents, to get the cots in there, to get us off the ground. I think it was—our mess hall was a big tent too. Even if it was raining, you went up, get your food and went outside in the rain and ate. Water was a scarce commodity, only had one water trailer for a battalion. Of course, when it rained or any other problems like that, cut back on our water supply. I remember one time they couldn’t get food to us some reason. This is still in base camp and we ended up eating canned salmon, saltines with a little bit of water that we had, for about a couple of weeks. It was only a year or so ago I started eating salmon again. (Laughs) I just had a hard time with that.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">Tell me a little bit more about your impression of <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> when you arrived. The heat, the terrain, you mentioned the bugs. I'm interested in anything you have to say about physically what it was like to be there.</u>
      <u who="ACKERMAN">It wasn’t super hot when we got there. It was definitely different than what I was used to—even though we were up in the mountains, I went down in the delta and all that stuff and it was just weird. We had some of the local refuges in the village, they’d hire them to come out and help clear the perimeter around the base camp, that was the first introduction to the people. Of course, they were all black pajama refugees and they come out there chopping down the trees with those little hook things, which were very efficient like scythe type things. They’d cut a tree down to here, maybe next day down to here. I don’t know if that was job security or what, but it was the same tree, go down that far. We had found of that some of them were the guerillas and they’d be out there, they’d let you take a break, when you take a break you just star peeling bark off of it, not thinking anything about it. Somebody else with that little chopper chopping and stuff like that. To get the perimeter, you had to come to the base camp and go by our fox holes and they could see what we had, the machine guns and whatever. They’d go out there and peel that bark off and at night that just glowed. They’d lay it down, the guy who was chopping, he’d make a couple of chops and maybe one chop, that would indicate what was in the hole. We’d get back to work, they would just lay a stick down and it’s pointing right at the foxhole and told them what was in that foxhole. So at night we had to switch stuff around the holes, once we found out what they were doing. You know, this was <date when="1965">’65</date>, when we first went over there, we had to learn a lot of this stuff the hard way. I thought that was kind of ingenious of them, but it definitely wasn’t appreciated. (Laughs)</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">I can understand that. Tell me about the first number of weeks of shakedown operation you guys went through.</u>
      <u who="ACKERMAN">We went—well, our first actual mission that we were supposed to go on, which I found out a few years later they didn’t expect us to come back from, was a down helicopter on a sandbar. They loaded us up into a Chinook and on the way they were telling us where—they told us a Vietnamese word for halt, “Dung Lai” in case you needed to stop somebody advancing and they don’t shoot them. This chopper was down, it was on the sandbar and we had to supposedly provide the defense for it while they were repairing it so they could get it out. Later on, the word was that it was a general with all kinds of good stuff, food, stuff like that and they didn’t want to lose that. Risk our lives for that but I don’t know how true that was. Halfway there they aborted it for some reason, and we came back. We just did a lot of patrolling around there. Take us out and drop us off, we’d go on patrols and come back again. It wasn’t a lot of action at that time. It was just long hard days out walking. I was usually point man; I was in a recon platoon. When I was usually point man, I didn’t mind that, but I was like I said, drafted late. I was twenty-four years old over there. Would rather me be in front than some young kid that took it for a lark. I figured out I was more responsible, so I didn’t mind being in the point. Not a good place to be. (Laughs)</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">Were you good at it?</u>
      <u who="ACKERMAN">Yeah, I think I was. I was told I was. I didn’t like being back in the middle of everybody else anyway. I liked being where I could see what was going on.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">Tell me about the events leading up to several days in <date when="1965-11">November</date>.</u>
      <u who="ACKERMAN">Well, just before <name type="event">Ia Drang Valley</name>, I was on R&amp;R (Rest and Recuperation) in country, out of <placeName>Vung Tau</placeName>. The guy who come to greet—well, as I was waiting to leave, I had three days down there. As I was waiting to leave, all of the sudden things started happening. You see stuff going on around you and I was sitting on the back of a deuce and a half, waiting for the plane and I could see these two helicopters, I can tell they were going to hit each other. One was a Chinook, and one was a Huey. I could see the guys in the Huey, but I could tell they were going to hit each other. All I could do is sit there and watch them. They hit, went down in flames. I go, “Woah.” That was right around the beginning of the <name type="event">Ia Drang</name>, in the first initial part of it because we were—our plane was late, we lost a day just sitting around there waiting because everything was directed towards <placeName>Ia Drang Valley</placeName>, I don’t think it was <placeName>X-Ray</placeName> yet. I think it might’ve been a <placeName>Plei Me camp</placeName>. Finally, when the plane came in, we got on the plane and were taxiing. They stopped, they came back and said “Lift your feet guys, start throwing body bags in. So we had nothing to do but to put our feet down on the body bag. I mean, you can’t sit for a whole flight like that. Then we taxied again, they stopped, and they came back, and they took all the body bags off again. I never have understood what that was about, but that was beginning of <name type="event">Ia Drang</name>. At the time, I didn’t know it. I went on to R&amp;R. The guy that greeted us down there came out, starts giving us fatigues and spit shining jungle boots. The first jungle fatigues and jungle boots I’d seen, and he’s running the R&amp;R center. He took us back, went in there, said, “I’ll see you guys in a little bit once we get settled.” We come back down, and he’s got shorts and tennis shoes on. Next time I saw him in uniform was when he took us back out and went to meet the next plane. The reason I brought that up is after <name type="event">Ia Drang</name>, when we got back, they had us take showers and that and issued us new uniforms and it was the old heavy khaki uniforms, boots. They didn’t have any boots in my size, I got mine from a dead man.  That’s because my boot soles were coming off of them, I got my mine from a dead man. But this guy running the R&amp;R center had jungle fatigues and jungle boots, that’s why I brought that up. Anyway, I didn’t think that was the greatest way to handle things over there. Anyway, when I got back from R&amp;R, I walked in and they said, “Saddle up, you’re going with us.” So I grabbed my gear and we went to a tea plantation. We were sitting there waiting to see what would happen. I draw a lot of blanks in here, I'm not sure why. The counselor I went to said, “Sometimes when you're drawing blanks, it’s just something you don’t want to remember or maybe just nothing happened that was memorable.” But I was point man going into there too, when we were walking through to relieve them at <placeName>LZ (Landing Zone) X-Ray</placeName>. We got attacked by our own helicopters, because they saw a force coming through the woods. I guess it’s good and bad they saw us. It good, but bad because they shot at us. The good part is I don’t think they hit anybody. That’s the bad part. (Laughs) So if it was the enemy force coming in, well you know, they didn’t get anybody. Anyway, we got to <placeName>X-Ray</placeName> and walked in. The first thing I remember seeing was the pile of dead bodies, stacked like cord wood, just off to the side, <orgName>NVA (North Vietnamese Army)</orgName>. I mean, piles as high as I was tall and I'm six foot. It was just stacks of bodies there. Woah, what did we get ourselves into? We had little scrimmages before, but nothing like this. I mean, it was just- snipers and that kind of thing, but nothing really major. This was the bodies, the smells. It was really—it was different. We got in there and they set us up for the night there at <placeName>X-Ray</placeName>. I have no idea what happened at night, I draw a blank. The next morning, I remember—I don’t remember morning happening, I just remember we were getting ready to walk out. I have no idea what happened that night, to this day. Then we were going to hypnotize me, if I wanted to try and remember. I said, “You know, maybe I just don’t want to remember that. I’ll just leave that, let it be.” The next day we provided security while <orgName>General Moore</orgName>’s men got airlifted out. They were supposed to bring in B52s because they were so entrenched there. We had to walk out because they didn’t have enough choppers to get everybody out at one time—time frame with the B-52s and that. So we started going out, our <orgName>battalion</orgName> followed the <orgName>2nd of the 5th</orgName> part way out, we branched off to the left, they keep going straight. I think they went to <placeName>LZ Columbus</placeName>, if I remember right and we started heading for <placeName>LZ Albany</placeName>. We were talking along, I heard a noise at one time and I turned and this big cat—I don’t know whether it was a lion or mountain lion, all I saw was a big cat bounding away from me. I don’t mean a kitten cat; I mean a lion of some kind. It’s bounding away from me and it jumped up from here to the camera, away from me and I’m going, “Woah, where the heck are we?” (Laughs) This is weird now. I just kept going. I think we were pushed too hard—well, making accusations here, I don’t want to but I think we were told our battalion commanders wanted us to get there so we could get out that night and not have to spend the night there. So we were pushed too hard and too fast and as recon, I was point man for the <orgName>battalion</orgName> on the right flank, we really didn’t get to do our job properly. We were moving too fast. We shouldn’t have been moving that fast.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">So you weren’t able to look, you weren’t able to pay attention—</u>
      <u who="ACKERMAN">Yeah. I just wasn’t able to do the job right. You want to be able to see what’s going on and when you’re in a fast walk, you're just going. You’re not paying attention like you should. We’d find some stuff, we’d find canteens, ammo. You know, just little things we’d find here and there and reporting it back, but I guess they didn’t think anything about it. We were still walking; the ground was shacking from the B-52 hitting. I mean, we were close enough that the ground was shaking, and you could hear the B-52s hitting over there and everything. We were walking along; at one point I heard a commotion behind me and that’s when they had captured two prisoners. I was out on a flank walking a point out that way and the people that were inside of me are the ones that came across because they were sleeping there. I’d walked by them out here, it was the jungle, the elephant grass this high, places where it was even higher. You really didn’t really have a lot of visibility. So they stopped there and they got these two guys. We went on a little further and they stopped and kind of—everybody was taking a break; I mean we were dog-tired from the last couple of days. It was hot that day and we stopped. I can look back, I can see all the company commanders and all that with the battalion commanders, they’re looking at the map and they’re doing all this pointing and all this stuff. They come up to us, the recon platoon was in the front, and they come up to us and said, “There’s <placeName>Albany</placeName> over there, we want you guys to go check it out and secure it and the we’ll move into it.” So we went—the <orgName>battalion</orgName> was this way and we went to take a left this way. We got no more than thirty seconds out and heard some shots, so we turned back to see what it was. Figured it’s just going to be a few shots exchanged and be done. So we got down on our knees and kind of one foot up, kneeling on the ground. All of the sudden, all hell broke loose. I mean, it was just shit fire everywhere—sorry. I mean, the whole world exploded. We got down, figured still going to be a short firefight. So I got down on my belly and kind of waiting for it to get over with and I can hear a guy yelling, and I think, “This isn’t going to get over with.” I kind of got up and I could see other recon guys against this line of trees here and my pack had worked its way loose, it was banging against me. I said, “I can’t run across the field with this pack.” I reached down there, undid it, while I’m doing it, there’s grass breaking in front of my face from the bullets, kicking dirt into my eyes. I have no idea how it missed me, because I was parallel to the kill zone there. I was a six-foot target laying there. I got the pack off and I ran over to the tree line there, there was about three or four recon guys there and we could see the <orgName>NVA</orgName> coming in to help their guys up here at the ambush and we just started shooting at them. The one I remember, one of guys down from me, this guy was kind of close to us. He opened up with his magazine, he emptied his magazine at them. The guy still walking. Did he hit him? Who knows. Come down, the guy next to me got about seven eight rounds out of his magazine, and his rifle jams. If he hits him, who knows. So I said, “I’ll get the guy.” I put mine into single shot, and I shot him in the head. I know I got him because I could see his head jerk, and he’s still walking. I shot him again in the head, jerked, and he still walking. He went a few feet, stopped. Fell down to his knees, sat back on his heels, and he started getting up again. So I shot him in the head again and he finally stayed down. I was thinking, “What are these guys?” (Laughs) I mean, I know I hit him with three shots in the head, the guy still wanted to go. Whatever they were on, they might’ve been dead after the first or second shot, but he was still—I’ve heard these stories before. He just—well, if it’s going to take this much to put every one of them down, we’re in trouble. Basically, we were snipping at the guys coming in. I'm not sure they even realized we were there because everything else going on. So we were just picking them off as they were headed to relieve their guys. Meanwhile back of us, they were regrouping in the trees and they started calling us, wanted us to start going back into the trees. I guess we were proving good security for them while they were setting up there on this side. So I covered for the two, three guys that were with us, they ran across the field and I took off. I went down and one of them started coming back, I said “That’s okay, I would’ve tripped over my pack that I left out on the field.” I always carried extra ammunition and everything with me, it was there. But by the time it fell, I must’ve been ten foot away before I got my bearings and got back on my feet, went back out to get the pack. I got in there and got behind a little tree about this big around. I was leaned up against it and go, “What the hell is going here?” Talking to whoever was next to me. I looked up and there’s Sergeant Major <persName>Scott</persName>. He was in his t-shirt and he’s giving directions like this, you could see where when had his arm down, he took a bullet right through here. His t-shirt was all torn open, his flesh hanging here and he’s still up there giving directions. “Woah, what a guy.” So I'm talking to this other guy, and I ask him, “What the heck is going on here?” I felt a big thunk and I looked around that little tree, there was a big ol’ bullet hole, splinters and everything. It stopped a bullet from going into me, and I got down low, I'm not going to use this tree no more. I got down to the ground. I think they started getting organized and they put us on the perimeter facing where the kill zone was. Now, this afternoon there’s a lot of blanks there too. We got—we were there firing; we didn’t have any foxholes or anything. We were trying to dig whenever it goes in kind of low, we were digging with the bayonet and scooping out, my trenching tool is with my pack out in middle of the field. We were just doing the best we could to protect ourselves. We could see all kinds of stuff going on and sometimes they’d come out and attacks us. My opinion of the turning of the <name type="event">battle</name> is when they dropped the napalm. Because all the other support they gave us was nice, but napalm is when I saw the battle turn. But the napalm was dropped on our own guys too. They dropped right where the kill zone was. As they’d come running out of the woods, we’d just shoot them like ducks in a shooting gallery. But after that, you could see that their aggression had stopped, and they were backing off a little bit. Even though there was still fighting going on, it was not as intense. It seemed like, “Woah, back off here.” That’s my viewpoint of it. I'm trying to think, there’s something else I was going to say there, I can’t remember what it was.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">You must have been running low on ammunition at some point.</u>
      <u who="ACKERMAN">Yeah, we were getting to that point and I had—I’m kind of one of the guys that always wanted to be ready for something. I carried extra ammunition, but it was in my pack. I mean I had my normal load, I carried extra with me in my pack, but it was out there in the field. Where we were, we were doing mostly single shots because we were facing the kill zone and our guys were out there too, so we weren’t randomly spraying. We, the recon group, we were able to conserve ammunition by just using the single shots. Targets of opportunity and not just randomly spraying. I know one time during the <name type="event">battle</name>, I had to pee real bad. I just rolled up on my side, I pulled my legs up to balance myself and I'm laying there taking a leak. One of our sergeants saw me and I guess he thought I was hurt because he saw me like this. (Interviewee shows interview how his body was positioned.) And he come running over there to see if I’m alright. “Yeah, I'm just taking a leak.” “Oh you son of a bitch!” And he ran back. (Laughs) I guess kind of humorous in the middle of all this stuff going on. I thought it was pretty brave of him to just to come over there to see if I was alright. I guess from the back it looked like I was shot and holding myself. (Laughs)</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">How would you characterize your own behavior? How did you behave? Were you calm?</u>
      <u who="ACKERMAN">Yeah, I was surprisingly calm. What I’d found out talking to others too is you don’t have time to get scare. You just react and do what your training had taught you to do. You get scared later, when you think about it and things have calmed down, but during all the intense going on, you’re just reacting and doing, you’re not scared. As far as what I did, I'm not sure a hundred percent everything I did. Like I said, there’s a lot of blanks there. I was told that I did alright by a company commander and it just—you do what you got to do to survive, that’s all it is. There was some hand-to-hand combat and the things you remember; I remember one guy I shot; I was telling you about because of what it took to get him down. Other people you shot, it just happened. But hand-to-hand if you—when you kill somebody, you’re right there. It’s personal, I guess the way to put it. You’re right there and those faces stick with you. They’re still here. I’ll never get rid of them, the faces in there. The guys that you shoot at with the napalm and running out. They’re just people with bodies that we had to shoot, but there’s no faces with them. Hand-to-hand, there’s faces. That’s the tough part, to deal with that. As things went on, things slowed down a lot. We got some holes dug, I don’t know how or when. I remember being the holes. I didn’t sleep for two or three nights we were there. I didn’t eat. The smells were horrendous. You had all the gunpowder, the napalm, the burned bodies and everything burnt. The smells were overwhelming, you didn’t want to eat, it was just awful. Then, through the night they kept flares, I guess from—helicopters were dropping flares or planes were dropping flares and artillery was firing flares. We had light almost all night long, there were only a couple of spells where it was dark. The flares coming down a little parachute like this, all these shadows. (Laughs) I'm sure all these trees got killed that night too because, trees would move on you, bushes move on you. (Chuckles) When you’re sitting there just watching, they’ll move. Through the night—we had small scrimmages through the night, no major assaults that I remember.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">You’re still separated, sort of hanging out there on one side as a unit.</u>
      <u who="ACKERMAN">Yeah, we’re still on the copse of trees that we got pulled back into, the survivors that were able to make it. But that kill zone out here—during the night, in the beginning we could hear shots out there, of course everybody fired back. But they had come around to make an inventory of what kind of ammunition we had left, and it was very low, they’d started splitting it up. If you got three magazines and this guy got one you give him one and that type of thing. Sometime during the night, two helicopters were able to get in and they brought ammunition with them. They brought M60 machine gun as I remember. We didn’t have any M60 with us. They brought some men into two helicopters’ worth. It was wonderful, just to know a helicopter made it in there was a good feeling.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">Who were you with? Who’s right next to you? Do you know?</u>
      <u who="ACKERMAN">No, there’s a couple other recon guys. I’ve tried just like the other CO (Commanding Officer) to come over there. I don’t remember which one it was, and I’ve talked about this with a couple of the others, they don’t remember who’s exactly next to them either. I know it was some of other guys in the recon, but I don’t remember particularly which ones it was, and I don’t know why. Then that night that night, like I said was small scrimmages. The next morning, they came around before daylight and told everybody to just stay in their hole, and we were going to have a mad minute where everybody opened up with everything. So everybody stayed in their holes and then we were told to fire. M79s would rake the trees and M60s would rake the grass, they were out there waiting on us. For us to get up in the morning and do our farting and burping, and comfortable daylight comes, everything safe again to us, you know. They’re waiting there for us to do that. Whoever said we ought to have a mad minute, it was a good idea because we could see them falling out of the trees. They’d been waiting on us, getting up on the grass and running because we were strafing the grass and everything else. From that viewpoint it was good, the other viewpoint it was bad because we were having to shoot towards the kill zone, and we had some of our guys still in there. During the night, that’s what I was going to say earlier, we could hear guys out there crying and we couldn’t do nothing about it. “Help me” and crying, just physically crying. We couldn’t do anything to help them. The shots were at the beginning, but we were firing back and what we found out the next day was these <orgName>NVA</orgName> coming and getting their guys, hauling them out, and if they found our guys they would either machete them or beat them with their rifle butt or bayonet them. They didn’t want them alive in there. But we couldn’t hear that, so we did react to it and shot back, that’s why they quit shooting our guys when they found them. The next morning, after that mad minute, they kind of split us up in half, and half would provide security as we expand our perimeter and the other half would go in, trying to find our guys and our job was not to stop then help anybody, it was just to get out and form that perimeter. Got out of the hole, the first thing I saw was a GI (Government Issue) boot standing up right. It had a bone sticking out of it just about this far, flesh hanging out of it, smoke rising off of it. Jesus Christ, what else are we going to see as we go out here? I don’t know if I ought to have this on film, but I’ll do it anyway. The first <orgName>NVA</orgName> that we had seen as we expanded, he was wounded, and he was laying there. There’s another guy here and he was there. We went up, saw him there, had our rifles pointed at him. I said, “Sergeant, come here.” He came over there, I said, “What do you want us to do with them?” He said, “Kill him.” So we did. That’s what we did to all of them that we found that were wounded. Because—I’ll put it in context here because I know everybody gets upset about this sort of thing. We are expanding perimeter; we don’t want live enemy behind us, and we didn’t have the manpower to deal with these people. To say, “Okay, now we’ll set up a little guard post and drag them.” We had to take care of our own guys first. So that’s what we had to do. It’s war. It’s not—I know there’s people that will get up tight about that and next thing you know I’ll be at court or something for doing it. It’s what you had to do to survive. What it was. So we kept expanding the perimeter and as we’re going through the kill zone from the ambush. The things that we saw were the results of everything that went on and them coming in at night, what they did to our guys at night. We had guys that survived the night out there to saw what they did. Some of it, you know was not done in the actual combat, it’s when they came and dragged their guys out, saw our guys and brutalized them. You see a guy you know sitting up against a tree and his heads on the ground next to him and it makes it—it was easier to shoot the guy you didn’t want behind you. Just the way it was, I don’t know. I'm not sure what I should be saying here.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">You can say anything you want.</u>
      <u who="ACKERMAN">Okay, we spent—once we got past that kill zone, we provided the security and these guys would be dragging weapons back, finding our wounded and bringing them back, dragging dead bodies back. That night we pulled back into the perimeter again and I do not know what happened that night at all. I do not remember it. Next morning, I was on the thing where we had to bring the guys in and somebody else provided—the other half provided security. I remember this one point I was walking out, and they said, “Come here, give us a hand.” They had a body there, four guys had to bring in. They had to roll him on a poncho and when we got over there, this was swollen, he was green. It takes a day or two in that jungle, in the heat and everything. He was just swollen; it was digging into his arms and stuff like that. I said, “Roll him on the poncho, get ready to roll him.” My hand hit his hand and the flesh just broke off in my hand, it just stunk. I help carry him up there with the poncho and I said, “I can’t drag anymore bodies back.” I went out and I grabbed weapons. I loaded weapons so much you probably couldn’t see me because I had weapons all around me carrying them back. While I'm doing that, they will leave me alone. Nobody is going to say, “Hey come here, come help us with this guy.” That was a sight that’s always there, and I can’t get rid of it and I will always remember it but I sure didn’t want to do it again that day. I ended up having to do it a couple of times but not—I didn’t end up with a guy’s flesh just breaking off. It was just rotten already. Just a couple of days. We finally got out of there and got back to <placeName>Pleiku</placeName>. They give us a shower and of course those raggedy-ass uniforms. The boots, they didn’t have in my size like I said, and we spent the night there. I don’t remember why, but we just slept on the ground there. I'm not a hundred percent sure. We got showers and stuff, then they got us on trucks the next day to go to base camp. We were over at base camp and there was a bunch of replacements there already. I walked up—by that time, the pup tent and going to the other tent and then they had squad tents up. Even had lightbulb in ours, if you had a flashlight, you could find it. We were in that last tent, one bulb in that whole tent. Anyway, the squad team went in there and some guy laying on the bunk. It was obvious it was somebody’s bunk; the new guy didn’t know any better. “Get the ‘uck out of my bunk!” He jumped up and move out. If I ever knew who it was, I’d apologize to him but that’s—it ticked me off, those guys in my bunk. We spent the next couple of days going through the guys’—the dead people’s belongings. Separate the <orgName>military</orgName> from personal. The personal could go home and the <orgName>military</orgName> stayed there. That’s where I got my boots. I finally came across a pair that fit me and that’s where I got my boots from. Meanwhile, a guy in R&amp;R, he had a spit-shined jungle boots. I was a smoker back then. All they had for us in our little CONEX container PX was Salem lights and kits. I smoked Lucky Stripes. Well, in R&amp;R, I picked up two or three cartons of Lucky’s down there. I couldn’t get them in our PX, but I sure got them in the black market down there. (Laughs) I don’t know if that says something about stuff that was going on there, behind the scenes. I think under circumstances they did what they could to support us, but I think they could’ve done more. Just like right now what’s going on, I think they could do more. They’re directing their energies away from the troops and not doing everything they can to protect them, with us I don’t think. We should’ve been the ones who got the new stuff coming in not some guy running R&amp;R center. We should’ve been able to get all the good stuff or had the smokes we wanted or whatever and not have to fight for all the stuff we wanted. These guys just had it. I just think that’s wrong, that’s my opinion. All in all, it was an experience that I never want to relive again, but it’s a memory that I have that I can look back on it and say I did it. I live through it obviously; I didn’t get wounded. I don’t know how or why. When I got back to <placeName>Pleiku</placeName>, there were rips in my uniform and scratches and all that stuff, but no actual wounds. Luck of the draw, I guess. I don’t know how else to describe it. Some made it through, some didn’t. The wounds that are here, are still there, especially survivor guilt. As point man, how come I'm still alive? Just luck of the draw. They said, “You guys go check that out.” Thirty seconds out of the kill zone. That’s where we were running in, which was right there. Just thirty seconds made the difference of me being alive or dead, I guess. I don’t know what else I can tell you. What do you what to know?</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">I think this is a place where we need to stop. I think we’ve done a really, really hard hour.</u>
      <u who="ACKERMAN">Well, it was.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">I know it was. Just speaking for myself, it was an absolute privilege to listen to it.</u>
      <u who="ACKERMAN">Thank you. (End of interview) </u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
