<?xml-model href="../schemas/ddhi.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ttu_475">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Transcript of an Interview with Willard Parish</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>
          <orgName>Vietnam Center and Sam Johnson Vietnam Archive</orgName>
        </authority>
        <date>
          <!--  Date of publication, e.g. for citation purposes  -->
        </date>
      <idno type="DDHI">ttu_475</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <recordingStmt>
          <recording xml:id="primary_recording" type="video" dur-iso="00:32:32">
            <!-- https://www.digi.com/resources/documentation/digidocs/90001437-13/reference/r_iso_8601_duration_format.htm -->
            <media url="https://vva.vietnam.ttu.edu/images.php?img=/OH/OH0475/OH0475.mp4" mimeType="video/mp4"/>
          </recording>
        </recordingStmt>
        <bibl xml:id="primary_transcription">
          <respStmt>
            <persName>Philip F. Napoli</persName>
            <orgName>Vietnam Center and Sam Johnson Vietnam Archive</orgName>
            <resp ref="http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/trc.html">Transcriber</resp>
          </respStmt>
          <ref target="path_to_file">https://vva.vietnam.ttu.edu/images.php?img=/OH/OH0475/OH0475.pdf</ref>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The Oral History Project of the Vietnam Center and Sam Johnson Vietnam Archive</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application ident="DDHIEncoder" version="1.0">
          <desc>Conversion from Word docx to TEI xml.</desc>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en-us">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <particDesc>
        <person xml:id="NAPOLI"/>
        <person xml:id="PARISH"/>
      </particDesc>
      <settingDesc>
        <setting>
          <date when-iso="2005-11-05"/>
          <locale/>
        </setting>
      </settingDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <u who="NAPOLI">Mr. <persName>Willard Parish</persName>, at the <placeName>Crystal City Hilton</placeName> and we’re going to talk a little bit about several days in <date when="1965-11">November</date>, forty years ago. I want to say by way of making sure that you’re totally aware of what we are going to do, you can stop the tape at any time. You can tell this guy to shut it off and we’ll all shut it off. Reason for doing and saying all of that is that you’re in control of this. In a real way, this is your interview to do with what you want to do. You can say what you want to say and not say things you don’t want to say. It’s very important to me that you know that you’re in control. The first thing I want to do is get you to introduce yourself a little bit. Tell me a little bit about your age, where you’re living today and then I'm going to ask you to back up and tell me a little bit about how you entered the military, your training and movement to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> and then we’ll do the several days in <date when="1965-11">November</date>.</u>
      <u who="PARISH">Okay.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">Start off with a bit of introduction to you.</u>
      <u who="PARISH">Well, I'm <persName>Willard Parish</persName>. I was born and raised in <placeName>Bristow, Oklahoma</placeName>, where I live today. I am sixty-four years old; I have four daughters. I have one that will be twenty-two and one that will be nineteen next month and I have fourteen-year-old twins. I kind of had a late start. I graduated high school there in <date when="1959">’59</date>. I was drafted, as a matter of fact, I was to report Friday, the week after <name type="event">John Kennedy was assassinated</name> in <date when="1963">’63</date>. I took my basic training at <placeName>Fort Polk, Louisiana</placeName>, and then I left there in <date when="1964">February of ’64</date>, went to AIT (Advanced Individual Training) training  at <placeName>Fort Benning, Georgia</placeName>. I was in the <orgName>2nd 23rd Infantry</orgName>, in the <orgName>2nd Infantry Division</orgName>. We were on <placeName>Kelley Hill</placeName>, at <placeName>Fort Benning</placeName>. Out of the <placeName>Harmony Church</placeName> area, they were testing the helicopter concept, that which the <orgName>11th Airborne</orgName> became the <orgName>11th Air Assault</orgName>. The <orgName>2nd and the 23rd</orgName>, and the <orgName>1st and the 38th</orgName> shared <placeName>Kelley Hill</placeName>. Air assault was little understrength, so they more or less loaned us out to them to test this helicopter concept out. So we had the <orgName>2nd Infantry Division</orgName> patch on our left shoulder, had <orgName>11th Air Assault</orgName> patch on our pockets of our fatigues. I see in <date when="1964">’64</date>, all of <date when="1964">’64</date> we went <placeName>South Carolina</placeName> and played army against the <orgName>82nd Airborne</orgName> to test this helicopter concept out. We come back to <placeName>Benning</placeName> and just kind of went in hiatus, you know. Didn’t really do much training and just—pretty soon we started hearing the rumor mill about <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. Of course, most guys my age were saying “Where’s that?” We’d never heard of it. Of course, when we grew up, it was <placeName>French-Indochina</placeName>. The rumor mill started, we were told not to write home, and this is big secret, secret. We found out we were going when  <persName>President Johnson</persName> gets on nationwide TV and said, “I’m sending the <orgName>1st Air Cav</orgName>.” Oh, yes I forgot about that, we became the <placeName>1st Air Cav</placeName> in—it was either in <date when="1965-06">June</date> or <date when="1965-07">July of ’65</date> and I thought, “Well, they’re going to transfer us all to <placeName>Korea</placeName> where the <orgName>1st Cav</orgName> is and them here, but we just exchanged patches. I remember taking the patches off all of our uniforms and boxing them up, sending them and then we got the <orgName>1st Cav</orgName> patches.	</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">Do you remember watching that television program? I'm just curious.</u>
      <u who="PARISH">Yes, I was in the day room, down in <placeName>Fort Benning</placeName> when he came on TV and a bunch of us were in the day room when we saw it. I remember they had first talked about sending us on troop training across to <placeName>Long Beach</placeName> and loading on the ship there. Don’t know, but the rumor mill was they had a bunch of protestors, so they decided they wouldn’t do the troop train thing. A lot of people don’t remember <orgName>Continental Trailway</orgName> buses, the ol’ cream and maroon colored buses. They came to <placeName>Kelley Hill</placeName> and we walked out before daylight and just far down that street as you could see was <orgName>Continental Trailway</orgName> buses. We loaded on the buses, went to <placeName>Charleston, South Carolina</placeName> and loaded on the ship, <orgName>USNS Rose</orgName>. We went down to the <placeName>Panama Canal</placeName>, came up to <placeName>Long Beach</placeName>. Spent the night there and then took off. Twenty days later we landed at <placeName>Qui Nhon</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">What do you remember about that trip? The boat trip.</u>
      <u who="PARISH">I did alright, but there was a lot of fellas sitting around the quote, “butt cans” and looked like they were bobbing for apples. (Laughs) But I decided that complete thirty days on ship that I wasn’t cut out to be sailor. (Laughs)</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">You didn’t like this up and down thing, huh?</u>
      <u who="PARISH">Well it wasn’t so much the up and down or this way, but it was all forward motions. It was a little tough to take. Then we hit a tail end of a typhoon that was hitting <placeName>Japan</placeName> and it was really getting rough then, but I got through alright. I remember that we had practiced at <placeName>Benning</placeName>, climbing down a cargo net, you know like the old <name type="event">World War II</name> movies you see getting in the LSTs (Landing Ship Tank). We walked down a ladder, had our duffle bags and I remember sitting in that LST with the duffle bag like this and we’re going in. Of course—and I'm sure all the other guys were like me, all these visions of beachheads, like in all these <persName>John Wayne</persName> movies, But we thought, “Man, when this thing hits and that front end drops down, all hell is going to break loose.”</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="PARISH">Well, about that time I felt a bump on the bottom and tractor went up, dropped that front and started hollering for everybody to “Get off,” and “Hurry, hurry, hurry!” He ran off and my first vision of <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> was a big CONEX container and two guys laying on top of it and playing cards. (Laughs) So that was my beachhead, which I was thankful for. Then we loaded on a chopper, went to <persName>An Khe</persName>, and just—best I remember, most of the time we just went out. The first area we went to was <placeName>Happy Valley</placeName> and kind of little scrimmages broke here and there, not anything really major. They had an artist for <orgName>TIME Magazine</orgName>, for the buildup and he came around and made sketches, then went back to <placeName>Saigon</placeName>. We were getting ready to go to <placeName>Happy Valley</placeName>, where they decided that a mortar platoon—a squad actually, that’s the picture they wanted to use. So there was about five of us, six I guess it was. We went out to set mortar up and the guy painted the mortar first, then he painted Graham, the gunner, then he painted <persName>Charlie Marshall</persName>, fixed dropped around the tube and then he painted me holding a round. So we made the cover of <orgName>TIME Magazine</orgName>, which was kind of neat. The artist, he was very nice, he took everybody’s name and sent us all an autograph copy of the cover and he said—I can’t remember, Henry was his first name, pretty nice fella. Then, we started hearing about special forces camp up in <placeName>Plei Me</placeName> and the rumor mill started again. Sure enough, we went up by that area and I can’t—I really don’t remember just how many days we were out. But I can remember it was a Saturday evening and our section sergeant, <persName>Mathis</persName>, came down and said, “Well, we’re going to go into another area tomorrow and if we don’t run into anything there, they tell us we’re going back to <orgName>An Khe</orgName>, the base area.” Sunday morning, well—I was assistant squad leader of this squad and when we came in, I would take half the squad on one side of the chopper, <persName>Sergeant Thompson</persName> would take the other half. When we landed into the valley, we knew then it was a hot LZ (Landing Zone). When the choppers lifted, I look to my right and it was all the way across the LZ. Well, if I took my guys and ran that way, we would’ve ran into the battalion CP (Command Post). Nearest wood line, which was to the left and that’s where <persName>Thompson</persName> was running, and of course we were running right into him coming down of <placeName>Chu Pong Massif</placeName>. Most of the rest of the day was basically running wounded guys out to the choppers, <persName>Major Crandall</persName>’s guys and go out. I think <persName>Joe Galloway</persName> used the phrase “God’s lunatics” and they were. One kid got hit, who was helping me carry a guy out and the crew chief on the helicopter jumped off and helped him then to the chopper. One thing that <persName>Colonel Moore</persName> had done, instead of taking all the mortars out, we just took every other squad’s mortars out and then, like my squad, we didn’t take our mortar. We backpacked the ammo because he wanted to have plenty of ammo. We’re over here, nobody has a clue where the mortars are and I can’t find where they’re at and I'm thinking, “Well, we got all the ammo, it’s not going to do much good.” So finally, one of the sergeants there in <orgName>Charlie Company</orgName> and one of the line platoons said, “The battalion’s CP was over there.” Which is clear cross the <placeName>LZ</placeName>. At that time, there were couple little A-1E Skyraiders coming in, dropping butterfly mines. So I lined my guys up and I said, “Here’s the deal. When that first planes comes in, drop his ordinates, I’ll run across there. If I make it, then you guys come across when the second plane comes in. Or we can all go together when the second plane goes in.” <persName>James Coman</persName>, who was in my squad, he said “No, we’ll all go together.” So I dispersed them out, second plane started dropping its ordinates and thank god we all got across. The first guy we ran into was <persName>Sergeant Major Plumley</persName>. He told us where the mortars were, so we went over there. At that time, my basic issue was a .45. What I had been doing when they bring the wounded guys out, I got with <persName>Platoon Sergeant Freeman</persName>, we called him “Big Daddy Freeman”, and I was getting his wounded guys’ M16 ammo and gave them to my guys. So <persName>Coman</persName> gave me his .45. So I wound up with two .45s. Basically, that evening, <persName>Sergeant Mathis</persName> said “We’re going to have to pull our own defensive perimeter because we don’t have enough people.” I said, “What are we going to pull it with, sarge? Mortar platoons, they don’t have any fire power.” He said, “Well, we’re working on it.” Then he told me to take a squat and go over and get some more ammo and work to company CP. I came back, <persName>Coman</persName> had the foxhole dug, he and I shared that foxhole. That evening they came around with an extra M60 machine gun and they wanted to know if anybody qualified with it and I said, “Yeah.” Which I’d never touched one before, but the next morning back to the right flank where <orgName>Charlie Company</orgName> was at, those guys started getting hit bad. You could hear all the gun firing, explosions and all the screaming and hollering. <orgName>Delta Company</orgName> was to the right. I could hear those guys hollering, “They’re coming around, they’re coming around!” Well out to the front, there was a big termite hill and elephant grass. I could see the grass kind of going down like that. So I hollered, “Who’s out there?” There was weeds and nobody answered, and I hollered again. So I turn around to <persName>Coman</persName> and you know, “Burn him.” He shot once and I hollered at him, “Put it on fully automatic.” Well, we had trouble with them jamming on full automatics, those early M16s and he said, “It’s jammed.” I remember I looked at him, he looked at me and then I looked back to the front and—I don’t know if I can describe it like these <orgName>Disney</orgName> movies where they do that time lapse photograph of the plant coming up out of the ground. It’s like they just started growing up out of the weeds. Things kind of went into slow motion and then all at once, everything broke out. After this, like I said in the book, the training takes over and you just become actions and reactions. A lot of guys, I know in the book remember every little minute detail, but I just remember when it started, and I remember it seemed like somebody turned the volume down. It was like I was way, way far away and I really wasn’t here, I'm just watching this from a distance. I remember when we had started, I had laid <persName>Coman</persName>’s .45 down on the bottom and mine on the other side. After the book came out and I read the book, I remember thinking at one time, “Aren’t they ever going to run out of people?” It just seemed like no matter what, they just had more people. Next thing I know it’s all quiet, and I'm standing up in that foxhole and I got a .45 in each hand and they’re telling me what I did and I—“No, I didn’t.” “Yeah, you did.” I just, like I said, then I started—everything started coming back. The day we landed in the valley, I had fourteen days left to go in the army. I had a very good friend, his son is here now with us, that was killed that morning, that second morning. The day he was killed, he had seven days left to go. I remember when we got back to <placeName>An Khe</placeName>, <persName>Sergeant Mathis</persName> came in and he said, “I saw what you did, I'm going to put you in for a Bronze Star.” I'm loading that duffle bag, “Sergeant, that’s great I can take that fifty cents go anywhere and buy a beer.” (Laughs) I came home in <date when="1965-12">December of ’65</date>. According to my DD-214 form I was held for four days for the convenience of the government. About 6 months later, my sister called me, I was living in <placeName>Tulsa</placeName> then. She said, “You have a big manilla envelope here and it says ‘<orgName>US Army</orgName> Official Business’” I said, “Oh. They’re calling me back.” She said, “Do you want me to open it?” I said, “Yeah, go ahead and open it.” She said, “Well, there’s some kind of medal in here.” I said, “Medal?” She said, “Yeah.” “I swear <persName>Sergeant Mathis</persName> said he was going to put me in for a Bronze Star.” And she said, “Well it looks kind of bronze.” And my brother was in the background and he said, “According to this paper, it says silver star.” I said, “Nah, can’t be that.” Sure enough. I was kind of surprised and somebody asked me when we got back to <placeName>An Khe</placeName> about how I felt. I said, “Well, I'm just running a whole rafter full of emotions.” I said, “I was very sad that my friends had been killed.” At the same time, I was madder than hell because they were. I was elated I was alive, and I felt guilty because I was. Especially because I never got a scratch. I told a guy one time on a military forum, I said, “Maybe if I got wounded, I’d felt better.” But basically, that’s about it. I still can't remember when the really tough fighting started, and I used to wonder why we used to go out on a field there and set up a mortar and tear it down. Set it up and tear it down. Now I know why. I was a draftee, and I didn’t have too much of a military mind, my mindset was to do my two years and get out. But after that battle, I have a completely different perspective and respect for our military forces and the people that are in it. What I do now, since the book and the movie came out, I get a lot of calls from guard units, especially those that are fixing to go to <placeName>Iraq</placeName>, “Would you come and talk to us?” Here, about three years ago, I got a call from a major at <placeName>Fort Sill</placeName>, he wanted to know I’d go talk to their battalion. They asked me, “What do you charge for these?” I said, “I don’t charge anything. This is my way of paying back. If I can do something to get one of these young men or ladies home safe, I done my job.” That’s the way I feel about it. </u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">Talk to me about coming to these events.</u>
      <u who="PARISH">Well, actually I didn’t know about it until <persName>General Moore</persName> contacted me about the book in <date when="1988">1988</date>. At that time, I only had two daughters and he said we could either write or just talk on tape. At that time, I was disc-jockeying our local radio station. Well, I could talk better, or I could write. I just put it down, also ran a copy of my silver star orders and sent that to he and <persName>Joe Galloway</persName>. In <date when="1992">’92</date>, I believe when the book came out, I had sent a picture to <persName>General Moore</persName>, but he called me in <date when="1992-07">July</date>, and the book came out in <date when="1992-11">November</date>. He said, that “They couldn’t copy the picture, so do you have a recruitment picture?” I didn’t know what he was talking about at the time, so he said, “You know, when you went through basic, the little—they took your picture and put it in the book.” I said, “Oh yeah, I think I’ve got one of those.” So I sent it. Being a small town, we don’t have a bookstore. Then I had said I wanted to get my two daughters a copy of the book and I—of course by the time the book came out, I had four daughters because I had twins! I had put a little note in there and asked the guy at <orgName>Random House</orgName> if I could order books through them. About two weeks before the books’ release date, <orgName>UPS</orgName> truck stops out front and there’s a book, this guy just sent it to me. I wound up buying one and then he wound up sending me another one. Anyway, I wound up with four, actually five books because I got one for myself and then when <persName>General Moore</persName> contacted me, he told me about these <orgName>1st Cavalry</orgName> reunions. When I was a kid, I remember looking in a cigar box and all my dad’s army stuff, he was in the <placeName>Philippines</placeName> in <name type="event">World War II</name>. I noticed the <orgName>1st Cav</orgName> patch. He’s never talked to me about it until I came back <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, “Now we can talk about it,” he said. He did most the fighting in with the <orgName>Americal Division</orgName>, right there just before they dropped the bomb. He was going to be in the second wave of the invasion of <placeName>Japan</placeName>. Of course, they dropped the bomb, or both of them and that kind of stopped that. But he didn’t have enough points to rotate back home, so they transferred him into the <orgName>12th Cav</orgName> and sent him in the occupation of <placeName>Japan</placeName>. He said, “I wasn’t in there but maybe six months.” “That doesn’t make a difference, you’re <orgName>1st Cav</orgName>.” So when I joined the association, I got him in. In <date when="1993">’93</date>, he and I went down and that’s the first time I’d seen <persName>General Moore</persName> since I’d left <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. That’s when I got to meet <persName>Joe Galloway</persName>. You know, somebody said, “You didn’t see <persName>Joe</persName> over there?” I said, “Hey, I had a foxhole and for three days that was my little world right there.” What went on in other places you know, as I read about it in the book. I can just tell you what went on around my area. </u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="PARISH">Anyway, in <date when="1993">’93</date>, <date when="1995">’95</date>, and <date when="1997">’97</date> I went to the <orgName>1st Cav</orgName> reunion at <placeName>Fort Hood</placeName>. In <date when="1995-11">November of ’95</date>, I got an email from <persName>Joe Galloway</persName> and they were doing a ceremony here at the wall, on the 30th anniversary and he said, “They’ve asked <persName>Hal</persName> and I to pick somebody out to sit on the speaker stand, to represent the three hundred and fifty of us and <persName>Hal</persName> and I decided that you’re the man.” Down at the bottom, he said, “By the way, the old man said this invitation ain’t optional, you will be here.” So I came and this is the first one I’ve back to.	</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">How does it feel?</u>
      <u who="PARISH">Good and sad. It’s like De La Paz’s son, he comes to all these, his dad was killed. He’s the one that was killed. All of us guys, he’s kind of our son now, you know. As I told him last night, “You know with four girls, it’s nice to have a son.” (Laughs)</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">So it’s a bit of a family gathering in a way?</u>
      <u who="PARISH">Yes, yes. Because they are my brothers and he’s my son now. It’s good to see him, we have some good memories, and we have some sad memories, and really it helped me with my emotions and things. To get together with these guys because we have somebody you can talk to. I know when the movie came out, my sister came, and she thought it was pretty graphic. I said, “Yeah, war is graphic.” She asked me what I thought about it. I said, “Well, they can depict the visual.” But I said, “The smell on that battlefield is something that stays with you. It’s just a death smell.” It’s the only way I can describe it. Still forty years later, a certain sound or a smell can—(Interviewee snaps fingers)It’ll bring something up from then. Not quite as bad as I was when I first came back. I know I was an assistant manager of a Quick-Trip, a convenience store there in <placeName>Oklahoma</placeName>. Back then, they weren’t air-conditioned, and we had these sliding doors, we just slide the whole front open. I was standing there one night, writing up a grocery order. Some kids drove up through the parking lot, threw out a cherry bomb. When that thing went off, the pencil went one way, the book went the other and by the time I hit the floor, I felt kind of foolish but—luckily there wasn’t but one or two people in the store, so they kind of giggled a little bit until they saw I was kind of mad. I apologized to them, I said, “Sorry.” They said, “Hey, don’t worry about it.” Anyway, I'm alright.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">But the point is that most people don’t understand what you went through, right? I mean your sister didn’t get it; these people didn’t get it. The people who do get it are here at these meetings.</u>
      <u who="PARISH">Yeah. That’s it. That’s why you can relate to them. I guess that’s why for years my dad would never talk to me about <name type="event">World War II</name>. But now, since I’ve been through it, he tells me a lot of things now that he would never talk about before. I asked him one day and he said, “Because you understand now.” It’s like with my sis, “Was it really that bad?” “It was the bad and worse.” as I say when I talk to these young men and lady, even at schools, I go talk to schools on Veteran’s Day. I try to instill a little bit of that patriotism on these young people. I tell them, it’s kind of like the old man said, “Hate war, but don’t hate the American Warrior.” I said, “I just asked that you support the troops because they’re just there doing their job and you know they probably don’t like being there either.” I said, “I hope to, pray to god that none of you young people ever have to experience anything like this. But if you do, I hope you have all the support of the people back here.” As I told the lady at the radio station that I worked for during <name type='event'>Desert Storm</name>, there are having lots of parades there in town. They were boxing up things to send to the troops over there then and made my own heart feel good. She asked me one time, she said “Well, why do you think there such a turn around that they were supporting this war and didn’t support the <name type="event">Vietnam War</name>?” I said, “<persName>Deana</persName>, I really don’t think they are supporting the war as they are supporting the troops.” You know, I said it’s like that ol’ phrase I used to hear in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, “Well, it wasn’t a popular war.” Well if you talk to my dad, he didn’t think <name type="event">World War II</name> was very popular either. I don’t think anybody thinks a war is very popular. Anyway, getting back, she said, “Why do you think they’re supporting the troops like they are down there?” I said, “The main reason is, now it’s their sons are over there. The ones that were protesting us, it’s their sons and it makes a lot of difference when it’s your own flesh and blood that over there, instead of somebody else.”</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">Would you want your children to join?</u>
      <u who="PARISH">I would. I think if that’s what they wanted to do. Like I said, I didn’t join, I was a draftee. Of course, they don’t have the draft now, but if they decided to join, I’d back them a hundred percent. If they come up in the draft, and they drafted them, I would expect them to go. Somebody said, “Well, all those other people were going to <placeName>Canada</placeName> and things like that.” They said, “You know, you probably could’ve got out of going there” I said, “You know, I could never look my dad in the eye again.” Because he went through it. If I’d done that, I could never look that man in his eyes again.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">It’s a good place to stop. Thank you.</u>
      <u who="PARISH">You bet.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">Will, it was a privilege. (End of interview)</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
