<?xml-model href="../schemas/ddhi.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ttu_477">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Transcript of an Interview with Robert Bowen</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>
          <orgName>Vietnam Center and Sam Johnson Vietnam Archive</orgName>
        </authority>
        <date>
          <!--  Date of publication, e.g. for citation purposes  -->
        </date>
      <idno type="DDHI">ttu_477</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <recordingStmt>
          <recording xml:id="primary_recording" type="video" dur-iso="00:58:55">
            <!-- https://www.digi.com/resources/documentation/digidocs/90001437-13/reference/r_iso_8601_duration_format.htm -->
            <media url="https://vva.vietnam.ttu.edu/images.php?img=/OH/OH0477/OH0477.mp4" mimeType="video/mp4"/>
          </recording>
        </recordingStmt>
        <bibl xml:id="primary_transcription">
          <respStmt>
            <persName>Philip F. Napoli</persName>
            <orgName>Vietnam Center and Sam Johnson Vietnam Archive</orgName>
            <resp ref="http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/trc.html">Transcriber</resp>
          </respStmt>
          <ref target="path_to_file">https://vva.vietnam.ttu.edu/images.php?img=/OH/OH0477/OH0477.pdf</ref>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The Oral History Project of the Vietnam Center and Sam Johnson Vietnam Archive</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application ident="DDHIEncoder" version="1.0">
          <desc>Conversion from Word docx to TEI xml.</desc>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en-us">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <particDesc>
        <person xml:id="NAPOLI"/>
        <person xml:id="BOWEN"/>
      </particDesc>
      <settingDesc>
        <setting>
          <date when-iso="2005-11-11"/>
          <locale/>
        </setting>
      </settingDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <u who="NAPOLI">Today is <date when="2005-11-11">November 11th, 2005</date>. I'm <persName>Philip Napoli</persName> with <persName>Mr. Bob Bowen</persName>. We are at <placeName>Crystal Hilton City</placeName> and we are going to talk a little bit about some days in November forty years ago. <persName>Mr. Bowen</persName>, would you tell us a little bit about yourself? Can you introduce yourself for us? How old are you and where you live today? </u>
      <u who="BOWEN">Yes, I'm now 64. Most of the people I’ve seen here in the last day are a lot older than the last time saw them. I live in <placeName>Holly Springs, Mississippi</placeName> now and at the time of the <name type="event">Ia Drang-Pleiku campaign</name>, I was a 1st lieutenant in the <orgName>17th Aviation Company</orgName>. Really, the story starts at <placeName>Fort Benning</placeName>. During the <name type="event">11th Air Assault</name>, and I was a part of that after completing flight school at <placeName>Fort Rucker</placeName>, I accomplished the CB2B Caribou transition, which was a twin-engine transport that the army used basically for five years only from about ’<date when="1960">60</date> to the end of ’<date when="1966">66</date>. That period in there, the army flew it at the end of that period, and we turned those assets over to the <orgName>Air Force</orgName> and they became <orgName>Air Force</orgName> operations thereafter. The <orgName>11th Air Assault Division</orgName> had five Caribou companies assigned to it at <placeName>Fort Benning</placeName>. But when we converted from the <orgName>11th Air Assault</orgName> and combined that unit with the <orgName>2nd Infantry Division</orgName> to become the <orgName>1st Cavalry Division</orgName>, the Caribou companies basically were pulled out of the <orgName>Cav</orgName> and only one company, the <orgName>7th Aviation Company</orgName> that I belonged to, was attached to the <orgName>Cav</orgName> for intro-theater tactical transport. In the Summer of <date when="1965">1965</date>, we began preparation for deployment, even before <persName>President Johnson</persName> announced on television that “I have today deployed the <orgName> Airmobile Division</orgName> to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>.” That only confirmed what we already believe to be the case. The <orgName>Cav</orgName> quickly began transferring their men and materials to ships for transship across the Pacific. Helicopters were flown to <placeName>Mobile</placeName> and you were in ports for deployment where they were disassembled and loaded onto ships. In our case however, we had already trained for and were prepared to fly aircraft across the Pacific. So we were the first company size unit of Caribou to deploy across the mid-Pacific route. We left <placeName>Fort Benning</placeName> on <date when="1965-10-06">September 6th</date>, flying from there non-stop to <placeName>San Francisco</placeName>, overnighting in <placeName>San Francisco</placeName> and then deploying across basically everywhere there was land. We flew first to <placeName>Honolulu</placeName>, <placeName>Hickam Air Force Base</placeName>, about a seventeen-hour flight. From there to <placeName>Midway Island</placeName> to <placeName>Wake Island</placeName> to <placeName>Guam</placeName> to <persName>Clark Airbase</persName> and finally into <persName>Vung Tau</persName>, <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. We took eighteen aircraft across the Pacific; we had a thousand gallons of internal fuel in the fuselage strapped down and eight hundred plus gallons in the wings. So we had a total capacity of slightly better than eighteen-hundred gallons to make that long leg to <placeName>Hawaii</placeName>. In <placeName>Vung Tau</placeName>, we immediately began preparing the airplanes for use in-country. Took the fuel tanks out, put the seats back in. Drained the oxygen tanks, so if anyone of those tanks got hit, it wouldn’t explode. We had already installed self-sealing fuel tanks in the wings of the airplane, so we were basically ready to go when we got in-country. My company was originally scheduled to be deployed to <placeName>An Khe</placeName> along with the rest of the <orgName>Cav</orgName>, but as they started preparing the space, because this was a twin-engine transport with a ninety-five foot wing span and required a lot of ramp space for the airplanes—as they began doing the initial sight work to for a place to park the Caribous, they discovered that area in the <placeName>An Khe Air Field</placeName> was a former French minefield. They had to find a place quickly to put us somewhere else and that place was <placeName>Camp Holloway, Pleiku</placeName>. It was originally prepared for a company of Chinook helicopters, but they were sent elsewhere. So we took their space at <placeName>Camp Holloway</placeName> and were there during the entire <name type="event">Pleiku campaign</name>, the <name type="event">Bong Son campaign</name> and up until six weeks before I deployed back to the <placeName>States</placeName>. When they finally cleared the French minefield, leveled it, put down PSP and we were able to get the airplanes over to <placeName>An Khe</placeName>. We began flying in-country about the  <date when="1965-09-18">18th of September</date>. I was a part of the advance party because I was the <orgName>17th Aviation Company</orgName> Administrative Officer and so I had some administrative responsibilities, in addition to my flying responsibilities. I was part of the advanced party to go to <placeName>Camp Holloway</placeName> and get the spaces ready for our people to bring the rest of the airplanes in there. I got my in-country aircraft checkout and the terrain checkout on the <date when="1965-09-21">21st of September</date> and began flying very shortly thereafter. The <name type="event">Ia Drang operation</name> for me really began on <date when="1965-10-22">October 22nd</date>. That’s about when things really heated up at <placeName>Plei Me</placeName>. The special forces camp came under attack shortly after that and we started moving men and materials forward from <placeName>An Khe</placeName> to support that operation and ultimately the launch into <placeName>LZ (Landing Zone) X-Ray</placeName> and <placeName>Albany</placeName>. <date when="1965-10-17">The 17th</date> had six primary missions that it performed for the <orgName>Cav</orgName>. First, the <orgName>Cav</orgName> used us to move men and material forward from <placeName>An Khe</placeName> to the most forward fix wing strip. The reason they did that is all of the <orgName>Cav</orgName> had four hundred plus helicopters, the Hueys could only carry about eight plus people at one lift and they burned lots of gas and they were relatively slow. To try to deploy the men forward by helicopter made no sense. The Chinooks burned even more fuel, carried more people obviously, but they were needed to move artillery and some fuel but mainly they wanted to hold them in reserve for the artillery movements. One of the lessons learned at <placeName>Ia Drang</placeName> was to be sure that we didn’t use the Chinooks for things other than that because when it came time to move the artillery, there was nothing else that could lift it and carry it where it needed to go and it had to be carried by air. Second primary mission we flew was once we had moved the troops forward; we then began immediately resupplying the helicopters with jet fuel. The same two five-hundred-pound bladder containers that we used coming across the Pacific, were the same type bladders we would put inside the fuselage. You can fill them with JP4, roll them inside, lash them down and fly a thousand gallons of jet fuel forward to the helicopters. We did a ton of that. We also, as the troops began being engaged, we would fly forward ammunition, water, food, any other supplies needed and back haul wounded. So we continuously did that. The <orgName>Cav</orgName> would typically try not to have a ground unit engage for more than five to seven days so we would—once we had brought in one regimen or battalion, whatever size operation was needed, we would, within a week we would begin bringing in fresh troops and back hauling the ones that had been engaged out. That happened throughout the year, they got into that pattern. The fourth primary mission that we flew was one of resupply for artillery. When the helicopters were not available, or it was too hot to air supply it by helicopter, we would air drop to the artillery units by parachute. We developed a system using a parachute we would drop from nine-hundred feet in two-thousand-pound packages, artillery basically right behind the trails of the guns so that they would have ammunition to continue firing. Medevac mission was a very important role we played. Fundamentally what would happen is that the men that on the ground that were wounded would be evac’d to a MASH (Mobile Army Surgical Hospital), a field hospital. There was one step up during the <name type="event">Ia Drang-Pleiku campaign</name> at <placeName>Camp Holloway</placeName>, where we were based. Typically, Hueys, sometimes Chinooks would fly them out to <placeName>Camp Holloway</placeName>. The doctors in this mobile hospital would try to stabilize the men and then we would load them in the carried litters on the Caribou and fly them to either <placeName>Qui Nhon</placeName> or <placeName>Nha Trang</placeName>, where there was a significant field hospital where they could be treated further. The final mission we flew throughout the war, when we were there, was a radio relay. During <name type="event">Air Assault II</name> in <placeName>South Carolina</placeName>, where the <orgName>11th Air Assault Division</orgName> was testing these air mobility concepts, one of the things they discovered they needed was some way to efficiently permit communications between the units on the ground with <placeName>An Khe</placeName>, while we were in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, but—command and control from the ground forces to where the commanders were that were not in the battlefield. They discovered that one of the most efficient ways to do that was with the Caribou. They installed in the fuselage of the airplane a huge rack of radios that would retransmit—and a bay of antennas looked like quills stuck out of the back of airplane on the big board, where we could handle up to a dozen frequencies at one time. The ground units would be using hand-held radios or backpack radios and they would be talking and they wouldn’t know what was happening, but that message, the signal was being transmitted up to us at ten-thousand feet over the battlefield. Then, those radios on the airplane would retransmit it down with a stronger signal automatically to <placeName>An Khe</placeName> and the other commanders that need to understand what was happening on the ground. That was a twenty-four-hour day mission and we had two airplanes assigned to it in six hour shifts. As you can imagine, we typically would fly from noon to 6 p.m., 6 p.m. to midnight, midnight to 6 a.m., etcetera. So the second airplane would come up about thirty-minutes early to accomplish the transfer of the frequencies over to the new airplane and once that was accomplished, the one that had been on station was released to go back down. It was refueled, serviced, crews were changed, and it was made ready to go again at the next shift change. As things warmed up in late October, and as I look back at my flight records to refresh my memory as to what exactly happened, I think it’s interesting to note that we, like the folks on the ground did not have much perspective on what was going on around us. We were assigned a mission, we would say, “<persName>Lieutenant Bowen</persName>, you’re to fly, go to <placeName>An Khe</placeName>, pick up a load, take it to the tea plantation, take it to <placeName>Camp Holloway</placeName>.” And we would do that all day. We would know that there was a significant action on the way because we could see the smoke from the bombs, we could see the fighter aircraft stacked up particularly over <placeName>X-Ray</placeName> when we were down there. We got heavily involved in that period, so basically from the <date when="1965-10-22">22nd of October</date> to the <date when="1965-11-20">20th of November</date>, I flew a hundred and twenty assault missions, and a hundred and seventeen hours of flight time. That month, we flew everything we had around the clock. We had two flight platoons in the <orgName>17th Aviation Company</orgName>. One flight platoon would handle the mission requirements from midnight to noon, the other flight platoon pilots would be ready to go, and the planes would come back in, crew change, refuel and they would go back out. So the airplanes were fundamentally—until something broke, they were flown around the clock, every day for the month. If you were not flying, you were in the sack because by the time you were ready to go for a twelve hour shift, you obviously had to be in operations at least an hour ahead of that to get your mission sheets and understand what you were going to be doing. You took about an hour after that to debrief and to be released to go to bed and get something to eat as you could. Typically carried C-rations on the airplane so that we never stopped to eat. We would have rations so that we could—whoever was the non-flying pilot would eat, next landing we would change seats and the other guy would get a bite to eat and the crew chief could as well. Depending on the mission requirement, typically it was a three-person crew. Two pilots and a crew chief. If we were flying a lot of cargo, we’d carry two crew chiefs because it required that the loads be tied down before you left and untied when you arrived so you could push it out. The fuel bladders we could roll out the back of the airplanes. Ammunition pallets had to be lifted out with a forklift or in some cases when it was really hot and there wasn’t a forklift there, we had a roller system inside the airplane, we could land, turn around, lower the back gate, roll them to the edge and push them off as the plane slowly taxied forward, so the crews on the ground could get them. We flew—I have no idea how many thousand hours during that period. But as I said, we learned very quickly that flying from <placeName>An Khe</placeName> to <placeName>Pleiku</placeName>, where the <orgName>7th regiment</orgName> and the <orgName>5th regiment</orgName> were initially deployed in <placeName>X-Ray</placeName>, was far too far. It is a miracle to this day that the <orgName>North Vietnamese</orgName> did not respond faster than they did because when <persName>Hal Moore</persName> and his regiment was first deployed in there, there was only a handful of people on the group. Had they responded faster, they could’ve wiped them out easily because it took so long for the helicopters to fly from <placeName>Pleiku</placeName> with a fresh load to <placeName>LZ X-Ray</placeName> and dropped them in and come back again. That they were really vulnerable early on. One of the lessons the <orgName>Cav</orgName> learned was you got to have fixed wing stripped very well forward so that transit time was short. After the <persName>Pleiku</persName> campaign was completed, the <orgName>Cav</orgName> began building, scattering around different places fixed wing strips out of the forest, so that we could fly into it on a much closer basis. After the initial insertion of the <orgName>7th Cav Regiment</orgName>, we began flying—they realized that first of all, we could barely carry enough fuel to the helicopters to keep them resupplied, the flying time was so long. We moved all the operations forward to a French tea plantation called <placeName>Catecka</placeName>, which was southwest of <placeName>An Khe</placeName>, if my memory serves me, ten or twelve miles. All operations were conducted out of there. It was a composite of what we did with the Caribou and supplemented with Air Force C-130, C-123. It was kind of an all hands-on deck operation to keep the <orgName>Cav</orgName> going at that time because we basically had every unit engaged, not much in reserve when they were on the ground. As that operation began whining down, I had more time to spend back at <placeName>An Khe</placeName>, back at <placeName>Pleiku</placeName>, at <placeName>Camp Holloway</placeName>, to take care some of my administrative responsibilities and the wounded and dead began being evacuated in a significant fashion. One day, I can remember coming in, going out for a flight and the Chinooks were coming in with the dead, they were brought in in the fuselage of the Chinook. They were just piled in there like cordwood. Still in their web gear, just as they’d been removed from the battle ground. There was a grave registration unit set up right across the street from where our company headquarters was. The dead were laid out there, many of which were unidentified originally because it—in my discussions with the people over there was that the dog tags had been removed by the <orgName>NVA (North Vietnamese Army)</orgName>, particularly from <placeName>LZ Albany</placeName> where they were intermingled with our troops. It was an effort to get the survivors from those two battles to come in and identify the people that were dead. They were there—the dead were there a couple of days at least, maybe a little longer than that in two different areas, laid out typically on stretchers, sometimes on the ground while they went in there and identified the dead. Once that was done, the grave registration could start processing. I remember there were huge piles of boots, large piles of web-gear, and the uniforms, once they were put in body bags, the uniforms were taken and burned in fifty-five gallons drums with JP4 on the bottom. Once they collected the personally effects, that was it. They typically—<orgName>the Air Force</orgName> flew a lot of them out of <placeName>Camp Holloway</placeName> down to <placeName>Saigon</placeName> for transshipment to the <placeName>US</placeName>. Very unpleasant period of time. My hat’s off to the surgeons in the hospital, they were—I mean, it was magnificent what they did. The dead and the wounded—dead of course were sent to grave registration, but the wounded were brought into <placeName>Holloway</placeName> by helicopter typically. When the helicopter would hover land, the dust would blow into the tent and the surgeons when they’re trying to operate on these guys, and it was unbelievably unsanitary in the conditions they operated in. They too worked around the clock until they could get everybody processed and shipped out. But I know I counted over a hundred-fifty dead on the ground and that was not all of them that were brought into <placeName>Camp Holloway</placeName>. So I’ve heard it was the greatest single-day loss of <orgName>American</orgName> life in the <name type="event">Vietnam war</name>, at <placeName>Albany</placeName>. There were a lot of lessons learned there, as I'm sure the veterans who were on the ground can articulate more clearly than I. But the lessons learned, there were numerous ones. Like I mentioned earlier, you have to have a shorter transit time for the helicopters. You cannot use the Chinook helicopters for miscellaneous rules of moving troops, you got to do that in some other fashion. Don’t march troops on the ground, move them by helicopter. Many, many lessons were learned during that effort that translated into safer missions later on into the war. Kind of an interesting side-bar to this, as the <orgName>Cav</orgName> was still at<placeName>Camp Holloway</placeName>, because after the <orgName>7th Regiment</orgName> was moved out they came back to <placeName>Camp Holloway</placeName> to refit and finally take a shower, get fresh uniforms, they used the shower right as far of me to the other wall, away from where I was billeted. Unfortunately, they did not have hot water, but they were delighted to have water period, to clean up in. As we began moving them back to <placeName>An Khe</placeName>, I was going out to fly that day, their rifles were stacked, and the web-gear was lined up. I guess they were maybe at lunch or something, but on one of those stacks of web-gears, one person had a brass bugle. I remember thinking at the time, “God, what a wonderful souvenir that’s going to make for somebody.” Because there were a variety of SKS rifles and helmets and miscellaneous stuff that they had recovered off the battleground. <orgName>Army</orgName> got a little more sophisticated in its rules about what you could take off the battleground after this one, so much stuff got removed. But it was only about a year ago, less than a year ago that I was trading emails with <persName>Joe Galloway</persName> and he explained the history of that bugle and that it’s still being used here today. So it was significant to me to have seen that at the time, that somebody recouped that thing off of the battleground and carried it out. He explained to me who had that bugle and what happened to him subsequently, so that made it even more meaningful. So that’s the typically mission we flew. Very, very intense period in <date when="1965-10">late October</date> to late November period. The most intense period of us of the entire year that I was over there. There were a few other times that we flew a lot but never again we fly around the clock twenty-four hours a day. During the month of <date when="1965-12">December</date>, we flew some, but not much because most of the airplanes were down for maintenance. Our ground crews did a magnificent job. As I mentioned, the airplanes were typically—during that first half of November, they were typically on the ground only a matter of maybe a half hour while we did a crew change and a refuel, so if there was anything wrong with the airplanes—they go out there with engines stands, uncalled or changed spark plugs, whatever needed to be done to it to make it air-worthy again for the next trip. We were mounting out of our eighteen airplanes about fourteen of those at a time during that period, so we had about four that were on the ground being worked on more extensively. Sometimes we would bring an engine—an airplane would come in with an engine out, that plane would be down for a while and put another one in service there. But the planes were unbelievably reliable during that period of time. The ground crews did a fabulous job in keeping them going and I think that just like any other operation where you have the guys that are actually out doing the work, there’s a huge force of people behind them on the ground supporting that effort that nothing would happen if they didn’t get their job done correctly. So I would be happy to fill in any other blank spots there that you may have.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">One thing that occurs to me is the question of, what operational lessons did you learn as a pilot during this period?</u>
      <u who="BOWEN">There were a number of those. We learned you don’t fly above fifty feet or below fifteen hundred feet. If the weather was good and in <date when="1965-10">late October</date>, <date when="1965-11">November</date> period the country was coming out of the monsoon period, so the weather was pretty good then. So you had a lot of latitude as to what you wanted to fly but if you flew between fifty hundred feet above the ground and fifteen hundred feet, everybody out there is shooting at you and had a pretty good chance of hitting you. Above fifteen hundred feet, their accuracy dropped off significantly. So we learned that in the monsoon season—the other lesson we learn was learn the road nets, learn the road marks, the road signs, the visual things. Learn where the field strips were because come monsoon time, you won’t have the luxury of being high enough to see them. So we all memorized the routes so when the monsoon season came later on, we were down in the trees and typically flew as low as we could. What I discovered was that, and you can see this very accurately, some of the Vietnamese civilians were working in the rice fields, we would come across there typically, have to pull up slightly to make sure the props didn’t hit one of them on the ground. But we were down right as low as we could get it. We used our memory of the roads and the turns in the roads to help us navigate to where we were going because you were down so low, you couldn’t see much down there. As illustrated by—one time we were on our way from <placeName>Camp Holloway</placeName> up to <placeName>Kontum</placeName>, to the north. We’re down right in the tress and the road turned to the right and down, so I slip the plane out to the left a little bit and turned right and the wing tip went down in the roadbed. Just as I made that turn to follow the road, a <orgName>Vietnamese</orgName> truck was coming the other way and I can still see the white of his eyes as he turned hard right off the road and I rolled the wings level and pulled up slightly to clear him. As we continued the route, the crew chief who was sitting in the back said, “Sir, do you know that you just ran a truck off the road?” So we were down pretty low over there. But that was the safe—I never took a hit when I was down low, I never took a hit above fifteen hundred feet. But the transition typically—they’d learned that if you get somewhere around where the fixed wing operations were going on, you could catch airplanes in the pattern, and it was pretty risky there. We developed a strategy to do 360 overhead approaches, so that you could stay very close to the field. We had typically <orgName>Air Force</orgName> support that we could call in when we started getting ground fire, to suppress that fire around airports that we were using. So those were important lessons to us there. Some of the others we learned was try to stage the loads by aircraft. By that I mean, if you had an eight aircraft lift going on and you were flying a combination of troops and Jeeps and fuel, try to have airplanes dedicated to one of those missions. So that you weren’t putting seats down for troops and lifting them up the next time for fuel and installing rollers for ammunition palettes. So we got much more efficient in how we used the airplanes after the Ia Drang operation took place. I think that those were important lessons from the way we operated. The other thing we did was we learned to have alert crews. We had two crews on call twenty-four hours a day, even if nothing was going on because several times early on in our tour, we’d get an emergency call from the <orgName>Cav</orgName> headquarters saying, “We’ve got to have two airplanes here, now!” Sometimes we would have crews that were off somewhere or asleep or whatever the case was. So we kept two airplanes with the doors open, the crew chiefs had already preflight them all, the switches were turned on, so you just had to throw the master switch on and put the crews in there and you were ready to go.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">As an administrator, is it your job to make sure these kinds of changes take place?</u>
      <u who="BOWEN">It was really an operations role more than that. I was really responsible, and my primary responsibility of course was a fixed-wing aviator, but my administrative role really ran to making sure the morning reports got done, we kept up to where people were, who was sick or wounded and where they were and that sort of thing. Get to keep the paperwork flow going there. Again, we had wonderful specialists that were on the ground all the time doing it, so often times I just had to fix my signature to the paperwork. The operations guys were really responsible for the assignment of the crews. We had some spectacular platoon leaders and section leaders who paired up the pilots for the missions and matched the experience levels with the difficultly of the missions. We flew into some terrible weather over there. The flights in a combat environment- you will take risks that you don’t in the <placeName>States</placeName>. For example, in moving artillery ammunition in the <placeName>States</placeName>, we would have to have two aircraft assigned to every mission where there was a movement of artillery or rocket ammunition because they wouldn’t let us fly the fuses with the projectiles. In <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, we flew not just them together, the fuses were already screwed into the warhead, they were put back into the fiber-cube and we airdropped them to the artillery. So there were shortcuts taken in the interest of combat expediency. We flew a lot of ground control approaches, that was the typical way of getting in during bad weather. We had some highly experienced ground crews that were doing a radar guidance that could tell you, “Left off course, right off course, turn left, turn right, on course, on glide slope.” They would take us down to—the typical minimums were three-hundred-foot ceiling and 1-mile visibility, and those approaches were being run into twelve hundred foot strips. So we learned early on that you fly that approach down until you broke out power off, full flaps. Let the plane sink low to use every foot of the runway, little power at the bottom to catch it on the round out and to reverse the props and roll in. So we got—it sounded as I’ve explained it to others, it sounds a little spooky in particular to other pilots, but when you do it every day, you get really, really good at it.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">Is this anything you would’ve practiced in <placeName>the United States</placeName> ever?</u>
      <u who="BOWEN">Yes, yes. We practiced that during <name type="event">Air Assault II</name>. It’s one of the things that we would find—part of the techniques, there were a lot of helicopter techniques were found during those test exercises in <placeName>South Carolina</placeName>. One of the things we learned was how to make short field approaches in the very short and unapproved strips using these radar guidance techniques.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">What about losses in your unit?</u>
      <u who="BOWEN">You know, we went over sea with the highest average time pilots of any Caribou company. I think the reason we went with the <orgName>Cav</orgName> was we were the only one of the five Caribou companies that were assigned to strike-com, which was the highest level of readiness of aviation companies. So from a readiness standpoint, we were more able to go quicker than the other companies were. When it came time to make the deployment, we actually had the newest airplanes, the lowest time airframe hours, so we had to—knowing that others were coming behind us, we had to take half of our new airplanes and trade them with other units and take some of their older ones in and prep those to go. We didn’t take anything overseas that had less than half five life remaining engines, tires, propellers. Anything that was less than half live remaining got changed at <placeName>Fort Benning</placeName> before we went. So it would minimize the maintenance requirements in-country. We practiced the overseas deployment by long non-stop flight to <placeName>Puerto Rico</placeName> over-water, so we practiced that. We learned how to operate the airplanes the most fuel-efficient way. So we prepped as best as we could. We made a long over land flight, preceding that <placeName>Puerto Rico</placeName> over-water flight. We went from <placeName>Fort Benning</placeName> to <placeName>Kansas City</placeName>, to <placeName>Fort Meade, Maryland</placeName>. The air traffic controllers never did understand exactly what we were doing going west when we intended to land at an airport well to the east. But we had measured the distance to make sure that was at least the length of the leg from <placeName>San Francisco</placeName> to <placeName>Hawaii</placeName>, which was a risky mission. We had about an hour’s worth of fuel remaining when we got to <placeName>Hawaii</placeName> on that leg, after seventeen hours in the air. We had a big fifty-five-gallon drum of oil inside the fuselage that when we get our level lights— because these engines burn about an gallon an hour of oil. They had a control panel inside the crew chief could turn these valves. It was real <persName>Rube Goldberg</persName> rig, but it worked. They could turn the valve and had a crank inside to pump oil into the oil tank to the lower engine that measured how many gallons had been pumped back in because they knew what level the old light came on. But it worked, it was very rudimentary, had rudimentary navigation equipment on board. The air force guys at <placeName>Hickam Field,</placeName> of course they’d never seen any airplanes like that. They couldn’t believe we were foolhardy enough to be flying across the Pacific, but we got over there with no losses. One aircraft had an engine failure halfway to <placeName>Midway</placeName>. It descended from ten thousand feet down to fifteen hundred feet before the other engine had enough power to catch the flight, so they were four-five hours behind the rest of us getting into <placeName>Midway</placeName>, but again we had a C-130 flying with us it was full spares. Spare engines, spare gears, spare props and that airplane taxied directly into the maintenance hangar about the four o’clock in the afternoon. The engine was changed overnight, it was test flown at seven o’clock in the morning, at eight o’clock it was on the line, ready to go for the next leg. So we didn’t miss a lick the whole way. Had we not had the benefit of the training that we got at Fort Benning, and the lessons that we learned there, we and the <orgName>Cav</orgName> would’ve been in a lot worse trouble than we were. Lot of the kinks had been worked out during those air assault exercises over there. There were, as I said lots more lessons learned in-country when the shooting started.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">Two questions. I'm actually, first very interested in your personal reaction, if you can recall it to taking anti-aircraft fire or fire from the ground the first time.</u>
      <u who="BOWEN">The bullets made a snapping noise when they went by the cockpit. Most of the hits that we took were in the half of the airplane. We did take some in the cockpit. Not a lot, but it was sporadic. We might fly two months and not take a single hit. Then we’d come in and we—after every landing we would, if we were not in the field, if we were at <placeName>An Khe</placeName> or <placeName>Pleiku</placeName>, we’d always get out and walk around to look at the airplane, see if it had any damage. You know, we would not irregularly get some small arms fire in there. I remember one of the cases a crew chief had toolbox sitting back there that he would use in case if something happened. A round came up to the belly, went into the toolbox and it made the biggest clanging noise and rattling it sounded like somebody dumped a box of rocks in the back. We all had thought a wing had fallen off or something, we weren’t sure what happened back there. Overall, it was a safe year for us. As I said, we had an extremely well-trained pilots, had high time guys in the aircraft. We flew fifteen thousand hours, and we didn’t tear up a single airplane. If you think about the small margin of error that we were flying over there, the shortest strip we flew into was nine hundred feet at <placeName>Plei Me Special Forces camp</placeName>. The typical strip length was twelve hundred to fourteen hundred feet. We got a freebie like in An Khe, which is probably twenty-five hundred feet or three thousand, maybe longer than that, you could almost go to sleep going into a place like that. We were lucky we had reverse pitch propellers and we used those going in. In the monsoon season, it was particularly risky because you didn’t get much traction on the ground, the ground was always wet and muddy and you had to be careful when you reversed the engines, to make sure they were both reversed before you applied or else the plane would turn sideways on the ground. Sometimes when it would start sliding, you could apply more reverse on one engine to the other to straighten it back out. The strips that we flew into were really short, a lot of them we were flying into at night with extremely poor lighting. One I remember, sort of south, southeast of <placeName>An Khe</placeName> in the mountains. We flew into that rascal all night long. It was about twelve hundred feet long, it was lit by 105 shell casings with JP4 in it that they would have to go and relight each time because when we reversed props, they’ll blow the fire out. They finally put a jeep on each end of the runway so it would at least illuminate the lead end and the far end. It was grass. There was a village at one end and a mountain on the other, so you could only go in one way and come out that same direction. So we were fortunate that we had well trained crews and we were fortunate that wasn’t about nine months after we were in country, so we had a lot of experience going in there. Those kinds of missions, it took all the skill that you had to pull it off successfully.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">That is actually the major thing that I'm hearing, the professionalism of the unit that you flew with. These are really experienced, well trained professionals doing—</u>
      <u who="BOWEN">Right. We would kill, rape, or plunder to accomplish the mission. When the <orgName>Cav</orgName> called, we were going to be there, and they knew it. I don’t care how bad the weather was, how far it was, how short the strip, or how dark at night it was. We never turned down a single mission all day. As I said, we were supplemented by the <orgName>Air Force</orgName> frequently on the big lifts and you could count on it. When the sun went down, the <orgName>Air Force</orgName> left, and they might come back the next morning, maybe if they didn’t get, in my view, a higher priority mission. That was one of the advantages of having aircraft intro-theater tactically transport assigned to the <orgName>Cav</orgName>, so that the commanders—we worked for those commanders, we didn’t have to go through the <orgName>8th Air Force</orgName>, or <orgName>7th Air Force</orgName> whatever it was down in <placeName>Saigon</placeName> and sort out the missions and say, “Oh well, maybe we’ll see you in the morning, maybe we won’t.” You know, when the <orgName>Cav</orgName> was in the field, we felt like those were the guys that were really at risk, not us. The guys that were on the ground were the ones in great jeopardy. So there was no way were going to be in bed when those guys needed ammunition or food or water.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">Tell me about your leaders. Your leadership.</u>
      <u who="BOWEN">The company, as I said, the company was organized. Had a company commander, of course. Two platoon leaders, then two section leaders in each of those two flight platoons. The platoon leaders and the section leaders were peerless. They were out there flying with us. If they weren’t flying with us, they were meeting the planes with coffee, whatever it took to kind of help us keep us going. But fundamentally, they flew as much as we did. The section leaders, the platoon leaders would typically receive the orders for the next day, or depending on what the missions and say, “Okay, we got these kind of missions.” The two platoon leaders would get together and sort of split up those missions between them. They’d say, “Okay, I got”—the maintenance division would tell us, “We can fly thirteen airplanes tomorrow.” We had a twelve plane lift requirement. I’d say, “Okay, we’ll keep one in spare. Wile you take six, Larry you take six and here are the mission sheets that go with these.” Each one would have a mission sheet with an airplane assigned and then they would pass those down to the two sections and the section leaders were then responsible for pairing up the pilots that were to fly those missions. You knew—normally you knew what was going on the next day. We would typically get up at five in morning, take a shower, get a quick bite to eat, be down in operations at 6 or 6:30 on a normal day, not when the <orgName>Cav</orgName> was in the field and would leave at 7, come back usually about nine o’clock at night after flying all day. If things were hot, it took longer and would fly longer. My high time single day over there was twenty-seven takeoffs and landings in one day. I flew a little over nine hundred hours in combat time over there and six hundred and thirty-three combat missions during that year. So we flew a lot. Not every day because we couldn’t sustain the pace. You couldn’t get up at five in the morning and fly to eleven o’clock at night and be ready to go at five o’clock the next morning. Fortunately, the <orgName>Cav</orgName> normally would not have so many missions that we would have to fly around the clock. We could do it—typically one flight platoon would manage the missions for one day, the second of the flight platoon would do it the next day, so it kind of rotated on and off. That didn’t hold true when the <orgName>Cav</orgName> was in the field. When the <orgName>Cav</orgName> was in the field, we always had a radio relay shift going on. We always had more than one flight platoon engaged. So it was a little bit of this and if you talk to the troopers on the ground, they’ll say it was long periods of boredom and lots of periods of sheer terror. As we brought the <orgName>Cav</orgName> guys out of the field, and we did this a lot of times, I mean frankly, you couldn’t tell the blacks from the whites. It was so filthy and so dirty with that red clay mud all over them and they were so exhausted, there was never a word said. We loaded them onboard, they sat down and went immediately to sleep. They were just delighted to be out of there.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">Your <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> experience ended in Fall of ’<date type="1966">66</date>.</u>
      <u who="BOWEN"><date when="1966">’66</date> that’s right. I completed my tour in <date when="1966">’66</date>. I got out of the service in <date when="1966">’66</date>, I was on my initial tour as an obligated volunteer, they called them at the time. I went to <orgName>Emory University</orgName>, where I went to graduate school. Got an MBA there and then went to work at <persName>Arthur Andersen</persName>, and I finished my career as a partner there, retired from <placeName>Andersen</placeName> in <date when="1999">1999</date>.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">Very good. What kind of community service do you do? If any.</u>
      <u who="BOWEN">You know, during my time in <placeName>Andersen</placeName>, I worked heavily with the <orgName>United Way</orgName>. I was a chairman of the board for a four-year art college in <placeName>Memphis</placeName>. Did some work for senior citizens. I'm now the chair of <orgName>Audubon society Mississippi</orgName>. Still actively involved in chairs of different community boards. I'm also on three corporate boards now, using my financial background under the surveying acts era we are actually in now serving several committees today. I stay about the right level of busyness if I were doing it again because I could work a few hours in the morning, get that done and in the afternoon I could go work around the farm, or play, or go fly, I still actively fly. It works out, I'm just busy enough. People have asked me several times, “If you had to do it again, would you have gotten out of the army?” And I said, “Well, you know at the time, I felt I’d used up about seven of my nine lives” The army aviators at that time were on a year on, year off rotation out of country. They were so short of army aviators and they were ramping up so quickly that most of the guys that I flew with in 17th that were career officers, served two or three tours in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. But you know, if I had to do it again, I’d probably—I think I would’ve liked to have gone back to helicopter school and gone to a dust-off unit. I had a lot of respect for the missions those guys flew. We worked with them a good bit at night on radio relay, when they were down in the bushes. They were trying to locate a unit and the unit was trying to see them. Sometimes that turned over in that rotating beacon and we can see them down there and the unit could be trying—they couldn’t talk to each other because they were so low. Often times we would relay to the ground unit, ground unit would relay back to us and I would say, “Turn left fifteen degrees, you’re two miles out.” And help them get into where they need to pick up the wounded. There were a lot of people over there that really went way beyond what you would expect. I think that’s—you know, that’s really a testimony to the professionalism that everybody had over there. From the lowest PFC (Private First Class) to the colonels on the ground.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">To the flyers in the air.</u>
      <u who="BOWEN">To the flyers in the air. Like everybody—you know, we didn’t do anything special. We didn’t do anything more than everybody else was doing. Everybody was at maximum effort, all the time. Nobody whined, nobody complained and just put your head down and go.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">Tell me about being here.</u>
      <u who="BOWEN">This is the first reunion I’ve been to. It’s the first time the aircrews have invited. I view this as—this is all about the ground crews. I think it’s an honor and a privilege to be back with these guys. I didn’t know many of them. You’d pick them up, they were all in green. </u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">All dirty. </u>
      <u who="BOWEN">All dirty, at least when they came out. They didn’t say much going in, and they said even less coming out. We would typically—we didn’t know what unit they were from; we only knew they were <orgName>Cav</orgName> troopers. If you’d asked me, was the <orgName>7th Cav Regiment</orgName> engaged at <placeName>X-Ray</placeName> or the <orgName>5th</orgName> at <placeName>Albany</placeName> or anywhere else, I would have said, “I have no clue.” We’re just flying troops into the field. Armed troops and their machine guns, they would put all their gear between their feet because they sat down on the sides and strapped in and put all their stuff in the middle. Typically, the non-flying pilot would give the brief, tell them the procedure, the emergency procedures and the emergency exits. Give them some insights, where we were going, about how long the flight would be. We’d strap up front and away we’d go. They were very accommodating, even the guys that were wounded coming out didn’t whine much. We evac’d several helicopter pilots that had spinal injuries from being shot down low to the ground and the impact had spinal compression. They were under great pain; those guys were in stretchers. Tried to be as gentle with them as we could and tried to put a cargo strap across the top of them, so they could use their arms to stabilize themselves with.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">Do you remember one in particular?</u>
      <u who="BOWEN">I remember one warrant officer in particular. I don’t know his name, who had spinal compression that we put back in the back and he was in tremendous pain, we took him over to <placeName>Qui Nhon</placeName>. We took the cargo straps, strapped the stretcher handles down and them gave him a strap across top to make sure he didn’t slide around if there was any turbulence or landing jolts. So we tried to be as gentle as we could with those guys. I remember one guy we evac’d, one of the ground guys—he was a mess. He had unusual sized pair of boots and they had brought his boots out with him on the stretcher and the only thing he said to us when we were putting him on the airplane was, “Don’t forget my boots.” So he didn’t want to lose those boots, I remember. We put them on the stretcher between his feet. Last time I saw him he was going to the hospital in Nha Trang with—he and his boots. Lot of kind of interesting stories like that. The only secret message we got during the whole war during the time I was there, was for the Bob Hope Christmas Concert at <placeName>An Khe</placeName>, when he came to entertain the troops. That was a big deal, I did not get to attend, I flew—we took three Caribous over there, flying people from <placeName>An Khe</placeName> over there that were <orgName>Cav</orgName> troops and we were not permitted to go to the concert out of fear if we got mortared they wanted the crews with the airplanes to fly them out of there. Lots of fun things like that, there were moments of really funny things happening. I think anybody that was honest will say they experienced every human emotion while you were over there. It was a period of really funny things that cracked you up, sad things, scary things, boredom. Everything like that happened while you were over there. So I can’t think of any time in my life that had such a range of human emotion over there. Certainly, there’s never been a time where I worked as much as I did and as consistently as I did over there. But we were all in our twenties, bulletproof and had high energy level.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">Long term, what’s it meant to you?</u>
      <u who="BOWEN">You know, that’s an interesting question. I made some great friends over there. Probably a period of highest single level of activity of my life and I worked a lot of hours over the years. Lots of life lessons learned about how much can you do. I really felt like over there, I got lucky and got to sleep between sheets most of the time. Those guys were out there with ponchos around them or in the dirty, so you were never going to find me complaining. Those guys on the ground were the ones that were paying the toll. When I got out of there, I felt good about my experience. I volunteered for as many medevac missions as I could. So when I left there, I said, “By my actions alone, I know I’ve saved a lot of American lives.” So I don’t have any regrets. That’s why I said if I were to go back, I would’ve gone back as a dust-off pilot.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">We can stop there.</u>
      <u who="BOWEN">Okay. Thanks very much. I guess it’s important to capture the what the Caribous did over there.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">Yes, sure.</u>
      <u who="BOWEN">They were in the army for such a short period of time that you ask the active guys today about the Caribou, they don’t know anything about it. You know, the army— one thing I didn’t mention to you was—</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">(Speaks to third-party)</u>
      <u who="BOWEN">I think it’s important to understand why the <orgName>Army</orgName> got out of the Caribou business. At the time of the ’<date when="1965">65</date>, ’<date when="1966">66</date> era, that’s when the armed helicopter came along. If you talked to the air crew, <persName>Bruce Crandall</persName> and others, they had door gunners. We didn’t have any significant armed helicopters at that point in the war. The army needed them badly. That’s a close ground support role.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">Yes, sir.</u>
      <u who="BOWEN">That is an <orgName>Air Force</orgName> role. Intro-theater tactical transport is an <orgName>Air Force</orgName> role, and they were rankled at us flying those transport in-country. So a deal was worked out that the <orgName>Army</orgName> would transfer to the <orgName>Air Force</orgName> all of the caribous and the <orgName>Air Force</orgName> would concede the armed helicopter close ground support role. Probably in the long term, that was the right answer. I remember <persName>General Kinnard</persName> came over to <placeName>Pleiku</placeName> and met with the <orgName>17th</orgName> crews and told them how disappointed he was about that and how he disagreed with the conclusion to give up the Caribous. But you know, at the end of the day, that may have been the right answer. It would’ve been nice if we kept them both, it was unfortunate that we had these inter-service rivalries like that because I think the Caribous,  although they carried a smaller load than the bigger <orgName>Air Force</orgName> planes did, the army knew they could count on us to carry the water farm when it needed to be. They were less sure of the <orgName> Air Force</orgName>. First thing when the Caribou was transferred to the <orgName>Air Force</orgName>, they tore up a number of them. A lot of people were killed, including one plane at <placeName>An Khe</placeName> that flew into a mountain with some medevacs. They were not experienced pilots in the first six months they had them, they tore up. In our airplanes they tore up four of them with fatal accidents. Couple of them were shot down later in the war. I think they paid the price of not having well trained pilots. I did some of the transition training for the <orgName>Air Force</orgName> guys when they came in. They were guys coming out of B-52s. They’d gone through Caribou transition, they had thirty or so hours in the airplane. They had gone on leave; they’d gone to the <placeName>Philippines</placeName> for survival trainings. A lot of them hadn’t been on an airplane in two months. One of them climbed in there one day, got in the right seat, he got on the left. He sat there for a minute and I said, “Well, let’s light him up!” He said, “I’ve forgotten where the master switch is.” I knew it was going to be a long day when he said that. So you had to be careful, they were used to airplanes with anti-skid brakes on them, you could get on the brakes as hard as you wanted on the strip, and ours didn’t have that. They blew a lot of tires out, had a lot of damaged airplanes from that had to be repaired. They really paid the price for inexperience. All of the guys had flying time, they didn’t have flying time in airplanes that were short take offs and land, low airspeed approach airplanes. It could scare you sometimes those short approaches. If you didn’t time it right, you had to carry a little power at the bottom to make it round out. I’ve landed it once or twice with full throttle and airplane just barley landed because if you land it too slowly and you ran out, it just falls like a sack of potatoes. You learn that at <placeName>Fort Benning</placeName> and in-country. In fact, the flying at <name type="event">Air Assault II</name> in <placeName>South Carolina</placeName> was more treacherous frankly, than flying in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. We could add—the strip was fourteen hundred feet; you could add five knots for the family and be a little safer in the process. It’s a great airplane, the army was testing the <placeName>Buffalo</placeName>, which was the follow up to the Caribou as a twin-engine turbo prop. Had a fuselage size the same size as a Chinook, so you could take a load directly out of a Caribou, put it in your Chinook. Caribou fuselage was a little smaller so you couldn’t carry quite the same load. They fixed a lot of those problem and the <orgName>Army</orgName> bought three or four of those Buffalos for testing and they were in-country getting testing but that was about the time when the decision was made to transfer them into the <orgName>Air Force</orgName>. So that was the end of that. </u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">So you still fly?</u>
      <u who="BOWEN">Still fly. I have a private airplane; actually, have an open cockpit biplane I fly as well, just for fun. So it’s kind of fun to keep my medical license. I was one of the younger guys in the unit at the time. I was one of the lower time pilots because we had so many experienced captains in the unit and CWOs (Chief Warrant Officers) in the unit. So we had great pilots, great friends and all-in-all a positive experience.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">Okay. <persName>Mr. Bowen</persName>, it’s been fabulous. Thank you.</u>
      <u who="BOWEN">Thank you. Glad to tell this side of the war.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">Yes, sir.(End of interview.)</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
