<?xml-model href="../schemas/ddhi.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Transcript of an Interview with Theodore Danielsen</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>
          <orgName>Vietnam Center and Sam Johnson Vietnam Archive</orgName>
        </authority>
        <date>
          <!--  Date of publication, e.g. for citation purposes  -->
        </date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <recordingStmt>
          <recording xml:id="primary_recording" type="video" dur-iso="00:50:07">
            <!-- https://www.digi.com/resources/documentation/digidocs/90001437-13/reference/r_iso_8601_duration_format.htm -->
            <media url="" mimeType="video/mp4"/>
          </recording>
        </recordingStmt>
        <bibl xml:id="primary_transcription">
          <respStmt>
            <persName>Mark Steven Varela</persName>
            <orgName>Sam Johnson Vietnam Center and Archive</orgName>
            <resp ref="http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/trc.html">Transcriber</resp>
          </respStmt>
          <ref target="path_to_file">https://vva.vietnam.ttu.edu/images.php?img=/OH/OH0478/OH0478.pdf</ref>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The Oral History Project of the Vietnam Center and Sam Johnson Vietnam Archive</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application ident="DDHIEncoder" version="1.0">
          <desc>Conversion from Word docx to TEI xml.</desc>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en-us">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <particDesc>
        <person xml:id="DANIELSEN"/>
        <person xml:id="NAPOLI"/>
      </particDesc>
      <settingDesc>
        <setting>
          <date when-iso="2005-11-11"/>
          <locale/>
        </setting>
      </settingDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <u who="DANIELSEN">Went to the infantry school, was commissioned infantry school. Took a basic school, airborne course, and ranger. Went to the <orgName>82nd Airborne Division</orgName> <date when="1961-01">January ’61</date>. <date when="1962-06">June of ’62</date>, I went to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> as an advisor with the <orgName>2nd ARVN (Army of the Republic of Vietnam) Division</orgName>. Part of that tour, I was a senior advisor to the <orgName>1st Battalion, 5th Regiment, 2nd ARVN Division</orgName>. I was reassigned to <placeName>Fort Benning</placeName> to test the helicopter concept with the <orgName>11th Air Assault Division</orgName>. Went through that and was commanding <orgName>D Company, 1st of the 8th Cav</orgName>. By the brigade commander we’d gotten word that we were going back to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> and the brigade commander came to me and asked me if I would consider going back to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> for my 2nd tour. I was on orders to go to the advanced course and I told them, “Not as a combat support company commander, but if I were commanding a regular infantry company, I would certainly go back.” Went home, told my wife what I’d done and the reason I’d done it. We’d been married nine months. I think it was foggy Wednesday night, <persName>Colonel Brown</persName> came into the club and I was having dinner with my wife, <persName>Cynthia</persName> and the <orgName>Charlie Company</orgName> commander and he walked over and look at my wife and said “I’m sorry.” And he looked at me and he said, “You’ll take over <orgName>A Company</orgName> Monday morning.” Which was a rifle company. So I knew at that point that I was going back for my second tour. As—what every infantry officer wants to do when he is a captain rank, is to command a rifle company. Not only was it a rifle company, but it was a parachute because our brigade was designated parachute brigade. As we filled up to go to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, I was getting enthusiastic troops out of the airborne school. You got to have some bit of enthusiasm in a land to go to airborne school. But they were coming into my company and I was getting NCOs (Non-Commissioned Officers) out of the <orgName>101st</orgName> and the <orgName>82nd</orgName>. As I understand it, whoever had been on post the longest, meaning those that they wanted to keep there were the first ones that had to come down to our outfit. So I had the privilege and good fortune to weld these enthusiastic soldiers with these really professional NCOs. Then, I know it wasn’t part of the <orgName>Army</orgName>’s wisdom, but they put us on a boat and they locked us up—excuse me, ship and locked us up for thirty days, for the trip over there. Now, you can’t sleep this far from another guy for thirty days and not get to know him. That really paid off when we got to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> because everybody was friend of everybody. Then, the way you continued that is you get replacements, you assign them to an old guy. That sort of brings him into the foe.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">Before we go to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, tell us more about the training you took your men through.</u>
      <u who="DANIELSEN">At <placeName>Benning</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">Yes, sir.</u>
      <u who="DANIELSEN">Well, what we did was we found out how to use helicopters as a means of transportation and as a means of support, the aerials rockets, etc. To get to a point to adopt procedures to get out in an organized fashion and go about whatever mission you were assigned to do. Of course, when you land in an area, the first thing you do is secure it and then you go about your mission. As you did this over and over and over, you develop shortcuts. Example of a shortcut, usually when you set up a perimeter, you’ll say, “Twelve o’clock is north. 1st Platoon you're from 12 to 3, 2nd Platoon 3 to 7, 3rd Platoon 7 to 12.” That’s not evenly divided but mortar’s in the middle. We find out during the course of training, that for the platoon leader to take out his compass after he got on the ground wasted precious seconds. So the direction of flight became twelve o’clock.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">I see. </u>
      <u who="DANIELSEN">Because the helicopters always came in the same position. Everybody knew where twelve o’clock was. Nobody had to look at a compass, nobody had to tell anybody, everybody already knew when they got off the helicopter exactly where to go. Those kinds of SOPs (Standard Operating Procedures) really made it lightening quick to go anywhere. We could tailor forces in the air. I could be going one place; something happens on the ground somewhere else and I'm told to divert and reinforce that way. We’re talking about a hundred, hundred-fifty soldiers that all of the sudden got to know what to do when they get on the ground and how to get there. The helicopter, the Huey, D model and H model could carry an infantry squad and—so it was very easy to organize these four helicopters lifting a platoon. We learn to employ aerial rocket artillery, which is—we had an aerial rocket artillery battalion, they were capable to getting to you in a hurry if you needed fire support. We had two artillery, but they had to get somewhere on the ground, had to be taken there, secured, set up their cannon before they could fire, or their Howitzers. So initially you could use these aerial rockets until the artillery get set up and then you had your sustained fire support. This combination of firing and maneuvering is a way we set things up. We learned a lot of tricks to the trade. For example, you could lift a 105 Howitzer on a strap and at a long length, you could hang its ammunition. So the helicopter could come in, put the ammunition on the ground, move over, go down a little further and drop the Howitzer off. So you had your ammunition, you didn’t have to put the Howitzer down and wait for the ammunition to come in, it was there at the same time the Howitzer was. We usually ran an infantry company there to secure it until the Howitzer got set up. You could leapfrog all over the place, supporting any place you wanted to go with ground fire suppose. Initially though, you used the aerial rockets. My personal training, as I said I was a military academy graduate. Went through the basic course, which taught you how to be a lieutenant. Then I went through Airborne and Ranger school. Ranger school, the familiar expression is “I wouldn’t do it again for a million dollars.” But I wouldn’t take a million for having done it. It showed me how far you can really push yourself and others. It’s surprising to a lot of people how hard they can go and for how long they can go when they need to.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">That became critical for your command?</u>
      <u who="DANIELSEN">Not so much. I never had to do that. </u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">I see.</u>
      <u who="DANIELSEN">Push myself that hard. We had to push ourselves, but never to that point where you almost couldn’t operate. When I went through Ranger school, it was only seven weeks long because they wanted us to finish before Christmas. Normal school is nine weeks. The only thing they cut out was sleep. We went for nine days and eight nights and had six hours of sleep. Of course, your calories were built up by food. It really did show you how far you could push yourself. Fortunately, in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, we never encountered that amount of endurance. We encountered a lot more dangerous situations from enemy action, etc. But as far as endurance, my time in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> could best be described as long periods of intense boredom, punctuated by very short periods of stark terror. So it was bounce, walk, walk, walk, beat the bushes down. Big spike in energy if something happened, walk, walk, walk looking for them. Then, the helicopters would come back, and you’d go off to some other place.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">So tell me about those days in October and November. You guys arrived, must be September and did some shake out.</u>
      <u who="DANIELSEN">Right, we got there, I don’t even remember the date. Landed in <placeName>Qui Nhon</placeName>, went up to <placeName>An Khe</placeName>. Our first tactical mission was to secure three hills south of <placeName>An Khe</placeName>. We were called the “Alpha Gators” by the way. We used to have the Alligator from Pogo, he marked our entrance to the company area. Called ourselves the “Alpha Gators”. But the three hills south was secured by a company from the <orgName>101st Airborne division</orgName>, as we are coming into <placeName>An Khe</placeName> to protect our ingress into the country. So I went down there to take over from lo and behold a classmate of mine, <persName>Swift Martin</persName>. He was in <persName>Charlie Company</persName>, <orgName>2nd of the 327th</orgName>. That was my first mission, very simple, nothing happened. Went down there, set the company up. Cleared fields of fires in case we got hit, we could shoot further than the bush right in front of you. We were there a couple of days. I don’t remember all the precursors to November, but the first brigade went up to the <placeName>Pleiku</placeName> area, where were at <placeName>Catecka</placeName>. We went to several LZs (Landing Zone) around in the <placeName>Ia Drang river</placeName> and we never ran into anything. We were—I think we had B, A, and D company. <orgName>C Company</orgName> was on a mission down on the coast and we were up at <placeName>Pleiku</placeName>. You can do that with helicopters. I got a call on the radio to go to <placeName>Duc Co</placeName> and I was going to be co-located with <persName>Colonel Stockton</persName>’s <orgName>1st Squadron, 9th Cavalry</orgName>. He was an <orgName>Air Cav</orgName> troop in the division—<orgName>Air Cav Squadron</orgName>, sorry, not a troop. Lot of difference in organization. <orgName>Air Calvary</orgName> troop had a red, white, blue team. A white team was the OH-13 Scout Helicopters. The red team was a gunship, the old A-Model Huey. The blue team was a regular infantry platoon commanded by a captain instead of a lieutenant as in my company, but it had its own organic aircraft. Their job is to go out and find them, not to fight and sustain battle with them, but to find them. That’s why they had the scouts, they have a platoon to develop the situation. Then, if you can find a lot of them there, you call in the regular units, not the scout units. Anyway, I was assigned by the division to be co-located with <persName>Colonel Stockton</persName> for this purpose, if his people went out and ran into something, I was there. We got down there, and they didn’t have any fire support, so I loaned them my mortars and let them go with them. They were going down to establish a base at a place that was initially called <placeName>LZ Betty</placeName>. They put ambushes out from there. My mortar platoon went down there with them so we could provide mortar support if they ran into something. I stayed up at <placeName>Duc Co</placeName> with my three rifle platoons and <persName>Colonel Stockton</persName> and whatever he had in the area. We found out later that the North Vietnamese had decided to cut the country in half and this was subsequent to <placeName>Plei Me</placeName>, which is where they first ran into their—which stopped them and then they were coming back toward the Laoshan border. So we were trying to find out where they were. We found a hospital and anyway, the <orgName>1st of the 9th</orgName> was to set up ambushes out in the <placeName>Drang River</placeName>, on trails coming in from <placeName>Laos</placeName> and one of them sprang their ambush on a force a lot bigger than they were. So they withdrew back into the LZ and <persName>Major Zion</persName> was in command, <persName>Captain Nolan</persName> sprung the ambush. <persName>Major Zion</persName> was the commander on the ground. The enemy force that they ambushed, the rest of them followed him in and surrounded the LZ. <persName>Colonel Stockton</persName> came over to tell me he’d gotten a call from <persName>Zion</persName> that the force was getting larger and larger, and his situation was becoming more and more tenuous. So I guess about 11:30 he asked to tell me when to send one of my platoons down to reinforce <persName>Zion</persName>. My third platoon leader was my senior platoon leader, <persName>John Hanlon</persName> who was wounded that night and has been a paraplegic since. Great solider, just great. Anyway, good attitude, everything. He went first and then stopped and came over. He was attached to <persName>Zion</persName>.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">Yes. </u>
      <u who="DANIELSEN">Okay. Then stopped and came back over and said, “Get the rest of your company ready, you’re all going.” We flew down there, and I was with the 2nd <placeName>Platoon</placeName> in the lead ship and I’ll never forget looking down at the LZ. I wanted to name it LZ Spiderweb because from the tracers, the red American tracers and the blue North Vietnamese tracer, it looked like a spider web because it was flat terrain and they had the tree line and we didn’t. That’s what we went into. It was the first time the American forces had ever used helicopters in a nighttime assault, of a hot surrounded LZ. So we went in, my mission was to take the southern part of the perimeter and to hold on to reinforce until daylight. We got down there, and I had called the 3rd Platoon, told them to move over again, we were landing to the south. Told him to take <date>9 to 12, 2nd</date> Platoon took 3 to 12. Then, when the 1st <placeName>Platoon</placeName> came in, it was to go to twelve o’clock and these two on the side would shift back. That’s the way we locked the perimeter. After that it was pretty much shoot at them if they shoot at you. I remember crawling up aside to this one kid, he wasn’t from my outfit, he was from <date>the 1st of the 9th</date>. Buttons were too thick on their uniforms that night because it was flat terrain. You could shoot from one side of the thing to other and there was nothing on the ground. There was one anthill on it and those anthills were ten, twelve feet high. I crawl up aside this kid and said, “What are you doing back here? You ought to get up to the front line!” He looked at me and said, “Sir, this is the front line.” So there was a lot of humor in it. My troops did, as did <date>the 1st of the 9th</date>, they just did a magnificent job of the things that they were trained to do. Taking up sectors of fire, interlocking the sectors, employing the machine guns either singly or in pairs depending on the platoon leader, to cover your front. We didn’t do mortars the way they were trained to do because we had to fire by adjustment. We couldn’t say such and such charge, such and such elevation. What you did was stand the tube up straighter and fire another round and walk it into you because it was less than forty meters from where the mortars were to the perimeter and it doesn’t do any good to shoot a hundred and fifty yards over there when they’re only forty yards away. Did a great job, they were just wonderful.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">Describe yourself. How do you characterize yourself during that night?</u>
      <u who="DANIELSEN">One, I was scared. I had two radio operators just moved around in the southern part. As easy as I could making sure the platoon is on the line. Had what they needed. Of course, during this period of time, from—I think I got in there at 12:30 until daylight, we were bringing in ammunition, distributing ammunition, we were putting causalities back on the helicopters to fly them out and those helicopter drivers they just kept coming in and out. Come in, kick the ammunition off, and put the causalities on. I had one medic I recommended for the <orgName>DSA</orgName>, Distinguished Service Cross. He was wounded six times and had to be ordered to get on the helicopter himself.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">You ordered him?</u>
      <u who="DANIELSEN">Yeah. <persName>Specialist Ortiz</persName>. Otherwise he would have stayed there and still tried to treat. That’s the kind of guy he was, lives in <placeName>Texas</placeName>. That was about it. Same thing over and over. Trying to inspire the guys, if you see a kid scared you got to make light of it.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">How would you do it?</u>
      <u who="DANIELSEN">Well, you got to crawl up beside him. You got to let him know that you're there with him and he’s not there by himself. You can’t do that to everyone. You do this over a period of time. They know that you’re going to do everything you can to protect them and to not sacrifice them needlessly. They develop that with you over the months ahead of going into combat. So they know when you crawl up there, that you’re in there with them. Nothing is worse than being alone in a place where there’s danger. Soon as there is somebody else, that’s what you do. Let them know that the army is there with them and they’re not out on a shoestring. There’s nothing magic, it’s just that there is a thing that a solider have, that I think they have, that most people don’t talk about. But I was talking about a <date>thirty-day</date> boat trip, the troops learned to love each other. They are fellow human beings in the same predicament. They know that they become buddies and they know they could be taken care of by the others. I made my troops a promise before we left for <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. I said “I will never leave one of you behind. You will all come home, I don’t know whether you’ll be alive or dead, but you will all come home.” I was successful in that. General <persName>Moore</persName> was successful in that, and he had a lot more than I did. Troops will learn to understand—no, they will come to understand, not learn to understand. Come to understand that you and the <orgName>Army</orgName> are going to take care of them as best you can. Now it’s a dangerous environment, you can’t protect them. But you can take care of them. It’s simple as that.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">It’s simple and complicated at the same time.</u>
      <u who="DANIELSEN">I go back to—there’s a relationship between soldiers, I call it love. That it’s part of doing the same thing for your country because I grew up with duty on our country and I think it’s more than that. There’s a thing between soldiers. I always tell replacements “First thing I want you to do is go write a letter. I don’t care who you write it to, but tell them you got here, tell them you got a place to sleep, and somebody is feeding you. Send it to your girlfriend, your mother, I don’t care. But that’s the first thing you got to do for me.” Does that answer it?</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">I think so.</u>
      <u who="DANIELSEN">Okay. (Chuckles)</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">I wanted to know what kind of commander you were. That’s why I was asking those questions.</u>
      <u who="DANIELSEN">I always did what the troops did, you know, I was never an absentee commander. I protected the troops as well as I could. I always had flank security out, rear security, point man. As you move through the jungle, you have to make sure you don’t get surprised and the only way to do that is stick people out. They hated it because they had to beat through the jungles and out on the flanks and they’re not following behind the one guy with the machete. They hated it at the time, but then they come to realize what they were really doing. Make sure that the whole body doesn’t get ambushed and that’s a way soldiers take care of soldiers, making sure you do that. They recognize that if a commander doesn’t make them do that, they see it right away. I think I was a good company commander. You’ll have to ask my bosses. (Chuckles)</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">So what happened after that night?</u>
      <u who="DANIELSEN">Let’s see. The next morning, the D and B Companies of <date>the 1st of the 8th Cavalry</date> came into the LZ and <date>the 1st of the 9th</date> left. I was supposed to cross a stream, north-south stream, over to the south bank of the Ia Drang River and sweep along to the east. With the Ia Drang running east-west on my left flank and <persName>Chu Pong Mountain</persName> on my right flank. Later we found out that <persName>Chu Pong</persName> was an assembly area, whatever you want to call it of three <placeName>North Vietnamese Regiments</placeName>. <date>32nd</date>, 33rd, and <date>66th</date>. I got one man across the stream and they aborted the mission. I don’t know why they aborted the mission. In hindsight, I'm glad they did because nothing would have been worse than having three regiments coming off of the mountain and you got to turn and look up the mountain and you got a river at your back. Because the other two companies of our battalion were going to be on the other side of the river. Then, we came back to An <persName>Khe</persName>, they brought the first brigade back and we were going to be replaced by the 3rd brigade, which had <date>the 1st and 2nd of the 7th</date>, and I think <date>the 2nd of the 12th</date>. They were going to go out and take over the operation in <placeName>the Ia Drang River</placeName>. At that time, I went over to see Colonel Moore because we had become good friends at Fort Benning.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">Yes, sir.</u>
      <u who="DANIELSEN">I went over to see him because this is the first time that we’d started running into North Vietnamese, PAVN (<orgName>People’s Army</orgName> of <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>) we called them. I said, “When you go up there, they’re going to be the North Vietnamese regulars, and not the <placeName>Vietcong</placeName>, so be ready. He was ready. After that, different operations, I think our next big fight was on <date>the 18th of December</date>. As I said, long periods of boredom, short periods of stark terror. In that fight, it was a case of, I thought, the epitome of the way the helicopters are so flexible because we could change missions ten minutes out from a landing zone and you’d just tell the company commander he’s going somewhere else and all he’s got to do was tell his platoon leaders—or all of the sudden, somebody else can get in a fight and you can detach them from this unit and send them to that unit and attach them to that unit. We learned all that at Fort Benning, in the 11th <orgName>Air Assault</orgName>. After our tour there, we went to the advanced course and there were twelve company commanders from the 1st <orgName>Calvary Division</orgName>, in the advanced class. They were teaching airborne air mobile operations and they didn’t understand what we were telling them. They didn’t know you could operate that way. They were still troop leading procedure. This headquarters takes half the time passes down the order, half the time available, and each subsequent headquarters takes half the time available until the start of—they were still mired in that. We said, “No, you don’t have to do that. You can operate faster and more flexible, in a more flexible manner.” I had two tours in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> at the time and I was one of the few out of our advanced course. This was in <date>’66</date> and if you didn’t have a tour in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, they could’ve cut your orders right then. You were going right after the advanced course. If you had one tour in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, you were going back after the advanced course. I was one of those people that had two tours already. I had the advisor tour and then the command tour. So I got sent to a <date>three year</date> tour in <placeName>Europe</placeName>. Big NATO (<orgName>North Atlantic Treaty Organization</orgName>) headquarters. Nice town—<placeName>Holland</placeName>, the Dutch love Americans. I was there and then I—after <placeName>Holland</placeName>, I was assigned to <placeName>Korea</placeName>. This was in <date>’70</date>. Guess who my division commander was? General <persName>Moore</persName>. I was a major at the time and I wanted to be a battalion executive officer and I talked to the G1, the personnel guy and wrangled myself in the executive officer’s job in the battalion. I didn’t know it, but I found out that General <persName>Moore</persName> was the division commander and I called his aid and said, “I knew General Moore in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> and in <placeName>Fort Benning</placeName>, and I’d like just to come up and pay a call.” He said, “How’s eight o’clock <date>Monday</date> morning?” I said, “That’s fine with me.” Just before I went up there on <date>Sunday</date>, the brigade commander where I was said, “I’d been fighting <date>all weekend</date>, but I might lose you.” I went up to see General Moore, walked in and saluted and reported and he says, “Ted, it’s great to see you! You’re going to be <orgName>the Division Operation’s</orgName> Officer and that subject is not open for discussion. How the hell have you been?” So we sat down and talked. He’s a fine person.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">What did you learn about either yourself or commanding men, as a rifle company commander?</u>
      <u who="DANIELSEN">That I was well prepared. The <orgName>Army</orgName> system of training, my days at <placeName>West Point</placeName>, that I always made sure they were prepared, and I felt confident. I think largely because I’d been to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> on an advisor’s tour. I felt very confident and like I had an advantage over my fellow company commanders who had not been there. Now, some of them preformed much better than I did. But I did think I had that having been there before advantage.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">What I'm looking for is a connection from what you took away from the experience and used throughout your entire military service.</u>
      <u who="DANIELSEN">Well, hopefully when we went back to the advanced course, we took a different appreciation of helicopter warfare and left that. My tour after that—I did not leave very much from that experience in <placeName>Holland</placeName>. It was a very high headquarters. There was not much brought from that experience to that job. In the <orgName>Army</orgName> it’s always <orgName>OJT</orgName> (On the Job Training). I was never trained to do a job before I had the job. I had to learn it at the time. Now there’s certain traits that every individual has. I hope that commanders like Colonel <persName>Brown</persName> that told this Captain, “You go over and command <orgName>A Company</orgName>.” Can recognized these traits. I recognized those traits in people I see. People who say they’re going to do something, and then they do it. Right away the opposite, people that say that they are going to do something, and they don’t. I really have a hard time with that. “I’ll call you tomorrow” And you don’t. That really—I have a hard time with it. I don’t—I did not find that in the military. When somebody said they were going to do something, they did it. It was as simple as that. I don’t find that in most pursuits since I retired. I went to <placeName>Korea</placeName> with <orgName>General Moore</orgName> and I came back from there. I had a son born blind and I thought he was going to be treated in <placeName>South Carolina</placeName>, so I had ROTC (Reserve Officer Training Corps) assignment in <placeName>South Carolina</placeName> after that. Then I went to <persName>Fort Leavenworth</persName>, then to trading and doctrine command. Worked on equipment and personnel, how to organize a unit. Then I went to what was called a rapid deployment joint task force as a plans officer. That later became <placeName>CENTCOM</placeName> (<orgName>United States Central Command</orgName>) and that’s the command that’s doing <placeName>Iraq</placeName> now. We were the first people that were assigned to that command back in <date>1980</date>. Then I went to <persName>Fort Jackson</persName> and took up training soldiers for <date>four years</date> and then I retired. Took up teaching high school mathematics. I’d never thought about this until your question came up, but after I left teaching high school mathematics, one of the girls I taught, she was in the tenth grade, <date>two years later</date> was a class speaker at their graduation. She said during her speech—I didn’t hear her speech. It was reported to me by her mother through a friend of mine to me. <persName>Said</persName> that she was talking about things that people taught her and she said “Colonel <persName>Danielsen</persName> taught me accountability. If he said it, it was. If he said, ‘If you don’t do that, this is going to happen to you.’ It did. And that goes back to ‘if you say you’re going to do something, do it.’ People will appreciate it more. Regardless of how it affects them.” I don’t know if that answered your question.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">It did. Tell me about these events, coming to these kinds of reunions.</u>
      <u who="DANIELSEN"><date>The 1st of the 8th Cav</date> has a reunion <date>every year</date>. We just had one in <placeName>San Diego</placeName>. Then I had my class reunion <date>last month</date> at <placeName>West Point</placeName>. The 45th anniversary of our graduation. Not our forty-fifth reunion because we only had one every five years. <date>Last year</date> was the first time I came to one of these. I just thought I’d come and got an email from <persName>Joe Galloway</persName>. Mail to the world. So I wrote him, I emailed him back said, “I think I’ll come.” He wrote, “Good. You’re the keynote speaker.” The dinner tomorrow night, I was the speaker <date>last year</date>. My speech was primarily about the—when Colonel <persName>Stockton</persName> committed me to down to LZ Mary, he told the General that he had no recourse but to commit me. This was over the radio. The General did not give him permission to do it. So when he told me to go, I went and you have to think about why I went instead of saying, “Sir, you’re not supposed to—remember my mortars are down there.” I told him I wasn’t going to leave them. So we went. Troops pick up on this. Troops come to appreciate it and know that you’re in this together and they’re not in it by themselves. You’re in it because your country asks you to do it. That’s what I talked about at the last speech. I think <persName>Stockton</persName> got the raw steel I’ve seen in the <orgName>Army</orgName>. With one exception. I thought he was—he was eccentric, but he was inspiring commander. His troops loved him. They’ll do anything for him. A little eccentric, but he did his job, he went after them and found them, which to me was his job. I met him—they started cranking up a reunion also, <date>1st</date> of <orgName>the 9th Cavalry</orgName>, they asked me to come to their first one. They made me an honorary lifetime member, so I go to their reunions. So that’s four different reunions I go to now and love it. Seeing my old soldiers, seeing guys from other units like here. It’s that bond as a leader you develop with your troops. All these people that participated in this Ia Drang River thing become bonded because of a common experience. Anybody would find that no matter what it is, what kind of experience it is, the people that do it together if it’s worthwhile doing, become bonded by it. No individual can go do anything. No individual soldier can do anything. You got to have this organization that works and works right. And when you do, it is synergistic.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">You were professionals.</u>
      <u who="DANIELSEN">I hope so. I couldn’t have done it any better, I don’t think. I would’ve liked to have seen a different outcome, but that wasn’t my decision.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">Yes, sir. I think that’s a good place to stop.</u>
      <u who="DANIELSEN">Okay.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">I got to hear you talk <date>last year</date>, it was wonderful.</u>
      <u who="DANIELSEN">Oh, thank you. I didn’t know you had heard it.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">It was good, it was really good.</u>
      <u who="DANIELSEN">Thank you. Well, you met <persName>John Hanlon</persName> then. He was the guy in the wheelchair.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">Yes sir—well, I didn’t get to shake his hand, but I saw him.</u>
      <u who="DANIELSEN">When they asked me to—first thing I did was call him up, I said, “<persName>John</persName>, they want me to do this, and I want you to make the introduction.” It’s the same thing that I was talking about awhile go. He gets to be a part of this. A Company got to be part of everything. That’s the way it we were.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">Perfect.</u>
      <u who="DANIELSEN">Now I'm just old and fat. (<persName>Laughs</persName>)</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">I kind of think you could probably outrun someone.</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
