<?xml-model href="../schemas/ddhi.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Transcript of an Interview with William Franklin</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>
          <orgName>Vietnam Center and Sam Johnson Vietnam Archive</orgName>
        </authority>
        <date>
          <!--  Date of publication, e.g. for citation purposes  -->
        </date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <recordingStmt>
          <recording xml:id="primary_recording" type="video" dur-iso="01:07:35">
            <!-- https://www.digi.com/resources/documentation/digidocs/90001437-13/reference/r_iso_8601_duration_format.htm -->
            <media url="https://vva.vietnam.ttu.edu/images.php?img=/OH/OH0479/OH0479.mp4" mimeType="video/mp4"/>
          </recording>
        </recordingStmt>
        <bibl xml:id="primary_transcription">
          <respStmt>
            <persName>Mark Steven Varela</persName>
            <orgName>Vietnam Center and Sam Johnson Vietnam Archive</orgName>
            <resp ref="http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/trc.html">Transcriber</resp>
          </respStmt>
          <ref target="path_to_file">https://vva.vietnam.ttu.edu/images.php?img=/OH/OH0479/OH0479.pdf</ref>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The Oral History Project of the Vietnam Center and Sam Johnson Vietnam Archive</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application ident="DDHIEncoder" version="1.0">
          <desc>Conversion from Word docx to TEI xml.</desc>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en-us">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <particDesc>
        <person xml:id="FRANKLIN"/>
        <person xml:id="NAPOLI"/>
      </particDesc>
      <settingDesc>
        <setting>
          <date when-iso="2005-11-11"/>
          <locale/>
        </setting>
      </settingDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <u who="NAPOLI">I am Professor <persName>Philip Napoli</persName> from <orgName>Brooklyn College</orgName>. Today is <date when="2005-11-11">November 11th, 2005</date>. I'm with Mr. <persName>Franklin</persName> in a meeting room in the <placeName>Crystal City Hilton Hotel</placeName> and we are going to talk a little bit about the <name type="event">Ia Drang Valley Battle</name> and your memories of those days. I’d like you to introduce yourself, if you would.</u>
      <u who="FRANKLIN">I appreciate it. My name is <persName>Bill Franklin, William W. Franklin</persName>, I go by <persName>Bill</persName>, I prefer <persName>Bill</persName>. I was born and raised in <placeName>Miami, Florida</placeName>. Had an interest in the military in high school, had a couple of friends ahead of me one year, went to <orgName>West Point</orgName>, one of my classmates. I applied for an appointment, didn’t get it my first year of high school so I went onto <orgName>Florida State University</orgName>. Like many young men at seventeen years of age, I wasn’t sure what I was going to do with my life or what I was going to do with the military especially. I joined the <orgName>Air Force ROTC (Reserve Officer Training Corps)</orgName>. I’d been a pilot, I started flying as a senior in high school, I was already a private pilot. Had an interest in that. That’s how you think when you’re young. The <orgName>Air Force ROTC</orgName>, they raised the age—they actually raised the obligation in <date when="1956">1956</date> time frame from a three-year obligation to a five year obligation for young men, pilots, navigators, and air observers. So I said “Well,” and started looking at the <orgName>Army</orgName>. Found out they had a six month and a two year obligation for 2nd lieutenants, so I switched over from <orgName>ROTC</orgName> to the <orgName>Army</orgName> at <orgName>Florida State</orgName>. Meantime, my appointment came through to <orgName>West Point</orgName> the next year under <persName>Danny Fasele</persName>, state representative in <placeName>Florida</placeName>. I was about to go up to <placeName>West Point</placeName> that summer and I’d been going with a young lady for a couple of years in South <placeName>Florida</placeName>. I loved her, but she didn’t want to wait four years for me to go through school and then get married so I forewent my appointment to <orgName>West Point</orgName> and a friend of mine named <persName>Lander</persName> took my place and went on up. But after two years, I still wasn’t sure what I wanted to do with my life so after two years of college, I joined the <orgName>Army</orgName> on <date when="1959-01-05">5 January 1959</date>, as an enlisted man. Met my lovely wife in <date when="1959">‘59</date> while I was stationed in <placeName>Redstone Arsenal</placeName> and we dated for some fourteen months and married in <date when="1960-05">June of ’60</date>, when I was a pay grade of E-4 and I liked the service. I later went to officer candidate school, I was a sergeant E-5, actually post E-6 when I was commissioned after five and a half years of enlisted service. I was commissioned <date when="1964-06">June of ’64</date> as a 2nd lieutenant. I wanted to be an aviator eventually, we had to be in the combat arms. I was trained in guided missiles; I was out in <placeName>White Sand Missile Range</placeName> and I remember one officer wanted me to very much so to go to artillery OCS (Officer Candidate School) since the <orgName>Army</orgName> had spent so much time training on me on guided missiles. But I at the time fought that because I knew you had to be in the combat arms, infantry armor, artillery, or transportation quarter to be an aviator and that’s what I desired to do at the time. So I became a <orgName>1542 infantry</orgName> unit commander in the <orgName>2nd Infantry Division</orgName>, which later became the <orgName>1st Cavalry</orgName> division on <date when="1965-07-01">July 1, 1965</date>. I was the third platoon leader in <orgName>Charlie Company of the 1st Battalion 7th Cavalry Regiment</orgName> when we left for <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> on the <orgName>General Maurice Rose</orgName>. I believe you already interviewed <persName>Captain Bob Edwards</persName> later retired <persName>Colonel Edwards</persName>, who was my company commander at the time. So off to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> we went. Being I was married with two children, I had a son born in <date when="1961">’61</date> out in <placeName>Texas</placeName> <orgName>Beaumont Hospital</orgName> and a daughter born in <date when="1963">’63</date> in the <placeName>Redstone</placeName> area, <placeName>Huntsville, Alabama</placeName>. Being an enlisted man and older than most lieutenants by two, three, and four years, they kind of looked at me as the old man. I appreciated that, I respected that. I appreciated they were looking to me for advice from time to time. Hope I gave them some good advice. I can remember some things in. Of course, we didn’t have a lot of—we left on the <orgName>General Rose</orgName> from <placeName>Charleston, South Carolina</placeName> and spent a month of our initial tour on the ship getting to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. Being a young man that grew up in South <placeName>Florida</placeName> on the water, I loved the water, I loved to fly, and I’ve never been seasick then or now. One of my vivid recollections is a little sense of humor on the ship, there were three officers, Lieutenant <persName>Jack Geoghegan, John Lance Geoghegan</persName>, who is a good friend of mine, and <persName>Neil Kroger</persName>. We occupied one half of the cabin, shared a latrine and on the other side was three lieutenants as well. Each morning of course we got up early in the morning, did our PT (Physical Training) and then we ate at different times. I remember it going over there fed quite well because I was about a hundred and eighty pounds starting out, and I ended up a hundred and ninety pounds in that thirty days by the time we got to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, even with the PT because they fed us well. One reason—or the sense of humor comes in, they set a basket of fresh rolls, pastries like warm buns and things of that nature on the table, each one—I think there were eight of us sharing that table officers. Six or eight, I don’t recall for sure. At least six, maybe eight. We got in a typhoon around <placeName>Subic Bay</placeName>, I was officer one day of that thirty day ship tour and I go to know a lot those men on the ship and saw how the officers lived. Three to a cabin compared to the enlisted men, more like three hundred to a hole down there, stacked three or four high with their bags and weapons chained to the end of them. So we lived a lot better than they lived at that one point in time, even going over on the ship. Reminding me that I’d made a good decision going to officer candidate school at the time. (Chuckles) I remember we got in this typhoon, which like I said lasted the better part of six days. Each one I’d look around and notice there was less and less young lieutenants and captains and majors in the mess hall or in the dining area, as we called it on this MSTS ship. So I had more and more sweet rolls and rum buns to eat each morning. Finally, it came down to the last day of the typhoon, I was the only one at my table, so I could eat that whole basket of buns! I think that’s part of the reason why I gained that ten pounds on the ship. But I did find myself carrying soup and crackers back down a rolling ship and putting my arms out to catch myself with each wind, to keep from spilling soup. Taking it back to five fellow 2nd lieutenants that were all sick back in the cabin. That was one of the humorous things on the ship going over. One of the less humorous, I got up one morning when it was rolling, getting ready for PT and we had steel lockers and heavy steel drawers. I remember pulling one out to get some boot socks out and as the ship rolled, I hit my right or left ankle, I think it was my right. Pretty bad, it swelled up and I taped it up, still had to take PT. They didn’t give us any slack. I can remember that vividly. Those are the two things on the ship that I remember quite vividly. I had a young man that slipped on a stairwell when we were going through the <placeName>Panama Canal</placeName>. He’d injured his neck quite badly, not sure if it was broken or not. So I made a determination that when we were going into <placeName>San Diego</placeName>, on the way over, that we’d take him off the ship. When we got to the pier of <placeName>San Diego</placeName> in the middle of the night, they weren’t allowing anyone to leave the ship except this young man and myself. Went down to get him and he was taken over to a naval hospital ship. So I went onto this naval hospital ship and met the captain. Then, I started having second thoughts about the army, I saw how the <orgName>Navy</orgName> lived. This captain had a dining room about the size of this room on the ship with sterling silver and china, and a little Filipino waiter in a white dinner jacket serving him in the middle of the night! I said, “Well, maybe I should’ve considered the <orgName>Navy</orgName> or the <orgName>Air Force</orgName>!” (Laughs) I had some coffee with this captain and enjoyed his hospitality while my man was getting taken care of. It was daylight then, and when I got back to the ship, lo and behold as often happens in the military, they change their policy from minute to minute to hour to hour sometime. I got back and not only was there me off the ship, there was a couple hundred guys off the ship at least. There must’ve been a hundred phone booths set up on the dock. They had the phone company out and all these guys were making long distance calls. They all asked me before I left the ship, “Will you call my wife? Call my mother, call my girlfriend” I couldn’t do much in the middle of the night, no cell phones back then. I said, “I’ll try to do it if I can” and I couldn’t. I get back and I see all these guys lined up talking to their honeys and their moms and all on the phones. The phone company did a great job setting a bunch of phone booths up. Something else I remember quite well is a young man, just a twelve, fourteen year old at the oldest. Newspaper boy, selling newspapers and the ship—there was probably that much room between the ship and the dock, and the gangplank was up and probably twenty feet to the water. This kid was leaning over to get something, and he fell straight down between the ship and the water. But he came up smiling and they fished him out and got him out. So all these things happened on our way over before we even got there. I knew we were in for a good time. Digression back, I will too say something. I remember when we left <placeName>Charleston</placeName>, <persName>Jack</persName> and I—I would like to even back up a little further than that. If this is going to be recorded for a longtime, the night we left for <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, if I can digress a moment, jump back about twenty-five days. <persName>Barbara Geoghegan</persName> and my wife <persName>Sarah Franklin</persName> were good friends. <persName>Jack</persName>, they’d just had their first child and their only child. <persName>Cammie</persName> was born in <placeName>Fort Benning</placeName> and actually in a Catholic hospital there, in the early Summer of <date when="1965">’65</date> <persName>Camille</persName> was born. The night we went out, unlike in the movie We Were Soldiers, the night that we left, we didn’t stand around the jump towers and wait miraculously to get levitated out to <placeName>Kelley Hill</placeName>. We actually had carried our weapons in the trunks our cars for several days, unbeknownst to a lot of people and our gear all ready to go. We had to be at our unit at midnight. Matter of fact, we had a lot of replacements come in, some of them from <placeName>Germany</placeName>, hadn’t even been home in a couple of years. To the credit of our commanders like <persName>Captain Edwards</persName> and others, these men said, “Sir, we haven't talked to our family or seen our family.” He said, “Here’s what’s going to happen. Go to <placeName>Atlanta, Georgia</placeName> meet your family there or wherever their coming from or whatever. If you don’t come back, don’t tell them I told you and I never knew you. Go do what you have to do. Go see your family, make sure you are back at a certain day and certain hour.” Late at night, actually midnight, we all showed up at <placeName>Kelley Hill</placeName>. We were bussed, some left from various ports of around the country. <placeName>New Orleans</placeName>, some from all the way to <placeName>California</placeName>. Some by train, some by <placeName>Savannah</placeName>. We left from <placeName>Charleston</placeName> on the <orgName>General Maurice Rose</orgName>. So we bussed to <placeName>Charleston, South Carolina</placeName>. When we left, <persName>Jack</persName> and I, my wife <persName>Sarah</persName> and <persName>Jack</persName>’s wife <persName>Barbara</persName> went down to the only all-night diner on <placeName>Victory Drive</placeName> there in <placeName>Columbus</placeName>. They drank coffee and cried together because they had a babysitter for <persName>Cammie</persName> and two young ladies whose husbands were officer’s in candidate school babysat my son <persName>Mike</persName> and he was four and my daughter <persName>Kim</persName> was two at the time. So my wife had time to take us out. So that backs up the night we left for <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> in <date when="1965-08">August</date>. Then, the ship and I can really remember it quite well. I have it recorded on an old pencraft pennies reel to reel tape recorder.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">That’s great!</u>
      <u who="FRANKLIN">I recorded the <orgName>Navy</orgName> band at <placeName>Charleston</placeName> playing (Unclear audio) and you could hear the ship horns going off. I still listen to it not too long back. I bought two of them. I left one home for my wife and one for me. That’s actually how we corresponded, by tape. So I actually got to hear my daughter say a few things to me over these little tapes. But the navy band played (Unclear audio) as the ship casts off, you could hear the commands being given by the captain of another officer on the ship, you can hear the horn sounds as we left, etc. Then, I remember quite well of course we’d been having problems with <placeName>Cuba</placeName> for some time as you know. <name type="event">Bay of Pigs</name> and thereafter. I remember as we were going close to <placeName>Cuba</placeName> early in the morning through the fog of it, they had <orgName>Navy</orgName> ships escorting us and a big frigate came across our—bigger than a destroyer, you know what a frigate looks like, and it was running, looked like flank speed as it went across. Quite impressive to see it coming out of the fog. We saw some light signals going on apparently between it and other <orgName>Navy</orgName> ship. Maybe perhaps between the ship I was on. That was quite impressive. Then, going through the <placeName>Panama Canal</placeName>, I’d never been to the <placeName>Panama Canal</placeName> before. That was a feat to see coming out. On the Pacific side early in the morning and the sun coming up over by <placeName>Balboa</placeName> and the beautiful Pacific coast and seeing the whales as we went along the coast of <placeName>Mexico</placeName> and later out in the Pacific. Lots of whales. We saw a lot of whales that was quite—I’d never seen that many whales in my life, I remember that quite well. We had another man that was injured. I remember we got to <placeName>Hawaii, Honolulu</placeName>. We didn’t go in the harbor, but we anchored outside the harbor and we had a ship come out, the <orgName>Coast Guard</orgName> Cutter to take someone off the boat in <placeName>Honolulu</placeName>. I remember a <persName>Major Gill</persName>. I don’t even know—a well-built guy, had a big scar from where he’d been injured before in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, this was going to be his second tour and he wasn’t—actually with the <orgName>1st</orgName> and the <orgName>7th</orgName>, he was attached, I'm trying to remember where his position was. I knew him just slightly. But we were all looking on the ship through binoculars at this <placeName>Waikiki Beach</placeName> and <persName>Captain Edwards</persName> was leaning on the rails, <persName>Captain John Herren</persName> and myself and all of us. We were looking at the beautiful beach and I remember <persName>Major Gill</persName> saying, “I wonder how many naked women there are in those hotel rooms.” (Laughs) For that he got a good slap on the side of the head from somebody. We hadn’t even gotten halfway to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> yet and already we have these guys thinking about naked women in hotel rooms in <placeName>Honolulu</placeName>, but I think they probably think about it all the time, isn’t that right? But that’s something that stayed with me. Like I said, after that, going across the Pacific, getting into a typhoon around <placeName>Subic Bay</placeName>, prior to getting to <placeName>Subic Bay, Philippines</placeName> and getting to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. Then of course, climbing down those ladders into the LST (Landing Ship Tank) type landing craft and going ashore. Then, a big helicopter to <placeName>An Khe</placeName>, took to our basecamp, the “Golf course”.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">Can I stop you for a second?</u>
      <u who="FRANKLIN">Yes, you may.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">Can I ask you your impression of the geography and the terrain that you’re seeing for the first time.</u>
      <u who="FRANKLIN">I had done a little studying about <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. <persName>Colonel Moore</persName> was also a sticker on the ship when you had that much time going over. There were certain books he would like for his officers to have read. Of course, some of us knowing that’s where we were going to end had done a little geography homework. Then, we read a book going over, we passed around about <persName>Ho Chi Minh</persName> about the <name type="event">defeat at Dien Bien Phu</name> by the <orgName>French</orgName> in <date when="1954">’54</date>. We read a book on that, along with several other books we had briefings given by different officers to us in some small group sessions. But when I saw it for the first time, I thought it was quite nice, the shoreline and the mountains in the background over there in <placeName>Qui Nhon</placeName>. Later on, I had more of an appreciation for the beauty of the country when I got to see more even then. My first impression was positive as far as appearance of it  goes. But when you get to ashore its typical—I’d been to some other countries in the <placeName>Caribbean</placeName>, I had not been in the far east before. I had since gone back to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> and I’ll tell you about that in a little bit for a few minutes. Then, there’s certain smells and sounds that you get around in third world countries that you haven’t experienced before. When you get around people there, they see the sights, the animals, the people. They are certain smells and sounds that come back to even now and later on I got a chance to go down to <placeName>Saigon</placeName>, I’ll tell you about that in a moment. We were flown in to <placeName>An Khe</placeName>. Of course, we had the green light, the inner perimeter. One impression you get is you see not hundreds, but thousands of Vietnam civilians coming by you every morning as they pass by in line, they were the workers that were working within the basecamp. Then, they all had supervisors that wore a little string around their button hanging down to denote they were a leader of a certain size group. A young 2nd lieutenant would go out as a pay officer and pay them at the end of the day for their work. What was interesting—we knew that of course our base camp was all around this huge mountain we called <placeName>Hong Kong Mountain</placeName>. Stood up right in the middle like a volcano you might say. We didn’t know until later that right within the perimeter of our camp was quite a few <orgName>Vietcong</orgName> living within that mountain and watching us each day because we later on we had a pretty serious fire fight with them. But we had an inner perimeter and an outer perimeter. Of course, these people would work each day clearing off this field of fire for us. But when they’d leave in the evening, which they took a couple of hours to leave just like it took a couple hours to get in the morning, you could take your crew-served weapons and you would reposition your machine guns. For example, you could walk down and get below the terrain and you could walk along and you could see where they’d taken bark. They’d marked trees, they’d taken bark off trees and laid it down to where it would be reflective at night you can—being smaller people for the most part than us, they can either walk almost upright or in a crouched position and they would be below the contour of the terrain. They would be masked from view by the terrain from somebody trying to observe them from up range to down range. But they would have arrows pointed. These notched on trees, they’d take arrows pointed to where your machine guns were. For example, where the platoon leaders CP (Command Post) or his foxhole was. His little command post or foxhole. You can shuffle your men around, move your claymores around. They did this every day. You knew somebody was doing something when they came into your base camp working because you knew that a certain percent of these people were <orgName>Vietcong</orgName> in all probability. So that was something we had with them, even within the inner perimeter. We lived in a jeep—the five officers, it was actually six initially but the fight officers at the time, we lived in a GP (General Purpose) tent, we had it much better than the enlisted men once again because they lived in two prong shelters put together in a form of a tent. If you went off in a patrol and you came back and you had a lot of rain on the side of the hillside where we were, you would find all your gear washed down the hillside into a ravine below and it was sorting it out, cleaning it up and putting the house back in order again. But the officers, we had a general-purpose tent, we stored communication gear, food and ammo. We were able to corner our areas off in a little match and little private area where we had a wooden footlocker and a cot. When you were back in the basecamp, we had like I said, once again the RHIP (Rank Has Its Privilege), you had a little extra facility that the average enlisted men had to live in. We went out fairly constantly on patrols. I can remember—unfortunately we had accidents, incidents. <persName>Jack Geoghegan</persName>’s platoon lost a man in a river crossing, the <placeName>Son Ba River</placeName> there. Drowned in a river crossing one night. We had a mortar platoon that fired in avertedly some mortar rounds. The division had built a shower point down in <placeName>Son Ba River</placeName>. Once a week we got a shower, we were back in the basecamp. It was kind of a futile effort because by the time you went down the road in a vehicle to the shower point, put your weapon in a weapon rack, take you a good shower, got back in a clean set of fatigues and you were covered with dust by the time you got back to where your particular area in the basecamp was. That was your routine. When you’re out in the field, you can get a—the battalion surgeon, <persName>Dr. Correa</persName> told us that, “Guys, critically places to bathe is under your arms, your crotch and between your toes. If you keep that part of your body clean, you’ll do pretty good!” Of course, <persName>Colonel Moore</persName> was a stickler as was <persName>Captain Edwards</persName> and I, we all shaved every day. We all had these little boy scout mirrors. The army didn’t have good mirrors so being a good GI, we bought the boy scout reflective mirror, you know. You could bend it; you can put it in a pouch and it would make a survival mirror if you need it. You could bend it back out, if you needed to use it as a reflective device. But you can hang that rascal up and you can shave by it in a helmet. So that’s what we did. We shaved every morning, we washed underarms, crotch, in between the toes. When we got an opportunity, sometimes out in the field we’d get into some streams and  put some guards in each side of the stream, up and down the stream. Like the old <placeName>Texas</placeName> saying, “Make sure you drink up stream of the herd.” We had our pills to put in our canteens to purify our water and we could usually find some water in a field like that and a place to get rinsed off if need be. So we’d squeeze in another bath now and then, when the opportunity presented itself in the right location. But we did go out as companies, the old search and destroy concept back then. A little different now. Take a company of three rifle platoons, put one in one area, one in another, one in another, the company commander back in another location and hopefully which ever one engages the enemy first, the others would be in range to where they could support you or at least be in range of supporting fire by your artillery, mortar artillery. It was a search and destroy mission, trying to find the enemy, flush them out and hope they’d engage you. The critical part—we had a lot of learning curve. I was a fixed wing pilot at the time, but not a helicopter pilot yet. But I knew enough of weight and balance and I was not yet a flight instructor, but later became one. At that time I knew enough of weight and balance that an aircraft could only hold so much. We even had some officers that had to get educated, that they could see an empty hole there in a helicopter and think you could fill it up to where there was no more empty space. They even realized what a hit check was to try to see if it could hover, what the density altitude was, to see if you could lift that kind of load. Even with a rifle squad, when you take at least twenty-one choppers to move Hueys, we had B, C, and D model Hueys back then. Didn’t have the Cobras for gunships then, they came in <date when="1967">’67</date>. We had a modified Huey with M60s and 20 millimeters on it and 2.75 rockets on it that we used for gunships. By the time they’d take the slick, as we called it, and they’d tried to fill up any space on it, these young pilots had to educate these other officers quick like this, “Sir, we can’t carry that, they might put it on one side, and fall out the other side” Whatever it takes guys for us to get off the ground. We always designated a bump man. Unfortunately, it meant disrupting your squad and platoon integrity, but if you had a hundreds helicopters come in and start to move a couple of three, which had been in operation before, we had a hundred on the ground running at one time, moving say three companies of men or more. They’d be more than one of those helicopters that would need to have somebody to get off. So what—you’d have an empty ship or two in the back and a man designated as a bump man and those squad leaders and fire team leaders had a man, each man knew who he was and they would just point to him and he knew to get out of the aircraft to go back of the formation. So you then had a composite squad made up of not necessarily strangers, but guys that didn’t know each other very well. That was a disadvantage of that, but that’s the only choice you had. We also know that when you extract people out of an LZ (Landing Zone) and go to put them in another LZ that there’s this critical element of going back and forth. By the time you put men on the ground, boots on the ground, you go back and get some more replacements, get them back on the ground. That’s when the guys are really hanging out by themselves in a small unit operations, waiting for their own reinforcements to come with the rest of their platoon or company to get in. That’s the way we operated.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">But you learned most of this stuff back in <placeName>Benning</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="FRANKLIN">At <placeName>Benning</placeName>? Yeah, at airmobile tactics. That’s right, a lot of guys had the advantage of training together for as much as two years. We got a lot of replacements in, right towards the end, and like I was saying, some of them came in, both enlisted men and officers. We had one brigade that needed to be filled up, the <orgName>1st Brigade Airborne</orgName> and  we had a lot of officers that were not airborne qualified that needed to go. We brought in guys from the <orgName>101st</orgName>, the <orgName>82nd</orgName>. We ran a two-week jump school instead of three week to get as many guys airborne qualified as we could to fill up that <orgName>1st Brigade</orgName>. I was at the time a member of the <orgName>3rd Brigade</orgName>, which was <persName>Colonel Brown</persName>, our brigade commander and of course <persName>Lieutenant Colonel Moore</persName> was our battalion commander of <orgName>1st of the 7th</orgName>. We trained and that was what <persName>Colonel Moore</persName> was upset about, losing a lot of these men today. There’s one here, <persName>Bill Carson</persName>, a lieutenant. <persName>Tom Mitchell</persName> was going to try to make it this time, <persName>Tom</persName> couldn’t. <persName>Tom</persName> was a <orgName>Georgia Tech</orgName> grad, <persName>Bill Carson</persName> was a <orgName>Clemson</orgName> grad, lot of these guys were on a two-year OBV (Obligated Volunteer) like I initially talked about, rather than a three or five. Their obligation was up early that summer, <date when="1965-06">June</date> and <date when="1965-07">July</date>. So we had a lot of 2nd lieutenants and 1st lieutenants who had fulfilled their two year OBV and had left the service. Of course, <persName>General Moore</persName> and <persName>General Kinnard</persName>, a lot of people preferred that they extend that. I can remember as enlisted man back in <date when="1962">’62</date>, late <date when="1961">’61</date>, early <date when="1962">’62</date>, we were having problems with the <orgName>Russians</orgName>. We extended the <orgName>armed forces</orgName> a blanket six month period, just whatever your obligation was, three years, it was six months. As things cooled down with the <orgName>Russians</orgName>, they began these young men out because they weren’t many women then, it was mainly men so they let them out and most of them didn’t stay six, they stayed four, three, two. Nevertheless, when they did that, the <orgName>Russians</orgName> got their attentions and were serious about this and they backed off. I think if we had extended the <orgName>arms forces</orgName> at the time, call up the <orgName>reserves</orgName> or something and made a real—they would have made a real impact on the <orgName>North Vietnamese</orgName> and the rest of the world and the American people that we were serious about what we were doing. And to the other GIs that had put all this effort into it and say, “Hey, we’re going to see this thing through, we’re going to get started right.” But they didn’t do that, so there was some criticism that the thing that should’ve happened was that they should’ve extended the <orgName>military</orgName> and kept those guys that were trained onboard for a while longer. Some of them wanted to go, they had mixed emotions. If you talked to them, they told me they had mixed emotions about where they stay in, going indefinite, they’d said, “Well, I should reenlist.” They really wanted to stay. They were torn between going back to the civilian or staying in the <orgName>military</orgName>. But anyhow, that’s the way we operated. Basically in the <placeName>States</placeName>, we trained a lot and we kept training. In <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, I can remember now—I look at what they got now, I was taken out of patrol one night, to go on a night ambush and we taped our dog tags and now they’ve got these plastic things that go over and rubberize. We did all these things, we’d tape all over everything that would rattle and you walked in front of each man and you jump up and down, make sure he didn’t rattle. Now they got a lot better equipment than we once had then. They’ve got specialized devices that they put their dog togs in and whatever else to keep it from rattling. It would be a snap link, it could be cover with a rubber material. But technology has come a long way, even little simple things like that. <name type="event">This war</name> now that we’re in at <placeName>Iraq</placeName> is quite a different war. Anyhow, talking about getting up to the <name type="event">Ia Drang</name>. I had my twenty-sixth birthday in <date when="1965-10">October of ’65</date>. I remember <persName>Lieutenant Kroger</persName>’s birthday was close to mine in <date when="1965-10">October</date>, he was younger than I by a couple of years. <persName>Lieutenant Geoghegan</persName>’s birthday was in <date when="1965-11">November</date>, not even a week before we went into <placeName>LZ X-Ray</placeName>. The <placeName>Plei Me Special Forces camp</placeName> had been under siege for several weeks. <persName>Captain Moore</persName> had an A Team there. I later was in <orgName>special forces</orgName> A team myself. At this time I was assigned—my platoon was assigned to the <placeName>Plei Me Special Forces camp</placeName>. I was actually in the <placeName>camp</placeName> and at the <placeName>camp</placeName> on the <date when="1965-11-13">13th of November of ’65</date> and word was sent to me to gather in the <placeName>camp</placeName> and come to a rally point, which I did and that’s the first time I did not see <persName>Lieutenant Geoghegan</persName> or <persName>Lieutenant Kroger</persName> in several days because their platoons were in different areas. We were all put back together. We were given a frag order, a rather abbreviated fragmentary order as to what was going to take place the next day, which would’ve been <date when="1965-11-14">Sunday the 14th</date>. I remember <persName>Jack</persName> and I celebrated his birthday with Kool-Aid, which my wife had sent in the boonies there. His wife <persName>Barbara</persName> had bought me a lightweight green ski jacket that she had sent me but I never got! It never got to me, somebody else was wearing it. But <persName>Barbara</persName> was kind enough to buy it, it was very lightweight with a hood, the jacket had one. I had admired it and <persName>Jack</persName> told <persName>Barbara</persName>, <persName>Barbara</persName> bought me one and put it in the mail. Anyhow, <persName>Jack</persName> and I celebrated his birthday with some Kool-Aid in the boonies that night. We all got together then, spread out with our platoons after we got together. Then Sunday morning, <date when="1965-11-14">the 14th</date> is of course when we began our air assault into <placeName>LZ X-Ray</placeName>. I had—it was my RTOs (Radio Telephone Operator), who I think a lot of then and still do now, <persName>Charles Dashner</persName>. <persName>Charlie</persName> is here today with his wife and one of his daughters and couple of grandsons. But <persName>Charlie</persName>’s 21st birthday was <date when="1965-11-14">November the 14th</date>. After we Air Assaulted into <placeName>X-Ray</placeName> and made our way—my platoon and my company, <orgName>Charlie Company</orgName> was given the direction to secure facing the <placeName>Chu Pong Mountain</placeName> to the west. The aircraft came in traditionally and landed there from south to north in the LZ they had. The Montagnards that lived in the area, the mountain folks there. The “Moi”, as the Vietnamese call them rather insultingly, or savages. Moi or savage. But the Montagnard are fine people and I had the privilege of being in one of their Montagnard villages with <persName>Joe Galloway</persName> and my company. Spent a night in one, one time. But they’d cleared off an area there for us later on, we’ll get that in a moment. But this time this was a hot LZ and we came into it, we moved into the tall elephant grass toward the west, toward the <placeName>Chu Pong</placeName> and then of course immediately we were engaged. I remember being behind a tree with RTO, on a very short lease as they all are next to me and we were getting quite a sniper fire from trees out front. I used a lot of M72 and was able to take a couple out of the top of a large tree. About that time, <persName>Charlie Dashner</persName> got shot through the chest on his 21st birthday. The exit wound came out below the radio and it was quite large. I remember a lot of his inners were coming out of that hole and I got big hands so I able to push it back in the hole, put my hand over his back and get a medic over to take care of him. <persName>Charlie</persName> was medevac’d out and went to <placeName>Walter Reed</placeName>, eventually in <placeName>Washington</placeName> where I later joined him for a few months but <persName>Charles Dasher</persName> was his name, fine young man. I was given another radio operator, I’m ashamed to say I can’t remember his name, I think it was Testa. There was a Testa that was assigned to my platoon the last minute and he was KIA (Killed In Action) on <date when="1965-11-15">the 15th</date>, I’ll tell you more about that in a moment.  We’ll get to that in a moment, but we fought the afternoon on the <date when="1965-11-14">14th</date> and night of the <date> when="1965-11-14">14th</date>, it quieted down, sporadically during the night, there was fire. We tried to keep our movement to a minimum, did some checking on the troops. <persName>Sergeant Charles Freeman</persName> was my platoon sergeant and quite a guy. <persName>Charles</persName> was a big heavy set man, big tattoos on his arms back when they were popular to have. Liked him bit a little bit, <persName>Charles</persName> is buried in <placeName>Jacksonville, Florida</placeName>. He died a few years ago. But <persName>Sergeant Freeman</persName>, I will never forget when I became a platoon leader he said, “Sir, you command a platoon, I'm going to run the platoon.” I said, “That’s okay with me, <persName>Sergeant Freeman</persName>, as long you run it the way it’s supposed to be run, I have no problem with that.” He was a good platoon sergeant. Being a former enlisted man and had a little more wisdom than others, I had the wisdom of letting him run the platoon because he did a great job. But he was a big man. I can remember on patrol before he got into X-Ray, humping through the boonies and I was back down to a hundred and eighty and then about a hundred and seventy-five pounds then, just lean and pretty good shape. He’d be in the back and I’d be in the front. He tried to get me to slow down, I kid him about not being able to keep up. But he did a good job for a big man as he was. He was quite large around the waist line, he could have been a great Santa Claus. But the man did a great job at his age, looking back hindsight it’s always twenty-twenty, I wished I had cut him some more slack sometimes, but he was able to keep up. But <persName>Sergeant Freeman</persName> did a great job in the <name type="event">Ia Drang</name> and keeping these guys alive. On the morning of the <date when="1965-11-15">15th</date>, like I said we got probed fairly often on the night of the <date when="1965-11-14">14th</date>, but the morning of the <date when="1965-11-15">15th</date>, <persName>Colonel Moore</persName> didn’t even know I went out until I sat it in a hotel room with him in <date when="1997">1997</date>, in <placeName>San Francisco</placeName> and told him. They called and asked us to sweep early in the morning. They asked each platoon leader what happened the night before, to bring you up to date. We had the <orgName>2nd Platoon</orgName>, <orgName>1st Platoon</orgName>, and <orgName>3rd Platoon</orgName>, we were on line and facing <placeName>Chu Pong</placeName>. After hours, the movie depicts somebody bringing them in, but actually I’m the one that brought them in. <persName>Jim Lane</persName> from <orgName>B Company</orgName>, <orgName>2nd of the 7th Cav</orgName> was brought in after dark as reinforcements. So <persName>Captain Edwards</persName> sent me back to the battalion CP with <persName>Colonel Moore</persName>, person to get me, <persName>Lieutenant Lane</persName>, and his platoon and I led them in between myself and <persName>Joe Marm</persName>. The dry creek bed was on my right, and <persName>Joe</persName> had already been wounded on Saturday—Sunday the <date when="1965-11-14">14th</date> and I didn’t know that at the time because again, you worry about what’s going on fifteen, twenty meters to your left and right. You’re in tall elephant grass and you’re in woods. You got ant hills all around you and enemy around you, so you don’t know what’s going on around much further than your left and right and what you find out and hear on your radio. Some word of mouth gets to you by snail mail, some guy crawling up and telling you what’s happening. I put <persName>Lieutenant Lane</persName> between myself, on my right flank which enabled us to—we had men spread out fifteen, twenty meters trying to cover that area in tall elephant grass. But we were grateful when <persName>Jim Lane</persName> came in that night. So I put <persName>Jim</persName> between me and <persName>Joe Marm's</persName> platoon on his right flank. So we had four platoons on line on the night of the <date when="1965-11-14">14th</date> and the morning of the <date when="1965-11-15">15th</date>. The word came for us to sweep out in front of our position. So each one of us platoon leaders took a squad and we went in an echelon right. Of course, way to my left was <persName>Lieutenant Kroger</persName>. Then <persName>Lieutenant Geoghegan</persName>, myself and <persName>Lieutenant Lane</persName>. So we were actually in a echelon right formation, sweeping out through the trees trying to get any guys in, snipers out, and any guys that might’ve infiltrated early in the morning. All of the sudden, all heck broke loose to my left front and that’s when they started their attack. They just popped out of the elephant grass and they were in full North Vietnamese uniforms, well camouflaged, and running towards us with AK-47. I lost one man on the way back as we were ordered to throw smoke to mark our line. I threw a purple smoke and began to fight our way back to our line, I lost one man in that fight back. Each one of us got back to our platoons, the platoon leaders did intact. Of course, that was the beginning of the initial assault on the morning of the 15th. But I can still see these guys because you can hit them with a M16— we’d just gotten our M16, we had M14, we’d only gotten our M16 a few weeks before we left for <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. We’d gone to the range and qualify our weapons. The M16 gave us some problems and issues. Extracting, jamming. The old .45 I carried was one thing, but the M16 was another. It was a good weapon, lightweight, but still had some improvements to be made and made multiple improvements on it over the next few years. The time you could hit these guys with these things and they just keep coming. We found out later on that some of them were on dope. You know, they had pouches and they’d gotten all doped up. I'm sure that’s what kept some of them going. But you know that you hit them because you’d see a big piece of their uniform and body fly before they would go down. But <persName>Captain Edwards</persName>, as it got worse in the morning, <persName>Bob Edwards</persName> was to my left. There was a machine gun behind an anthill, it was straight in front of <persName>Bob’s</persName> prone shelter. We didn’t have time to dig foxholes, we all dug two-man prone shelters. I was back behind one of them, <persName>Sergeant Freeman</persName> was to my right. I was to my left closer toward the company commander CP. But at the time I didn’t know <persName>Lieutenant Geoghegan</persName> had already been killed and <persName>Lieutenant Kroger</persName> had already been killed. I was a senior lieutenant and at the time I was going to be promoted to 1st before too long. They called for me to come and take the company. I didn’t realize how bad <persName>Captain Edwards</persName> had been shot. I was moving, I took a <persName>Sergeant Jeremiah Jivens</persName> was with me, <persName>Jerry Jivens</persName> we called him. Big, burly, Black NCO (Non-Commissioned Officer) that if you ever saw <persName>Sonny Liston</persName>, <persName>Sergeant Jivens</persName> little friendlier face but was built like him. He was just a real big solid built strong Black man, who had been in <name type="event">the Korea War</name>. <persName>Jerry</persName> had been frostbitten really bad during <name type="event">Korea</name> on his feet. I remember a couple of times—reason why in the movie, We Were Soldiers comes back to show <persName>Jack Geoghegan</persName> checking the young man’s feet. I remember checking <persName>Jerry’s</persName> feet at a time or two because I didn’t realize how bad they were and he had his socks off one day and between his toes was all rotten looking because he had gotten—we had these old corporate type military jump boots or old black combat boots. We didn’t even have the jungle boots at the time. They just got a brand new pair and in six weeks they get in bad shape. Reason why I was a little angry about that, I was sent earlier in the operation before <name type="event">Ia Drang</name>, I was sent to spend one week with <orgName>the 101st Airborne Division</orgName> and <persName>Lieutenant Kroger</persName> spent a week with <orgName>the 173rd Airborne Brigade</orgName> and we were doing some cross training with each other. I was out on patrol with <persName>Lieutenant Ken Eklund</persName>, a <orgName>West Point</orgName> graduate from the <orgName>101st</orgName>, we’d been out all night, got back in early morning on my 5th day and I got word to terminate my attachment early and get back to the base camp at An Khe. What happened when I got back—the first soldier I had killed in my platoon was a specialist <persName>Romanco</persName> from <placeName>Pennsylvania</placeName>. It was friendly fire, something like the <persName>Tilman</persName> situation. I got back and found out that during the night, the way our foxholes were traced along the green line there at the base camp, the Golf Course, some were down in front, some were back, some were down front. It was foggy and what I found out in an investigation when I got back, that one of our—<persName>Sergeant Calloway</persName>, who happened to be a fine, young, black, NCO buck sergeant, who had another gentleman with him, one of our E4s I believe—and then <persName>Romanco</persName> who was also E4, they were reliving in place. <persName>Sergeant Calloway</persName> was reliving in place, one man to each foxhole. They were coming through the fog, they were out in front of the perimeter. They’d left one gentleman by himself in the foxhole. They were approaching, and the gentleman in the foxhole they were approaching, opened up on them and it killed <persName>Specialist Romanco</persName>. I believe that story, I returned to camp, of course they didn’t find any fault with me, of course they talked to all the men, they found out they had all been trained properly. We had a procedure that they were supposed to follow, and the procedure wasn’t followed like it should’ve been. <persName>Sergeant Freeman</persName> was not in any trouble because of it or any of the NCOs or anything. But there was an unfortunate thing to happened. The young man was transferred for his benefit to an assault helicopter squadron and became a door gunner on a helicopter at his request. I say that to say this, <persName>Sergeant Calloway</persName>, the NCO I described, myself, my first trip to <placeName>Saigon</placeName>, back then, we were all operating under <orgName>MACV</orgName> circular number 1, which was fine when you had one advisor killed every few weeks, months, or a year. But what that required was that they had a funeral at their chapter number 1 at <placeName>Tan Son Nhut</placeName>. <orgName>The Vietnamese army</orgName> would present some medals to him, drape a flag on a coffin, have a funeral there and then send his body back home. That was fine when you were losing one now and then as an advisor but all of the sudden in that—later on that came back to bite us because when you lose 225 to 300 men in a couple of weeks’ time, still that circle had to be found and be rescinded. But at the time it took me, <persName>Sergeant Calloway</persName> and five enlisted men out of the field. We had to bum a ride from <placeName>An Khe</placeName> to <placeName>Qui Nhon</placeName>, to <placeName>Tan Son Nhut</placeName>. Got in there late at night, had to go—first of all had to go to a morgue, which was a little air conditioned office and then went into a room that was not airconditioned. Nineteen marines had been killed in an ambush, their bodies laying all over the floor with tags on their toes. Then, back in the refrigerator that was air conditioned, to identify <persName>Romanco’s</persName> body. The guys hadn’t eaten all day, late at night and then after I took <persName>Sergeant Calloway</persName> with me, we did that. Took the rest of the guys down, trying to find a chow hall about 22:00 hours at night, find something to eat. Finally we found a mess sergeant and let us sit in the back. We got some milk and a baloney sandwich and that sort of thing, it carried us over to the next day. It took us out of the field and that day—the next day we all had to bring khaki uniforms out of the bottom of duffle bags and tried to get them looking good. Mooch piles and ration piles we go down there. We go to the funeral there at chapel number one. We give him a sendoff. I’ll never forget seeing his big long tin sheds just coffin after coffin, lined up under these tin sheds there waiting to be used, these were empty coffins. This was in <date when="1965">’65</date>. So we got him taken care of there and then we had to hitch a ride back, and I’m on a C123 coming down. Going back I went on a Caribou, coming down I was on a C123 with <orgName>Air Force</orgName> crew and I happened to know the co-pilot, a friend of mine, it’s a small world. Anyhow, they had a bunch of fruit in the back and we broke into the crates and did get some fruit. I left that part out, but we did have some fruit on the way down to start with and then we got the sandwich later that night. On the way back we went on Caribou number 1, the first army <persName>Caribou</persName> that was assigned to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. We flew back to <placeName>Tan Son Nhut</placeName> and then from <placeName>Tan Son Nhut</placeName> back to <placeName>Qui Nhon</placeName>. While I was at <placeName>Qui Nhon</placeName> I was standing on the airfield there, I’m talking to neat looking little trim guy, about 5’6, major in an A1E Skyraider. He’s standing there talking to me, fifty-two years old, was back on flying status. <orgName>The Air Force</orgName> put everybody flying behind a desk at about forty-two years old back then, but when <name type="event">the Vietnam War</name> started getting cranked up they let the guys that could pass a flight physical and wanted to fly back on flying status, and he was fifty-two years old and flying an A1E Skyraider. Later on these Skyraiders had a big impact in helping us in the <placeName>Ia Drang Valley</placeName>. I was impressed with him and his physique and how excited he was about being back in the cockpit again, being a pilot myself. So I finally got my guys back to <placeName>Qui Nhon</placeName>, from <placeName>Qui Nhon</placeName> to <placeName>An Khe</placeName>, <placeName>An Tuc</placeName> to the base camp. Then, coming back to that, I’d mentioned <persName>Romanco</persName> was the first one we had killed. Then, the morning of the <date when="1965-11-15">15th</date>, when they called me to come and take over the company, I was moving from my right to left and this dead blade machine gun. I was crouched low and moved as best as I could, my knees and hands. Machine gun opened up on us, killed this young man radio operator. Hit the first two rounds—the first two I got hit with, it hit me on my right side, killed <persName>Sergeant Jivens</persName>. Hit <persName>Sergeant Jivens</persName> in the chest, but when <persName>Jivens</persName> went down, I’ll never forget—see, I was born in <placeName>Lima, Florida</placeName>. I grew up in a segregated time and never went to school with any black kids, high school or college. My first experience with good black friends was in the service, but I remember <persName>Sergeant Jivens</persName> asked me months back, “Sir, are you prejudiced?” And I said—we had dust all over us one time, kind of white chalky dust. I looked at him and said, “Jerry, you look like a white man to me anyhow. So why would I be prejudiced?” We joked and I’ll never forget he was down in the grass and he started calling for me and then, he stopped calling. But <persName>Sergeant Jivens</persName> was killed and this other gentleman, I believe his name was Testa, I can’t swear to that, the radio operator. I was in pretty bad shape, but I was able to get on the radio and I was almost to <persName>Captain Edwards</persName> positions and I don’t even remember who took out the machine gun behind the hill, it wasn’t me. We were still just trying to stay alive, fighting a little bit. I was on the radio talking and on my left side a sniper hit me from a tree up above, right through the center of my abdomen. That was the second time I got shot—the third one. After that I wasn’t worth much. (Chuckles) I do remember some of my guys driving me on a poncho liner across—I do remember looking back one time before I was out of it, seeing about twenty <orgName>North Vietnamese</orgName> soldiers running between me and towards the termite hill where the battalion CP was. Had to be careful shooting in the backs of them and that’s probably what you see in the film, a lot of these rounds coming into the battalion CP, some of them could’ve been friendly rounds for all I know. I remember being dragged on a poncho liner across the LZ, bouncing my bottom off the ground there, bouncing the corners of it. After I got in the LZ, I was triaged—I didn’t know this, but <persName>Sergeant Keaton</persName> was a senior medic and doctor battalion sergeant, said I wouldn’t survive and they put me over behind that ant hill with a bunch of guys in dead body bags and I didn’t know until the book came out in <date when="1992">’92</date> that—even talking with <persName>Sergeant Keaton</persName> at <placeName>Benning</placeName>, I didn’t realize they triaged me as unlikely to survive. I didn’t realize and later on <persName>Captain Dillon</persName> was the reason I got out, <persName>Matt Dillon</persName>. I’m laying over amongst these body bags—I saw a picture of myself at <placeName>Fort Benning</placeName> about <date when="1995">’95</date> or so in black and white, on the ground. I was unconscious at the time and a bunch of guys where dead around me there, some of them already in bags. I was there in that picture. But when I end up being medevac’d out of there, I was thrown in on top of <persName>Bob Edwards</persName> on the helicopter as they were taking me out to take me back to <placeName>LZ Falcon</placeName>. My chaplain, <persName>Neven Schneider</persName>, our battalion chaplain <orgName>1st of the 7th</orgName>, was an airborne chaplain, quite a guy. <persName>Neven</persName> lives about a couple miles from me in <placeName>Melbourne, Florida</placeName>. He’s been there since <date when="1993">’93</date>, I’ve been there since <date when="1998">’88</date>. We have breakfast about once a week together on Thursday mornings after our military officer’s association meeting. But <persName>chaplain Schneider</persName> was back at <placeName>LZ Falcon</placeName> and I remember <persName>Sergeant Gray</persName>, one of my sergeants that was supposed to be on R&amp;R (Rest and Recuperation), he was back at the base camp and lo and behold they had brought him to—they actually brought him to <placeName>Camp Holloway</placeName>, I think. Then, I was moved from <placeName>Falcon</placeName> to <placeName>Holloway</placeName> and they had a Charlie med set up at <orgName>Holloway</orgName> and it’s the first time they had ever given four units of whole blood to guys. Some of the guys were given four units of whole blood that—I lost, I was told, eleven pints of blood. I was getting four units of whole blood, one on each leg and one on each arm. Kind of put your body into shock but gets your blood pressure back up. Then, I was medevac’d over to <placeName>Qui Nhon</placeName> to <placeName>85th Medevac Hospital</placeName>. <persName>General Westmorland</persName>, I remember him coming to see me there and putting a purple heart on me. I remember <persName>Sergeant Brooks, Al Brooks</persName>, who again, fine NCO company clerk, had a smile wide as can be, all teeth. Put a helmet on and all you would see teeth. All you’d see was a black face and all these white teeth. Reason why I say that, <persName>Sergeant Brooks</persName> came over to see me. He’s the first one that told me about <persName>Lieutenant Geoghegan</persName> and <persName>Lieutenant Kroger</persName> being killed, and <persName>Sergeant Jivens</persName> and some of the other guys. When it came time to medevac me to <placeName>the States</placeName>, a C130 came in from <placeName>Clark</placeName> in the <placeName>Philippines</placeName> and I was the worst of the American wounded. There was two Koreans that had been hit by an RPG (rocket-propelled grenade), they were driving a fuel truck for the <orgName>20th Division</orgName>, they blew up and they were just burnt from head to toe. So they loaded all the Americans on the aircraft and then they put me on last. In the middle they put these two rocks on each side of them and their arms were just out and they were crisp as we were taxing on that PSB. I couldn’t see how they could survive. They had a full colonel, <orgName>Air Force</orgName> doctor and an <orgName>Air Force</orgName> captain with us in the back of the aircraft. When we got into <persName>Clark</persName>, I remember being put on an ambulance. I saw the three ambulances and I saw a big bus with a red light on and the walking wounded, got on a bus and the two rocks and myself were each put on an ambulance and taken to the hospital at <placeName>Clark</placeName>. Lo and behold I’m put in a room with <persName>Lieutenant John Hanlon</persName>. <persName>John</persName> was from <orgName>the 2nd of the 12th</orgName>. He was here at the reunion last year. I went all these years without seeing <persName>John</persName> from <placeName>Walter Reed</placeName>. I saw him there at <placeName>Clark</placeName> and he and I are on the bed. One policy <orgName>the military</orgName> had then, that I opposed, as an officer we had to buy our uniforms and do this and that, that’s fine I had no complaints for that, but also we’re supposed to pay for our meals on route. I’m naked now at this time, I had a brace on my knees and a big towel rolled up under my testicles and I’m all black and blue because a grenade had come in as well and right in front of my left eye. I had some burns and I’m in this hospital bed, <persName>Lieutenant Hanlon’s</persName> paralyzed from the chest down from a round through the chest, he was a platoon leader. We’re both laying up in there and this slick looking <orgName>Air Force</orgName> NCO comes in and I mean all dressed spit shine and Corfam shoes, clipboard and he wanted the meal money, a dollar and fifty-five cents for <persName>Lieutenant Hanlon</persName> and myself for a meal at <placeName>Clark</placeName>, which I don’t even remember eating, much less getting before they could put us on the aircraft to take us to <placeName>Tachikawa, Japan</placeName>. Before I could say anything <persName>Lieutenant Hanlon</persName> said, “You son of a bitch.” And he took a shoe and he threw it at that NCO and he had several stripes down his arm, I don’t remember now, he was probably an E6, an E7. He turned and went out of the room after <persName>John</persName> threw that shoe at him. We got put on the aircraft and we went to <placeName>Tachikawa</placeName>, <placeName>Japan</placeName>. There was snow on the ground. I remember they were carrying my litter down and they dropped one corner of it down. I had IV bottles coming out, I had tubes come out of my stomach, my IV bottle. They dropped one corner of my litter on the ground but I was looking at the snow and I remember I didn’t get upset about it. I remember when they put me on the aircraft C141 after staying in <placeName>Tachikawa</placeName> a couple of days to come to <placeName>California</placeName>. I’ll never forget this <orgName>Air Force</orgName> nurse captain; she had a face that looked like a pizza pie. She had to have had acne so bad when she was young that, bless her heart, she was old enough it looked like to be my mother and still a captain. She was the prettiest thing I saw there for a while. You know, the closest contact I’d had with a female. She pulls the sheet back and like I said I got this brace and this towel rolled up. She said, “What the hell happened to you lieutenant?” And I said, “It’s a long story captain.” She didn’t have time to hear it she just pulled the sheet back up. She just laughed, but she was a good ol’ gal and she helped take care of me across the pond there. Then, the night I got in <placeName>the States</placeName>, to show you what a small world it is, I was a—a Baptist chaplain named <persName>Captain Dale Burton</persName>, was a chaplain at the <placeName>85th Medevac Hospital</placeName> and he’d written my wife a long letter. Of course, my wife knows my sloppy handwriting and <persName>Chaplain Burton</persName> had a very nice handwriting. He wrote like six, seven pages and then at the end he wrote on there, explaining who he was as a P.S. Well, he put the letter in the mail. My wife the day she gets the letter—I’d gone to <placeName>California</placeName> and the guy in <placeName>California</placeName> was <persName>Sergeant John Rangel</persName>, who is here now. <persName>John</persName> was with <persName>Joe Marm</persName>, he got his Medal of Honor. <persName>John</persName> and I had a room together in <placeName>California</placeName> and we told each other goodbye, gave each other a little embrace as we were leaving and I was put on an old C54, then a four engine. Do you guys know what a C54 is? A little four engine prop job that the airlines flew then, DC6s, DC7 type aircraft. I was flown a long day and I ended up in <placeName>Scott Air Force</placeName> base in <placeName>O’Fallon, Illinois</placeName>. I’m being brought into the room to be cleaned up, a big room in <orgName>Scott</orgName> and a <persName>Major Larry Hess</persName> comes walking through with his wife. That was <persName>Lieutenant Larry Hess</persName>’, who was killed in <name type="event">Ia Drang</name>, dad who was an <orgName>Air Force</orgName> pilot at <persName>Scott</persName>. He asked, “Did anybody know <persName>Lieutenant Larry Hess</persName>?” They’d already gotten word that their son had been killed and—I and a couple others did know <persName>Larry</persName>. So they came over to speak to me, got my name, phone number and everything, where my wife was living <placeName>Guntersville, Alabama</placeName> with her family home, with my two children. He said, “I’ll call your wife.” And he went home that night and my wife had gotten the letter that day. She was all upset, she’d been on the phone trying to find out where I was. When <persName>Lieutenant Hess</persName> and <persName>Mrs. Hess</persName> called to tell her, “We just left your husband at <placeName>O’Fallon Air Force Base</placeName>. He’s on his way to <persName>Walter Reed</persName> tomorrow. That’s where he’ll be and that’s where you can find him.” So she found out, not form the department army about where I was, but from an <orgName>Air Force</orgName> major who cared enough to check me out and call my wife. So the next day I was put on the same type of C54. Long day, long day. Took off, went all the way to <placeName>Kelly Field, Texas</placeName> to <placeName>Maxwell Field, Alabama</placeName> to <placeName>Andrews Air Force Base</placeName>. Left when it was dark in the morning, got into <persName>Andrews</persName> at dark at night, the day before Thanksgiving. Got in the hall at <placeName>Walter Reed</placeName> and had me in a gurney in the hall that night, because they didn’t have enough room for us. All of us where starting to come in. They put me in a private room, in ward two—ward eleven, 2nd floor. I saw in that room the entire time I was there, from <date when="1965-11">November of ’65</date> to <date when="1966-08-03">August 3rd 1966</date>. Even when they let me out on convalescent leave, they kept my room for me. I had a private room, they treated me good. I was one of the early officers from <name type="event">the Vietnam War</name> to spend that much time at <placeName>Walter Reed</placeName>. It’s pretty young nurses and I had some of the finest medical care. <persName>Dr. Crayder Van Busker</persName> was a full colonel chief of urology. I had five operations, three where they open me up and two where they go in—(Audio not clear). A young—I had another major that was a doctor but I had a <persName>lieutenant colonel named Minimeyer</persName>, whose brother had been in the German army during <name type="event">World War II</name>. <persName>Colonel Minimeyer</persName>, through the quality of medical care I got, later on became Full <persName>Colonel Minimeyer</persName> and then <persName>General Minimeyer</persName>, and forget Major General <persName>Minimeyer</persName>, they bypassed the two stars and made him surgeon general of the army. So I knew him as a lieutenant colonel, I knew him as a lieutenant general. I got to see him in <placeName>Washington</placeName> a couple of times when I’d come up, but he was that good—that’s the quality of medical care you had back then. That good of a man as well as an army officer and a doctor, he was a great doctor. I remember as he took out some fragments—one bullet, to show you about how things go, I had a bullet taped to my left arm. I was dirty, I had blood on my hands and dirt from <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. I’d been in <placeName>85th</placeName>, been in <placeName>Clark</placeName>, been in <placeName>Tachikawa, Japan</placeName>, <placeName>California</placeName>, <placeName>Illinois</placeName> and now I’m at <placeName>Walter Reed</placeName> and my wife seeing me with the same dirt, the same blood and they didn’t have time to clean you all up. When my brother in-law, sister and my wife walked in to see me at <placeName>Walter Reed</placeName> on Thanksgiving day 1965, first time I’d seen them in a while. Then, they finally got around to clean this up and getting it off. Well, I had one bullet taped to my arm, after a couple of weeks I was complaining about a pain on my left side, so they took me down to a—at the end of this I had this private room but there was a little surgical room about half the size of this one, and they’d x-rayed me first and they’d said, “You’ve got something that is working its way out.” They just made a little local layer on my left and just popped it out. So I got another bullet which they gave me as a souvenir. Later on in surgery, after one of the surgeries they gave me one and some fragments, which I have in a jar. <persName>Colonel Minimeyer</persName>, little brown medical bottle that he wrote on some tape “VC stuff”, you know. He put the—not scotch tape, the white adhesive. It’s still on the bottle, sits on a little bookcase at home and I’ve still got the prescription note he’s written something on, it was an old army prescription pad, then the fragments and the bullet that he put in the jar for me. I still have that as a souvenir as well. Went back to <persName>Sergeant Jivens</persName> when he was killed. <persName>Sergeant Jivens</persName> married his high school sweetheart, had like six or seven children, I don’t remember exactly, maybe eight but I know it was at least six. In <date when="1993">1993</date> was the first reunion my wife and I ever made. When they were writing the book We Were Soldiers, they didn’t know where I was, they thought I was living in <placeName>Florida</placeName>, but I was actually flying out of <placeName>Alabama</placeName>, living in <placeName>Huntsville, Alabama</placeName> for sixteen years. I was a commercial pilot. <persName>Betty Jivens Mapson</persName> was her name, a little petite young lady, who wasn’t so young she was in her 40’s, she had a master’s degree. Had a daughter with a master’s degree in <placeName>Washington</placeName>. Shows up at our banquet here, sits at a table with me and told me who she was. She really wrote a nice—almost a full page on the fly of my book about  glad she was to meet me and actually talk to someone that had been with her father when he died. She said she was so young she wished she and her brother could talk to me and learn about her dad. I got the chance to see her and her brother a time or two down at <placeName>Fort Benning</placeName> on <date when="2002-02-13">February the 13th of ’02</date>, when we premiered the movie there at <placeName>Fort Benning</placeName>. (Audio cuts off here)</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
