<?xml-model href="../schemas/ddhi.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Transcript of an Interview with a Narrator</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>
          <orgName>Dartmouth Digital History Initiative</orgName>
        </authority>
        <date>
          <!--  Date of publication, e.g. for citation purposes  -->
        </date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <recordingStmt>
          <recording xml:id="primary_recording" type="audio" dur-iso="">
            <!-- https://www.digi.com/resources/documentation/digidocs/90001437-13/reference/r_iso_8601_duration_format.htm -->
            <media url="" mimeType="MIMEaudio/wav"/>
          </recording>
        </recordingStmt>
        <bibl xml:id="primary_transcription">
          <respStmt>
            <persName>Mimi Eisenberg</persName>
            <orgName>Wordcraft</orgName>
            <resp ref="http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/trc.html">Transcriber</resp>
          </respStmt>
          <ref target="path_to_file">Primary transcription</ref>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The Dartmouth Vietnam Project</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application ident="DDHIEncoder" version="1.0">
          <desc>Conversion from Word docx to TEI xml.</desc>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en-us">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <particDesc>
        <person xml:id="VERRONE"/>
        <person xml:id="JONES"/>
      </particDesc>
      <settingDesc>
        <setting>
          <date when-iso=""/>
          <locale/>
        </setting>
      </settingDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <u who="VERRONE">This is Dr. <persName>Richard Verrone</persName>. I'm conducting an oral history interview with Major <persName>Clovis Jones</persName>. We are in the <placeName>Crystal City</placeName> Hilton in <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <placeName>D.C.</placeName> It’s Veteran<date>’s Day</date>, <date>November 11th, 2005</date>. Major <persName>Jones</persName> and I are doing this, we are a part of the 40th anniversary reunions of the battles of the Ia Drang Valley, back in <date>November of 1965</date>. Major <persName>Jones</persName>, if we could, tell me about what your specific duties were there—you were with <date>the 1st of the 8th</date>?</u>
      <u who="JONES">Yes.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Tell me a little bit about what you did, what your duties were.</u>
      <u who="JONES">Well, I started out in <persName>Charlie Company</persName> 1st of the 8th Cav back in <placeName>Fort Benning</placeName> and was still in that unit when I got to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. I was a point man. However, I didn’t go to battle as a point man, I was called up to the headquarters by Sergeant Major <persName>Herbert P. McCullough</persName>. He felt that I would do a good job as his “Field Mail Clerk”, no such official position but he understood that the mail was extremely important and that food was important for morale. I’d worked with him at Fort Campbell. He’d been my sergeant major and really a mentor and kind of a second father to me.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">How did you feel about that request to do that?</u>
      <u who="JONES">I didn’t want to do it.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Why not?</u>
      <u who="JONES">As an infantryman with your buddies, going to a headquarters was like wimping out. (<persName>Laughs</persName>) You know, shirking your duties and that sort of thing. I wanted to be down in the line where I had served in previous command with <persName>Sergeant Major McCullough</persName>. Also I didn’t want to seem like I was shirking away from my duties. So I didn’t want to go. His words to convince me to come voluntary was, “We really need you to make sure that the troops get their mail and I know you’ll do a good job.” So I took it on and would deploy forward with the command <orgName>CP (Command Post</orgName>) and the mail would be brought in sometimes, and I’d make sure the units get it. Other times when we weren’t operating in the <placeName>Pleiku</placeName> province, I would drive a <orgName>Jeep</orgName> from An <orgName>Khe</orgName> all the way down—I think it’s Highway 14. </u>
      <u who="VERRONE">It is.</u>
      <u who="JONES">From An Khe to Highway 1, north bound to wherever the <placeName>CP</placeName> was when they were operating along the coast in Bong Son and find the units and hand the mail to them.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Wow.</u>
      <u who="JONES">And drive back.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">So I imagined the—I'm glad you’re here <date>today</date>, that was dangerous. What do you remember the men’s reactions when you would deliver the mail?</u>
      <u who="JONES">It was a morale boost. They’re like, “Here’s Jones!” or “Here’s the Mailman!” They would just brighten up. At the wall <date>today</date>, and I'm thinking back grieving a little bit because a lot of that I suppressed and I sent an email note to <persName>Joe Galloway</persName> and General <persName>Moore</persName> and thanking them for writing the book, and I’ll get to that a little later. The one thing is that they shared—I almost knew everybody in the battalion. Number one, from looking at the records that we maintained in the mailroom, and number two from just being associated with them. They were like, “Hey Jones!” <orgName>Cookies</orgName>, goodies, pictures of home.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">It was you, you were the delivery man.</u>
      <u who="JONES">Yeah, I was the delivery man. So you got to know people’s lives. Their hopes, their aspirations, their family members, mothers, fathers, sisters, girlfriends, wives, children, uncle, and aunts. You know, “Hey, I got this from home, have some of this.” It was a shared experience. It was like the unit was my family!</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">That’s a very special relationship you had with these—very unique.</u>
      <u who="JONES">Yes, yes. Then, the sad part about that, the downside to that was when we had any KIAs (Killed In Action). In the field, it was my duty to go before they went to the morgue to identify them. Match the social security number up and identify them. That was hard because when you lost anyone, at that time, we didn’t really know how to grieve, at least I didn’t. We would say, “Don’t mean nothing” Well, it meant the world to us! We just lost one of your best friends and there’s a special bond between members of combat. When you’re in a combat situation, members of your unit—there’s a special bond because you would literally give your life to save your buddy. That’s just how tight we were. You don’t find those kinds of relationship hardly ever outside of that military environment, that combat environment. So especially when you lost someone, flashbacks about what they shared with you, what they wanted to do. One of our troopers from <placeName>Detroit</placeName>, he was engaged and I don’t recall his name, but he was a black trooper. I remember that he got shot through the head and the bullet was still penetrating out. But he got a silver star for his actions, but just thinking about that life lost and remembering him telling me what he wanted to do when he got back was to get married and go to college and several others. It was that when you had that loss, it was a flashback to what they shared with you. A moment you may have enjoyed at <placeName>Fort Benning</placeName>. </u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Sure.</u>
      <u who="JONES">In training or going in the town or wherever we went to have fun, or just joking with people. So that was the downside of it.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">What did you do in <date>1965</date>, in <date>November</date>, how were you associated with <orgName>Moore</orgName>’s group at <placeName>Pleiku</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="JONES">Well, not so much directly associated. <date>The 1st of the 8th</date> had been in the Ia <placeName>Drang</placeName> prior to the 7th coming in. In fact, <date>the 1st of the 9th and 1st of the 8th</date> had been operating in the <placeName>Valley</placeName> and I think he’s retired, Colonel <persName>Danielson</persName>, <persName>Ted Danielson</persName> was the captain of A Company. They’d made the first hell of a night insertion in combat. I was deployed up at the tea plantation, I can’t remember the name of it right now. We were headquartered there, at least the command CP was. Was there, had the action, we were pulled back to An <orgName>Khe</orgName>, I think because there we were across the—we did something, I think we went across the border chasing the bad guys, and that was a no-no. </u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Of course.</u>
      <u who="JONES">There was some controversy about it, we weren’t sure what was happening, but anyway, we had been up there operating, came back to An <orgName>Khe</orgName>. It was a <date>Sunday</date> afternoon, I was in the command CP and heard the distress call. I went down to my old unit, <persName>Charlie Company</persName>, and said, “Guys, pack your bags, we’re going back out.” So we went back to Plei Me. I think <date>the next day</date> or sometime. Anyway, as soon as we deployed back, we went into Plei Me. It was an old special forces camp and I remember what had been used as a runway. There were bodies from the 7th Cav and those who’d been in X-Ray, stacked along that runway.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Did you know any of these troopers?</u>
      <u who="JONES">Didn’t know that I knew them. But you know, many of us had socialized or seen each other and just said hi and that sort of thing. But with the bodies being there, I didn’t take the time to go and try to see if I knew anyone. But you know, it was just the sadness and the sorrow to hear lives lost and guys who really had a fight.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">When did it hit you that how important this action was? What was happening in the <placeName>Valley</placeName>. This is so early on in the war—I mean to the American public and to the world 1965 marks that first ground troop action, we had many people there before. When did it hit you about the importance of what you were involved there in the Ia Drang Valley?</u>
      <u who="JONES">Not so much about the importance of it, it’s just about doing your duty but you knew something was special about the operation. Basically when they did that night insertions, they said, “Guys, we’re in a fight. This is not just <placeName>Viet Cong</placeName>.”</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">It’s the night of the 14th?</u>
      <u who="JONES">Yeah. Something else is going on here. Also operating there, we had a <persName>Frenchman</persName> who—well, he was born in <placeName>France</placeName>, he was in our unit.  He knew one of the men at the plantation and the report that we got was that—in fact I was there when the guy was telling him. He said, “Look, we have these regular North Vietnamese forces passing through the plantation.” I don’t think people really wanted to believe that, and when I say people, the higher commands didn’t want to believe that, but he was saying you know, battalion sized forces passing through at night. So we knew from that intelligence, from that information at least, you knew something was going on and we had a sense when we were headquartered at the tea plantation that there was going to be a major fight at some point and I'm thinking it was <date>the 1st of the 8th</date> that said it. Of course when they had the night insertion and all of that sort of thing, it’s like, “Hmm something is going on.” And when they pulled us back it’s like, “Well, I don’t know what’s this is all about.” There was rumors of people losing commands and all that kind of stuff. I said, “How do you do that for coming over here to do what we did?” Taking that fight to them.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Right. Is that how you saw it? Did you all want to take the fight to the enemy?</u>
      <u who="JONES">Of course. Of course. I mean, I had been in the <orgName>101st</orgName> and the great history of that unit and jumping out of airplanes, but then when I got to <placeName>Fort Benning</placeName>, I was still the 11th Air Assault. Going through all the training there, they had not only jumping, but you were rappelling, doing the ladders, you were doing all that kind of stuff. This is a special kind of combat unit. I’d done a term paper in high school on <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, so I was—</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Really? Interesting.</u>
      <u who="JONES">Yeah. The title was, “Is War Inevitable in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>?” and my conclusion was yes, the way we were headed. I had a wonderful French teacher by the name of Mr. <persName>Harrison</persName>, who taught us French. So I was fairly decent at the language, so that helped.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">So you had some historical background and when you’re actually there and you’re doing this, what do you remember from <date>the 14th, 15th, 16th of November</date>? And as that battle progressed and you found out news of what happened and how large the force was that attacked the 7th, what was your reaction?</u>
      <u who="JONES">The first thing when I knew it was the 7th, I thought about General <persName>Custard</persName>. Just close your eyes and say a prayer. I was telling someone <date>today</date>, “Thank God for Hal Moore.” People say, “Well <persName>Custard</persName>, and you know about the 7th.” I said, “Yeah, but <persName>Hal Moore</persName> redeemed them.” When I realized that they came out of the battle, it was basically through his preparation, his wit, the warrior in him that saved <date>the day</date>.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">What was his reputation amongst you all in <date>the 8th</date>? Did you know much about him?</u>
      <u who="JONES">Yeah, a little bit in training at Benning. But you have this guy over in the 7th Cav that was doing all kinds of crazy training. They even worked on <date>weekends</date>. So that’s the reputation they had. You got this guy over in the 7th Cav, that commander over in the 7th Cav and he is really training those guys and in the <persName>Garryowen</persName> shout, it was—those guys were as proud of that as we paratroopers were of airborne and all the way. It’s like, “There’s something different about those guys.”</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">After the battle at X-Ray, then <placeName>Albany</placeName> happens, what was your reaction to that second action when you heard about what had happen there.</u>
      <u who="JONES">You know, how could that happen in <orgName>Air Cav Division</orgName>? Guys walking in enemy territory. </u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Strung out, so long.</u>
      <u who="JONES">Yeah. It was just incredible. It was just unbelievable.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Was it demoralizing to you all? Or did you want revenge?</u>
      <u who="JONES">It was—who among the leaders decided to do that? That was the thought in my mind. How do you make that decision? Why not hold the ground you had at X-Ray until you got the support, you got all the artillery coordinates you need, you have everything in place? Why not wait until you could extract them? That was the thought through my mind. How do you make that decision? But then, you look at what happened and the heroism and you know just the fact the guys put up. Again, phenomenal.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Yeah. Does the phrase, “Don’t mean nothing.” Heard that a lot from <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> veterans. Inside though, what did you do? Your position here of identifying bodies. What did you do with that? Were you able to really suppress that while you were there?</u>
      <u who="JONES">I did, and that’s why I sent the note because I promised <date>last year</date> a thank you letter to General <persName>Moore</persName> and Mr. <persName>Galloway</persName>. When I saw—I thought I had handled it well and a book that was really relevant to read was the Thirteenth Valley by <persName>John Del Vecchio</persName>. Also, while I was in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> on my second tour, I read an analysis, a <orgName>Psychoanalysis</orgName> by <persName>A.A. Brill</persName>. It was one of those things that kind of helped you to put things in perspective and how things affect you, you think you got a handle. I’ve seen We Were Soldiers upwards of twenty times.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">What do you think of it?</u>
      <u who="JONES">I'll tell you my experience. The first eight times that I saw it, I cried through the whole movie. Just scenes from <placeName>Fort Benning</placeName> and bringing it back and realizing that when you lose, talking about identifying bodies. It’s people that you knew. Back in <date>the days</date> and kind of the track on setting of <placeName>Fort Benning</placeName> hard training and going out to <placeName>Columbus</placeName> and down to <placeName>Albany</placeName>, <placeName>Georgia</placeName>. My hometown is <placeName>Dawson</placeName>, <placeName>Georgia</placeName> so I would take troops down to my home, my parents would cook meals no matter what time of day we get in. My foxhole buddy was a fellow by the name of <persName>James Hutchinson</persName> from <placeName>Chicago</placeName>. So sometimes we’d get into my home at two o’clock in the morning and my mother would get up and she’d always cook fried chicken, she cooked for us. So no matter who I brought home, what time of day she’d get up and cooked. So those kind of experiences of sharing and caring just brought flashbacks of that. Then people that I knew and people that I lost like <persName>Sam Bess</persName>. <persName>Sam</persName> had a new car, I think it was a <orgName>Buick</orgName>. Some kind of new <persName>Buick</persName> and he was proud of his car, he was a Sergeant. You know, the rank and how we respected that. He was a sergeant and I was a PFC (Private First Class) at the time, I hadn’t made spec 4. He said, “While I'm going over here, guys get in.” Riding in his new car you know. He’s giving us a lift and he’s a sergeant and was a PFC. I’m thinking, “Aw man, this is a great guy.” Then you realizing he was among the first to get killed, he wasn’t the first get killed, but among the first. You think about that, you think about other moments. You know, personal experiences that you had with people. It really brought back a lot of those memories and I just couldn’t stop crying. I saw it eight times by myself. I saw it the first time and I cried and said, “I needed to see this again.” Because the music, you get the—the movie was so true to life, in terms of just the sounds of the weapons and the whole piece of it, all of that was just very authentic. Then, when I saw <persName>Chu Pong Massif</persName>, I got chills. Every time I say that word, I get chills. I don't know why, but that’s my reaction.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Stays with you.</u>
      <u who="JONES">Yeah, stays with you.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">You remember back then, when you saw it in the valley?</u>
      <u who="JONES">I remember that and you know, just the mountain. For some reason that—and I don't know how I saw it or where I saw it but just hearing the words and seeing that it’s like, “Oh, yeah.”</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">What about the book? What happened when the book came out? I mean, it got a lot of press. It’s been very widely read and then the movie of course, but before the movie, here’s <persName>Galloway</persName> and <persName>Moore</persName> walking the American public and you all through that battle step-by-step, literally minute-by-minute. How did you handle it all?</u>
      <u who="JONES">I didn’t read the book until after I saw the movie. </u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Really?</u>
      <u who="JONES">Because a lot of things—I guess that’s my way of coping. A lot of my experiences in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> was either not realizing how much my psyche was suppressing all of this. When I saw the movie, I said, “I better read this book.” So I read the book twice and it brought back a lot of memories, you know. <persName>Roger Bean</persName> was my ops officer. I left <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> as a spec 4. Had applied to flight school. Colonel <persName>Mortel</persName> and my sergeant major helped me a number of times with a number of absences, somehow they got lost. I didn’t know I had been accepted to flight school, but I wanted to fly since I was <date>four years old</date>. My parents wanted me to be a doctor, I kind of walked away from a scholarship at <orgName>Morehouse College</orgName>. I went back later once I got out of <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. I said, “Okay, I spent <date>three years</date> trying to get to flight school and it didn’t happen. I guess it’s not for me. I guess I'll try premed at <orgName>Morehouse</orgName>.” So I went to <orgName>Morehouse</orgName> and <date>about three months</date> into my time at <orgName>Morehouse</orgName> I got a call from <orgName>Department of Army</orgName>, they tracked me down there. “Are you still interested in going to flight school?” I said, “You bet.” So I finished a semester and in <date>February</date> of ’67—I got out in <date>June</date> of ’66 and in <date>February</date> of ’67, I reenlisted at Fort Campbell. I still had contact with <orgName>Sergeant Major McCullough</orgName>. I said “Hey, I got accepted to flight school, what do I need to do? I have to reenlist.” He said, “Well, reenlist for <orgName>Fort Campbell</orgName>. No school, no nothing. They’re going to offer you all kinds of stuff, but just reenlist for <orgName>Fort Campbell</orgName>. Let me know when you’re coming.” And I did. I called him and told him when I was coming. I got there and he says, “Well, we’re right in the middle of an <orgName>IG (Inspector General</orgName>) inspection, but come down to the unit.” So I did. They introduced me to the <orgName>IG</orgName> and his commanders and he said, “Just wait here until we finish this inspection.” From there he took me to a replacement unit at the division headquarters. He’d managed to get me assigned to his unit. I had been an infantryman, a mail clerk, and a clerk typist for him before and I was assigned to the headquarters S1 section and they were <date>about six months</date> behind in paperwork, so I caught them up before I went off to flight school. So I owe a lot to him and Colonel <persName>Mortel</persName> and a lot of other folk that helped me along the way.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">So the book was cathartic in a way? And the movie too? </u>
      <u who="JONES">Yes, it was. It helped me to walk through like nothing else had because the one thing that—well, you didn’t have—who could you talk to about that? Who could you tell these stories to? The one thing that was so—still resonates with me is when <persName>Joe</persName> in the movie, the character who was playing <persName>Joe</persName> is trying to write the story. How do you tell that story? And <placeName>Pleiku</placeName> just being red—you know, your clothes red with that clay and the movie depicted how our eyes looked because I remember seeing others eyes, you know our eyes are red. We’re tired, we’re dirty, we’re smelly. He’s trying to write the story, it’s like how do you tell that story? That’s what helped me to begin to release about this. It’s like, “Well, these guys have told it.” The, I started to write a little bit, hooked up with my guys from my flight unit and then there was In the Shadow of the Blade, you know. Matter of fact, sergeant from <persName>Charlie Company</persName>, <date>1st of the 8th</date>, he says, “Come on up, you got to be here.” Guys you haven’t seen—I think it was thirty-three, <date>thirty-six years</date> you got to come up to see them. I said I was sick, I was wearing a mask and that movie is not released—I’m sitting there, actually in this jacket and all that. </u>
      <u who="VERRONE">I’ve seen it.</u>
      <u who="JONES">It’s like—I said, “Look, I got a respiratory injury.” He says, “Take your medicine, get somebody to drive you up here, but be here.” I had four guys—three guys that I had served with and it was a wonderful experience, all of us sitting on the side of this helicopter. <persName>Earl Waters</persName>, <persName>Villagomez</persName>, and <persName>Perry Tillman</persName>. I said, “Man, this is great!”</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">May I ask you a question? <date>1965</date> when you’re in <date>the 2nd of the 8th</date>, how long had you been in the army at that point?</u>
      <u who="JONES"><date>1st of the 8th</date>.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE"><date>1st of the 8th</date>, sorry.</u>
      <u who="JONES">I’d been in the army <date>two years</date>.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">What was it like as an African American in <orgName>the US Army</orgName> in <date>the 1960s</date>, when outside of that <placeName>the United States</placeName> is in chaos with the civil rights movement and the things that are going on? <persName>Harry Truman</persName> said, you know he’s the one who desegregated the armed forces and he said and others after him, <persName>Colin Powell</persName> said, “The US Military, especially <orgName>the US Army</orgName> is the one place where everybody could be equal.” Could you make some comments on that?</u>
      <u who="JONES">Well, that’s nice of them to say and you could be more equal there, but I found discrimination in the army. I’d been a part of the civil rights movement. In fact in my hometown I wrote a letter to the superintendent demanding equal education for African Americans and got me almost kicked out of school and life threaten and all that. I’d go down to listen to Dr. <persName>King</persName> in <placeName>Albany</placeName>, <placeName>Georgia</placeName> for <orgName>the Albany Movement</orgName> and all that sort of thing. So I was deeply involved in that because as an American, you want rights for everybody. That’s what separates up from every other country in the world. It’s something we need to be proud of. Not to aggravate our differences, but the commonality that we all hold and be respectful of others views, you know that’s something that’s important and having an understanding. My great-grandmother was a slave. Understanding after slavery, this lady accumulated properties in <placeName>Georgia</placeName> and <placeName>South Carolina</placeName>. Had people employed for her. She had lost her arm in a cotton gin, so she had one arm.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Wow, what an example.</u>
      <u who="JONES">Yeah. If she could do this, I know that I could do whatever I want to now. The first time that I told someone that I wanted to be a pilot—was playing with some kids in a little sandy spot where everybody liked to play in the sand because if you fell, it didn’t hurt you as bad, was <persName>Richard Harris</persName>. He was an older guy in the community. Let me just tell this story. As a kid, you’d go to <date>Sunday</date> School. You’re raised as a Christian, belonged to a Baptist church. I was preschooler actually. We had these little <date>Sunday</date> School carts. The <date>Sunday</date> prior to this epiphany, the card had Christ standing with his staff on a side of mountain with sheep at his feet. The little caption there for us little kids who were barley learning to read was, “The Lord is my shepherd.” <date>Later that week</date> by <date>mid-week</date> I'm looking up at the clouds and the clouds look like a bunch of little sheep. I said, “Wow!” Reminded me of the <date>Sunday</date> School card. I said, “I want to be a pilot!” I don't know where I got the word from but I was <date>four years old</date>.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">You wanted to be up there in those clouds? Those sheep?</u>
      <u who="JONES">Yeah. I wanted to be flying. So I wanted to be a pilot. So you know how kids are enthusiastic, I said, “Hey, guess what <persName>Richard</persName>! I want to be a pilot!” He looked at me with both admiration and fear at the same time. I was kind of confused. There’s a guy I'm looking up and admiring, he’s got that kind of reaction by what I just said, so I didn’t tell anybody else until I graduated from high school. Told my dad, I said, “Look dad, I really want to be a pilot.” Because he wanted me to be a doctor, I said, “I really want to be a pilot.” He said, “Well if that’s what you want to do, you can do it.” That was my pursuit. I went to the army because you could go to the army as a high school graduate if you met all the other criteria and go to flight school. That’s what I did. I passed all the tests, everything. But I wound up in the <orgName>Airborne Infantry</orgName> first and that’s another story. (<orgName>Laughs</orgName>)</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">How has it been for the reunion <date>this year</date>, the 40th anniversary of the deployment over there in ’65. What’s it been like for you?</u>
      <u who="JONES">It’s been good. <date>Last year</date> I came because <persName>Ted Danielson</persName> presented and sent an email out that he wants some people from <date>the 1st of the 8th</date> to show up, so I showed up <date>last year</date>. This <date>year</date>’s really been good. Just seeing faces from <date>last year</date>, seeing <orgName>General Moore</orgName>. You know, having express my thanks to him. That was kind of a burden I was carrying around because really as a mail clerk, you don’t feel like you did anything. I was telling a gentlemen <date>yesterday</date>. I was a peripheral guy, I wasn’t in the thick of battle. I'm just a support guy and that’s how I feel. And especially you said the phrase “Don’t mean nothing.” People have given their lives, but you feel guilty about being alive because they’re dead and that’s a guilt that I had. But now I'm realizing that you know, I haven’t done too badly and that really, out to their memory and to celebrate what we did as young men.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">And you’re here. You’re here.</u>
      <u who="JONES">I'm celebrating them at the wall <date>today</date>, but a life well lived. That’s what I want to do, is really live a good solid life. I remember something my mother saying after I came back from <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> because I’d changed so much. I’m a happy go lucky kid to somebody who is kind of withdrawn, had very little tolerance for nonsense. Very analytical and to the point. They saw that as being insensitive. I'm thinking, “Hey, I'm accustomed to moving at a hundred miles an hour, over the ground you know, different place <date>every day</date>.” To come back to what people are guessing and thinking and not sure it’s like, “No!” (<persName>Laughs</persName>) Give me an answer, tell me the truth and I can deal with the rest. But coming back to the southern environment where you know people are a little laid back and they would say, “I reckon,” or, “I guess so.” That wasn’t good enough for me, I need an answer! I need the right answer of whatever it is, just give me the correct, whatever the right information is and I'm good. They saw that big change and she says, “I’ll be so glad when you come out and be a good citizen again.” It struck me deep. It wasn’t hurtful, but I was still trying to figure out what she meant and <date>today</date> I realize what she meant. You know, yes you’ve gone through some tough times. Yes, you have memories and things you may never be able to express, but I am beginning to write some down. But you really need to stand up and be the person that you truly are. So <date>today</date> at the wall is like, “I get it. Just stand up and be a good citizen again.” So that’s what it means to me. It’s really just coming out and being a good citizen again. Be involved, be active. A lot of times as young people, we gave it our all. We were tight, we were buddies, we gave our all. I think I pulled back from that some. In fact, I know I did. <date>Today</date> it’s like joining up again.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Well, good. In interest of time, we need to stop. Major <persName>Jones</persName>, thank you so much for this interview.</u>
      <u who="JONES">Well, thank you. Happy to be here. (End of interview)</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
