<?xml-model href="../schemas/ddhi.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Transcript of an Interview with Tracy Black Enders</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>
          <orgName>Vietnam Center and Sam Johnson Vietnam Archive</orgName>
        </authority>
        <date>
          <!--  Date of publication, e.g. for citation purposes  -->
        </date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <recordingStmt>
          <recording xml:id="primary_recording" type="video" dur-iso="00:25:51">
            <!-- https://www.digi.com/resources/documentation/digidocs/90001437-13/reference/r_iso_8601_duration_format.htm -->
            <media url="https://vva.vietnam.ttu.edu/images.php?img=/OH/OH0487/OH0487.mp4" mimeType="video/mp4"/>
          </recording>
        </recordingStmt>
        <bibl xml:id="primary_transcription">
          <respStmt>
            <persName>Mark Steven Varela</persName>
            <orgName>Vietnam Center and Sam Johnson Vietnam Archive</orgName>
            <resp ref="http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/trc.html">Transcriber</resp>
          </respStmt>
          <ref target="path_to_file">https://vva.vietnam.ttu.edu/images.php?img=/OH/OH0487/OH0487.pdf</ref>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The Oral History Project of the Vietnam Center and Sam Johnson Vietnam Archive</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application ident="DDHIEncoder" version="1.0">
          <desc>Conversion from Word docx to TEI xml.</desc>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en-us">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <particDesc>
        <person xml:id="VERRONE"/>
        <person xml:id="BLACK"/>
      </particDesc>
      <settingDesc>
        <setting>
          <date when-iso="2005-11-11"/>
          <locale/>
        </setting>
      </settingDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <u who="VERRONE">This is <persName>Dr. Richard Verrone</persName>, I am doing an oral history video interview with <persName>Tracy Black Enders</persName>. Today is <date when="2005-11-11">November 11th, Veterans Day 2005</date>, and we’re in <placeName>Washington, D.C.</placeName>, at the <placeName>Hilton Crystal City</placeName>. We are all part of the <orgName>1st Cav division</orgName> reunion and also the 40th anniversary of the <name type="event">Pleiku-Ia Drang Valley</name> campaign of <date when="1965-11">November 1965</date>. <persName>Tracy</persName>, tell me a little bit about your father and who he was.</u>
      <u who="BLACK">Dad was a military reporter for the <orgName>Columbus Ledger-Inquirer</orgName>, which was basically the hometown paper for the <orgName>1st Cav</orgName>. He started covering them when they were the <orgName>11th Air Assault Division</orgName>. Basically, followed them through. Somehow got himself on the troop buses and took the troop ships over to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> with them. So he actually traveled on the ships with him. A lot of the guys got to know him then, got to trust him, which was important for a reporter, and landed in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> with them.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">How did he get himself embedded?</u>
      <u who="BLACK">Early embedding.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Yes! How did that happen?</u>
      <u who="BLACK">He was just so persistent! But even more than that, I think the public information officers saw a great deal of—they just felt as though they could trust him and they felt as though he could take the story back to the hometown where the wives were waiting and that kind of thing. He was just a very persuasive man. (Laughs)</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">He was a career journalist. This is what he wanted to do. This was his—</u>
      <u who="BLACK">He kind of fell into journalism. He was a <orgName>marine</orgName>, knocked around with a lot of jobs. He was an iron worker. Basically, had hurt himself, broken his back doing iron working, had fallen on a job. Some gentleman offered him some tiny sum of money to read the news on the local radio station while he was recovering. Basically found a passion for it at that point but was really self-made.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">What kind of man was he? I mean, you described that what he kind of did, but tell me about his personality.</u>
      <u who="BLACK">He told a great story. Was incredibly smart, with a photographic memory. He had a great deal of respect for the military and was a real patriot. In house, you stood up even if the national anthem was on TV. (Laughs) And to this day I’ve never seen a <persName>Jane Fonda</persName> movie because we were forbidden to see anything with <persName>Jane Fonda</persName>.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">He was a really big supporter of the troops and what was—</u>
      <u who="BLACK">Big supporter of the troops.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Have you heard about what his thoughts were about the <name type="event">Vietnam War</name> in general, before he went over?</u>
      <u who="BLACK">I think that he—in the beginning his interest wasn’t following the <orgName>1st Cav</orgName>. I know that he believed that we needed to stop communism. He really did believe in the mission, in <name type="event">Vietnam</name>. What he became angry about and very upset about was the fact that men went over, women went over and served and they did so honorably, and when everything went bad politically, the American public couldn’t separate the two. They couldn’t separate the honorable service from the politics of the war. He became very bitter about the treatment of the soldiers when they returned home. Not so much in <placeName>Columbus</placeName> but he just saw it in general. I think he believed in <placeName>America</placeName> being there in the beginning. I think he believed that we didn’t fight the war to win it by the end.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">He went over in <date when="1965">1965</date> with the <orgName>Cav</orgName>?</u>
      <u who="BLACK">Yep, he went over with the <orgName>Cav</orgName>. He went seven separate times. I think he was there, I think as late as I think <date when="1969">1969</date>.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Wow. So he saw a lot of things, and he saw an evolution of the war as well.</u>
      <u who="BLACK">Absolutely.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">How old were you when this was all happening?</u>
      <u who="BLACK">I was born <date when="1964-11-20">November 20th, 1964</date>. Not even a year old when he was over there. In fact, I remember one of my earliest memories is of crying, trying to pull my mom away from dad because I didn’t know who he was. Because then, he would get himself over there, but they never really gave him a lot of money, so he would stay for a long period of time because that was more cost effective than making these multiple trips. It wasn’t until <orgName>Newsweek</orgName> maybe did a profile on him and printed his weekly salary that I think they probably almost quadruple his salary. At that point he was making nothing. I mean, next to nothing to be over there.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Well, tell me about the <orgName>1st Cav</orgName> and what he saw in <date when="1965">’65</date>. Part of the reunion here is about the 40th anniversary of the <name type="event">Ia Drang battles</name>. Did he witness any of this? Was he there to see this? Tell me about that.</u>
      <u who="BLACK">Oh yeah, absolutely. He was with them that entire campaign, essentially. He was a reporter, but they would actually bring him into planning meetings when they would be planning going into landing zone and what have you, to ask his opinion because he was really self-taught on military strategy and they had a lot of respect for him with that. But he would probably be in places that today they would shudder to think a journalist could get into, but they trusted him.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Right. That says a lot about him.</u>
      <u who="BLACK">That came across loud, and it still comes across to this day how much the guys trusted him. He went into—they did a night landing. He went in with <persName>Colonel Stockton</persName>, with the <orgName>1st of the 9th</orgName>. Who was shortly after there, relieved of his command. He was the third person off the helicopter behind <persName>Colonel Stockton</persName> and his radio operator. The story as I get it because my mom retold it and others have retold is that <persName>Stockton</persName> turned around and asked him what his wife’s name was and he says, “<persName>Mary</persName>” And he says, “You son of a bitch, crazy enough to get off the helicopter if he doesn’t have to, this is now Landing Zone Mary!” (Laughs)</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Oh wow, that’s neat!</u>
      <u who="BLACK">And I read about the account first in a book by <persName>JD Coleman</persName>, about the <placeName>Pleiku campaign</placeName> because he was really the historian that documented the entire campaign at that time. I called my mother and asked her about it because you know I hadn’t—I said, “Did you know this?” She goes, “Yeah, I just kind of forgotten about it. Time, age whatever.” She says, “Yeah, remember that old tobacco tin that I keep up on the shelf?” I said, “Yeah, the red one that kind of has the hole in it.” She says “Yeah, that was in his left breast pocket during that Landing Zone” And she said, “That’s what stopped the bullet.”</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Wow.</u>
      <u who="BLACK">She said, “He was almost killed two or three times because they got themselves in an ambush.” I guess it got pretty hot and heavy. He was there, he was at <placeName>Landing Zone Falcon</placeName>. He came in towards the end I believe of <placeName>Albany</placeName>, but everything was over at that point. But really he was there for the entirety of the campaign.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Do you remember, based on what your mother said and based on what you read, how he remembered that whole campaign and the significance of that campaign? With this being the real huge encounter—</u>
      <u who="BLACK">He understood the significance of it. He really understood the significance of this knew airmobile concept. I think he also understood that what they did during that battle was really going to change the face of warfare to a great degree. He always talked to me even before I could really understand it and relate it to the rest of it about how difficult it is to fight an embedded troops on hostile terrain, where basically they are using guerilla warfare. Dad got that early on that you couldn’t fight a conventional war and he thought that’s what this campaign proved. That you had to take it to them where they were and you know your conventional war was just not going to work in <name type="event">Vietnam</name>.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Right. Did he ever talk to then <persName>Lieutenant Colonel Moore</persName>?</u>
      <u who="BLACK">Oh, yeah.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Tell me about those conversations and what he gleaned from <persName>Moore</persName> and what his opinion of <persName>Moore</persName> was.</u>
      <u who="BLACK">He had a lot of respect for <persName>Colonel Moore</persName> and <persName>Colonel Moore</persName> has a lot of respect for him still. Dad never talked a lot about that part of his life with me, so I can’t say I know of any conversations in specific.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Do you remember what your mother has told you about him?</u>
      <u who="BLACK">What my mom has told me was that they talked a lot about tactics and repelling out of helicopters. Dad was actually certified to repel out of a helicopter with these guys and a lot of—he talked a lot with <persName>Colonel Moore</persName> about the actual, “How do you get these guys out of the helicopters and onto the ground.” You know, the real nuts and bolts of the <orgName>11th Air Assault Division</orgName> and what became the <orgName>1st Cav</orgName>. How do you make it happen without getting your guy shot before they even put a boot on the ground. So there was a lot of that I think before they left to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> where they talked about it.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">I am remembering it now, having read the book again for the fifth or sixth time that <persName>Colonel Moore</persName> mentions your father and the respect he has. He only saw just a few journalist who were worth their salt and he was one of them.</u>
      <u who="BLACK">Yep. Him, <persName>Bob Poos</persName> and <persName>Joe Galloway</persName>.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Yeah and <persName>Joe</persName>. Did you father know <persName>Bob</persName> and <persName>Joe</persName>?</u>
      <u who="BLACK">Oh, yeah. Yeah.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">I imagine they had to know each other.</u>
      <u who="BLACK"><persName>Joe</persName>—actually when I found this group, <persName>Joe</persName> was the first guy that I really talked to. I took this book and there were some articles with some names during the tenth anniversary of the <name type="event">Vietnam</name> wall and they started helping me plug names in and they all kept coming up at the <placeName>Arlington Hyatt</placeName>, at some reunion. I called and left a message at the hospitality suite and the guy kind of says, “If anybody knows your dad we’ll give you a call back. I’ll let <persName>General Moore</persName> and <persName>Joe Galloway</persName> know. If anybody is going to know them, it’ll be them.” So I figured I'd hear something the next day because it was pretty late already. About midnight I got a phone call and it was <persName>Joe Galloway</persName> and he said, “I couldn’t wait until tomorrow to find out—” I'm sorry. “If you’re the daughter, of my good friend <persName>Charlie Black</persName>.” It was nice because after all of those years, somebody remembered.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Yeah. It was a direct connection right there. What did <persName>Joe</persName> tell you about your father? Were you able to go over the next day and see?</u>
      <u who="BLACK">Yeah, I did. I was able to talk to him. His first words to me were, “Thank god you didn’t look anything like your father.” (Laughs)</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">(Laughs) Thanks <persName>Joe</persName>.</u>
      <u who="BLACK">I think he was expecting maybe a female version of my dad, that would not have been pretty. I was able to talk to him and he just talked a lot about how much dad taught him as a reporter and keeping confidences and really about how to get the story from the guys. The thing that everybody always talks about in dad’s articles are all the names and the hometowns. When you think about this, a lot of the time he was going in when a landing zone was already hot. He’s hitting the ground and he’s getting these names. It was his photographic memory that allowed him to remember a lot of it because there’s no time to write it down or anything like that. There was another reporter, <persName>John Laurence</persName> wrote the book, The cat from <placeName>Hué</placeName>. I’ve since met him and he talked to me about—he just followed him into a landing zone one day and was just amazed that two minutes he had twenty names and hometowns and everybody’s story. You know so I think <persName>Joe</persName> felt as though dad was a real mentor to him.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">That book is written a lot like that because a constant mention of names and where they’re from throughout the book, even if it was said before.</u>
      <u who="BLACK">I think that’s something that <persName>Joe</persName> really learned from Dad, that it was important to give their name and hometown because people were so desperate for news. I mean, we didn’t have the instant news of today where my god there was—where was it, we even saw the first <orgName>marine</orgName> hit the beach somewhere. I mean it’s instant, on. Then, you could wait because these guys would type their stories over there and if you were like my dad, you waited until you could get some solider to frank it back for you. They would really wait. That’s how wives found out their husband were still okay or they found out where their husbands were and what they were doing. Mothers and fathers, you know found out, “Okay, he mentioned my son.” It was particularly important for that community in <placeName>Columbus</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Right, absolutely.</u>
      <u who="BLACK">So many people there waiting for news. So I think <persName>Joe</persName> really learned that from dad, how important that aspect of it was. He and <persName>Bob Poos</persName> knew each other through their time there. Dad had a lot of respect for them. At dad’s memorial service, <persName>Peter Arnett</persName> was a speaker. He knew <persName>Peter</persName> really well. Dad and <persName>Peter</persName> were the only two reporters to cover the story that <persName>Peter</persName> won the Pulitzer prize for. He’s saying nice things at memorial service, but he said he always thought that the only reason he won it was because he was with a big organization because he knew he didn’t write it better than dad.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">That’s nice. Have you and <persName>Joe</persName> stayed in touch all these years?</u>
      <u who="BLACK"><persName>Joe</persName>, yeah. We stay in touch by email. <persName>Bob Poos</persName> occasionally. <persName>Jack Laurence</persName>, who’s over in <placeName>Iraq</placeName> right now doing a documentary I believe on the <orgName>101st airborne</orgName>, stay in touch with him. I stay in touch with a lot of the guys too. You know, email is a great thing. Then, I come here every year.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Tell me about that. What is it like for you to be here and be around all these troopers?</u>
      <u who="BLACK">The first time that I went over to the <placeName>Arlington Hyatt</placeName> it was weird for me because as soon as people started finding out who I was, I was just surrounded by a group of guys. But the thing that my husband noticed and it strikes me til this day, they always touch me.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Really?</u>
      <u who="BLACK">One way or another, they need that physical connection because they had such respect for dad. I think they see me as a way of you know—</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">There’s that personal connection.</u>
      <u who="BLACK">That personal connection. To this day, it still exists. Even if they didn’t know dad, they knew about his articles and they wanted to connect in some way. It’s amazing to me because I always like to say, I think it was because of dads age and where he was in his life, he wasn’t a father that was always there. You know, he was gone a lot and then there was a divorce between him and my mother. Wasn’t until I was fifteen, sixteen, maybe the three years before I lost him that we started getting a really close relationship. But what I always saw that even though maybe he wasn’t the greatest father, he was a really good man. Just a very—there were people who depended on him who shared fox holes with him and whose lives he saved and they tell me about it. He had qualities that he was just a very good man.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">When did he pass away?</u>
      <u who="BLACK">In—it’s hard for me to remember, <date when="1982">1982</date>. I was seventeen. I was born in <date when="1964">’64</date>. Let’s do the math. I kind of blank out a little bit, it was very hard.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">I can imagine. Tell me about your experience has been with this book coming out in <date when="1991">’91</date>, <date when="1992">’92</date>. I mean, here’s <persName>Galloway</persName> and your dad’s mentioned. Did <persName>General Moore</persName> or <persName>Joe</persName> contact you about your dad, or was it a surprise?</u>
      <u who="BLACK">They had tried to find me. That’s why he was so anxious to speak to me because he said they’d been trying to find me for a while, but my parents had divorced and we moved to <placeName>North Carolina</placeName>, then I went to college, moved to <placeName>D.C.</placeName> I was actually living in <placeName>D.C.</placeName> when I finally connected with them. I was working two doors down from where the reunion was that year.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">That’s amazing. Tell me about the book and seeing your father’s name in there three times.</u>
      <u who="BLACK">Yeah, that was pretty amazing. You know, here’s tangible proof that he was good. Because I think that because of the newspaper that he worked for, it was such a small home—not small, but a hometown newspaper. He never gained the fame that perhaps some of the other journalists did and my mother says that dad always had a very healthy ego. I think that always bothered him a little bit you know, that he felt like, “Okay, you know, people should know my name a little bit more.” Because he knew what he did, he understood what he did. I think that he would have loved it and had he been alive, he would’ve been able to have contributed a lot to it. But he would’ve loved the notoriety of the division. He would’ve wanted people to know what he knew about these guys, that they really were heroes and that they went over there and they did their jobs and they did it well. So he would’ve been very proud of that.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Yeah. You brought some pictures with you and some other information. What do you have here of your father’s if you could kind of describe it.</u>
      <u who="BLACK">Well, we started a website called CharlieBlack.net [Editor’s Note: Domain no longer exists, however cache versions accessible through www.archive.org] and that has a lot of his works on there. He would sometimes—he would just write a ton of articles. I mean the big joke was that somebody would make him come out of the field and sit him down until he produced enough that he could go back out on the field. But he wrote so many articles that sometimes they would publish two or three in a day. So we put a lot of those works on the website.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Who was doing this?</u>
      <u who="BLACK">My husband and I. My husband <persName>Michael</persName> and I. <persName>Michael</persName> really is the one—he did it for me as a surprise and gave it to me as a gift.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">How nice. What do the troopers who see these articles and these things, how do they react to that? </u>
      <u who="BLACK">It’s so funny because even in the room waiting, there were three guys that came in and one of them overheard me talking to another gentleman and he had to come over and shake my hand, “I knew your dad and he told me stories.” They don’t really have to wait for me because so many of them still have these yellow scraps of paper that they saved. That’s how we collected a lot of his works, guys send us things that maybe we didn’t have previously and we send them back because through some unfortunate circumstances, there’s no good archive at the <orgName>Columbus paper</orgName> of his works. So we collect a lot from the men that attend this reunion. They’ll send us scrapbooks and they trust us to take it and copy it and mail it back to them. We had a gentleman from the last reunion from <placeName>Maine</placeName>. He sent us a whole box of scrapbooks and we copied and cleaned it up and sent it back to them. They trust us with it. Which I think is an important thing.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">It’s a legacy to your father. It speaks a lot about him and you too obviously.</u>
      <u who="BLACK">They all like to look through the scrap book. They’re going to like the website, I think. They’re going to be able to do searches, many come up with their name if he wrote about them or come up with battles that they may have been in that they couldn’t read again and remember. But they like to see things that belonged to him. They like to tell me stories about their interactions with him, if they knew him.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">I imagine you learn a lot about your father every time you have these conversations.</u>
      <u who="BLACK">Absolutely, because so many different people find the reunion every year, we hear new stories every year. It’s amazing really. At the dinner, I stand up and introduce myself on Saturday night and I guarantee you that I'll meet fifteen new people that want to tell me stories about him and their contact with them.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">That’s great. We’re going to take this interview and we’re going to preserve for multiple generations into the future, so people could hear what you’re saying about your father and what you’re doing now in <date when="2005">2005</date> for him. What would you like to tell people a hundred years from now that listen to this about <persName>Charlie Black</persName> and about <name type="event">Vietnam</name> and his experience there?</u>
      <u who="BLACK"><persName>Charlie Black</persName> believed in the soldiers that he covered. One hundred percent. He trusted them with his life and they in turn trusted him with their lives. I think that says something about the quality of a man. And never once, even though he may have hated the politics of the war, never once would my father have ever said anything derogatory about a man or woman serving in the armed services.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">He got it way ahead of the time, versus now.</u>
      <u who="BLACK">He felt that that was sacred. I remember watching the POWs (Prisoners Of War) come home. My dad had us stay home from school, so that we could watch it on TV because they would do it live then. He wanted people to understand the sacrifices that were made in <name type="event">Vietnam</name> and to get over the politics of it and to understand how special these guys were. I think that’s what I would want people to know about him, just how much he loved the soldiers and his country</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Okay. <persName>Tracy</persName>, thank you very much for sharing this with us and honoring your father in doing this. We’ll take this forward and make sure he’s never forgotten, at least in our archive. Thank you, so very much.</u>
      <u who="BLACK">Alright.(End of interview)</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
