<?xml-model href="../schemas/ddhi.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ttu_488">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Rayburn G. Smith</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>
          <orgName>Vietnam Center and Sam Johnson Vietnam Archive</orgName>
        </authority>
        <date>
          <!--  Date of publication, e.g. for citation purposes  -->
        </date>
      <idno type="DDHI">ttu_488</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <recordingStmt>
          <recording xml:id="primary_recording" type="video" dur-iso="00:37:16">
            <!-- https://www.digi.com/resources/documentation/digidocs/90001437-13/reference/r_iso_8601_duration_format.htm -->
            <media url="" mimeType="video/mp4"/>
          </recording>
        </recordingStmt>
        <bibl xml:id="primary_transcription">
          <respStmt>
            <persName>Mark Steven Varela</persName>
            <orgName>Vietnam Center and Sam Johnson Vietnam Archive</orgName>
            <resp ref="http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/trc.html">Transcriber</resp>
          </respStmt>
          <ref target="path_to_file">https://vva.vietnam.ttu.edu/images.php?img=/OH/OH0488/OH0488.pdf</ref>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The Oral History Project of the Vietnam Center and Sam Johnson Vietnam Archive</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application ident="DDHIEncoder" version="1.0">
          <desc>Conversion from Word docx to TEI xml.</desc>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en-us">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <particDesc>
        <person xml:id="SMITH"/>
        <person xml:id="VERRONE"/>
      </particDesc>
      <settingDesc>
        <setting>
          <date when-iso="2005-11-11"/>
          <locale/>
        </setting>
      </settingDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <u who="VERRONE">This is <persName>Dr. Richard Verrone</persName>, I’m conducting a video oral history interview with <persName>Colonel Rayburn Gene Smith</persName>. Today is <date when="2005-11-11">Veteran’s Day, 2005, November 11th</date>. We are in <placeName>Washington D.C.</placeName>, at the <placeName>Crystal City Hilton</placeName> for the 40th  anniversary of the <name type="event">Ia Drang-Pleiku campaign</name> as well as the <orgName>1st Cav</orgName> association reunion. <persName>Colonel Smith</persName>, thank you for doing this. I want to ask you before we get into some of the details, tell me a little bit about what unit you were with, what your duties were, your assignment was there in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="SMITH">I was with the <orgName>1st of the 9th Air Cavalry squadron</orgName>. The reconnaissance squadron for the <orgName>1st Cavalry Division</orgName>. As squadrons, we had an infantry each troop, which was a company. We had an infantry platoon and we could settle prior to the main <name type="event">battle of the Ia Drang</name> infantry platoons that I ambushed and a major <orgName>North Vietnamese</orgName> unit coming out of <placeName>Cambodia</placeName>. But out job was to provide reconnaissance for the <orgName>1st Cavalry Division</orgName> and the gun platoon also to provide close air support. We were there the first day of the <name type="event">battle of the Ia Drang</name> when the <orgName>North Vietnamese</orgName> didn’t run like we thought they would. (Chuckles)</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Right. Tell me about your commander, <persName>Colonel Stockton</persName>. He was the one over you all. Tell me about him. What kind of man was he?</u>
      <u who="SMITH"><persName>Colonel Stockton</persName> was quite a flamboyant individual and he always said we did that same thing for the <orgName>1st Cavalry Division</orgName> that <persName>Stuart</persName> did for <persName>Robert E. Lee</persName> in <placeName>Virginia</placeName>. But he was quite an interesting character. He would lead you into battle, but when you got back to base camp, he would party with the rest of us. He was quite an individual. Everybody loved it.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">You flew with—were you by yourself in the chopper? Or did you have a co-pilot?</u>
      <u who="SMITH">No, each of our troops—again, I was in <orgName>Charlie troop</orgName>. Each troop had a ground reconnaissance platoon and then an aerial escape platoon, they flew H13s, the little bubble helicopters. We had to lift the aircraft Hueys to carry to the infantry platoon and I was in the gun platoon and we had the weapons aircraft rockets and machine guns.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">So tell me, looking at those days in <date when="1965-11">November 1965</date>, before we get into what happened there, when did it dawn on you all about the significance of <name type="event">this battle</name>? That what was happening was different and what was happening was going to be very influential or at least possibly influential with the people in charge of organizing and running <name type="event">that war</name>.</u>
      <u who="SMITH">It was probably well into the <name type="event">battle</name>, towards the end of the week. You know, we read about it in the paper. I think at the time, nobody understood the full significance of it. Looking back on it, it’s always easy to look back and say, “That was very significant.” But we didn’t really realize it at the time. I think being young also you don’t realize, you think things like this are going to happen for the rest of your life and nothing like that thank goodness has happened since.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Tell me about yourself personally, how did you prepare yourself to go into a situation like that. I mean, you don’t know exactly what you were getting into at first. How did you prepare yourself to get in?</u>
      <u who="SMITH">Well, I just tried to prepare myself psychologically and being the youngest pilot in my troop—</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">How old were you then?</u>
      <u who="SMITH">Actually, I was twenty I think, but later that wasn’t particularly young but at the time most of the pilots were quite a bit older. Of course, I was twenty but I looked like I was sixteen and acted like I was about twelve. (Chuckles) Since I was young and inexperienced—they put most of the young and inexperienced pilots with older pilots, so I flew with <persName>Captain Jim Kidd</persName>. He was an instructor, so I flew in the pilot seat, he flew in the co-pilot seat. Unfortunately, <persName>Jim</persName> passed away from cancer back in <date when="1990">1990</date>. So I look back on the captains, majors, and colonels that I served under and I think of what role models they were and just all gentlemen in a very difficult situation. But to answer your question, at that time I think I was somewhat naïve. So it was later on the next month I lost my wingman in the <placeName>Ia Drang</placeName> and in <date when="1965-12">December</date>, just before the <name type="event">Christmas truce</name>, my aircraft was shot up three out of four days in a row—it was shot up three of those four days and twice bullets came through the windshield. So that was a wakeup call. In fact, <persName>Jim</persName> was pretty cautious, the pilot I flew with. We were the last aircraft in the squadron, there was somewhat vulgar term for it, but we were the last aircraft in the squadron to be hit by enemy ground fire and we weren’t hit until the <name type="event">Ia Drang</name>. You know, after that I would allow that night and think, “There’s no way I can make it.” I'm not going to make this year because if you think of it, how many times your aircraft has been hit, your buddy’s aircraft had been hit. How many times bullets come through the windshield and you think, “I'm not going to make it!” And the way I dealt with it, this is of course after the <name type="event">Ia Drang</name>, I didn’t really deal with it very well in the <name type="event">Ia Drang</name>, but the way I dealt with it after the <name type="event">Ia Drang</name> and maybe this wasn’t a very healthy way to deal with it, but I just accepted the fact that I'm not going to make it. So why worry about it? I'll just go ahead and do my job. That’s how I came to terms with it. Whether it was a good way to come to terms with it, I don’t know.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Well, tell me about your action there in the <placeName>Ia Drang</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="SMITH">On the first day I remember we were out there and we just assumed they landed the <orgName>7th Cavalry</orgName> guys. We assumed the North Vietnamese were going to pull back and they didn’t, they kept coming. I remember it was after about thirty minutes the guys on the ground started screaming for ammo. Everybody was basically fairly new to combat. What we didn’t realized is when you become frightened in combat, you like to hear noise and nothing makes more noise than an automatic weapon. These kids were down there with their weapons on automatic and it doesn’t take long to burn up all the ammo you were carrying. After that I believe they came out with a rule in the division that they had to fire their rifles on semi-automatic to keep from using it. Because they couldn’t keep ammo—supply to them. Then, I remember one day coming back from a reconnaissance mission in the <placeName>Ia Drang</placeName>, we were at <placeName>Pleiku</placeName> just outside the perimeter there. All we used to say, “We fought the <name type="event">battle of the Ia Drang</name>. The <name type="event">Ia Drang campaign</name> said we could get to <placeName>Pleiku</placeName> to find a place to take a shower.” Anyway, I remember the only time I had an engine to go out and we got it on the ground before it quit, we were headed back from a reconnaissance mission on the <placeName>Ia Drang</placeName>. The aircraft started to yaw but we got it to the ground before the engine quit. I remember how good it felt to see those infantry. We called on the way down and they flew an infantry squad in there. I remember how good it was to see those guys coming. Now, I’ve forgotten the original.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Tell me, on the <date when="1965-11-14">14th</date>, on that Sunday you’re hearing about the ammunition problem. From there what happened?</u>
      <u who="SMITH">Of course, we were responsible for resupplying but a lot of times like I was telling my wife, I wish I had known more about what was going on at the time but you know, you’re just aware of what’s going on where you are and even more aware of the big picture. We provided reconnaissance obviously and on the <date when="1965-11-16">16th</date>, we had an aircraft— we were at the <placeName>tea plantation</placeName>, which was closer to the <placeName>Ia Drang</placeName> than <placeName>Pleiku</placeName>. That’s where we flew our missions out of. On the <date when="1965-11-16">16th of November</date> we got called—we were up by the <placeName>tea plantation</placeName> that refueled, we got called back into the <placeName>Ia Drang</placeName> because one of our gunships had been shot down. They’d managed to make it to a clearing and the <orgName>North Vietnamese</orgName> were trying to get to them. So we were trying to keep the <orgName>North Vietnamese</orgName> off of them until they could get the Chinook to come in and lift the Huey out. After they got the Huey out, they had split us, we flew as teams. My wingman—there were two aircraft. Sometimes they split us up and they would put one H13 down low and a Huey up high, gunship to provide cover. Normally, it was one Huey down low and a teammate up high but they would split us up sometimes. This particular day, our wingman had gone off to support for an H13 and while we were down trying to get the other aircraft out. As soon as they got the aircraft out, this H13 <persName>Captain Jonny Gallow</persName> headed on down to the <placeName>Ia Drang</placeName> and we followed him, we were going to go ahead and start a recon mission at that point and support him. We were up high, he was down low. We got him to the <placeName>Ia Drang river</placeName> and he said, “Hey, there’s an aircraft down. Hey, it’s one of ours!” The <orgName>9th Cavalry Aircraft reconnaissance squadron</orgName> had a yellow insignia on the door. <orgName>227th</orgName> and <orgName>229th</orgName> had blue insignia. This one had a yellow circle, and that was <orgName>Charlie troop</orgName>. <orgName>A troop</orgName> had a yellow triangle, <orgName>B troop</orgName> a yellow square, and <orgName>Charlie troop</orgName> had a yellow circle. At the time, I didn’t realize who it was. I didn’t realize it was my wingman, I knew it was one of our—there was six or seven aircraft in the platoon, I knew it was one of us, but I didn’t realize who it was. And <persName>Johnny Gallow</persName>—because we knew he had been there for an hour and a half, couple of hours, <persName>Johnny Gallow</persName> radioed, “I'm going in to check the wreckage.” And thought to myself, “There’s no way he’s coming out of there alive!” So we started making tight turns to try to keep—it was in kind of a clearing and I knew the <orgName>North Vietnamese</orgName> were set up in the tree line. We started making real tight turns to try to keep them occupied and off of him. Every time I could see <persName>Sergeant Rowley</persName>, who was the gunner on the aircraft. He was lying, his body was there beside the aircraft. He was the only one I saw. Every time we’d come around, we were low, I could hear the <orgName>North Vietnamese</orgName> blessing away with the automatic weapons.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">How far away from <placeName>X-Ray</placeName> was this? Is this north?</u>
      <u who="SMITH">No—yes, probably northwest of <placeName>X-Ray</placeName>. I sometimes get <placeName>X-Ray</placeName> and <placeName>Albany</placeName> mixed up, but I guess it was a couple of miles, it’s been forty years.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Sure, yes.</u>
      <u who="SMITH">We were making <placeName>Chu Pong Mountain</placeName>—we were probably, after the rest of the aircraft arrived and we were making gun drawn, we were probably getting a little bit inside <placeName>Cambodia</placeName>. It was on the <placeName>Ia Drang river</placeName>. I can always remember thinking, when <persName>Johnny Gallow</persName> went in there, it has haunted me for the past forty years, I wonder if I could’ve done that. When he went in, I said, “There’s no way he’s coming out of there alive, they had two hours to set up and get ready for.” I can remember—I don’t wear my religion on my sleeve, but I can remember the prayer I prayed that day. I can remember saying—</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">For <persName>Johnny</persName>?</u>
      <u who="SMITH">No, for me. (Laughs) I thought <persName>Johnny</persName> was gone. No, I could remember praying, “Please god, just let me live one more day.” You know, “If you get me through <date when="1965-11-16">today</date>, I'll figure out how to get through the rest of <date when="1965">this year</date>.” Anyway, <persName>Johnny</persName> came out of there. He got back to the aircraft and I guess we were able to pin them down enough—they were concerned, it’s difficult for one aircraft to pin somebody down like that because you have to turn. I guess they were so concerned that they knew we were coming back that it kind of just diverted their attention from <persName>Johnny Gallow</persName>. I met him a couple years ago, a reunion. The first time I’d seen him in all those years and he said, “You know, I never thought about until I got out of there. I never thought about the danger I was in.” I think that’s typical of so many people that do very courageous things. They’re concentrating on helping the other person and they don’t realize the danger they are putting themselves in. But by then, as soon as we spotted the wreckage, we called back to the <placeName>tea plantation</placeName> and they launched the rest of the gunships. When they came in, we marked a spot with smoke and then people entered there. Rockets and machine guns into the area and what had happened, evidentially these guys had been captured after they got on the ground. <persName>Sergeant Rowley</persName> may have been killed getting off the aircraft. But the rest of <persName>Johnny</persName>, at least one of their bodies—the rest of them had been taken out to the edge of the woods and executed. I’ve always heard of target fixation and we’re taught about target fixation in flight school. Pictures of <name type="event">World War I</name>, <name type="event">World War II</name>, pilot gets an aircraft on his tail. He dives straight down to the ground and pulls out at the last second. Because when you’re trying to kill somebody, there’s so much fear that’s all you’re concentrating on. <persName>Jim Kidd</persName> and I, when we flew, both went horrible when we were flying the other one kept his hand right in front of the side click, in case the other one was hit. I realized on one of these runs that <persName>Jim</persName> was not going to pull out. We were right at the tree. I pulled back on the stick on the last second and he said, “Way to go, <persName>Smithy</persName>” and everybody called me <persName>Smithy</persName>. But if I haven’t pull back at the last second, we would’ve gone.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Why, did he not?</u>
      <u who="SMITH">He was just concentrating so much on killing those guys that were shooting at us and going to shoot at <persName>Johnny Gallow</persName>, you know. That’s all that you think about and you lose—a lot of aircraft and dogfights in <name type="event">World War II</name>, they ran into each other.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">So this is on <date when="1965-11-16">Wednesday, the 16th</date>?</u>
      <u who="SMITH">Yes.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Okay. Did you get the chopper out of there? Were you able to lift it out?</u>
      <u who="SMITH">No, it was <date when="1966-01">January</date> before anyone—the infantry went back in there. <date when="1965-11-16">That night</date> or the <date when="1965-11-17">next day</date> the <orgName>Air Force</orgName> dropped a five hundred pound bomb on it to keep them from salvaging anything else off of it, but by then I'm sure they’d taken the machine guns and anything they wanted. But in <date when="1966-01">January</date> they went back in. I think it was <date when="1966-01">January</date> an infantry unit went back in and recovered the remains, what was left of them.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Right. What about the rest of that week? What happened with you?</u>
      <u who="SMITH">Well, of course that night, I remember going back to <placeName>Pleiku</placeName> and going to the club and we were talking about everybody. One guy suggested we fly around the <placeName>Ia Drang</placeName> with a loudspeaker. We couldn’t accept the fact that those guys were dead. Having some drinks at the club and then hitting back out to my area. It gets cold in the mountains of <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> at night around <placeName>Pleiku</placeName>. Outside of the fence, I was afraid to walk back to where my tent was to try to find them, where they’d been shoot. You didn’t move around much at night. So I can remember with no cover or anything sleeping in the back of that aircraft that had been shot down. They had slung over back into the area and crawled up to the back on the metal floor, trying to sleep that night and freezing to death. I lose track of the sequence of when these different things occurred. The thing I also remember about the <name type="event">Ia Drang</name>—for a week it was never night down there. The flares just hung over the <placeName>Ia Drang</placeName> all week. One night, we were flying—we would go up and fly a radio relay. Infantry or somebody on the ground was trying to contact <placeName>Pleiku</placeName>. They would call and then we would be in the air and we would relay the message to <placeName>Pleiku</placeName>. I remember that one night flying a radio relay over the <placeName>tea plantation</placeName> and a Chinook going in, but nobody was killed. I don’t think anybody was killed or hurt. I don’t remember if it was shot down or if it was a mechanical problem. I remember one day, later in the week after the B-52 strikes and that’s an awesome thing.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Did you see this happen? Or you saw them other times?</u>
      <u who="SMITH">Well, from a distance—hearing them and seeing them from a distance. It’s a pretty awesome thing.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Did you see them on <date when="1965-11-16">16th</date> and <date when="1965-11-16">17th</date>, when they dropped on the mountain? On <placeName>Chu Pong</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="SMITH">I can’t remember if this was right on <placeName>Chu Pong</placeName> or further down in the <placeName>valley</placeName>. But we had to go in and recon after the strike. I couldn’t imagine anything living through that. It looked like the surface of the moon, just multiple craters. We were the third aircraft, which isn’t a real good idea. There were normally two aircrafts. We were following, I believe the troop commander was up front. I don’t remember who was number two, we were number three. They were in a bank to the right. What we were doing, we were re-conning and sending back a report on the B-52 strike. The lead aircraft that started screaming that they were receiving fire from these guys on a crater and I could not believe somebody had lived through that. Anyway, they were ready for us. When all of those machine guns are firing, and everybody is screaming on the radio, you can’t hear anything. The gunner behind me was firing and you know the rounds come up and hit you in the back of the head, at the end of the mission, you just rake the spent cartridges out of the aircraft. One stuck between my helmet and my flight jacket and just sizzled.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">It was hot, yeah?</u>
      <u who="SMITH">I was screaming for <persName>Jim Kidd</persName> to take the control and he couldn’t hear me because all these machine guns were firing. Everybody’s screaming on the radio. The round just sat there until cooled off.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">So, were you involved with the support around <placeName>Albany</placeName> and the march out to <placeName>Albany</placeName> in <placeName>that LZ (Landing Zone)</placeName> that they created there?</u>
      <u who="SMITH">We were flying missions and I wasn’t aware of the march exactly. I wasn’t that aware of what was going on. Maybe I was—a lot of times you’re flying and you’re just looking for the <orgName>North Vietnamese</orgName> to radio to the infantry where they are. I remember one day, we were low level and this was a more jungle area of the <placeName>Ia Drang</placeName>, down around <placeName>Albany</placeName> the vegetation is not that thick. It’s a strange looking. Anyway, I flew over and I got a lesson from <persName>Jim Kidd</persName>. I flew over and I guess there was a <orgName>North Vietnamese</orgName> squad or platoon down on the trail and they were with their weapons and everything and the gunner saw them. But when I turned, we couldn’t find them again after that. Because I made the mistake instead of allowing turning right and then circling back, to try to go back to the exact same spot. I’d just made a turn which put me off a little bit. Another thing is—I don’t know if it was the <name type="event">Ia Drang</name> that we learned this or not, all the gunners carried some smoke grenades. If you saw something, you’d drop the smoke grenade immediately and then you could locate the target. Well, what happened the gunners would become excited and they would start firing and not drop the smoke grenade. What we had to do is we started making the gunners pull the pin in the smoke grenade and hold it in their trigger hand. So they had to throw the smoke grenade in order to fire their weapon, that was the only thing that worked. I can remember late one afternoon, one of the—I don’t know which company it was, they were being attacked and they were about to be overrun and I will never forget the company commander screaming on the radio begging for close fire. I can remember <persName>Dick Marshall</persName>, my platoon leader rolling, into the target and firing rockets and machine guns and I could just see the traces coming up, enveloping his aircraft. We started to roll in and something happened with the electrical system, the weapon systems wouldn’t work. So we had to break off the attack and you know you feel terrible and then you feel a little guilty because there is a certain amount of relief that you don’t have to go into that. I can remember the first dead <orgName>North Vietnamese</orgName> solider I saw, I guess it was in <placeName>LZ X-Ray</placeName>. They called us at the end of the mission one morning, on first flight recon mission to come on in and help carry out the dead and wounded. As gunships, we didn’t have much space and we didn’t take care of people. You know we are loaded with ammo and fuel, but towards the end of the mission, we’d burned off so much fuel, you could get about two individuals in the back. I can remember landing there and looking out through the woods. The <placeName>Ia Drang</placeName> was an eerie place, the vegetation and you can see for a long ways. It wasn’t a real thick jungle where we were. To see all of those guys wounded and dead laying there. We took the last two wounded guys and realized in combat when you get hit, you don’t always get hit in nice places. You get hit in the groin and all kinds of places. These guys were filthy, they hadn’t had a bath in gosh knows how long. We carried—my aircraft picked up the last two wounded guys and the aircraft behind us began picking up the dead that came behind us. One teammate began to pick up the dead guys.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">What is it like to take out the wounded? How do you deal with that? What do you do with that?</u>
      <u who="SMITH">To take out the wounded, it’s a good thing because you’re helping them out. The thing that’s really difficult to do, and I remember getting back to <placeName>Pleiku</placeName> right after that. For some reason after our aircraft had been shot up, one of the rounds—we took two hits when the aircraft was shot down and we were trying to get those guys back up. We landed at the <placeName>tea plantation</placeName>. By that time, that started to get mortared. So we cranked up and head to <placeName>Pleiku</placeName>. Once we get to <placeName>Pleiku</placeName>, the crew chief looked in the book and said, “Hey, we are not supposed to be flying this.” Because most of the strength of the rotor blade is in the leading edge and this round had penetrated that leading edge about the third of the way down. So the next day, I couldn’t fly because our aircraft, they had to change the rotor on it.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Did you stay in the same aircraft? The whole time?</u>
      <u who="SMITH">Yes, 621. Not the whole tour, but until at least <date when="1966-01">January of ’66</date> it was the same aircraft, 621. But you asked me, I was getting around—so the next day I wasn’t flying in. So I was walking over to get inside the compound at <placeName>Pleiku</placeName> to take a shower. As I was going over there, these soldiers are coming in piled with bodies. These kids are eighteen, nineteen years old. Most of them not from upper-class families. They don’t own the shirts on their back and they’re dead. I’m looking at them and it was really depressing to think about—to look at them and think about what they had lost, but to think that might be what’s waiting for me. But you know, I can remember they would put them on these <orgName>Army</orgName>, they called them mules. They would load the bodies on those and take them over to the tent where they processed them. You know, you think about when you’re growing up that when you die in combat—these guys, you know, their arms were sticking up in the air and it was really grotesque. Just sad.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">When you see things like this and you realize—you’re a young man at that point and you’re doing very, very dangerous missions in this attack helicopter and you’re closer to your support. Does it make you want to fly closer, fly harder to protect the future troops that are coming in and doing recon for? Or does it back you away? Or does it numb you?</u>
      <u who="SMITH">That’s interesting. I'm not sure.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">What do you remember it doing to you?</u>
      <u who="SMITH">As far as close air support, it didn’t bother me if I couldn’t see the person I was shooting at. Most of the times, you can’t see. It didn’t bother me if he was shooting at me. What bothers you—if you catch somebody in the rice patty or something, occasionally you catch them in the open and they’re running and you almost root for them because you know, that scared you off and you know what he’s going through. In a crazy kind of way you bond with your enemy because nobody knows how you feel back home like your enemy knows. I thought about—I know what he is throwing at me and I cannot imagine what he’s going through because we are throwing a lot more stuff at him than he’s throwing at us.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">What did you hear about <persName>General Moore</persName>? <persName>Hal Moore</persName>?</u>
      <u who="SMITH">I didn’t really know him because the guys that flew the H-13s that I talked about, my buddies in the troop supported him directly. Everything I heard was positive. I mean, guys just really liked him. They were always telling <persName>Hal Moore</persName> stories. One guy, I think it was <persName>John Shant</persName>, landed there one day and shut his H-13 down and was over talking to—I don’t know, this may not have been the <name type="event">Ia Drang</name>, but was talking to some of the guys. Here’s this H-13 cranked up and I guess <persName>Hal Moore</persName>’s flying his aircraft around. I assumed <persName>Hal Moore</persName> was checked out in the H-13, but that’s the story <persName>John</persName> told. He just took it for a ride. (Chuckles)</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">What’s it like here forty years after the fact? You know, being around all the troopers, being around your fellow pilots. What’s it like?</u>
      <u who="SMITH">I don’t know, it’s a strange feeling. I came to the 30th anniversary of the <name type="event">battle of the Ia Drang</name> with the <orgName>7th Cav</orgName> when <persName>Colonel Stockton</persName> was the guest speaker. What really hit me there was for the first time I started to see the children of people who were there and they just wanted to know something about their fathers.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">These are of the ones who didn’t make it out?</u>
      <u who="SMITH">Who didn’t make it. That was—I would’ve wanted to do that too if my father had, you know. Since then, I'm also a member of the bull whip squadron which is the <orgName>1st of the 9th</orgName>. At our last reunion we had the daughter of our troop commander, who was killed after the M-66 before we went home. She walked in and no one had seen her, that’s the first contact. It’s just really an emotional thing, but also it’s different going to the <orgName>1st of the 9th</orgName> reunions as opposed to this because few of these guys I knew, but all of the guys in the <orgName>1st of the 9th</orgName> I knew. We flew together every day, supporting these guys. But to go to a reunion with <orgName>Colonel Stockton</orgName> and—I was the most Junior Officer in the troop and to be around these guys, captains I looked up to and majors, to be equal. It’s just an interesting feeling. It’s also nice to be able to be with those guys and their wives, and not have any pressure. No fear, no pressure.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">That’s interesting. Why do you say pressure? What kind of pressure would you feel?</u>
      <u who="SMITH">Well, when you’re in a military unit, there’s always pressure from above to do what’s right. Pressure from being killed, fear of being killed. Having a lot of responsibility, but then when you come to one of these, you just let your hair down. Besides being on somewhat equal terms with everybody, it’s nice just to be able to enjoy being with a person. </u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Tell me about your reaction to the book? This comes out in the early 1990s and it goes into great detail about that operation there, those three days at <placeName>X-Ray</placeName>. Then, the next few days going into <placeName>Albany</placeName>. <orgName>1st of the 7th</orgName> gets a lot notoriety and still do, now with the movie. What was your reaction to this story being told in such detail, with such high profile people?</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Well, I guess I was just flattered and in awe that I could have been a part of something like that. The first time I knew about the book, I was stationed at <placeName>Fort Meade</placeName>. This friend of mine said his wife was in the OWC (Officers’ Wives’ Club), “Why don’t you come to the club tonight? Somebody is over—” and somebody probably gave the name, “Talking about a book.” So I went and it was <persName>Joe Galloway</persName>. I don’t know if I knew who <persName>Joe</persName> was or not. I'm sure I did because I read about something in <orgName>Newsweek</orgName>. Anyway, he starts talking about the battle. At the end of it, people had books for him to sign. I didn’t have a book and I told <persName>Joe</persName> about <persName>John B. Stockton</persName>. That I’d flown for <persName>John B. Stockton</persName> and he gave me his book and he autographed it. I told him—<date when="2004">last year</date> we had the <orgName>1st of the 9th</orgName> reunion and <persName>Joe</persName> was there autographing books. I reminded him that he had given me my book and he says, “Well, you better hang onto that book. That book is now worth about three hundred some dollars.” I got off track, I can’t remember—</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Just about the reunion being here, being around these men again. I wanted to ask you, how would you like the future to remember your job there at <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>? What you did, but also specifically <placeName>X-Ray</placeName> and <placeName>Albany</placeName>, and that action. What would you like to say to people listening to this years from now?</u>
      <u who="SMITH">I think the thing I would like them to remember most—two things, number one, the guys who didn’t make it back. You know, like my wingman and all the guys in the <orgName>7th</orgName>. The things that they missed out on that we have able to enjoy all these years. I feel a tremendous amount of guilt about that. </u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Really?</u>
      <u who="SMITH">Yeah. The other thing I would like for them to remember is that even though the <name type="event">war</name> may not have been fought in a very wise matter or maybe in hindsight we shouldn’t have gone in there, but our goal was nevertheless noble. I think the war against international communism was a very noble goal and effort and I think it’s not always portrayed this way in the media, but the communists weren’t nice guys and both people didn’t happen until the communist took over. I’ve felt tremendous—I like the Vietnamese people. I felt sorry for them and because they had a very difficult life, a very difficult time. That’s what I’d like most to be remembered. The people, the guys who didn’t come back and the fact that it was a noble effort.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Alright. <persName>Colonel</persName> thank you so much for doing this interview.</u>
      <u who="SMITH">Yes sir, pleasure.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">It’s an honor to do it. Thank you sir and Happy Veteran’s Day.(End of interview)</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>