<?xml-model href="../schemas/ddhi.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ttu_491">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Transcript of an Interview with Calvin Gilbertson</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>
          <orgName>Vietnam Center and Sam Johnson Vietnam Archive</orgName>
        </authority>
        <date>
          <!--  Date of publication, e.g. for citation purposes  -->
        </date>
        <idno type="DDHI">ttu_491</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <recordingStmt>
          <recording xml:id="primary_recording" type="video" dur-iso="27:16">
            <!-- https://www.digi.com/resources/documentation/digidocs/90001437-13/reference/r_iso_8601_duration_format.htm -->
            <media url="https://vva.vietnam.ttu.edu/images.php?img=/OH/OH0491/OH0491.mp4" mimeType="video/mp4"/>
          </recording>
        </recordingStmt>
        <bibl xml:id="primary_transcription">
          <respStmt>
            <persName>Mark Steven Varela</persName>
            <orgName>Vietnam Center and Sam Johnson Vietnam Archive</orgName>
            <resp ref="http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/trc.html">Transcriber</resp>
          </respStmt>
          <ref target="path_to_file">https://vva.vietnam.ttu.edu/images.php?img=/OH/OH0491/OH0491.pdf</ref>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The Oral History Project of the Vietnam Center and Sam Johnson Vietnam Archive”</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application ident="DDHIEncoder" version="1.0">
          <desc>Conversion from Word docx to TEI xml.</desc>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en-us">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <particDesc>
        <person xml:id="NAPOLI"/>
        <person xml:id="DEBUACHE"/>
        <person xml:id="GILBERTSON"/>
      </particDesc>
      <settingDesc>
        <setting>
          <date when-iso="2005-10-12"/>
          <locale/>
        </setting>
      </settingDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <u who="NAPOLI">My name is <persName>Philip Napoli</persName>, I am here with Mr. <persName>Calvin Gilbertson</persName> and Mr. <persName>Richard DeBauche</persName>. We are at the <placeName>Hilton Crystal City Hotel</placeName> and we’ll talk a little bit about the <placeName>Ia Drang Valley</placeName> events forty years ago this weekend. What I’d like to do first is to get you gentlemen to introduce yourself one after the other, even though we’ll focus on one story first. Let’s get you both on tape, tell us a little bit about how your life is now, where you live, something like that. Mr. <persName>Gilbertson</persName>, why don’t you go first?</u>
      <u who="GILBERTSON">I’m <persName>Calvin Gilbertson</persName>. I live in <placeName>Oregon, Wisconsin</placeName>. Little town ten miles south of the capital city of <placeName>Maddison</placeName>. I'm sixty-four years old and married, have two daughters and three grand-children. I served in the military from <date when="1963-12-05">December 5th of 1963</date> to <date when="1966-01">January of 1966</date>. I did my basic training in <placeName>Fort Leonard Wood, Missouri</placeName>. From basic training, we went to <placeName>Fort Benning, Georgia</placeName> to <orgName>the 2nd Infantry Division</orgName>. I did my AIT (Advanced Individual Training) and was stationed there until they changed our titles to the <orgName>11th Air Assault</orgName> and then from there we picked up the <orgName>1st Cav</orgName> colors and we went to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> in <date when="1965-07">July of ’65</date>.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">Let’s turn to Mr. <persName>DeBauche</persName> and just get you to introduce yourself and we’ll get back to Mr. <persName>Gilbertson</persName>’s story.</u>
       <u who="DEBAUCHE">: I'm <persName>Richard DeBauche</persName>. I'm from <placeName>New Franken, Wisconsin</placeName>, just outside of <placeName>Green Bay, Wisconsin</placeName>. <persName>Cal</persName> and I have been buddies for many, many years. I live out in <placeName>New Franken</placeName> with my wife, three children out there. I entered into service, went into <placeName>Fort Leonard Wood, Missouri</placeName>. From there we went to <placeName>Fort Benning, Georgia.</placeName> Spent most of my training down there and got into the <orgName>11th Air Assault</orgName> when they formed that until we recalled over to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">Very good. Why don’t you pick the story up with Mr. <persName>Gilbertson</persName> from arrival at <placeName>An Khe?</placeName></u>
      <u who="GILBERTSON">Okay. What I remember about <placeName>An Khe</placeName> was that they took us off of the <persName>General Darby </persName>and we all got on a landing craft from <orgName>Seabees</orgName> or <orgName>Coast Guard</orgName>, <orgName>Seabees</orgName> I suppose. They took us in as close to land as we could get. Then we all just—we ran off the ship and then I can’t remember how far we either were trucked or we marched, I can’t remember. We went to <placeName>An Khe</placeName> and we set up base camp. I believe that was the <placeName>Hong Kong Mountain</placeName> that was right at the foot of that. We remained there most of the time. I remember being gone from base camp nineteen days without coming back. I remember that seventeen of those days it rained. I think we marched across that mountain once. I remember my jungle boots being wet so many times and my feet got so sore that I was the RTO (Radio Telephone Operator) for Platoon Sergeant <persName>Fred Kluge</persName> in<orgName> Company A, 1st of the 5th </orgName>and the 1st Platoon. I just couldn’t hardly walk anymore, so he pulled another rifleman off of the platoon and had him carry my radio. I still monitored the radio, but I just walked beside him, just handled the radio and he just carried the radio. I remember it weighing probably about thirty, forty pounds on your back besides the rest of your gear. I remember getting to go into town once and I think I had one beer, maybe two. We were looking for something to eat and the only thing we could find was some fresh baked bread and we didn’t have butter or anything like home. We put that and we just ate it because that’s all we had. No more got that ate and then they came and said—made us leave town and we went on helicopters. I can’t remember where we went. I know I got sick and I remember we marched into—I remember going across a stream and it was probably as deep as I was, I don’t know how to swim. They had a rope across and we all hung onto the rope. It was just enough to keep our feet on the bottom. I remember going into the <placeName>Ia Drang Valley</placeName>, from that point that’s all I can remember. Seeing all the dead <orgName>VC (Viet Cong)</orgName> that were already there. The napalm coming in on the hillside. It was just stumps for trees. I remember a big ammo dump there, that we took the ammo we could carry when we left and blew up the rest, as I recall. Then, we marched from that point, we were marching as a reinforced battalion with the <orgName>1st of the 7th</orgName>, I think it was. We were the reinforcement for that battalion. Then we got ambushed, I want to say it was in the afternoon but I can’t remember what time of day it was.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">How do you remember that happening? What took place at that particular moment when it started for you?</u>
      <u who="GILBERTSON">Personally? </u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="GILBERTSON">Personally, we started hearing the mortar rounds coming in and at first they weren’t right on us because I suppose they had to adjust. I remember them coming in and they were spread out through the whole column. One mortar round landed directly on— almost one of the rifleman that was behind me in his column. I remember his name, is it alright to say names?</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">Yes!</u>
      <u who="GILBERTSON"><persName>Vincent Locatelli</persName>. He probably never knew what hit him, it was just devastating. It blew me forward with the radio on my back. Blew me forward and took shrapnel in my legs and little pieces of shrapnel in my arms and back, shoulders. I didn’t think my radio worked, but my platoon sergeant told me, “Yes, it worked. The only reason you didn’t think it worked was because nobody else’s worked.” So I couldn’t talk to anybody, so I didn’t think that it was working. But he said my radio at the end of that night was the only one that was working out of all of them we had in the company. Then, I was rushed off by a Huey, one of the first Hueys that came in. <persName>Platoon Sargent Kluge</persName> got me on that Huey right away to <placeName>Nha Trang Hospital.</placeName> I spent that time there until—I can remember days now, but then I was flown to <placeName>Clark Air Force</placeName> base in the <placeName>Philippines</placeName>. Was there for two three days and I suppose until they got enough wounded in that we’re able to make the trip back to the <placeName>States</placeName>. I came back to the <placeName>states</placeName> and ended up at the <placeName>Great Lakes Naval Air Station</placeName> because that was closest to my home in north of <placeName>Chicago</placeName>. I stayed there, got home for Christmas and New Year. Then I came back and I stayed there for a few days until my papers did get back from <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, so I could be discharged.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">You were ready to get out?</u>
      <u who="GILBERTSON">I was ready to get out. My ETS (Expiration Term of Service) was the<date when="1965-12-05"> 5th of December of ’65</date>. They held me in the service—well, first off they held me in the service because of my wounds, it wasn’t healed completely. Secondly, they held me back for a lack of records. I was discharged in <date when="1966-01">January of 1966</date>.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">Had you stayed conscious through the night as that ambushed developed?</u>
      <u who="GILBERTSON">Yes. I never lost conscious unless it was momentarily with a mortar round. It landed on my chest and probably knocked the wind out of me, I don’t remember that. I know I had awful sore ribs from my ammo pouches were up front and they were loaded with ammo. We took everything that we could carry and I probably had eight clips or more of ammo, but they landed right on my ribs. That’s basically my story, that’s what I really remembered.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">How bad was your leg?</u>
      <u who="GILBERTSON">I had metal shrapnel go right on through, missed the bone in this one. There was one in my—on the side of leg that ended up embedding right in by the bone. I still got shrapnel in my hands, it was in by the nerves and they don’t want to take it out. My fingers get cold quick on this hand, especially this one. I don’t really—if you have any questions that might get something else out of me, that’s fine. I don’t really remember too much more. Like I said, I got out of there right away. So I do remember when I was in <placeName>Nha Trang</placeName>, <placeName>Platoon Sergeant Kluge</placeName> sent me a note and got it to me somehow. He promised me if I reenlisted to come back and help him out that he was going to make me—I never did make E4. I never got demoted for anything, but I never made E4 and most—an awful lot made E4 and E5, but I don't know if the RTOs just didn’t get it or what, I never made E4 but he promised me E4 and E5 strip if I came back and helped and, no. No, I didn’t enlist to go in, I was drafted. Come from a family of men that were like that. Had an uncle killed in <name type="event">World War II</name>. My dad was in <name type="event">World War I.</name> My stepdad was in <name type="event">World War II</name>, he was a prisoner of war in <placeName>Germany</placeName>. Both of my brothers served in two years, they were both drafted in the <orgName>military</orgName>. Both of them were in <placeName>Germany</placeName>. So my brother in law was in service. My uncle was killed in <placeName>Italy</placeName> in <name type="event">World War II</name>. Basically, that's my story.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">Very good. Mr. <persName>DeBauche</persName>, do you want to pick up? </u>
      <u who="DEBUACHE">Yeah. Right from the ambush part is—I was the very last man on that patrol at that time. We had stopped, we had taken a break. I don't know exactly how long maybe fifteen, twenty minutes or half hour. I did doze off because I had been up all night before. When we did get up and move, we no more stood up and I heard all this firing in front of us and by the time I got up there, I see bodies lying all over the place. Mortar rounds are coming in and that's where <persName>Calvin</persName> was at that time. When we did finally cease firing, we tried to clear the zone, so we could get some helicopters in there to get the wounded out and then deal with the next. So we spent a little bit of time there cleaning up the mess after. After we did get it cleaned up, we took all the weapons that we couldn't carry with us and just buried them and we got out of there and went to another zone. I don't know exactly where that was, but we got into that area and we no more got there and we were fired upon too at that time. I didn’t even have a foxhole dug. I ended up in one of the trash dumps where there were all kinds of C-ration cans. So I started digging the C-ration cans just so I can get below ground level because we were getting shot at. It got too intense, so we had to pull back and I did find a hole, a fox hole me and another fella where we could stay in. At that time, I have been given a radio too because all of our RTOs were gone. I was dragging this radio behind me on my foot and trying to crawl as low as I could because the shells were cracking over our heads and I couldn’t do any firing because our perimeter was setup and I was behind the perimeter and I didn’t want to hit any of our guys. But we did pull back into a fox hole and this went on into the night. The fella that was in the foxhole with me got shot in the neck and I said, “Oh no” and it was dark out, “Now what do we do?” They had been sending in flares, all night long they sent in flares. I heard the next day that they had sent eighteen hundred flares that they had shot out of planes and shot out with mortars. It was pretty well lit up most of the night while we were there. Well, my buddy that was in the foxhole with me, I did manage to bandage him up. He had got hit in the jugular vein and he had lost a lot of blood. Luckily, it was not through his neck, it was just a scratch. But it was in a critical spot and they would not take him out of there that night because of the intense fire. He had wait until morning to get out of there. I actually lost track of him, I don’t where he is or what his name is. I lost track of him. As we were getting fired on, we were running low on ammo, so they had called in for more ammunition. They sent a Chinook and ammunition in it and it came landing no more than fifty feet from me. We were under fire. Apparently, the pilot did not see that. As he was coming down, I was trying to flag him off to get out of there, but he got shot in the foot. So he came down pretty fast. At least we did get the ammunition, we were able to have enough ammunition to supply us for the next day. The colonel’s helicopter was sitting down in that area next to his tent, it got around and it blew up, went up in flames. So the colonel didn’t have his helicopter either. That <persName>Cal</persName> doesn’t remember because <persName>Cal</persName> was out the day before. That was the rest of our group. We spent that night there and the next day we got all the wounded out again and then we moved out, went back to <placeName>Pleiku</placeName>. From there, we stayed there a day. Then, we went back to base camp because I was due to get out on <date when="1965-12-10">the 10th of December</date>. Spent Thanksgiving at base camp, C-rations. So that was our Thanksgiving meal. We did get into <placeName>Saigon</placeName>, I believe on the 8th or <date when="1965-12-09">9th of December</date>. We ended up getting out of there, I got back into <placeName>California</placeName>—<placeName>Oakland, California</placeName>, where I came down with a fever of 104. I was just ready to get out. All I had to do was to go medical and paid line, I would’ve been out. It took myself and three other guys, transported us over to <placeName>San Francisco</placeName>,<placeName> Letterman General Hospital</placeName> where I spent four months with Malaria. So I got out in April 2006—I mean <date when="1966-04">1966</date>, excuse me, different century. But yeah, it was April before I ever got out, four months longer than I planned on. Like I say, we always kept in contact.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">You guys became friends?</u>
      <u who="GILBERTSON">In the service.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">In the service.</u>
      <u who="GILBERTSON">Well, he was pretty lucky, he had a car on base and we used to come back home together. We arranged our leave so we jumped in the car and he was always good, he could drive all night seemed like. I could never do that, still can’t. Drive up all the way from <placeName>Fort Benning, Georgia</placeName>. We’d leave in the afternoon down there and be home the next afternoon. He was pretty good at that.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">How did you find one another after you guys were separated from the service? You guys knew hometowns?</u>
      <u who="DEBUACHE">We were about a hundred fifty miles apart.</u>
      <u who="GILBERTSON">Yeah, and we still get together every year, at least once a year, sometimes more. Now we’re trying to get a group of <orgName>Cav</orgName> guys from our company together every year. Maybe only eight or ten of us make it, but we try to do that at least once a year at one of their hometowns. Last year we were in <placeName>Green Bay</placeName>, <date>this year</date> we’re here. <date>The year</date> before that we were in <placeName>Illinois</placeName> at <orgName>Lavender’s</orgName> place in <placeName>Murphysboro</placeName>. <date>Next year</date> we may go to <placeName>Denver</placeName>, to one of the guys. We do it for <date>a weekend</date>, we just try to get together for <date>a weekend</date>.</u>
      <u who="DEBUACHE">We decided to do this every year because of the fact that <date>two years ago</date> we were down by Lavender in <placeName>Illinois</placeName> and two of the guys that were there are no longer with us. So we decided to keep on doing it <date>yearly</date>.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">Talk to me about why it’s important to do it.</u>
      <u who="GILBERTSON">Well, every year you do it you gain more memories and more—like I wrote in a lot of the guys that brought their books along for We Were Young—Soldiers Once…and Young, brought their books along and I said, “When you read this book, don’t just think about the bad times and the rough times in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, think about all the good memories we had at <placeName>Fort Benning</placeName> and since we got out.” So we tried to do that. Want to keep that camaraderie together.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">Long term, what’s been the significance of those events forty years ago for you? You mentioned sometimes your hand is sometimes cold, I mean surely physical consequences. Are there other kinds of consequences? Other kinds of significance? Did you learn things about yourself or your country forty years ago that have stuck with you?</u>
      <u who="DEBUACHE">I think mainly bringing back memories and you know enjoying, you know talking about stories from when we first got in. Being able to actually do this where some people weren’t able to do this.</u>
      <u who="GILBERTSON">I think one of the things for me is—I guess when I was drafted, I said, “When they want me, they’ll come and get me.” You know, if I'm good to go, I'll go. I'll serve my time just like everyone else. I always figured that I needed to do the best job I knew how to do. I think that’s one thing I’ve learned, in life you always try to do the best job that you could do, no matter what you’re doing. Something that you can be proud of and what at least will be—set a standard for maybe your children and other people who might observe. I think that’s probably one of the main things. Learn how to take orders. You better learn how to take orders and usually once you take the order, in the end you can figure out why the order was given, if nothing more, it was to build character and you. So that other people could learn from that. I guess that’s the main significance for me. I tried to leave the military that and I never let it to my mind other than—you know, I never let it possess me or make me negative about life or about the military.</u>
      <u who="DEBUACHE">That’s about it.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">Okay, we can stop.</u>
      <u who="GILBERTSON">That’s about all I can remember.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">Fair enough. [End of interview]</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
