<?xml-model href="../schemas/ddhi.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Transcript of an Interview with Edward Times</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>
          <orgName>Vietnam Center and Sam Johnson Vietnam Archive</orgName>
        </authority>
        <date>
          <!--  Date of publication, e.g. for citation purposes  -->
        </date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <recordingStmt>
          <recording xml:id="primary_recording" type="video" dur-iso="00:59:52">
            <!-- https://www.digi.com/resources/documentation/digidocs/90001437-13/reference/r_iso_8601_duration_format.htm -->
            <media url="https://vva.vietnam.ttu.edu/images.php?img=/OH/OH0492/OH0492.mp4" mimeType="video/mp4"/>
          </recording>
        </recordingStmt>
        <bibl xml:id="primary_transcription">
          <respStmt>
            <persName>Mark Steven Varela</persName>
            <orgName>Vietnam Center and Sam Johnson Vietnam Archive</orgName>
            <resp ref="http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/trc.html">Transcriber</resp>
          </respStmt>
          <ref target="path_to_file">https://vva.vietnam.ttu.edu/images.php?img=/OH/OH0492/OH0492.pdf</ref>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The Dartmouth Vietnam Project</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application ident="DDHIEncoder" version="1.0">
          <desc>Conversion from Word docx to TEI xml.</desc>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en-us">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <particDesc>
        <person xml:id="NAPOLI"/>
        <person xml:id="TIMES"/>
      </particDesc>
      <settingDesc>
        <setting>
          <date when-iso="2005-12-11"/>
          <locale/>
        </setting>
      </settingDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <u who="NAPOLI">I’m Professor <persName>Phil Napoli</persName>, today is <date when="2005-11-12">the 12th of November 2005</date>. I'm with Mr. <persName>Edward Times</persName>. We’re at the <placeName>Crystal City Hilton</placeName> and we’re going to talk a little bit about <name type="event">Vietnam</name>. You’ve got some articles you want to describe to us, and you were telling us something about the content of these articles and how and when they were written about you, so go ahead.</u>
      <u who="TIMES">Well first off, my name is <persName>Edward Lee Times</persName>. I would like to explain the situation of how I was found after being lost for hirty years and <persName>General Moore</persName> was looking for me by my last address in <placeName>Marin City, California</placeName>. </u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">Okay. </u>
      <u who="TIMES">I used to live with my brother before I got drafted to go into the military. But I got drafted from <placeName>Baton Rouge, Louisiana</placeName> because I used to live in <placeName>Baton Rouge</placeName>, but when I graduated high school I decided to go back to my home, where I was born in the Bay Area. I was in between colleges. I was between <orgName>Southern University</orgName> a freshman and going back to the <placeName>San Francisco</placeName> area to get a job and get enrolled in school out there to continue my education. But while I was working, this took place in <date when="1963">1963</date>, I graduated from <orgName>McKinley Highschool</orgName> in <placeName>Baton Rouge</placeName> in <date when="1962">1962</date>. So in <date when="1963">’63</date>, <date when="1964">’64</date>, I was intending to work and go back to school, but I got drafted from local 99 and <placeName>Baton Rouge</placeName>, they sent a letter to my brother’s address. They found out where I was and they drafted me in <date when="1964-06-10">’64, June 10th, 1964</date>. When I got drafted in <date when="1964">’64</date>, I was in <placeName>California</placeName>, there was no sense sending me back to <placeName>Louisiana</placeName> to go into the military. They sent me to <placeName>Fort Ord</placeName>, down in <placeName>Monterey, California</placeName>. So I went to <placeName>Fort Ord</placeName> for my basic training, then I went to my advanced training at <placeName>Fort Gordon</placeName> in <placeName>Augusta, Georgia</placeName>. I did my AIT (Advanced Individual Training). Then after my AIT, they sent me to <placeName>Fort Devens</placeName> in <placeName>Ayer, Massachusetts</placeName>, to be in my regular unit for the rest of this two-year draft. When I got to <placeName>Fort Devens</placeName>, I was in my second year of my two-year draft. Roughly nine months short of being discharged of a two-year draft. <name type="event">Vietnam</name> started getting hot, they decided to activate the <orgName>1st Cavalry Division</orgName>. What happened was I got put on orders to go to <placeName>Fort Benning</placeName> in July—<date when="1965-07-01">July 1st, 1965</date>, to train with the <orgName>1st Cav</orgName> and go to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. We went to <placeName>‘Nam</placeName> on the ship, as I know you know already. My last nine months on the two-year draft, I got on the ship with the <orgName>1st Cav</orgName>, met all these new guys in the mortar platoon. I was in <orgName>B Company, 1st of the 7th</orgName>, which was <persName>Captain John D. Herren</persName>’s company. We proceed to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, stayed on the ocean thirty days on the ship. Took thirty days to get there and I was glad we were on the ship because I got a chance to meet everyone on the ship. At least meet, you know, see the nametag or something. So you know, I had a bonding with all the guys. I learned more about them as we got on over there, on those thirty days. Three days on the typhoon, people getting sick. I told them, “Hey man I’m not coming down there. I’m going to ride the deck for about three days, however long this storm is.” You know, I had my mind centered on—concentrating on what I’d do and how I’d react going on the battlefield. I used to pray every day. I saw they mentioned that in this article here, about how I was staying in touch with the Lord, preparing me. You know, my mind—you know, how to respond. One day seemed like something—the lord came in my mind and told me, don’t worry about the things I was going to do, go through, or see. And I sort of put this in this article. But this article was done in <date when="1995">’95</date> after I returned home. Getting back to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, I stayed in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> from <date when="1965-09">September</date> when we got there, from <date when="1965">’65</date> to <date when="1966-02">February of ’66</date>. I was with the unit, <orgName>1st Battalion B Company, 7th Cavalry</orgName>. After <name type="event">Ia Drang</name>, I started becoming ill, because of all of them chemicals and bombs and all this. Started having some sinus problems, headaches and different things. I didn’t get wounded, but they ended up evacuating me because I was running temperatures and then to <placeName>Japan</placeName>. First, I left of a sick call, you know the company area and we got evacuated to <placeName>Qui Nhon</placeName> where we landed on the ship and they were still checking me and things and they said, “These temperatures are different” or whatever. So I had the congestion and things, and my sinuses and all that, so they decided to send me to <placeName>Japan</placeName>, to <orgName>the 106th General Hospital</orgName> where they were sending all their wounded and guys that were ill or whatever for further evaluation. I was being evaluated with you know, taking blood from my fingers and different things under observation and it ended up stretching in about three months of me being in the hospital. So I never did go back to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, because I only had nine months left on a two year draft when I got there in <date when="1965-09">September</date>. So I ended up staying in the hospital in <placeName>Japan</placeName> until <date when="1966-05-22">May, about the 22nd</date>. They decided to send me home instead of sending me back to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. So I flew home. They didn’t send me home with my records or anything so they couldn’t discharge me proper. But they decided they were going to discharge me, <date when="1965-05-22">May 22nd, 1966</date>. My ETS (Expiration Term of Service) should’ve been <date when="1966-06-09">June 9th</date>. You know, regular normal ETS, but I would’ve been discharged one day instead of <date when="1966-06-10">June 10th</date>, it would’ve been <date when="1966-06-09">June 9th</date>. Coming back from the hospital and all this, they asked me if I wanted to wait on the records or something or go home. Natural me, being under all this stress and still ill, I decided to take the early out. I thought I was better or whatever, but I was still ill and stressed from all this and you know, the hospital situation. But I got out of the military and decided instead of staying in <placeName>California</placeName>, went back to <placeName>Louisiana</placeName>. <persName>General Moore</persName> didn’t know where I was when I left to the hospital. When he wanted to try to find out where I was, he was searching for me by my last address in <placeName>California</placeName>, and didn’t know I was in <placeName>Baton Rouge, Louisiana</placeName>. He was looking for me for thirty years, but this guy here, <persName>Ronald Sisson</persName> lived in <placeName>New Rose, Louisiana</placeName> and he was in the unit. He was at <placeName>Fort Benning</placeName>—well, he was stationed at <placeName>Kelley Hill</placeName> and all these other—he was a regular trooper there. All the guys from <placeName>Louisiana</placeName> used to get around a certain pilot on the ship, you know. I met all the guys from my area. He knew I was in <placeName>Baton Rouge</placeName> when they started putting the book together, We Were Soldiers Once…and Young, and <persName>General Moore</persName> didn’t know how to locate me. There’s a newspaper article that actually traveled all over the country and someone found it, or he got in touch with him or some kind of way they found me. <date when="1995-11-03">November 3rd of 1995</date>, this article was released. You know, <date when="1995-11-11">Veteran’s Day</date> was coming up and this, that and other. And hey, before I knew it, I was coming to <placeName>Washington, D.C.</placeName>, to get back with you know—get back into the perimeter with <persName>Sergeant Major</persName>, <persName>General</persName> and all that, you know, all my comrades. I thanked the guy for finding me, it was a blessing. Actually, I was going to the <placeName>VA (Veterans Affairs) Hospital</placeName> in <placeName>New Orleans</placeName> before this happened and the guy told me that we had a book out, We Were Soldiers Once…and Young, and I didn’t know it. When he found me, I got the book and before I knew it, I was coming to <placeName>Washington</placeName> to get back into the perimeter, from this article. This article tells the story of some of what I went through in the battle and it explains itself. So here’s <persName>Hal Moore</persName>’s signature and all my comrades and stuff. When I really found them for the first time, I decided to bring this article with me. I got it laminated, so it would hold up and stay. That’s the explanation about this.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">Yes, sir,</u>
      <u who="TIMES">When <persName>Hal Moore</persName> found me through that article, he had done the book and my story didn’t get into the book because he couldn’t find me. He wanted to put my story in the book. He, like I said, “Since I didn’t get your story in the book, I want to give you something to do.” Me and him were so close in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, and this and that. I was an RTO (Radio Telephone Operator) for a while with my mortar platoon and for a while. First night in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, we had an incident, it was how he really got to know me closer. When we got to <placeName>An Khe</placeName>, the grounds were still kind of raw. No tents, just clear area, but they still had snakes sprouting around. The first night there, I had an incident with a snake. I didn’t see him or nothing, I'm glad you know if had saw him, I'd probably be dead. But it was at night and it was dark. What happened was, the platoon—it was a thirty-one man platoon. Everyone paired off in the platoon. You had to share the half, and I had one and we had to make a tent together. Everybody paired off and I didn’t have anybody to make a whole tent with. I put up half a tent and my mosquito net and blow my air mattress up and made me half a house. About one o’clock at night or in the middle of the night, it started raining. So here I'm laying down here and it started raining. Water started dripping down through my mosquito net. I’m laying down here, tired, pinched nerve, you know. Carrying four mortar rounds around my back. Water started hitting me on my face and I kind of woke up and that scared me, and I thought about somebody had seen a snake earlier that day before the sun went down and man I jumped up and took the whole house in the air. (Laughs) If the snake was in there, I throwed them off before he could even bite me. But anyway, I was screaming and yelling so loud everybody came running, <persName>Colonel Moore</persName> and all. “What’s the matter, son?” “There’s a snake or something bit me on the face.” I thought he had bit me, but that was water drops. I’m thinking that was the good Lord waking me up to get me off that ground before I do get bit. So all my friends come running in, <persName>sergeant major</persName> and everybody. Shining that light in my face, “Where he bit you?” All of the sudden, <persName>Colonel Moore</persName> said, “Hold up here, what’s going on anyway?” <persName>Sergeant Montgomery</persName> or somebody said, “Everybody paired off in the platoon but <persName>Times</persName>. He made a half tent.” And he said, “Take all them tents loose and snap all them tents together we are going to make one big tent.” They made one big tent, <persName>Colonel Moore</persName> told me to go find me somewhere to lay down and get a little rest. That settled that. But when reveille came around that morning somebody killed that snake. It was a bamboo viper. They called them “two steps”. A few bites and two steps, you’re dead! But you know, my friends were teasing me all night about the incident, but this was the good Lord waking me up.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">But there was a snake.</u>
      <u who="TIMES">Yeah, it was snake. We had reveille formation. I don’t remember the guys’ name, but he killed that thing and brought it to the reveille, straight to <persName>Colonel Moore</persName>. “<persName>Colonel Moore</persName>! Look what I found! <persName>Times</persName> was telling the truth last night, look! What kind of snake is this, <persName>Colonel</persName>?” <persName>Colonel Moore</persName> looked at that snake and said, “My god, that’s a bamboo viper” He said, “Son, that’s a good thing you did get up from there last night, this is two steps!” So me and him got to know each other. Got kind of tight and well, he used to come into the ranks anyway to get to know his men. I came from <placeName>Fort Devens</placeName>, but this started a relationship between me and him, you know. Well, you know, the operations of this and that, and the other and kind of radio for a while you know. I had callsigns and signals and whatever. We had search and destroy missions until we came up to <placeName>Ia Drang Valley</placeName>. We went out in the <placeName>Pleiku</placeName> area. I can’t remember the date, but it was a few days or so before <date when="1965-11-14">that Sunday morning</date> that we went in the valley. We had been on search and destroys here and there for a couple days and the day we were supposed to go back to base camp, we ended up going to <placeName>Ia Drang</placeName>. We went about a week and a half or something like that—I don't know, without any proper rest or sleep or whatever, but we ended up getting surround by these two battalions or whatever and the battle took place. When we first got into the valley, we ended up trying to find out when we cut these guys, you know?</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">I do.</u>
      <u who="TIMES">What was out there in the valley. Then the valley got going or whatever. Me being in the mortar platoon, fired our rounds, ran out of rounds. I ended up in a situation where I got separated from the rest of the platoon because you know I was like point man at a time and we were spread out and the guy that was next to me, he didn’t touch me or called me to let me know they were pulling back. I got separated from everybody and ended up a couple of hundred yards or so. And everybody had pulled back and something just told me to look around and I thought they were still there, and everybody was gone. So you know how you can feel eyes staring at you? I was close to the wall on the mountain then and I could feel that stare, but I didn’t panic or anything. I just got up like nothing was happening because I know they saw all of us coming. I don’t think that the men on that side wanted to attack on this side of the valley yet anyway. So they let me get up and go back to where I came from. So that was fine with me, but as I was going back that way, I ran into fire. Then I ran into the guys—saw guys wounded and all kind of stuff. Then, things started getting hectic then. The battle started getting hotter and hotter. I ended up in the first creek bed. I think before I got over their snipers were about to take me out, somebody spotted one. About to shoot me and shot him and screamed to me, “They’re in the trees, tied to the limbs!” When I heard that, I just spray the whole area. Then, the artillery was getting ready to set up a perimeter. Spot round came over my head, after I sprayed the whole area and he yelled, “You got him!” In the trees or whatever. Spotting round coming through the valley, they were getting ready to set up the perimeter. I knew I had to get out of there. Meanwhile, a friend of mine, he come from somewhere, I don’t know— a guy named <persName>Perkins</persName>. Me and him were there and he was all excited. Battle was just getting started really and he wanted to stay up in this area we were and watch what was going on. I told him, “Hey man, we got to get out of here! Didn’t you see that spotting round?” He was in the mortar platoon with me. I said, “They are getting ready to open up!” As soon as I said that a couple of rounds came over our head and started getting trees out and things. And he had told me he wanted to stay and watch that, I told him, “I'll see you later.” (Chuckles) I started heading back toward the direction, where you know the fire was less. Before I knew it, he was screaming, “<persName>Times</persName>! Wait for me!” Because the rounds were getting closer, they were drawing them in, pulling them in to set up a perimeter and we were out beyond the line of fire. So that is just a part of something I wanted to say. Getting back to these articles. This first article is where I was found when the movie was released in the theater. <persName>Jim Gooden</persName> and I—<persName>Jim Gooden</persName>, he was in the <orgName>2nd Battalion, 7th Cavalry</orgName>. He was a veteran of <name type="event">Korea</name>. So you can see all of his decorations and things. The guy that did this article, he came into my house and talked about you know <name type="event">Ia Drang</name>, he took his notes and did this article and <persName>Sam Elliott</persName> had come in at the reunion of <date when="2001-11">2001, in November</date> after <name type="event">9-1-1</name> and I just decided to put a picture here with him in my belt buckle. Me being the wreath layer with the <orgName>1st Cavalry Honor Guard</orgName>, he was in my house at the time and I just opened up a photo album of me standing with the <orgName>1st Cavalry Division, Honor guard</orgName>. Open that up. (Editor’s Note: Interviewee is referencing documents the interviewer has.)</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">Which one do you like?</u>
      <u who="TIMES">Nah, I'm just trying to get this. Yeah. I have a picture here of where you know—</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">What year is that?</u>
      <u who="TIMES">This was 2001.Yeah, November. <date when="2001-11-11">Veteran’s Day, 2001</date>. I think <persName>Sam Elliott</persName> came into—yeah, I think this here relates to this article when he came to the reunion after you know they had released. Well, when they released the movie in the theater, they released this newspaper article showing that me and <persName>Jim Gooden</persName> were in the <placeName>Ia Drang Valley</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">Yes, sir.</u>
      <u who="TIMES">That’s what took place with this article. I just thought to bring this article to let you see, I didn’t know if y’all were going to have time to read it or whatever, but this is telling a lot of my story of what took place also. You know, I came to sit here to explain to you about what’s in this article.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">Would you be willing telling us more about—you just left us with the mortars and artillery rounds dropping in around you. I’d love to hear more about those days in <date when="1965-11">November</date>, if you’re willing to narrate it.</u>
      <u who="TIMES">You mean the days in the battle?</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">Yes, sir.</u>
      <u who="TIMES">The battle was just developing, like I said. After that incident—when it was setting up the perimeter?</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="TIMES">Well, I ended up getting back to the mortar platoon and we got pinned down and somebody was trying to put up the aim mistake and the enemy shot the aim mistake before he got ahead, I think. I was ammo bearer at the time. You know, I was trained as gunner also, but I got my rounds over to the gun and so much was happening and things happening so fast. You know this was forty years ago, I can’t just pinpoint exactly what took place. The battle was just breaking out all over the place and people were—I’ll say you know, terrified, excited and things were just happening all around. It’s just hard to say you know what I did or whatever. A lot of my friends told me things that I did that I don’t remember now. I mean, you know, when you’re in action you know, you just don’t have time to concentrate and it’s not easy to sit down and talk about what’s what. I mean you know it’s kind of hard for me to explain what I did or where I was at this time or whatever. But the battle went on for three days and it came to a time where we got pinned down and if it wasn’t for the air support and artillery, we’d all gotten overrun for sure. If you want to ask me something, I can tell you something or explain or something.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">Let me change the subject on you. When you came back, you didn’t feel well. You got out of the service in Spring <date when="1966">’66</date>.</u>
      <u who="TIMES">Yeah, they discharge me out of the hospital with no service connection.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">No service connection?</u>
      <u who="TIMES">No service connection.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">Uh-huh. So that’s a little war right there, with the <orgName>VA</orgName>.</u>
      <u who="TIMES">Well, I'm thinking I was alright, so I called myself going back to college. In <placeName>Baton Rouge</placeName> then. In <date when="1966">’66</date>, I caught myself resting through the summer thinking I was okay. I had anxiety neurosis or PTSD (Post-Traumatic Stress Disorder) and didn’t know nothing about none of that. Young, you know, still kind of strong thinking I was alright. So I got back and my friends were teasing me about how I couldn’t play any drums anymore because I used to be a snap drummer in <orgName>Southern University</orgName> marching band. <date when="1962">1962</date>, after I graduated from <orgName>McKinley</orgName>, I went to <orgName>Southern University</orgName> on scholarship from Highschool. I stayed in band until I decided I was well off—wasn’t really able to concentrate on my education like I really did. The first—that semester was the fall semester. As I caught myself trying to get back into civilization, that stress got on me more. By <date when="1966-12">December of ’66</date> I was in the hospital in <placeName>New Orleans</placeName>. Stressed out, chest pains. Just burned out. I put that drum on, started practicing twice a day and going up and down that field that aggravated all that was wrong with me. I went to <placeName>New Orleans</placeName> with chest pains and whatever else I felt was bothering me and told them about it and they checked me in the hospital, but the way I was checked into the hospital was they were getting ready to put me on mental ward. They had looked at my records I imagine and saw I was under all that stress in <placeName>Ia Drang</placeName> and whatever. They took me to the ninth floor and showed me all the cells and this, that and other, getting ready to medicate me with maybe some Haldol or something and put me in one of them cells. I told them I came here with chest pains! So they took me on the lower floor and put me on a bed on the fifth floor and treated me. When they treated me, they released me and started me at ten percent disability. I knew something wasn’t right with that. Started filing claims against it. It increased. But while that was happening, I couldn’t live off a hundred dollars. Ten percent was a hundred dollars then. I decided to try to go to work. Still feeling stressful, burned out. Went took the postal service test. Went to the postal service. They like harassed me through the postal service. Like I said, I got to tell it like it really is, whatever you know.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">Of course, you do.</u>
      <u who="TIMES">Well, I keep a pen in my pocket you know in case I get harassed. Even my union. I went through a postal career of being harassed and filing the EEOs (Equal Employment Opportunity) and this and that and the other. I sort of kept <name type="event">Ia Drang</name> out of the picture and tried to make a living because I had a family. Took care of my mother, the best I could. No one helped getting me home. Tried to make a normal life, but I was still messed up, stressed out from <name type="event">Ia Drang</name>. But I did what I had to do and tried to make it. Ended up with my disabilities not ever being the way it should’ve been in the beginning. I tried to get <persName>Hal Moore</persName> to help me get my disabilities up to a hundred percent the way it should’ve been in the beginning. So I got denied with him back in <placeName>New Orleans</placeName>, at the <placeName>VA hospital</placeName>. He told me to get a lawyer in <date when="1999">1999</date>. Which I got a lawyer, and the lawyer took it to the courts. It ended up all the way in the federal circuit court. Federal circuit court remanded it back to the <orgName>VA</orgName> for adjudication with the veteran’s benefit because the judge looked up the whole case for the thirty years or whatever and saw the prejudice. They ruled the prejudice in the case, so out of the federal circuit court, back to the veteran’s court for final decision, I believe where they correct where the messed up way back there. So I don't know what’s going to happen.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">So you’re still fighting?</u>
      <u who="TIMES">Still fighting for what should’ve been done forty years ago. Not just me, there’s a lot of veterans. There’s a couple of guys here from <placeName>Baton Rouge</placeName>, they’re going through the same thing. One guy, I just found him. He was living in <placeName>California</placeName> and now he's back in <placeName>Baton Rouge</placeName>. He just lost his wife a couple months ago and he never been service connected. I knew you weren’t expecting this but it’s a lot of stuff went down with us when we come back home. They were throwing us away and stuff after going through all this and battling and stuff. You know, I’ve been wanting to tell—well, you know the story needs to come on out. I have a lawyer like I said, you know; he has power of attorney and everything. Hopefully they’ve straightened out this mess because I was messed up when I came home, and I'm still stressed from this. I’ll never get over this. Anyone that is in <placeName>Ia Drang valley</placeName>, they still have night sweats, they have been jumping up in their sleep. No proper sleep. PTSD is something you don’t know how your body is going to respond to it physically or mentally. It’s something we’re living with. All this publicity and all that is fine. I’m glad to see it. Coming to ahead and people are recognizing what we did for our country. But to be denied like we were denied you know, after doing our duty. That’s not justice. This guy here, <persName>Ron Sisson</persName>.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="TIMES">I don’t know what he might tell you, but if we ever interview him or whatever, but the man got malaria. About three days before we went into the <placeName>Ia Drang Valley</placeName>, this article is telling how a guy took his place and got killed. Now he is feeling hard and heavy about that hurt. Because he went in there to do his duty in <placeName>Ia Drang</placeName> and this man had lost his life and place. When he found me, this here, we ended up visiting the man’s parents. He wanted to make amends with his parents, so I went with him. He found me in <placeName>Baton Rouge</placeName>, so we ended up going through this. I was glad to be right there with him. But he had malaria and they never service connected him. I think he had full blown malaria. Now he’s just being—well, he was kind of hard, you know we were tough dudes back then man. We didn’t take no stuff. So this man tried to make a life for himself. Occasionally lectured him. They messed over him, so he didn’t pursue it. I tried to pursue mine. I talked to him about pursuing his. So you know, I got him on the right track finally and he got on the right track but he’d gone to PTSD treatments as I am right now today by the <placeName>Vet center</placeName> from <placeName>New Orleans</placeName>. I mean, we lost <placeName>New Orleans</placeName> because of <name type="event">the storm</name> [Editor’s Note: Interviewee referring to Hurricane Katrina which occurred in September of 2005] and all that but at the <placeName>Harley Davis place</placeName> in <placeName>Baton Rouge</placeName>, I have a counselor that meets me and my group. Then, you know, by us not having a real place because what happened in <placeName>New Orleans</placeName> and they were trying to find a building in <placeName>Baton Rouge</placeName> already so we could have our treatment there because it got a lot of veterans there. Without that connection, like I got with this connection with the General, that’s what’s actually been keeping me alive I believe. Me and a lot of these other veterans around here, it’s the bonding we have. Before our country throw us away the way they did man. It’s real bad. I just hope my case sets a standard for these <name type="event">Iraqi</name> kids coming back here with their legs gone. We look good and calm on the surface and all that, but we been through hell all in the inside, anybody coming in here that you’re interviewing. We’ve been through a living hell and back in <placeName>that valley</placeName>, you know. Other people can tell you a lot of things, what went down and stuff. Some of us can’t explain ourselves the way you’d like to hear. But within me, everything that you hear coming to this room, I was there and a part of it. In some form or fashion. That’s why we have this bonding. A brotherhood. From the general down. Me and the general’s wife. That’s like a momma to me and he’s like my dad because we had a bond. Last <date when="2005-04">April</date>, we had a reunion at <placeName>Fort Benning</placeName>. I drove over there from <placeName>Baton Rouge</placeName>, passed by <placeName>Auburn, Alabama</placeName>. Ended up going the wrong way, just like a spirit sent me the wrong way so I could pass through that way. When I got to <placeName>Fort Benning</placeName>, somebody told me that she was in the hospital on her death bed that Thursday. I called his house that Friday. Left a telephone message. “Tell my momma that I love her and I'm praying for her and god bless her. You and the family.” Because they were in the hospital. All of them. <persName>Galloway</persName> came to the dinner that Saturday night. “<persName>Times</persName>, I got message for you from <persName>Momma Julie</persName>. Said tell you that she loved you and she accept your prayers.” I’m an ordained deacon, working for the lord because of what he brought me out, all this. “Tell him that I love him and accept his prayer and god bless him and his family.” She died that <date when="2004-04-18">Sunday</date>, about 1:30 or something like that that afternoon, I was on the way back to <placeName>Baton Rouge</placeName>. Had a blow out on my <orgName>Jeep’s</orgName> back left tire. About that time felt like something just grabbed that <orgName>Jeep</orgName> and guided me over to an exit. Got out of the <orgName>Jeep</orgName>, check my donut tire, wasn’t enough air pressure in it, tried to walk to a service station to see if I could get a pump or something to try to put some air in it. Come back and the pump wouldn’t get the right proper air in it. Two young ladies come right around my <orgName>Jeep</orgName> and stopped. “Can we help you?” It’s like two angels came to me and said to me, proceeding from <placeName>Mobile, Alabama</placeName> on home. They helped me get the right proper amount of air in that tire at <orgName>Walmart</orgName>. Brought me back to my truck, put the tire back on the truck. Then them young ladies prayed on the side of the road and sent me on home. Just like I felt something wasn’t right though. Had the tire on with the right air and everything. I said, “Hey man, I think I better put my emergency flashes on and cruise home.” Still had enough gas where I wouldn’t have to stop to make it home. I drive on into <placeName>Baton Rouge</placeName>, put the <orgName>Jeep</orgName> in the garage. Went in the house and turned my computer on and <persName>Galloway</persName> had sent me an email telling me <persName>Momma Julie</persName> died around 1:30. It kind of broke my heart because I loved her and she loved me. She loved all of his men too. We just had a bonding that’s forever. It’s kind of hard to go down here to this wall here and read those names tomorrow morning and she’s not there.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="TIMES">Normally, you know, me and him being close like we are, I stand right in front of him, while he is reading them, I be reading the names on the wall as he’s talking. But we’ve been doing that since I been found. She isn’t there. Me and him always embrace after the reading of the names because I want to try to help console him and he consoles me. So he tells me he loves me and I tell him I love him. Last year, we did that, and he just strayed away and walked around in circles.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">I saw it.</u>
      <u who="TIMES">Yeah. I wanted to go hold him then, but I know he was just out of it. It’s kind of rough, you know. I’m glad I was found by him and I'm glad this story got told because I never thought I’d be found. I was lost for thirty years and that really stressed him not knowing where all his men were. As you know in the movies, “I’m going to take you all over here, I’m going to bring you all back. Dead or alive!” I was missing all that time, until this article was done. So I’m glad this guy found me so I could get back with my brothers or sisters. Now, if you be at that dinner tonight, you’ll see how much love is surrounding me. Because you know, it’s a bonding with the kids and all. <persName>McKinney</persName>, he was in the <orgName>2nd Battalion</orgName>, he just died <date when="2005-10">last month</date>. He has a son, his son <persName>John McKinney</persName>. He’s twelve years old, when I’ve been hanging around him since I was about six! So he looks up to me as a big brother. I love him just like he’s my own son. I got a bunch of girls and young ladies and stuff that just love me to death because we have this bonding. I just wish them all well and I hope they grow up strong like trees. But they’re going to live through a lot of stress knowing what their parents have been through. A lot of love here. I'm glad to see the <persName>general</persName> still trying to hold on. I respect all the guys that are here and all that are not here. I just thank god some of us got back here to tell this story. For it to get all the way out.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">Perfect.</u>
      <u who="TIMES">I just wanted to do this and let you know.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">I think we heard. That’s good. I was trying to listen hard.</u>
      <u who="TIMES">I have a bunch of albums here.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">You got pictures to show us? That’s what it is?</u>
      <u who="TIMES">Yeah, I got a bunch of pictures. Me and my momma and my daddy.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">I don’t know if <persName>Mike</persName> can get those.</u>
      <u who="TIMES">This little thing here getting torn up. That’s <persName>Julie Moore</persName> there and <persName>Hal</persName> and the <persName>sergeant major</persName>. That’s like two dads of mine. That’s <persName>Sam Elliott</persName>, this was at <placeName>Fort Benning</placeName>, <date when="2004-04">2004 in April</date>. <orgName>1st Battalion</orgName> meets somewhere every April.  He’s honorary <orgName>7th Cavalry</orgName> member now. <persName>Matt Dillon</persName>. Wife, <persName>Jennifer</persName>. That’s <persName>Bill Beck</persName>’s wife. Here’s <persName>Joe Galloway</persName> and he was just coming in from the airport and we surrounded him coming into the door. All this here is at <placeName>Fort Benning</placeName>. Here’s <persName>General Shinseki</persName>. He came to one of the reunions, I think it was around <date when="2002">2002</date>. Something like that. Lot of love in here. <persName>Freddy Owens</persName>, <persName>John</persName>, and his wife. This was at <placeName>Fort Hood</placeName>. This really hurts me because this dude’s not here. <persName>Jessie Hernandez</persName>.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">You mentioned him.</u>
      <u who="TIMES">Yeah. <persName>Hernandez</persName>. [Editor’s Note: Interviewer and interviewee chats among themselves regarding a couple of photographs]</u>
      <u who="TIMES">Like I said, <persName>Jessie Hernandez</persName>. Him and <persName>Mitchell</persName>. <persName>Mitchell</persName> was standing on the road cheering fifteen thousand of them as they ran by and this is <persName>Jessie Hernandez</persName> here. He’s not here and is not coming. He hasn’t come in four or five years now. I don’t know why but I'm going to have to make a trip through <placeName>Missouri</placeName> to steal him or kidnap him or something. He’s an inspiration to this gathering and everybody, a lot of people missing him. I just wanted to show you a picture of <persName>Jessie Hernandez</persName>. This was a reunion at <placeName>Fort Hood</placeName> in <date when="2003">2003</date>. I just love this man to death. <persName>Bob Barker</persName>, that’s our artillery commander. Man kept us from being overrun. There’s <persName>Jim Gooden</persName>, he lives in <placeName>Kansas City</placeName> now. He’s not in <placeName>Baton Rouge</placeName> anymore. <persName>Martin</persName>, him and his wife is here. But I hate to see him move but he had further plans, but he may be here tonight, I don't know. I just wanted to show you a few pictures of the love that’s—I don’t want to try to explain all this but here’s my commandant. He’s here now. That’s <persName>Sergeant Milligan</persName>, <persName>Kevin Milligan</persName>. In charge of the <orgName>1st Cavalry Division Honor Guard</orgName>. They’ve been in <placeName>Iraq</placeName> for a year. So they’re back now. I'm glad he’s back because there’s a bonding for me and him and his troops had before they went to <placeName>Iraq</placeName>. Thank god they made it back save. There’s <persName>Emile Gunderson</persName>. He’s been going to the wall with me for two years now. Like I said, <persName>General Moore</persName> gave me the honor to put these wreaths out. Starting in nine to five. Me and him was discussing my case here. He’s knows all about it too. I’ve showed it to him. I just hope I get some justice out of it. Because it wasn’t done right. Just pictures of me putting my wreaths out. To myself. Every Veteran’s Day and I'm honored to do it and I wouldn’t have it no other way. As long as I can walk, I'm going to try to do it. Because my brothers, I love them. Those that left us and on that wall. As you can see, all of this is about reunions and <orgName>Honor Guard</orgName> and here’s <persName>General Peterson</persName>, <date when="2003">2003</date> before he left <placeName>Fort Hood</placeName>. In charge over there. This was the 228th birthday of the <orgName>Army</orgName> cake. I cut it with a saber. Couple of pilots cut it with saber. These two pilots got shot down in <placeName>Iraq</placeName>. But they made it out safe, so we were honoring them at this reunion also. I was on the news. <persName>Sam Elliott</persName> in the crowd when he was up here autographing, having a good time. This man’s name is <persName>Maury Drummond</persName>, he’s in charge of the <orgName>USS Kidd</orgName> in <placeName>Baton Rouge</placeName>. We were going into a room to view the movie—well, a film of the <orgName>USS Kidd</orgName> when it was in battle back in <name type="event">World War II</name>. Me, him and the governor of <placeName>Louisiana</placeName>, <persName>Kathleen Blanco</persName>. She knows me also. She’s been to my church, <orgName>Shiloh Baptist Church</orgName>. We have some evacuees from <name type="event">Hurricane Katherine</name> living in our church. About thirty of them. It’s very nice of my pastor to do that, take them him. <persName>Charles T. Smith</persName> is the pastor of <orgName>Shiloh Baptist Church</orgName>. It’s been kind of rough on me, I’ve been through both of those storms. I have some roof damage and things, but it got kind of rough. Went ive days without lights and I have chronic sinusitis and they couldn’t get no electricity or nothing. It gets bad, you know. You never know how the sinus is going to act.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">The mold and all that stuff.</u>
      <u who="TIMES">Oh man, it was rough. But they had people worse off than me, so I managed some kind of way to make it here. <name type="event">Katrina</name> did damage to the roof. <name type="event">Rita</name> came through there. I had this oak tree right in my back window, like out of my back bedroom window and you know with PTSD, I kind of sleep off and on, you know. Something kind of draw me to the front window say about 1:30 in the morning and man look, it was dark, rainy and cloudy and all of the sudden, the sky is clear blue out that window. That was tell me man, a tornado might be somewhere. All the clouds drawn together. I think it was over the top of my house. The top of my oak tree is spun out. Like leaves are still full at the level of the house. But as you go up past my house, the leaves all torn up. The top of the tree got an opening up there. My oak tree.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">Just got stripped off.</u>
      <u who="TIMES">Got stripped off. It was probably skipped. I'm glad it didn’t stay there.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">What do you know? Well, thank you, yes. (<orgName>Laughs</orgName>)</u>
      <u who="TIMES">I believe that’s what saved me, you know. If that tree wasn’t been there, it might have grabbed the whole house! But I was praying in the front window when I saw that blue sky because I knew something wasn’t right. The Lord spared me from <name type="event">Rita</name>. From taking me and that house away. Well, I just wanted to get that out.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">Yes, sir.</u>
      <u who="TIMES">Because you know, all this here is nothing but love. That’s why I wanted you to look. A lot of the guys from the <placeName>Ia Drang</placeName> coming from <placeName>Texas</placeName>. Like he’s around here somewhere. I just wanted you to look at a few pictures.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">I appreciate it! We do.</u>
      <u who="TIMES">This reunion here was in <placeName>Nashville, Tennessee</placeName> <orgName>1st Battalion</orgName>. <persName>Sergeant major</persName> made a trip up there, I don't know if he’s going to be here with his wife—</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">I keep hearing the answer’s no.</u>
      <u who="TIMES">That sounds like him. (Laughs) Yeah, I saw him at <placeName>Myrtle Beach</placeName> in <date when="2005-04">April</date>.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">He doesn’t go north.</u>
      <u who="TIMES">Yeah. This is the Day family; they were over the reunion in <placeName>Nashville</placeName> in <date when="2003-04">April of 2003</date> and she had just lost her husband to cancer. He was in the battle with us, took his life. But when we came up there, we just cheered him up. His daughter, she fell in love with us. <persName>Captain Herren</persName> was there. That’s <persName>Jack</persName> and one of his partners. You can see the love in here. This young lady was the daughter and we just cheered them all up. I just wanted to show you a little.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">I appreciate it! I think we did a good job today. We told a part of the story that needed to be heard. </u>
      <u who="TIMES">Yeah. I'm glad I could do that. There’s a whole lot more that needs to be said. A little bit comes out at a time, certain questions that you may have to ask me to get something out of me. This is how my therapist has to do me now, because some people can’t explain certain things. It just depends on what they ask or what they may remember or whatever. I’m honored to be here.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">So are we. We’re honored that you’re here.</u>
      <u who="TIMES">Just trying to hang on in here and I appreciate it.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">Thank you.</u>
      <u who="TIMES">Thank you.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">It’s our privilege, our honor.</u>
      <u who="TIMES">Glad I could help.[Editor’s Note: Interviewer and interviewee discusses regarding articles, not relevant to this interview]</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
