<?xml-model href="../schemas/ddhi.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Transcript of an Interview with a Narrator</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>
          <orgName>Dartmouth Digital History Initiative</orgName>
        </authority>
        <date>
          <!--  Date of publication, e.g. for citation purposes  -->
        </date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <recordingStmt>
          <recording xml:id="primary_recording" type="audio" dur-iso="">
            <!-- https://www.digi.com/resources/documentation/digidocs/90001437-13/reference/r_iso_8601_duration_format.htm -->
            <media url="" mimeType="MIMEaudio/wav"/>
          </recording>
        </recordingStmt>
        <bibl xml:id="primary_transcription">
          <respStmt>
            <persName>Mimi Eisenberg</persName>
            <orgName>Wordcraft</orgName>
            <resp ref="http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/trc.html">Transcriber</resp>
          </respStmt>
          <ref target="path_to_file">Primary transcription</ref>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The Dartmouth Vietnam Project</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application ident="DDHIEncoder" version="1.0">
          <desc>Conversion from Word docx to TEI xml.</desc>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en-us">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <particDesc>
        <person xml:id="BARKER"/>
        <person xml:id="VERRONE"/>
      </particDesc>
      <settingDesc>
        <setting>
          <date when-iso=""/>
          <locale/>
        </setting>
      </settingDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <u who="VERRONE">This is Dr. <persName>Richard Verrone</persName>, I am conducting a video oral history with <persName>Robert Lee Barker</persName>, Lieutenant Colonel. We are in <placeName>Washington D.C.</placeName>, at the <placeName>Hilton Crystal City Hotel</placeName>. The 40th anniversary reunion commemorating of the Ia Drang Valley, as well as the 1st <orgName>Cav Division’s</orgName> <date>annual</date> reunion. Colonel <persName>Barker</persName>, those days back in <date>November 1965</date>. In the interest of time, we will cut right to that. But I would like for you to make some comments before we talk about those days, about air support, and artillery support and fire support and the role that—which you brought the ideas of how that would function with the Cav and how that would function with troops on the ground. A lot of people who look at operations on the ground forget there are supporting batteries off in the distance, taking care a lot of business. Could you make some comments on what that role is and your personal ideas on it?</u>
      <u who="BARKER">Sure. One of the basics of tactical support through artillery support is to make sure you put a fire support plan together that supports the infantry maneuver plan. The infantry can’t go without some kind of good fire support plan. That includes artillery, <orgName>TAC</orgName> (<orgName>Tactical Air Control</orgName>) air support, navel gun fire if we were in that kind of situation. Up to B-52 strikes, which in this particular battle did happen for the first time. When you consider all the available fire support to an infantry unit commander, there is a heck of a lot of it and this is from 105 mm <orgName>Howitzers</orgName>, which is my battalion, my battery, up to the 8 inch 175 guns during that time frame. During the <placeName>Pleiku</placeName>, <persName>Ia Drang</persName> campaign though, there was only 105 mm batteries available. There was no 8 in, no 175, but a lot of <orgName>TAC</orgName> air and that included, I believe some of the <placeName>Naval</placeName> and <orgName>Marine Corps</orgName> provided some fighter support.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Yes, sir. You were at LZ (<persName>Landing Zone</persName>) <orgName>Falcon</orgName>?</u>
      <u who="BARKER">I was at <orgName>Landing Zone Falcon</orgName>.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Tell me what your role there was. Before the battle, how did you understand what you were going to do and how you prepared?</u>
      <u who="BARKER">I got the order to relocate from where we were with <date>the 1st of 7th</date>. We were at a landing zone somewhat south of <orgName>Catecka Tea Plantation</orgName>. Got the order to make a reconnaissance, aerial reconnaissance of Landing Zone Falcon early in the morning of the 14th. It was a quick reconnaissance as I recall. We went out—</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Who was with you? Do you remember?</u>
      <u who="BARKER">When I made the aerial reconnaissance?</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Yes, sir.</u>
      <u who="BARKER">I went in an H-13 I believe. So just with a pilot and we went out and made a fast reconnaissance and came back. Got a good look at the LZ and what we were going to have to work with. Selected a portion of it that looked like a good place to land the Chinooks. It takes nine or ten Chinooks to move a battery in total, but there weren’t that many available to move my battery in total that morning. We had to be in position, as I recall by about ten o’clock in the morning, ready to shoot the preparation, the preparatory fire.VERRONE: Falcon at this point is empty. There’s nothing there. You selected this. Did you coordinate with <orgName>Moore</orgName> about here’s where we’re going to be?</u>
      <u who="BARKER">Oh yeah. He knew. Colonel Moore knew where we were going to place the batteries and that was not my choice obviously, but probably that decision was made at brigade headquarters and it came down through the brigade to the infantry battalion. But through my battalion it came through to me that we were going to Landing Zone Falcon and that’s how we knew where we were going along with my sister battery, A <placeName>Battery</placeName>. I started moving the battery late in the morning, probably about 8:30, anticipating I would take about an hour, hour fifteen minutes. Simultaneously, A <placeName>Battery</placeName> was going in also. When I landed with my advanced party, in <placeName>Landing Zone Falcon</placeName>, my advanced party consisted of myself, my first sergeant, chief of firing battery, commo sergeant, a gun chief or a canon air from each gun section, I had six-gun sections. I would position them where I wanted them to. We pull my <orgName>Jeep</orgName> and trailer off the <persName>Chinook</persName>. Immediately, it bogged down into the mud. Little did we know that part of the LZ was kind of mushy, marshland perhaps. We were able to get the <orgName>Jeep</orgName> out and moved up to some higher ground. I selected a different place to even land the Chinook later on as they brought the <orgName>Howitzers</orgName> in so we would not bog those five-thousand-pound piece of machinery down into the mud. I then gave the order to my battery executive officer to march order the section back to where we were, each gun section in our previous LZ. I might mention at this point, <persName>Landing Zone Falcon</persName> was about fifty-five hundred meters away from where <persName>Landing Zone X-Ray</persName> was going to be. That’s about optimum range for 105 mm <persName>Howitzer</persName> and we get less range dispersion, less deflection—we never have much deflection dispersion, but range dispersion is critical to us. That’s the optimal range for us to be shooting and support any kind of infantry. We were in a real good position to give them real accurate and close end fire support. As I recall, we got the battery in total by shuttling the battery one gunner at a time, all internal loaded in the CH-47 Chinook helicopters. For some strange reason, to this day no one has been able to explain it to me. When we trained back at <placeName>Fort Benning</placeName>, <placeName>Georgia</placeName>, in the 11th Air Assault, we trained to sling load our houses underneath the <orgName>Chinooks</orgName> and sling load the ammunition underneath the <persName>Chinook</persName>. But when we went to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, for some strange reason, we didn’t have the slings to sling load our Howitzers or the ammunition to use.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">So this is a completed different. You guys had to internally load it and secure it?</u>
      <u who="BARKER">Internally load it and secure it with the crew and all their gear and about thirty rounds per <persName>Howitzer</persName>. That was about the maximum load that hook could pick up. (Chuckles)</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Wow. Did that slow you down?</u>
      <u who="BARKER">Yes, it did. Quite a bit because you have to land the <persName>Chinook</persName>, they have to open the ramp, untie everything, let it roll out and then bring—the way we move our <persName>Howitzer</persName> into position was with my <orgName>Jeep</orgName>. We go over, hook onto it, pull it into position where the gun section chief—where I played out his particular gun section. So that took a lot of time to do that. That’s part of the problem we had that morning in getting into position to shoot the preparatory artillery fire in support of Colonel Moore’s 1st <orgName>Battalion 7th Cav</orgName>. I might go back and say at this point too that the mission I got that morning was direct support, <orgName>1st Battalion 7th Cavalry</orgName>. My battery was <persName>Charlie Battery</persName>. Which simply means that the priority of fire I was to give were to go to—my forward observers were with his battalion and A <placeName>Battery</placeName> was a reinforcing battery and they would take fire missions also from <date>the 1st of the 7th</date> and only at my battery <orgName>FDC’s</orgName> (Fire Direction Center) direction. So at any rate, we got into position. A <placeName>Battery</placeName> was coming in also and they had to shovel their gun sections in also, so that’s what really slowed the whole operation down and put us about fifteen or twenty minutes behind time. I think the book said the preparatory fires were to be at 10:17, it was about 10:30 when we were really ready to shoot. Meantime, Colonel <persName>Moore</persName> and his lead elements were airborne, and they had to orbit for a while. But when we did shoot the prep, we were on time and on target. When I say on time, we lifted the fires at the right time, as did A <placeName>Battery</placeName> and the aero-rocket took over and <orgName>TAC</orgName> air, whatever else was in on the preparatory fires. We lifted and shifted our fire from X-Ray to other targets in the vicinity of X-Ray. There were two other landing zones, <orgName>Yankee</orgName> and <orgName>Tango</orgName>, I believe. We lifted and shifted our fires up to them. Further up the mountain side.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Were you aware that—I know Colonel Moore had seen and did a reconnaissance and there were some Montagnard villagers and tribes people out there around the X-Ray landing zone. Did he say anything to you about that? “Make sure—let’s do this around here. Let’s be careful.” Because in the book he does mention, he says, and I’ve talked to him about this, that, “We were careful not to pour everything in on there because we knew there were civilians in there.”</u>
      <u who="BARKER">Yes. I don’t recall exactly getting that kind of information from Colonel Moore. If I did, it would’ve come through his battalion fire support officer. But I'm sure as I made up my map reconnaissance of where our targets were going to be, as well as fire direction center—my battery fire direction center, we took in consideration whatever friendlies there might be and where their locations were, meaning the <persName>Montagnard</persName> villages. So we picked our targets on likely avenues of approach into X-Ray and along the perimeter and up the trails and further up the mountain side, knowing little of what the real enemy situation was. At my level, as the battery commander, we got intelligence of what we were going to shoot at. We picked trails, road junctions that type of thing. Likely avenues of approach. If we knew where enemy position was, well obviously we’d target it. But a lot of times that kind of information from intercepted communications doesn’t really filter down to battery level. We may get a plot on a map that said, “Suspect location” and that’s about the size of it. We plot that as a target and unload the world on it if we had to.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Tell me about your men who were working the guns.</u>
      <u who="BARKER">Okay. Well, when we left <placeName>Fort Benning</placeName>, <placeName>Georgia</placeName> on <date>August the 18th</date>, my battery consisted of eighty-two enlisted men and six officers. Which was about strength a little bit over. When we arrived in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> a little over <date>a month later</date>, no sooner when we got in country, got to the Golf Course, walked to our battalion position, battery position, I had a man started rotating home. He had <date>thirty-one days</date> to go into the service, but the cut-off was <date>thirty days</date>. So he came in and went right on out. By the time we went to the Ia Drang, I went into that battle with about fifty percent strength. Forty-two, forty-three enlisted men and the three officers and the battery. Myself, the battery commander, my executive officer, Lieutenant <persName>McPherson</persName> and my fire direction officer, Lieutenant <persName>Fisher</persName>, <persName>Ralph Fisher</persName>. Of course—</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">That’s it.</u>
      <u who="BARKER">Well, I had my enlisted men.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Right. Right.</u>
      <u who="BARKER">But that was my three officers and that’s typical. See, the other three officers were forward observers. They were <persName>Bill Riddle</persName>, <persName>Tim Blake</persName> and the third one I can’t recall right off, but they were with the Colonel Moore’s 1st Battalion.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Right. So it’s pretty well depicted in the movie to an extent and in the book about how busy you all got. Had you prepared for or had you all envisioned that kind of busyness? Just firing as quick as you could, as much as you could for such a long time. And were the guns ready? Physically ready?</u>
      <u who="BARKER">I think the best way to answer that question is yes and no. Yes, we were prepared as we went into the landing zone, got all the guns ready and did all that. We had the ammunition to shoot the preparatory fires and we had allocated that ammunition. Later on, I went into the air in a H-13 as an aerial observer. Not only to call in fire missions for my battery, but to relay fire missions for my forward observers with the infantry. About two or three o’clock in the afternoon is when we realized we were into big time battle. Fortunately, the <orgName>TAC</orgName> air and air rocket artillery, they were doing a superb job providing immediate fire support. We were shooting missions for them also, the 105s, my battery and A <placeName>Battery</placeName>. By about four or five o’clock in the afternoon I went back to my battery position from where I was aerial observing kind of south—southeast of <persName>Landing Zone X-Ray</persName>. I could see it pretty well what was going on. Went back to Landing Zone Falcon about five o’clock in the afternoon. As I was getting off the chopper, Colonel <persName>William Becker</persName>, division artillery commander showed up. We had a conversation and he said, “<persName>Bob</persName>, are you going to need some ammunition?” And I knew what my ammunition status was at that point. We were down low on HE (High Explosive) and had a bunch of illumination. Illumination doesn’t do very much for you—for the infantry, except put lights on the target, they don’t kill anybody. So he said—well, I told him, “Colonel <persName>Becker</persName>, we are going to need a lot of ammunition.” He said, “You got it.” Well, he gets back into his Huey helicopter and takes off. Within about an hour, the first <persName>Chinook</persName> started coming in loaded with ammunition. Between my battery and <persName>Alpha Battery</persName>, every <persName>Chinook</persName> that came in would either take half of it or if one battery needed more, we took more, whatever the case was. They had to go back to internal loading. All that ammunition had to be internal loaded. A 105 mm <persName>Howitzer</persName> ammunition comes in a fiber container total, projo as well as the shell casing, brass shell. Powder increments are on inside so whatever range we are shooting at, you take the powder out, put it back together and loaded it and away it goes. So those canisters, those fiber canisters were laid into the bed of the <persName>Chinook</persName>. The crew chief would strap them down. So when they got to our landing zone, all he had to do was open the ramp, flip the tie down clasp. The pilot would raise the front of the hook and the rounds would roll out in their containers, those fiber containers and all we had to do was go over with our little mules and pick those things up and deliver them to the battery position.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Tell me about the first few hours after you did the preparatory fire, and how did that day evolve?</u>
      <u who="BARKER">Like I said, I was aerial observing most of that afternoon, a couple of hours that afternoon. I watched the heat of battle and listened to it on the radios relaying the fire missions. The gun sections were working pretty hard, even at the point. Answering all the calls for fire and keeping it sorted out, which is part of the battalion fire support officer—that was part of his job too. Keep all that sorted out, attack air, air-lock artillery, field artillery, whatever. From my standpoint, it was hectic. It was absolutely hectic. As I said, I knew the ammunition was going to get critical. Just wasn’t shooting battery one round, we were shooting battery three and four and five rounds on target, which eats up a lot of ammunition pretty doggone quick. Again, A <placeName>Battery</placeName> was more than likely doing the same thing. So it was a hectic afternoon. I knew, as I said when I met <persName>Colonel Becker</persName>, that it was going to get even more hectic before the next 24 hours, whatever it was going to take to provide that artillery fire support that we were famous for.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">What did X-Ray look like when you were up in the chopper checking it out?</u>
      <u who="BARKER">Smoke and dust. Just a lot of smoke and dust is best I could say. I had to stay off the gun target line when watching what was going on and staying out of the way of the <orgName>TAC</orgName> air. So my vantage point was to see a lot of smoke and dust over the target area itself. I could see the air and rocket artillery going in <orgName>TAC</orgName> air. I watched the <orgName>Skyraider</orgName> go in. It got shot, to a round somewhere and he never pulled out. Flew that thing right into—that was kind of a traumatic event, to watch that thing go in. It was late in the afternoon when I went back to the battery and realized we were—it’s going to be a hard, long fight.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">The guns overheating, was this a concern?</u>
      <u who="BARKER">Oh yeah. On the first night, it must’ve been around two o’clock in the morning. I was sitting there in my battery command post and my 1st sergeant commo chief. I didn’t hear all the fire mission, but all of the sudden the fire mission became real critical. I heard the fire direction officer started giving commands, “Shoot! Shoot! Shoot! Fire!” There was little time, they were just absolutely—the gun chiefs were loading that ammunition into those <orgName>Howitzers</orgName> one night after the other. We had sustained fire parameters. I don’t remember the details or the numbers after <date>all these years</date>, but we exceeded our sustained fire. What happens when you do that, you run into the risk of overheating your tubes and blowing the seals on the recoil mechanisms. Well, we did that on one of my <orgName>Howitzers</orgName>. This was on the first night, sometime around two or three o’clock in the morning. This sustained fire just shot for thirty, forty-five minutes. As fast as we could load them and put them down range into X-Ray. So I had two gun sections go down sometime around three thirty, four o’clock in the morning. One was from the recoil mechanism when they blew the seals on it and the other one the tube was just overheated. Early in the morning, I’d already notified battalion headquarters of our situation, down to four guns. They had an ordinance team out there shortly after daylight and they brought a new tube and they brought repair parts for the recoil mechanism on the other <persName>Howitzer</persName>. About around noon, one o’clock something like that, both Howitzers were repaired and back in operation. Had all six guns back ready to shoot. In the meantime, you know fire mission were coming in and we did what we had to do with four guns.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Sure. Do you remember <date>the day of the 14th</date>, when <orgName>Herrick’s</orgName> platoon was lost and then the fire missions coming in from Savage to protect them? Do you remember any of that? I know you weren’t apart of that specific—those calls, but you were directing them. What do you remember about that event and protecting that one platoon?</u>
      <u who="BARKER">I had a reconnaissance sergeant which was part of—let me back up, fire support team and a company level consist of a lieutenant, a fire support reconnaissance sergeant and his <orgName>RTO</orgName> (<orgName>Radio Telephone Operator</orgName>). Well, the recon sergeant is a fellow by the name of <orgName>Sergeant Brown</orgName>, E-5 and he was with that cut off platoon. I remember his call for fires, I remember what we did. We knew exactly from our fire charge were that platoon was. Every time you know in fire direction, we put a pin on the chart where that target is. So we knew around that platoon is where he built the fire support, the artillery fire support to protect them. That’s about all I can remember, except that when I think about the fire direction chart in my battery fire direction center where X-Ray was, where this cut off platoon was. We didn’t have to move that pin very much to change the range and deflection to shoot that artillery. By the time that was all over, that pin was a pretty good size. But that’s—they were very close together. A lot of ammunition went down range. In the period of <date>about three days</date>, over four thousand rounds. That’s phenomenal for a 105 battery to be able to shoot that much ammunition.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Would you say your busiest time was the morning of the 15th?</u>
      <u who="BARKER">The first busy time was in that morning of the 15th. About two to four in the morning and then again early in the morning. The rest of the day it was constant during daytime hours. The second night, we fired a lot of illumination, but we also fired a lot of HE, high explosive, along with some white phosphorus and with variable time fuse and time fuse. It got hectic again that second night. We put a lot of rounds down range the night of the 15th, and 16th. Then again, during the daytime, during the 16th it was steady. We were not lollygagging around having a good time, smoking and joking—it got a little serious. My gun crews, as I said earlier were—we were down about fifty percent strength. Gun chief, gunner, system gunner and a couple of cannoneers on each gun. They got very little rest. None of us got very much rest at all. When you had a chance to rest, you got it and so did they. About the 17th, we were pretty—even though we weren’t in X-Ray or in <placeName>Albany</placeName> later on, those gun crews did a magnificent job.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">A lot of people have said that the fire you all supplied from <orgName>Falcon</orgName> saved <date>the day</date> in a number of ways. You have a lot of elements coming in to take care of things and on <date>the second day</date> of the “Broken Arrow” call, where you had a lot of air support. Looking back at it now, <date>forty years later</date>, how vital was your role from <orgName>Falcon</orgName>? And now that you’ve kind of had a chance to look and analyze and see all the different pieces on the ground. I know you found that out later during <date>1965</date>, but people I'm not sure they understand the importance of what you all did during the that battle. You weren’t there at X-Ray, but you had people on the ground for you, and you were above. But what can you say about the significance of this artillery fire and your boys who did it? </u>
      <u who="BARKER">Yeah. Literally, a steel curtain if you will and that’s what we did. We knew the significance of what was going on in X-Ray, didn’t take long to figure it out.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">I was going to ask you, when did you all sense that this is not only big, this is very significant what’s happening? </u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Probably afternoon. About two o’clock, one o’clock in the afternoon of the 14th, my forward observer with Captain <persName>Nadal</persName>’s company, shot in the first hour or so. Killed in action. When that word came back through from the battalion <orgName>O&amp;O</orgName>, it shocked me as did my first sergeant. Had a First Sergeant by the name of <persName>Charlie Sanford</persName>. Probably the oldest man in the division when we rotated over there, when we deployed. <date>Fifty-five years old</date>. He had a certain aura about him that he had a great relationship with the young lieutenants and heck, I was only a <date>twenty-eight year old</date> captain. But with the young lieutenants who are only six years younger than me for the most part, he had that fatherly instinct. That father-son relationship. Loved those boys. <persName>Tim Blake</persName> was killed in the first hour of combat. That got my attention, as did him and everybody else. By that time, we were listening and obviously hearing the fire listening—monitoring their command net of <date>the 1st of the 7th</date> that knew generally what was going on, but it was going to be a heck of a fight. That was really the first time, when he was <orgName>KIA</orgName> (Killed in Action). When <persName>Tim</persName> was <orgName>KIA</orgName>, I got a feeling it was going to be a long struggle. A hard fight. That was a shocker. No one wants to lose the first man in combat, but that was the first. Lieutenant <persName>Tim Blake</persName> was the first causality, <orgName>KIA</orgName> out of my battery and I don’t choose to make that as a distinction, but it just happened that way. It’s a part of history and a part of this battle and never will forget it.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Yes, sir. Tell me about Colonel Moore during <date>those days</date>, what do you remember about him?</u>
      <u who="BARKER">Dynamic person. When we trained at <placeName>Fort Benning</placeName>, <placeName>Georgia</placeName>, I was his battalion fire support officer. Another name for it, battalion <orgName>L&amp;O (Law and Order</orgName>) back then. I lived and slept for those guys in the field while we were training air assault tactics and techniques up in the <placeName>Carolinas</placeName> and around <placeName>Fort Benning</placeName> and so forth. So I became very well acquainted with him and his staff. Knew his company commanders and one of the company commanders, <persName>John Herren</persName>, he and I had served together in <placeName>Germany</placeName> previously. So I built that relationship with him as a battalion fire support officer, along with my liaison sergeant. I’d been invited to Colonel Moore’s house, to battalion functions, officer’s functions on occasion. So that’s the kind of relationship I had with Colonel Moore. He never developed his maneuver plan without having me present to develop that fire support plan which included the <orgName>TAC</orgName> air, the artillery, the navel gun fire if that was the case. At that time, we were training, we had some armed <orgName>Mohawks</orgName>, gunships, air cavalry, the whole bit. Obviously, that was my job and I established that relationship with him and his staff. So when I became a battery commander, I didn’t see much more of Colonel Moore at that point. It just wasn’t the way it went. But he knew who I was, and he knew who was commanding which battery and who was going to be his direct support. So I carried that relationship with him <date>all these years</date>, especially very important back then. When you have that kind of relationship, and you develop those kind of leadership techniques that he employed, I can remember seeing him as he was planning for an operation. Whether it was the real, whether it was a training mission at <placeName>Fort Benning</placeName>, <placeName>Georgia</placeName>, or even on a couple occasions in his operation tent, he would sit there and look at that map and you could just mentally see him going through the courses of action that he could take and develop his maneuver plan. I can’t explain forever how much I think of that man. So when they went into battle, that relationship carried on and it wasn’t hard to put all that ammunition down range in support of his unit.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Mm-hmm. What’s it been here <date>forty years later</date>, almost to the day of those battles? How is it <date>today</date> for you looking back and being with all these men?</u>
      <u who="BARKER">(Chuckles) I go a little bit crazy. No I—</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Can you clarify that?</u>
      <u who="BARKER">Well, it all starts in <date>late October</date>, first of <date>November</date>. As we were getting ready to go out there from An <orgName>Khe</orgName>. You start thinking about those days and come back leading up to, when we deployed from An <persName>Khe</persName> up to the valley out to <placeName>Pleiku</placeName> and the tea plantation so forth. I suppose <date>yesterday</date> making that walk down in front of the wall meant a lot to me. Very moving experience, but it’s that way with me every time I come for this, come here for our reunion and especially when we go to the wall. Knowing that we didn’t bring everybody back. But when you have a man like General <persName>Moore</persName> leading you down that long path in front of that wall, the feeling of admiration, of desire to still do the best you can to support the man. <date>Forty years later</date>, and you think about those men that aren’t with us anymore. A lot goes on in your mind and in my mind. I look at my family. I might add, on <date>the 19th of November</date>, and this is after <placeName>Albany</placeName>, got a letter from my wife <date>about a month</date> beforehand and she said, “Well, you’re going to have a baby on <date>the 19th of November</date>.” I didn’t know it was going to be a daughter, nobody knew back then. Well, I got orders that morning of the 19th to move the battery from <orgName>Falcon</orgName> to <persName>LZ Crooks</persName>, with the 2nd of the 5th Cavalry. And in the move, I knew <date>the 19th</date> was coming, I knew she was going to be in the hospital. Going to have that baby. The remainder of the battalion, my battery was detached from my parent battalion, the 21st <persName>Field Artillery</persName> and attached to the 1st <orgName>Battalion 77th Artillery</orgName>, who was a direct support of the 2nd Brigade. <orgName>The 3rd Brigade</orgName> was going back to An <orgName>Khe</orgName>, the 2nd Brigade was coming out to take over the operation. So I was moved over to Crooks to the 2nd of the 5th Cavalry, to fire direct support artillery fire for them. You know, when you’re good, you’re good, you get all those wonderful choice assignments. The rest of the battalion goes back, you get to stay here and have a good time some more. We had to move obviously all the battery in four, five thousand—105 <persName>mm</persName> canisters had to be moved too. We got all of those moved over there. Out of Falcon, close to <orgName>the Landing Zone Crooks</orgName>. I still had no idea whether I was a father again the third time or just exactly what was going on. <orgName>The Red Cross</orgName> had the mission of getting information like that, births out to the troops. Well, we were out in the middle of nowhere.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">And this is conscious? You’re thinking and thinking and thinking about this?</u>
      <u who="BARKER">Oh yeah, sure I was thinking, “What’s going on?” I was trying to get through the communications channel back to An <orgName>Khe</orgName> to find out just how she was and what had happened. It didn’t happen that way. On <date>Tuesday</date> before <date>Thanksgiving</date>, I don’t remember the exact date or <date>what year</date>. But it was the <date>Tuesday</date> before <date>Thanksgiving</date>, I got the order to leave <persName>Landing Zone Crooks</persName> and return to <placeName>Pleiku</placeName> and go back to An <orgName>Khe</orgName>. A Battery of the 77th <persName>Field Artillery</persName> was coming in to replace my battery. The battery commander was a guy by the name of <persName>Neil Crocker</persName>, who is a close friend of mine, we’d been to the career course together. Captain <persName>Neil Crocker</persName> gets off that <persName>Chinook</persName> with his advanced party and I hug his neck and said, “Hey man! Am I glad to see you! And by the way, would you take care of the four, five thousand brass canisters and back haul those for me?” To <date>this day</date>, he has never forgiven me for leaving him those four. But he did it, I moved my battery back to <placeName>Pleiku</placeName> and we spent the night there and the next morning. We hooked them up behind the <orgName>Howitzers</orgName>, behind <date>two and a</date> half ton trucks and road marched back to An <orgName>Khe</orgName>. Got in there late in the afternoon, mail was stacked this deep for the troops. We hadn’t had any, we’d been out there over <date>two weeks</date> again. There was a letter from my mother, and she said, “You have a baby daughter. Mother and daughter are fine.” Hour or so later here comes a <orgName>Red Cross</orgName> guy carrying his telegraph. “Hey, I got some good news!” I said, “Little bit late.” That’s just a little bit of the personal things.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">The letter got there before the <orgName>Red Cross</orgName> order.</u>
      <u who="BARKER">Letter got there before the <orgName>Red Cross</orgName> guy did. That’s from <date>the 19th of November</date> to the <date>Wednesday</date> before thanksgiving that was only four, <date>five days</date>. <date>Six days</date> the most.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">That’s interesting, when all this was going on there in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, you’re becoming a dad again for the third time, and you have that memory connected with this battle. Well, looking into the future, people listening to this a hundred years from now. What would you like them to know about you, <persName>LZ Falcon</persName>, this battle, the men you commanded?</u>
      <u who="BARKER">I think I would like for people to know that the troops is what make you. My cannoneers, my guy section chiefs, our fire direction center, the forward observers. You know, I just happened to be the battery commander. Yes, I had the leadership techniques and all that good stuff, and they followed my orders. But those men is what made me. Those men made that battery, not me. Those guys dedicated as they were, professional from the moment we hit the ground in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, till the time we all left. I would like to say that those men deserve a lot more credit than I do as battery commander. Heck, I just commanded a battery! I don’t have to load those 105, those forty-five pound projos. Hour after hour, minute after minute, day after day. All I have to do is to look back and make sure that they had the ammunition and the people to do that job. That was my job. I never did obviously, but those men are the ones that did what I asked them to do. Back then, nobody talked about loving their fellow man. That was not the manly thing to do. You just never said it. But I got to tell you, General <persName>Moore</persName> had it right when he said, “Love your men.” And he just said that recently. So as I look back, that’s probably—I probably love those men, but I couldn’t stand there and say “Hey, I love you.” Go out and do this job, you know? But that’s what he really meant.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">But you can now?</u>
      <u who="BARKER">Oh yeah. Oh yeah.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Okay. Well, I have stop the interview now, thank you very much Colonel <persName>Barker</persName>.</u>
      <u who="BARKER">My pleasure, sir.(End of interview)</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
