<?xml-model href="../schemas/ddhi.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ttu_496">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Transcript of an Interview with Yvonne Guidroz</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>
          <orgName>Vietnam Center and Sam Johnson Vietnam Archive</orgName>
        </authority>
        <date>
          <!--  Date of publication, e.g. for citation purposes  -->
        </date>
        <idno type="DDHI">ttu_496</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <recordingStmt>
          <recording xml:id="primary_recording" type="video" dur-iso="00:16:53">
            <!-- https://www.digi.com/resources/documentation/digidocs/90001437-13/reference/r_iso_8601_duration_format.htm -->
            <media url="https://vva.vietnam.ttu.edu/images.php?img=/OH/OH0496/OH0496.mp4" mimeType="video/mp4"/>
          </recording>
        </recordingStmt>
        <bibl xml:id="primary_transcription">
          <respStmt>
            <persName>Mark Steven Varela</persName>
            <orgName>Vietnam Center and Sam Johnson Vietnam Archive</orgName>
            <resp ref="http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/trc.html">Transcriber</resp>
          </respStmt>
          <ref target="path_to_file">https://vva.vietnam.ttu.edu/images.php?img=/OH/OH0496/OH0496.pdf</ref>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The Oral History Project of the Vietnam Center and Sam Johnson Vietnam Archive</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application ident="DDHIEncoder" version="1.0">
          <desc>Conversion from Word docx to TEI xml.</desc>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en-us">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <particDesc>
        <person xml:id="VERRONE"/>
        <person xml:id="KONRARDY"/>
        <person xml:id="SAMMONS"/>
        <person xml:id="GUIDROZ"/>
      </particDesc>
      <settingDesc>
        <setting>
          <date when-iso="2005-11-12"/>
          <locale/>
        </setting>
      </settingDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <u who="VERRONE">This is <persName>Dr. Richard Verrone</persName>, I am doing a video oral history interview, it is <date when="2005-11-12">November 12th, 2005</date>. We are in <placeName>Washington D.C.</placeName>, at the <placeName>Crystal City Hilton</placeName>. We are here commemorating the 40th anniversary of the <name type="event">battle of the Ia Drang Valley</name>, <placeName>Pleiku</placeName>, <placeName>LZ (Landing Zone) Falcon</placeName>, <placeName>LZ X-Ray</placeName>, and <placeName>LZ Albany</placeName>. So if you all please introduce yourselves and tell me why you’re here and who you want to talk about today.</u>
      <u who="GUIDROZ">My name is <persName>Yvonne Guidroz</persName> and my uncle was  <persName> Sergeant Ronnie T. Mathis</persName> and he was killed at <placeName>LZ Albany</placeName> on <date when="1965-11-17">November 17th, 1965</date>.</u>
      <u who="SAMMONS">And I am <persName>Sergeant Mathis</persName>’ sister, <persName>Glenda Sammons</persName>. We—I guess that’s all I need to say, you said everything else. (Chuckles)</u>
      <u who="KONRARDY">I am <persName>Bob Konrardy</persName>, I was a platoon leader and <persName>Ronnie</persName> was my RTO (Radio Telephone Operator). This is with <orgName>A Company</orgName>, <orgName>1st of the 5th</orgName>.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Tell me about <persName>Ronnie</persName>, what was he like? What was his personality like? I know you all can probably comment from different angles.</u>
      <u who="GUIDROZ">He was like a brother to me. Very playful, he was my best friend actually. When my mother and father divorced, we moved in back with my grandparents and <persName>Ronnie</persName>. He was about thirteen years older than me. So I’ve known him since I was an infant. I grew up with him in my life, so he was a major part of my life. My grandfather left when I was about six years old and he was the man in my life. Very important person in my life.</u>
      <u who="SAMMONS">Well, we were very close growing up. I had an older sister, but it seemed that he and I were the closest. We had a wonderful relationship he and I. We spent a lot of time together. He was very easy going, pleasant, wonderful personality.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Do you know his thoughts about his service to the country and what he thought about going to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="SAMMONS">Very dedicated. As a matter of fact, he had the opportunity to—when he first went into the <orgName>army</orgName>, he was drafted. He spent his two years, but then when time came for him to get out, his decision was to reenlist, and his plan was to make a career out of the <orgName>army</orgName>.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Sergeant, would you like to talk about what you knew of <persName>Ronnie</persName>?</u>
      <u who="KONRARDY">Well, like I said <persName>Ronnie</persName> was my radio operator. But for me and to me he was more of a mother hen. I think he was two years older than I was, but he acted like he was thirty. I can give you some examples.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Please.</u>
      <u who="KONRARDY">One night we had some hot dogs and mashed potatoes flown in because we were supplied every night with choppers and out of the whole platoon, were out in the middle of nowhere, I got deathly sick. I was throwing up and everything, and we always take turns, one guy sleeps, one guy watches. So I crawled back into the perimeter and I go to take our watch. <persName>Ronnie</persName> and I share the same foxhole because if I needed the radio, he was there. So he says, “You take first watch, I’ll wake you up when it’s your turn.” He never woke me up. I get up in the morning, I said, “Why didn’t you wake me?” He said, “You were sick, you needed your sleep.” There was another time just before we went into <placeName>Ia Drang</placeName>, we heard the firefight from where we were, so all of us stayed up all night, none of us went to sleep that night. So we’re all deadly tired already.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">This was what? <date when="1965-11-14">Sunday night the 14th</date>?</u>
      <u who="KONRARDY">This is the <date when="1965-11-13">day before</date> we flew into <placeName>X-Ray</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Before you guys went to <placeName>X-Ray</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="KONRARDY">Yeah. The <date when="1965-11-13">day before</date> <name type="event">X-Ray</name>, we were supposed to go back to base camp. So we took all of our ammunition, extra ammunition and buried it. Filled in our foxholes and waited for the choppers to come to pick us up and take us back to our base camp. So we had three days off. The choppers never came. So late in the afternoon they called us up and said “We can’t pick you up you up. Dig all of your ammunition out and dig your foxholes, you’re spending the night there. So the <date when="1965-11-14">next morning</date> was when we went into <placeName>X-Ray</placeName> and the noise we were was the <orgName>7th Cav</orgName> getting hit. So everybody stayed awake that night. So in the morning we were waiting for the choppers again to take us out and they told <persName>Ronnie</persName> it would probably be two or three hours, so he grabbed six or seven guys and found a little thicket off to the side. He said, “Lieutenant, you need some sleep. You want to go over there?” “I can’t do that.” He says “You need to get some sleep in case you have to lead us out of here. One of us has to be able to think.” And that’s how he was like for me all the time.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Wow. So you all were going to be positioned at <placeName>Falcon</placeName> is that correct?</u>
      <u who="KONRARDY">No, we were—we went into <placeName>X-Ray</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="SAMMONS">You were like backup, weren’t you?</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">The reserve.</u>
      <u who="KONRARDY"><orgName>7th Cav</orgName>—I got hit the <date when="1965-11-14">first day</date>. We went into the <date when="1965-11-15">second day</date> as reinforcements.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">What was it like? What did you see? What was that battlefield like when you arrived on the <date when="1965-11-15">15th</date>?</u>
      <u who="KONRARDY">Well, there was <orgName>Viet Cong</orgName> bodies everywhere. There was Americans still not picked up yet because we got in fairly early. The smell already was bad, there was flies. We went to our perimeter and we took one section of it and we had to pull back so that the platoon that was still there could take their dead out of the foxholes, so we could take them over. We walk into a perimeter that had already been hit hard before. So that was a strange feeling. Just wondering, what did they do wrong? Could have they done something different? Can we do something different?</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">What was <persName>Ronnie</persName> like? What was his attitude there once you guys got on the ground in the middle of that fight?</u>
      <u who="KONRARDY">He always was on my right-hand sight so if needed a radio, it’d be like this. And his attitude was he’s getting me home. We didn’t get personal often, even though we lived together for—24/7, but he did show me a picture of his wife and his little girl one night. This was just before <name type="event">X-Ray</name>. You kind of get afraid to talk about personal things. You don’t want to get too attached, but yet since he had to be with me all the time, in case I needed the radio, we accidentally too attached.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">(Chuckles) Accidentally. When you go through something like the <name type="event">X-Ray campaign</name> and what happened there, those three days I can only imagine that you get tighter because you’re still relying on each other. Tell me about what your platoon did. You get there on the <date when="1965-11-15">15th</date> and you’re there through the night, I assume, to the <date when="1965-11-16">16th</date>. </u>
      <u who="KONRARDY">Yes.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">What happened on the <date when="1965-11-16">16th</date>?</u>
      <u who="KONRARDY">The morning of the <date  when="1965-11-16">16th</date>, we had to go out and check some of the bodies to see if we could find any identification papers, anything pertinent.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">The enemy bodies?</u>
      <u who="KONRARDY">The enemy bodies, yeah. So we did that and we started to move out to <placeName>Albany</placeName>. Our platoon, <orgName>A Company</orgName> was the last company in the column. Our platoon was the last platoon. So we were way in the tail end.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Yes, with <persName>Captain Forrest</persName>.</u>
      <u who="KONRARDY">With <persName>Captain Forrest</persName>. So late, late morning the column stopped. So right away we put out our security and <persName>Captain Forrest</persName> went up front. Couple of minutes later, we started getting mortared. We thought that our own people were doing that because they didn’t realize we were spread out so far. So <persName>Ronnie</persName> calls up to find out and tell them to stop the friendly fire and we found out that it wasn’t ours. Right after he had said that, then everything exploded all around us. I ended up getting hit with the mortars. I couldn’t walk, I got hit in the back and in the side. Mentally, I was gone and physically, I could barely move. So <persName>Ronnie</persName> puts me on a poncho and he should’ve been protecting himself, but he put me in a poncho and called three other guys over. The four guys would pick up the poncho and carry me and drag me into the next safe area, while they would fight the enemy, they picked me up and dragged me again. I fell out of the poncho about four, five, six times because it was so bloody. I kind of laughed, but they were dead serious. I had no sense of reality. I'm guessing this went on for hours, at least hour and a half. I lost track of time. But if those four people hadn’t picked me up and carried me all that while until we established a landing zone, I wouldn’t have made it. Then <persName>Ronnie</persName> went back to our platoon after he knew I was safe, and <persName>Ronnie</persName> did not make it.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Did you know what happened to him? This is after the fact.</u>
      <u who="KONRARDY">Everybody was detached because when they hit us, they just spread us all over. Since we were the last element, we were completely detached. So what had happened when we went out to help the rest of the platoon, they got cut off and never made it back.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">What do you all know about what happened with <persName>Ronnie</persName> <date when="1965-11-17">that day</date>?</u>
      <u who="SAMMONS">Well, we located a real good friend of my brothers as a matter of fact, through an article that was written in a <placeName>Columbus, Georgia</placeName> newspaper. We contacted him and he gave us a better description of what had happened and evidently from his information that <persName>Ronnie</persName> became wounded and he was away from his group. During the night, they said the Vietnamese soldiers were going through the brush finding Americans that were still alive and killing them and massacring them. That’s what happened to him.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">What did you hear about this?</u>
      <u who="GUIDROZ">Same story, same story.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Lieutenant, when you got out of there and you were recovering from your wounds, when did you find out about what happened to <orgName>Alpha</orgName>.</u>
      <u who="KONRARDY">Last summer. Last summer.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Really?</u>
      <u who="KONRARDY">It was an accident.</u>
      <u who="GUIDROZ">It’s an amazing story.</u>
      <u who="KONRARDY">When the movie came out, my family bugged me that they wanted to go to the movie. Because I had gotten the book a few years earlier. Read it once and put it on a shelf and blocked out everything completed. So I thought, “Well, I better check the movie and see what’s it like.” And I like <persName>Mel Gibson</persName>. They had a <orgName>1st Cav</orgName> guest page as part of their website. So I signed it because this was the middle of the night and I wasn’t thinking too well. So I sign my name, my unit and everything. Then a few days later, I get an email note from a <persName>Freddy Owens</persName>. He said, “I was with you in <placeName>X-Ray</placeName> and <placeName>Albany</placeName>. We got a reunion coming up in <placeName>Washington</placeName> <date when="2003">this year</date>, would you join us?” And this was <date when="2003">two years ago</date>. So I wrote him back and said, “I can’t make it.” That’s it. I didn’t erase his name out of my address book, but I was going to. A week after <placeName>Washington</placeName>, after that reunion here, I got curious, so I just wanted to write to <persName>Freddy</persName>. So I wrote and said, “What happened in <placeName>Washington D.C.</placeName>?” What I did accidently was send it to everybody on the email note, I hit reply all. So everybody got it that was at the reunion, including her. So I get an email note from a strange lady saying, “We had a wonderful time—”</u>
      <u who="GUIDROZ">“My uncle was—”</u>
      <u who="KONRARDY">“Found some information about my uncle, <persName>Ronnie T. Mathis</persName>. Did you know him?” And a few other little things. So I did not respond.</u>
      <u who="GUIDROZ">No.</u>
      <u who="KONRARDY">No way. A week later I got another one.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">But you didn’t know what happened to <persName>Mathis</persName>?</u>
      <u who="KONRARDY">No. No, I didn’t. A week later I got another one from her. She didn’t give up.</u>
      <u who="GUIDROZ">No, I didn’t give up.</u>
      <u who="KONRARDY">She said, “I found out you were my <persName>Uncle Ronnie</persName>’s platoon leader. Would you please write back to me?” How can you say no to that?</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Right.</u>
      <u who="KONRARDY">That started it. Last summer, we got together. Our families met down in <placeName>Columbus, Georgia</placeName> and one of my squad leaders is <persName>Paul Welch</persName>, who had found <persName>Ronnie</persName>—also was there at our reunion and that’s where we got to know each other. We’ve been corresponding ever since.</u>
      <u who="SAMMONS">And the information that I was giving you came from <persName>Paul Welch</persName>. He was my brother’s best friend. The reason—how we found it, my daughter by accident typed in on the internet my brother’s name and this article from the <orgName>Columbus Inquirer</orgName> came up and he talks of my brother in that article. He said that he had never had the opportunity to meet his family. So the very next day we got in touch with him and within three weeks we were in <placeName>Columbus</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="KONRARDY">Wow. What was it like to tie this—get all these facts together?</u>
      <u who="SAMMONS">Well, you know it’s really strange how you don’t know in the beginning what happens. Of course, you grieve and through the years you just sort of—it’s just always there, but in the back of your mind. We had always wondered, but we didn’t know what to do or how to do it to get the information. It was just amazing after it came to be thirty-eight years after it happened that we got the information.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">How is it being together now and on this 40th anniversary of that action?</u>
      <u who="SAMMONS">I think it’s wonderful.</u>
      <u who="GUIDROZ">It is.</u>
      <u who="SAMMONS">We have all become wonderful friends. It’s more family, more like family than just friends.</u>
      <u who="KONRARDY">I wouldn’t be here if they weren’t here. I would not have gone to the <placeName>wall</placeName> yesterday if they had not been able to be available.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Did you find <persName>Ronnie</persName>’s name?</u>
      <u who="SAMMONS">Oh yes, oh yes.</u>
      <u who="KONRARDY">Yes. </u>
      <u who="VERRONE">What was that like?</u>
      <u who="SAMMONS">Well, it wasn’t our first time.</u>
      <u who="GUIDROZ">No.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Was it your first time together?</u>
      <u who="GUIDROZ">Right. Very emotional.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Well, what would you want people listening to this interview generations from now, what would you want to know about <date when="1965-11-17">that day</date>? And about <persName>Ronnie</persName>?</u>
      <u who="SAMMONS">I think he was instrumental in getting us together. Just so much—things that happened. He just sort of guided us together, I think. I know he knows we’re together.</u>
      <u who="KONRARDY">One of the things that the <orgName>Cav</orgName> is really is strong is we leave no one behind. But in the middle of combat when everything is just flying all around, it’s total chaos. I mean, you can’t hear—nothing. You’re reacting as you’ve been trained. Theoretically, <persName>Ronnie</persName> definitely risked his life, but even rolling me over and putting me on a poncho. They should’ve left me and continued to defend themselves. <persName>Ronnie</persName> saved my life.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Then he went back.</u>
      <u who="KONRARDY">Then he went back to help the rest of the platoon. He was the radio operator, he thought that they might need the radio.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">That says a lot. Well, in interest in time, we’ll have to stop the interview, but this is a great tribute to him and his service, I thank you all for doing this.</u>
      <u who="GUIDROZ">Thank you for letting us.</u>
      <u who="SAMMONS">Yeah, it’s an honor. [Editor’s note: Interviewer asks for correct spelling of participants names.]</u>
      <u who="KONRARDY">When I was coming out of anesthesia, I was in the main room, my whole family was there. I was still incoherent. They said that I kind of looked up and asked for <persName>Ronnie</persName> and asked what he was doing there. Now I remember seeing <persName>Ronnie</persName> come in his dress green, walk around the area and walk over to my side of the bed and said, “Everything is okay, we’re okay.” So I talked to the vet counselor about that and she says she feels like he was in dress greens, he was safe. Because that’s what we wore when we were safe back in base camp. He looked young, he had his full uniform on and she said, “I feel he was letting me know he was okay.”</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Wow. (End of interview)</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>