<?xml-model href="../schemas/ddhi.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Transcript of an Interview with a Narrator</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>
          <orgName>Dartmouth Digital History Initiative</orgName>
        </authority>
        <date>
          <!--  Date of publication, e.g. for citation purposes  -->
        </date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <recordingStmt>
          <recording xml:id="primary_recording" type="audio" dur-iso="">
            <!-- https://www.digi.com/resources/documentation/digidocs/90001437-13/reference/r_iso_8601_duration_format.htm -->
            <media url="" mimeType="MIMEaudio/wav"/>
          </recording>
        </recordingStmt>
        <bibl xml:id="primary_transcription">
          <respStmt>
            <persName>Mimi Eisenberg</persName>
            <orgName>Wordcraft</orgName>
            <resp ref="http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/trc.html">Transcriber</resp>
          </respStmt>
          <ref target="path_to_file">Primary transcription</ref>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The Dartmouth Vietnam Project</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application ident="DDHIEncoder" version="1.0">
          <desc>Conversion from Word docx to TEI xml.</desc>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en-us">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <particDesc>
        <person xml:id="WEITZEL"/>
        <person xml:id="VERRONE"/>
      </particDesc>
      <settingDesc>
        <setting>
          <date when-iso=""/>
          <locale/>
        </setting>
      </settingDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <u who="WEITZEL">We set a liaison officer routinely to be part of it. During the <placeName>Carolina</placeName> operations, for <date>about three years</date>, there was a cream puff job. Everybody wanted it because that meant they didn’t have to fly; they were just on the ground with the infantry. I joined a unit—</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Actually, we should get this on tape. This part. What was your—tell me you were with <date>the 2nd of the 7th</date> correct?</u>
      <u who="WEITZEL">2nd of 7th.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">What unit particularly?</u>
      <u who="WEITZEL">I was with headquarters.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Headquarters? Okay.</u>
      <u who="WEITZEL">I functioned in reality as the S3 of the battalion—<orgName>S3 Air</orgName>, let me clarify that.  S3 Air lieutenant.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">So were you with <persName>McDade</persName>? </u>
      <u who="WEITZEL">Yeah. </u>
      <u who="VERRONE">(Chuckles) Well, I would like to ask you about him, is that going to be okay?</u>
      <u who="WEITZEL">Yeah. Head-to-head.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Well, I would like to ask you about him, is that going to be okay? </u>
      <u who="WEITZEL">Yeah</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Basically, what we’re doing here is short video interviews on behest of <orgName>General Moore</orgName> and <persName>Bob Daniels</persName>, one of the sponsors of <orgName>Franklin Global Forum Group</orgName>. They’re putting a lot of money into this to help this reunion go well. They asked us to do these interviews so we can, one preserve them forever, for history and to be deposited at <orgName>the Vietnam Archive</orgName> and preserved for lots of folk into the future. Also, we’ll create a DVD for you all, so you can have all these interviews. They will be on the internet as well, in the virtual <orgName>Vietnam Archive</orgName>.</u>
      <u who="WEITZEL">About how long from now will that be?</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">I would say by <date>the end of the year</date>. I am hoping by <date>Christmas</date> we’ll have— we’re going to give these raw tapes back to <persName>Bob</persName> for him. He has equipment to digitize these DVD tapes. Once we get that, well put someone on the task of getting these put into basically streaming files, so they are not too large for people to view online. Let me give you my card and website. Please pick up information down there, I mean if you haven’t already we have a ton of literature out. But this is the website. So go there and look at that. We have over <date>two and a half million</date> documents online thus far. We have over twenty million in the archive itself, plus tens of thousands of photograph slides</u>
      <u who="WEITZEL">Why can’t you beat <placeName>Texas</placeName>? [Editor’s Note: <orgName>Interviewee</orgName> refers to <orgName>UT Football</orgName>.]</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Well, you know we’re—</u>
      <u who="WEITZEL">I’m from <orgName>Ohio State</orgName>.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Well, I'm from <placeName>North Carolina</placeName>, so my heart is there with the Tar Heels which is great for basketball and occasionally good for football.</u>
      <u who="WEITZEL">Misplaced for football. (<orgName>Laughs</orgName>)</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Yeah, we’ve been top ten in the ‘80’s, with <persName>Lawrence Taylor</persName>.</u>
      <u who="WEITZEL">Didn’t they win <date>last week</date>? <placeName>North Carolina</placeName> won?</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">16-14, we were <orgName>BC</orgName>. Yeah, and we play <placeName>Maryland</placeName> <date>today</date>. But you’re right. <orgName>Tech’s Football</orgName> program is you know, they’re wannabes and they’re doing better and better.</u>
      <u who="WEITZEL">Something I think you’re going to find in the process of these—[Editor’s Note: Audio cuts out.]</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">This is Dr. <persName>Richard Verrone</persName>, I am conducting a video oral history interview with Lieutenant Colonel <persName>Ken Weitzel</persName>. <date>Today</date> is <date>November 12th, 2005</date>. We are in <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <placeName>D.C.</placeName>, at the <placeName>Crystal City</placeName> Hilton and we’re here for the 40th anniversary of the Battles of the Ia Drang Valley, LZ (<persName>Landing Zone</persName>) Falcon, X-Ray, and <placeName>Albany</placeName> and others. Colonel, I would like for you to kind of describe in the interest of time, we’re going right into <date>these days</date> in <date>November</date>. Tell me a little bit about your duties, what position you had and what your responsibilities were.</u>
      <u who="WEITZEL">Basically, what my responsibility was I was the interface between the aviation support and the infantry battalion. It was part of the overall concept of air mobility. We wanted to make sure we didn’t have a separation, that it was seamless, that we all felt that we were part of this overall larger unit. Each aviation company had responsibility for a battalion. We had responsibility, my aviation company of <persName>Charlie 229th</persName> had responsibility for <date>the 2nd of the</date> 7th Infantry and as such, I was a liaison officer to them and when they were not on an operation, I would strap on a helicopter and do my normal flying things and as soon as the alert was given for an order for us to move to the field with <date>the 2nd of the 7th</date> and I ceased flying and then I was part of the <orgName>S3</orgName> shop operations of the battalion. I would coordinate all helicopter air support during the course of the operation. In general terms, we’d go out for <date>seventeen, eighteen days</date> at a time. I’d be in the field the entire time and if there was a combat assault that was going to go on during the course of the time we are in the field, I would coordinate that, get the word back to my aviation commander and then the operation would flow from there. I was responsible of making sure that the sequence of the landing zone—the pickup and landing zones were appropriate. That type of thing.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Okay. Before we get into this, you were with the headquarters group. Tell me about Colonel McDade and your experience with him. What kind of person was he and what was he like to be in the field with?</u>
      <u who="WEITZEL">Colonel McDade was very mild mannered, somewhat soft spoken. Had been the division G1 and had taken over command of the unit, I believe shortly after we got into country. I don’t think he took the battalion over there, to the best of my recollection. Wasn’t very forceful. He’d had assigned—the aid to the general got assigned as the <orgName>XO</orgName> (Executive Officer) of the battalion, as I think more of a support for Colonel <persName>McDade</persName>. A gentleman by the name of <persName>Frank Henry</persName> who has since been deceased. The battalion itself was a ragtag battalion, if you really get down to it. It was formed in the later stages, before we deployed from <placeName>Fort Benning</placeName> and they brought elements with different units together. So it had not had the advantage of <date>two or three years</date>’ worth of extensive training that the 11th <orgName>Air Mobile</orgName> division went through. So it really wasn’t a very cohesive unit to begin with. We had people that were assigned like the S3 of the battalion. A gentleman by the name of <persName>Barney Gill</persName>. <persName>Barney Gill</persName> had been a football player at West Point and then spent <date>fifteen or sixteen years</date> as <orgName>Red Blake</orgName>, the coach’s assistant football coach and they decided that it was time to go back to the real army and do something. So <persName>Barney</persName> was assigned as the S3 of the battalion and knew nothing about operations or how to write an ops order or anything else. Within <date>the first month and a half</date> that we were in country, we replaced the S3 with <persName>Jim Spires</persName> who was outstanding. But you had this kind of turbulence going on. Even within the companies, they weren’t whole companies when they joined the battalion back in Benning. They were filled in with people. So they didn’t have the advantage of the continuity that the other battalions within the division had.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">That’s obviously going to affect you in the field.</u>
      <u who="WEITZEL">That affected later on. I think if you looked at the after action reports you’ll see that as one of the causal effects of what happened in the Battle of Ia Drang Valley and how the battalion performed.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Right. When were you put down into the <placeName>Valley</placeName>? Was it on the 16th? Did you come then? Or was it—</u>
      <u who="WEITZEL">Oh—well you throw a date at me.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">I'm sorry, that was—<date>Sunday</date> the 14th was the beginning of X-Ray and then 15th and 16th is when those guys, most of them were extracted, Colonel <persName>Moore</persName> is extracted.</u>
      <u who="WEITZEL">Right. Then we would’ve gone in on <date>the 15th</date>. We were in LZ, an artillery support base called LZ Columbus and I would estimate there were maybe eight to ten kilometers away from X-Ray. Our responsibility was to guard the artillery units so that they could fire in support of <orgName>General Moore’s</orgName> operation in X-Ray. Then we get the word late at night on, I believe the night of the 14th, that we were to move out by foot and at nighttime and do an early dawn link up with <date>the 1st of the 7th</date> at X-Ray.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">So <date>the 14th</date> was <date>the first day</date> of X-Ray and <date>the 15th</date>, on that <date>Monday</date>, was <date>the second day</date>. Was it <date>the second day</date> or the first night?</u>
      <u who="WEITZEL">No, it was <date>the second day</date>.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Second night? Okay.</u>
      <u who="WEITZEL">It was the night of the second day.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Okay.</u>
      <u who="WEITZEL">So getting into <date>the third day</date>, the next morning. You know, a lot of trepidation at the thought of moving over land. A link up operation is a difficult thing at best. Being able to approach friendly lines and make sure that there’s good interaction and so forth. But we also thought there was enemy between us and <persName>Colonel Moore</persName>, and there was no intelligence to tell us otherwise. So we were preparing to moving through there that we might have to battle our way into his position. Turned out that wasn’t the case, there was no enemy opposition at all. Although we took casualties going there because just at first light, a couple of gunships out—scout ships saw us and fired on us. So we took our first causalities of the Ia <placeName>Drang Valley</placeName> operation moving in to augment <date>the 1st of the 7th</date>.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">What did X-Ray look like when you got there?</u>
      <u who="WEITZEL">Chaotic at best. We moved in, collocated our <orgName>CP (Command Post</orgName>) with <orgName>General Moore’s CP</orgName>. There were mounds of equipment, mounds of weapons that had been stockpiled and everyone had that look on their face that you see when you haven’t slept for <date>three or four days</date>. They’ve been under intense stress and trauma and you could see it on everybody. General Moore’s face was totally covered with dirt. If I could give you a quick, quick side, you can edit this out later.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Absolutely.</u>
      <u who="WEITZEL"><date>Two weeks later</date>, I got a letter from my mother and she said, “I was watching television <date>the other day</date> and they had this battalion commander on. He started talking about his troops and tears started running down his face and going through the dirt, you can see the streaks of the tears going down and he talked about his love for his troops.” She said, “I hope first, you’re not in that battle. Number two, if you are, you’re led by somebody like him.”</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">That’s interesting. What do you remember of Colonel Moore then? Besides his physical look. </u>
      <u who="WEITZEL">Yeah, I guess the compassion and the—that probably came across more than anything else. The compassion, but the strength that he exhibited. He was a combat leader. I never served one day with Colonel Moore. Unabashedly, I’ll tell you I love him. I respect him so much, and when he became the brigade commander, I had no interaction with him then, but revered him and revered him through the entire rest of his career he had in the military.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Was that back in <date>1965</date>? Or was that because you knew what he had done in <date>those three days</date> and you knew what man he was?</u>
      <u who="WEITZEL">Yeah, I think it was less of knowing what he did than knowing the kind of man that he was. The type of leader that he was. There obviously was a contrast between Colonel <persName>McDade</persName> and the leadership of Colonel Moore. Difference in the experience level. Difference in how long they had their units and how long they trained with them. Colonel <persName>Moore</persName> was the real deal.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Tell me about the decision to walk to <placeName>Albany</placeName> instead of being lifted out. </u>
      <u who="WEITZEL">That’s an interesting thing because we spent that night collocated with another battalion. There was another battalion, in addition to Colonel Moore’s battalion and they left the next morning. We were left in the landing zone for a couple of hours and decided to move. <date>That day</date> before, I’d gone up with the battalion and <orgName>S3</orgName> in a helicopter and we had done a reconnaissance to find out where there was an appropriate area where we could have a landing zone. Probably for <date>about fifteen years</date>, I carried with me personally, the guilt that maybe we had spent too much time over the area where we were looking for the landing zone, maybe we had tipped our hand to where we had intended to go. It wasn’t until I read the book, where they had interviewed the PAVN (People’s Army of Vietnam) commanders to know that this was a chance encounter that we ended up having and it had nothing to do with it. But I’d always wondered, was I responsible? Was <orgName>Spires</orgName> responsible? We really weren’t—</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">So you were looking for <orgName>Falcon</orgName> basically?</u>
      <u who="WEITZEL">No, no we were looking for <placeName>Albany</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">I mean, not <placeName>Falcon</placeName>, <placeName>Albany</placeName>. You and <persName>Spires</persName> pinpointed this location.</u>
      <u who="WEITZEL">So we knew that’s where we were going to go. Then we got the order to move over land and you know at the time we didn’t know—we knew we had one responsibility and we knew we were going to, for the first time in the history of warfare, B-52s were going to be in direct support of a ground unit.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Right.</u>
      <u who="WEITZEL">In order to do that, we had a gridline on the map that we had to get pass by a certain time in order to have the safety margin for the operation. So we knew that and understood that as a reason to move. I reflected for <date>forty years</date>, why did we move overland? We were tired, we had to move in a hurry, the terrain was difficult. Security was sacrificed for speed. There was no reason to do it. I mean I would love to <date>this day</date> to talk to the brigade commander or the assistant division commander for operations and ask him, “Why did we do that?” A more logical thing would’ve been hit the mountain with <persName>B-52s</persName>, take our battalion and lift them out of wherever we were and assault right into the B-52 post strike and exploit whatever the advantages we had. Why we didn’t do that, I don’t know. Our philosophy in air mobile at that time was pile on. We didn’t shy from trying to find out where the enemy was and land several miles away and walk towards them. It was gleeful the day that we would land right in the middle of the hornet’s nest because we would pile on and have the fight. That was the advantage of air mobility.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Was there any discussion, do you remember with McDade and Moore or anyone else? I know they received orders from brigade, but you’re Air Cav and all of the sudden you’re going to be walking.WEITZEL: There didn’t seem to be a lot of discussion. In retrospect, I look at it and say, “Why wasn’t there a lot of discussion?” To <date>this day</date>, I don't know what the mission was after we got there. What were we supposed to do?
VERRONE: At X-Ray or <placeName>Albany</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="WEITZEL">Albany. We were walking there, what were we going to do when we got there? The whole logic of the B-52 strike, well obviously it was to damage the forces that would be there as greatly as we could. But what was the overall mission?</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Right, it was almost from what I understand, you all had to get two miles away from <persName>Chu Pong</persName> or some distance.</u>
      <u who="WEITZEL">I don’t know the exact distance.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">So they said, “Okay, let’s hike two miles away so we’re safe.”</u>
      <u who="WEITZEL">But we walked the other battalion too and it spun off and went—I believe they went to <placeName>Columbus</placeName>, I'm not positive. </u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Yes. </u>
      <u who="WEITZEL">So, yeah, I don’t know the reason for the walk, I don’t know the reason for the following mission. I’ve talked to people; they said our mission was to be picked up and taken back to <persName>Holloway</persName> after. That’s a hell of a reason to walk over land. If it was a rouse of some kind to make the enemy believe that we were still there so they should stay in position, I’d like for somebody to tell me that, if that’s what we were being used for. There’s no negative thoughts in my mind when I'm saying this, it’s just to this day I don’t know and I don’t think we question it very much.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">So you and the headquarters, you all started off at the head of the column?</u>
      <u who="WEITZEL">No.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">That’s right, you were back.</u>
      <u who="WEITZEL">Yeah. You know, being at headquarters, elements traditionally we would be two or three companies back and we were situated mostly between <persName>Charlie</persName> company and <orgName>Delta</orgName> company, which was of the other battalion that was the rear unit. We had recon up front. We were moving at a fairly good pace.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Was this—were you going down a trail of sorts or just kind of walking through the brush?</u>
      <u who="WEITZEL">Yeah, it was brush but it didn’t have all the characteristics of a heavily travelled trail or something like that. But moving through that was simple. The problem was you had high—like savannah grass and brush and then you had the regular trees and stuff, but not so dense that you couldn’t see through the trees. Anything that was down in the grass, it was virtually impossible five feet away to see anything. We had recon platoon out front and I actually can’t attest to how dispersed they were but based on where I know the enemy actually was when the attack was sprung, they could not have been dispersed very widely or they would’ve triggered the attack. </u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Right.</u>
      <u who="WEITZEL">We had next to no flank security. We had no rear-guard security.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">What about Alpha Company Back in the back? </u>
      <u who="WEITZEL"><orgName>Delta Company</orgName>.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">I mean all the way in the back. It was <orgName>Delta</orgName>. Okay.</u>
      <u who="WEITZEL">That was Captain <persName>Forrest</persName>, was in the back. So we didn’t have that and then other traditional things we routinely did was walk artillery with us.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">You did not do this.</u>
      <u who="WEITZEL">We didn’t do it. Now I don't know if that was in recognition that you had B-52 strikes going through, but the <orgName>B-52s</orgName> were so high there wasn’t any top of ordinance of anything we would fire in direct support. We also didn’t have aviation assets that normally would’ve been scouts, that would’ve been on top of us. It couldn’t be because they had to be outside the safety zone.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Do you know why these decisions were made? Or when you found out this, what was your reaction? Because you might not be in the dition to know why.</u>
      <u who="WEITZEL">Yeah, I really didn’t have any reaction to it. It was just something that we kind of accepted, that this was—I remember I had my famous words I ate for <date>years</date> and that’s when the B-52 strike hit, we couldn’t even see the planes. All of the sudden, the whole world erupted, and ants fell out of the trees, we had all this debris coming down on us. My response was, “That’ll teach them to screw with us.”</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">You said that there?</u>
      <u who="WEITZEL">Yeah. I ate those words about fifteen minutes later.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">What did the B-52 strikes feel like?</u>
      <u who="WEITZEL">It shook the whole ground, and we were probably several miles from where they dropped. You couldn’t see in it. The planes, you couldn’t hear the planes. Just all of the sudden the world shook. It was awesome and to think that anything on that mountain side where they had hit had survived, would have been incredible. But then, you know in retrospect of thinking, what a beautiful place for us to land on a combat assault, in the middle of an area that had been sanitized by <orgName>B-52s</orgName>.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Sure. Talk about what happened next.</u>
      <u who="WEITZEL">Well, let me tell you. We came across two North Vietnamese who for some odd unexplained reason were sitting there, apparently were eating. It didn’t make any sense at all that they were in that posture. But what was different about them, the people that Colonel <persName>Moore</persName> was fighting when they would capture them, their storyline was all the same. They were from the north, they didn’t want to be here, they were sick, they had malaria, they had no pills. You know, they were unwilling participants was a word we were getting. On contrary, what they were saying, they were fighting ferociously. So what was different about the two POWs (Prisoners of War) when they were interrogated, they said they had eight to ten friends dedicated to killing Americans, they were up in the trees and they would fight to their death. They all had new uniforms, new uniforms in their packs, fully equipped. So they had a tremendous amount of credibility. They did damage to the unit because of their credibility, when I look back on it. Because we really did believe them. They were finally telling the truth, that these were well trained troops dedicated to fighting Americans. So when we got the order to halt the movement, I think I was in a unique position. There was only two people who were called forward. Company commanders were called forward, staff was called forward. Now the head of the column had gotten to just right outside of <placeName>Albany</placeName>. We could visually see it. So it was a logical thing in any combat situation that a commander could lay out an objective on a map and say, “A Company is here to here and B company is here to here.” But when you have the advantage of actually being on the ground and say A Company is by that tree to that mound and you can establish your boundaries for your units, you certainly would want to do that. So part of <orgName>McDade’s</orgName> calling people forward, was to do that visual because he could. So that explains a little bit on why the company commanders were called forward. So the <orgName>D Company</orgName> commander had the advantage of walking in an entire line of the route of march and see all the troops and so did I from <orgName>Charlie Company</orgName> forward. I remember—well, first of all, there’s about a fifteen minute period of time that nothing happened. We didn’t know why anything had stopped, there were no communications. I, like everybody else just sat down on the ground, most people took off their helmets. Resting, drinking water.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">You weren’t with <orgName>McDade</orgName>?</u>
      <u who="WEITZEL">At that point, not with <orgName>McDade.</orgName> McDade was already forward at the head of the column. I remember—people told me later, I went to the bathroom and I walked about fifteen feet or twenty feet away where everybody was. Later on, people who were part of the assault said I actually walked past the positions from where the <orgName>NVA</orgName> (<orgName>North Vietnamese Army</orgName>) or the PAVN at that time, actually fired. So they had the discipline, fortunately for me, to not let me trigger their attack. So I was lucky.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Wow. Yes.</u>
      <u who="WEITZEL">Moving up that line, no one was in the traditional infantry defensive positions, with one exception and that was a platoon from I believe it was <orgName>Alpha Company</orgName>, it was led by lieutenant <persName>Don Cornett</persName>. He had a traditional perimeter defense, and they were all alert and it vividly stood out in my mind that this was the one unit that was doing what our doctrine would’ve told you to do.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">You felt that at the time?</u>
      <u who="WEITZEL">Oh yeah, absolutely. Reading has reinforced my mind later that’s the one unit that was in the kill zone. They were wiped out I think in its entirety. I don’t think anyone in his platoon survived. Most of them died in a perimeter defense when we looked at the bodies laying there.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">When I got to the head of column, they had already finished interrogating the two North Vietnamese and they were tied up and sitting down on the ground. Hadn’t given us any other information except for these eight to ten of their friends up that were up in the trees and prepared to fight. I was with a group—<persName>McDade</persName> was talking to his company commanders about where they should be located in the lines. The recon platoon had already moved through, they were the lead element. They were actually over in the area where the landing zone was. About forty people. I was with a group of eight people which included the battalion sergeant major and the <orgName>S3</orgName>’s sergeant and several other people over there. But there were eight of us in total plus the two prisoners. When the firing started, we all laid down and there was a huge ant hill, five six feet high and they were I don’t know how far out, maybe five six feet wide. You laid down in the grass and you couldn’t see anything. It really gave you a false sense of security. What you can’t see can’t hurt you. I would listen to the yelling and screaming, it was intense.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Of the others?</u>
      <u who="WEITZEL">Yes, all up and down the line. My assumption and I remember saying to myself how proud I was of our forces, our troops that they would yell and scream like this going after these eight people up in the trees. So these guys had really thrown at least our small group of people, I think they’d really thrown us off on what was going on. So we just—I laid there, I didn’t think I had any responsibility, the noise was all coming from down the line. All of the sudden though, we started getting heavy fire at our position.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">What kind of fire was it?</u>
      <u who="WEITZEL">Small arms. I don’t remember any mortar fire at where I was at all. I believe back where <persName>Charlie Company</persName> was, I think they were getting some pretty good mortar fire back there. The <orgName>SFC</orgName> (Sergeant First Class) <persName>Bass</persName>, I bet <date>today</date> he’s never gotten an award for anything. He was the operation’s sergeant. What he did, he said, “I’ll stand up and draw fire. The rest of you find out where the fire is coming from and I'll drop them, and you guys engage them.” So he did it the first time and he laid down on the ground and he said, “Did you guys see him?” I said, “No, we didn’t see him.” “Damn!” So he did it again. He did it eight to ten times. Each time we were saying—each time he got more frustrated that we didn’t see them. Frankly, I don’t think we were looking that hard. You know, you have the courage <date>forty years later</date> to say that you weren’t the hero that you thought you were. But finally, I never saw anybody coming towards that hill at all. But somebody yelled, “There all over us. Get out of here!” And it was like a herd mentality. Everybody stood up and started to run and five of the eight didn’t take two steps and were killed immediately.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Five of the eight people that you were with?</u>
      <u who="WEITZEL">Yeah. Then the young PFC (Private First Class) got hit or stitched across the stomach and he was running with the sergeant major and I down this open field and I later written something I just keep personally, I call it my “Run to Nowhere”, because I didn’t know where I was running to.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Let me ask you, were you running toward <placeName>Albany</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="WEITZEL">Actually, I was. But I didn’t know it. It was just an open field and I knew I couldn’t be where I was, and it was just running. This PFC his entire intestines were outside of his stomach. He was holding them with both arms and keeping up with us stride by stride. It was remarkable, I don’t know if he lived or if he—I mean, he made it out, he was lifted out. But whether or not he survived or not, I don’t know and don’t know his name. People that saw us, said it was incredible with the number of tracer rounds all around our heads. Every fourth or fifth round was a tracer round so it was three or four times what you were seeing. They said all of our heads were laced with tracer rounds. I could actually feel at times I’d flinch because it was so close and near it touched my ear kind of thing. I fell down on the ground, just stumbled. Sergeant major fell over me, the PFC fell over the sergeant major. We are laying there, and the recon platoon was in a wood line and they were yelling for us to come over there. It sounds really corny, but some young troop had a confederate flag and he carried it all the time, he stuck this small confederate flag on an ant hill. I figured being a brilliant captain, that they weren’t very many NVA carrying confederate flags, so it must be safe over there. The battalion sergeant major got up, ran to the wood line, fell to the ground and then he got up in traditional infantry mode like this and said, “Over here!” Got hit right in the chest and in the armpit motioning for me to come over. So it ended up, I was unscratched and got into this small perimeter.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">He was killed?</u>
      <u who="WEITZEL">No, he survived it, but he died <date>a couple weeks ago</date>.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Really.</u>
      <u who="WEITZEL">So out of the battle itself, maybe three of us made it. Probably two out of those eight. Survivors <date>today</date>, I'm probably the survivor. You certainly question in your mind, you know, war and casualties were so random. Still are <date>today</date> in <placeName>Iraq</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Did you think about it back then? Were you thinking about death or were you running from that?</u>
      <u who="WEITZEL">I wasn’t thinking about death, until we got into the perimeter. Once we got into the perimeter, I knew we were going to die. Then it was no longer a sense of thinking about death, it was thinking about more about the pain and suffering that this was going cause for other people. I think it was a more prevalent thought than my own loss.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">You’re talking about the perimeter up near the LZ?</u>
      <u who="WEITZEL">Yeah. The recon platoon was basically the forty people around the perimeter. Then we started getting stranglers in. That included the battalion <orgName>XO</orgName> was in there and <persName>McDade</persName> and all the company commanders except for <persName>Forrest</persName> who got back to—ran a gauntlet and got back to his unit.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Why did you think you were going to die? Why were you certain of that once you got to the perimeter?</u>
      <u who="WEITZEL">All night long, all day long we were probed. We’d break into the perimeter at times and we’d fight them back. I know things that I did later on as I did my own personally research <orgName>S.L.A. Marshall</orgName> wrote a book on men under fire and he talked about through interview what people did as they prepared for their final battle. As I review the book, I understood I did all those things. I had my ammunition, I rehearsed how I would reach for another clip so I’d be able to do it automatically, where everything was positioned, I could do it in the dark and that type of thing. I remember there was a lieutenant or Captain <persName>Callow</persName> I think was our S2. I know we took off our <placeName>insignia</placeName>, nametags, and everything else that identified. We ripped up pictures of family and things like that because we didn’t want that to be in the hands of the <orgName>NVA</orgName>.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">How did that feel to do that?</u>
      <u who="WEITZEL">It felt like saying goodbye. It wasn’t a good feeling. But I—you know, I kept running into the perimeter. Lieutenant <persName>Gwin</persName> who was a combat leader in the truest word, a warrior. He was standing up, fighting. The NVA rushing him <date>ten, fifteen</date>, twenty feet away. Get up and rush him again and he keep firing. So I came in after running and everything totally spent. Fell down on his feet, he said, “Get up and fight!” “I need water!” He said, “God dammit, get up and fight!” “I need water!” He threw a canteen of water at me and as I look back in <date>the years</date> and saying what was more important to me at the time, I had to have water before I could fight. Survival was less important to me than water at the time. As soon as I got a drink of water, I was up doing what I should do. But then I eventually I moved over to where <persName>McDade</persName> was. McDade was laying down on the ground totally frustrated, in command of nothing. No communications with the companies, they jammed our radios. His company commanders couldn’t direct them to do anything, they were all there. Really, individual soldiers now. Totally helpless position for him. I remember we were laying there and the bark from about this high on the ground up was all gone off the trees. We were receiving so much fire from all around this perimeter. He looked at me and apologized for getting me into this. As an individual.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Do you remember what he said to you?</u>
      <u who="WEITZEL">Exactly that, he said, “I’m so sorry I got you into this. I'm sorry.” The person that truly took over the battalion at that time was <persName>Frank Henry</persName>, who was the battalion <orgName>XO</orgName>. <persName>Frank</persName> was an aviator, but he was put on ground duty. Had been the division commander’s aid. He was sent down to give additional strength to the battalion and he was a very strong, dynamic leader. But he also was in the frustrating position of—he couldn’t communicate with anyone. We wanted to use all the resources available to us for <orgName>TAC</orgName> (<orgName>Tactical Air Control</orgName>) air and artillery and everything else. We couldn’t use it because we didn’t know where our people were. We anguished over it. We knew where some bad guys were, and we couldn’t bring in fire around them. It was such a frustrating thing.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">I guess, especially for you personally because you—</u>
      <u who="WEITZEL">Yeah. It was terrible. But that was during the daytime. Then, when it got dark, that’s when we realized that none of us thought we would make it to the next morning. We had wounded people and it was the dichotomy of war. We wanted an emergency insertion for a helicopter to take out our wounded before we died. It’s an amazing thing.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">It’s a dedication to your men.</u>
      <u who="WEITZEL">Yeah, dedication to the people even though you thought you probably weren’t going to be there <date>the next day</date>. So that’s where Colonel <persName>Bennett</persName>, who was the <orgName>C Company</orgName> commander, he was up in the air. He said he couldn’t get in; he couldn’t see us on the ground. It was just a holocaust blow with tracers all over the place, fires all over the place. Just a chaotic mess for many square miles around there.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">He could see the whole—</u>
      <u who="WEITZEL">Yeah. He could see it, but he couldn’t see anything individually. Finally, what to know how bad it was, I told him to switch over to our aviation company frequency, so in the clear I told him everything that was going on. I told him that chances are—he said, “I’ll come in the morning.” I said, “Don’t come in because it won’t be us that’ll be here.” He said, “That bad?’ “That bad.” So he said he will come in. He got a silver star for what he did. They came in, we didn’t control the landing zone for them to come in. It was in no man’s land. We were on one side, the NVA on the other side. We put down suppressive fire. The S3 of the battalion, <orgName>Spires</orgName>, went out with a flashlight with a little red dot on it to try to identify. He and I took turns doing that a couple of times. It was almost comically, I’m talking on the radio to the pilots trying to orient them in to where we are and <persName>McDade</persName> is saying, “Dammit, hurry up!” He was abstained out there in the middle of nowhere.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">What was <persName>McDade</persName>—was he up in control or was he down?</u>
      <u who="WEITZEL">Down. He was non-participant at that point.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Why is that going on?</u>
      <u who="WEITZEL">I don't know. I think he was so discouraged and felt like he had no influence anymore of the action.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">What was it like for you to run out in the middle of the LZ with a flashlight?</u>
      <u who="WEITZEL">It was crazy. The worst thing was when the helicopters came in, they came in through the sheet. I mean, actually a sheet of fires, incredible. They landed and they were being constantly fired at, taking all kinds of hits. We ran out and put wounded people on, other people are being wounded as they were carrying wounded out and they were being put on. I ran out and stood on the skid of the helicopter and looked at my company commander, <persName>Will Bennet</persName> and he looked at me and we both knew the same thing. That we would never see each other again.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Because he was staying?</u>
      <u who="WEITZEL">Well, he was going to leave, I was going stay. I thought for a moment, why don’t I just jump on this helicopter?</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Why didn’t you?</u>
      <u who="WEITZEL">You couldn’t do that. I mean if nothing else, what you were. The training you’d received there was just no way. But I thought about it later on, not then but <date>years later</date>, that I chose the risk of death over the risk of embarrassment of leaving the battlefield.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Do you know why?</u>
      <u who="WEITZEL">Nature? Sense of responsibility, loyalty. All those crazy things. But it was tempting. On their way out, I didn’t think they were going to make it. I thought we were going to lose those two helicopters and we’d be responsible for that also. Then, just try to shorten up all night long, we received probes. The worst part was that we listened systematically as the <orgName>NVA</orgName> walked through the battlefield and we’d hear our people yell, “No, no!” and then you’d hear, “Bam, Bam!”. It just about drove everybody crazy listening to that and having no effect on it. Then we finally had a really massing of NVA on the one side of where the landing zone had been. We had reached a decision, take the risk that we might have people there or call in an airstrike and it would save us but kill our own people. We didn’t know what to do. We reached the joint, and it was actually <persName>Henry</persName> and <persName>Spires</persName> and I had reached the decision that if we had friendly troops that were there, they were dead. Because there were probably hundreds of NVA. So we called in A1E and dropped napalm. Actually, close enough that napalm came into our position. Nobody was really injured, but napalm came into our position. That stopped probably what would’ve been the assault that would’ve finished us off, I think. The next morning, well, there’s one real quick thing. You’ll hear about <persName>Rescorla</persName> all the time. I have no personal attachment to <persName>Rescorla</persName>, I didn’t know him or anything else. There’s a lot of people that truly admired him. This guy was really something. He came in, he organized back at the base camp. Ragtag group of people, most of his platoon. Went over and insisted the aviation—not with anybody’s approval, the aviation take him in to there. That was his unit. Came in on the combat assault under fire. I think it was dark or maybe just starting to get a little bit of light and he jumped off and ran over. They just started falling on the ground and occupying position. I don’t know if you’ve ever seen <persName>Cal Ripken</persName> retired. He ran around the stands, all the way around the stadium and he hit everybody’s hand. <persName>Rescorla</persName> did that under fire to everybody that was in that perimeter, who was hunkered down, ready to die and thought all of us lost. He went around yelling and screaming, “Let’s go! Let’s go! Come on! Let’s go!” When he was finished, he had fired up that unit to the level that everybody stood up and started screaming for the NVA to come on.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Wow. </u>
      <u who="WEITZEL">You know what I'm saying, let’s get it on. When you think that he was a lieutenant, he had one major battalion commander, three or four company commanders, other ranking people to him and he was able to convince lieutenant, overcome all that rank structure and rally those people. It was an amazing event to see. Like I said, I have no personal—some people love and admire him and everything else and I don’t know him beyond that.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">But that’s what you saw, you witnessed. It inspired you.</u>
      <u who="WEITZEL">Yeah, and it gave you the hope. We only added probably twenty more people, but it gave you the hope that you were going. The rest of the thing that was—<date>the next day</date> was doing nothing but policing the battlefield. I personally went out just to look for my operations sergeant. Found him and we carried him back in again. Everybody spent the day going out and Chinooks came in and that was before the days of body bags, so we had ponchos. Never wore a poncho again in my life after that. Thought it was bad luck. Carried the bodies. By that time in <date>the day</date>, <date>two days</date> into it with the heat, they were bloated and everything. You’d be seeing around all the ponchos waiting for some more Chinooks to come in and all of the sudden you’d hear a, “Psst” and you’d see the poncho go down as the bodies were exploding in the heat. We captured one person. That individual had Lieutenant <persName>Cornett</persName>’s wallet, with a picture of Lieutenant <persName>Cornett</persName>’s wife was in his possession. That was the one lieutenant who would organize his platoon in a good defensive position. This, just by chance, this particular <orgName>NVA</orgName> had searched his body and taken his wallet. The guy was uncooperative, spit in the face of the sergeant who was trying to get him to sit down. Almost caused a riot amongst our people. There was the first time <orgName>McDade</orgName> took charge.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">What did he do?</u>
      <u who="WEITZEL">He just stopped everybody. Very forceful, yelling and screaming, “Leave him alone. Back up.” It was almost a mob mentality; people were very angry at that point. But one did he did do, <orgName>McDade</orgName> said, “<placeName>Strip</placeName> him and search him.” They tried doing it, he started struggling. <persName>Sergeant McDade</persName> said, “Subdue him.” A guy picked him up and threw on the ground. Searched him and tied him up. To the <orgName>NVA</orgName>’s credit he was belligerent to the end. Good solider, our enemy but a good solider.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">We need to finish up, in interest of time. Tell me about leaving and your feelings about looking back now on <date>those days</date>.</u>
      <u who="WEITZEL">Yeah. Leaving there, the lift back to <placeName>Pleiku</placeName> was horrendous too because we knew we were beaten. We were declared non-combat ready at the end of it. The only unit that had that happen to in the entire war. They’d set up a resupply area and you’d walk through and pick up things that you had lost on the battlefield. You’d go to triage at <placeName>Pleiku</placeName> and they had people all over. Some of them ours, some of the other units. A tremendous thing. Then we went to the officer’s club that night. We closed the officers club to any other officers except for our unit. Very forcefully decided that this was our time.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Yeah. <date>Forty years</date> after the fact, what’s it been like being here? And what do you want people to know about those guys and about you, about those days?</u>
      <u who="WEITZEL">Gosh. I guess I want the general public to know that we were what they think the Iraqi and <placeName>Afghanistan</placeName> vets are <date>today</date>, and that’s that people that went to war without an ideology. People went to war for the love of their country, to do what they were asked to do and not tainted by the political aspects of it. We are the same kind of people. It was really great that the book was ever written because there’s not enough personally accounts. If people would delve down into individual tales, there are so many other books that could be written.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Did you feel like the movie sided you all? Or do you regret that—</u>
      <u who="WEITZEL">Yeah, it did, but it wasn’t negative for me. You know, if you ask the people from <date>the 2nd of the 7th</date> who had the greatest battle, it wasn’t <date>the 1st of the 7th</date>. They won’t agree to that. Maybe in retrospect it wasn’t, if you wanted to judge the fierceness of the battle only by casualties, there is no question it was <date>the 2nd of the 7th</date>. But maybe we took more causalities because we shouldn’t have and maybe Colonel Moore’s group maybe did a better job and that’s why they didn’t take the casualties. We were missing one of our companies, <persName>Myron Diduryk</persName> in <orgName>B Company</orgName>. He was a rock.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">That’s what <orgName>Moore</orgName> said.</u>
      <u who="WEITZEL">He was a rock, he was a “soldier” soldier, he was a warrior. My last political statement is that when we went into <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, we had not been in combat for a longtime. Those people that were effective managers and administers became the leaders of the army. Throughout the structure, more NVAs and etc. It took us <date>a few years</date> and finally had warriors come to the forefront. <date>The latter years</date> in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, we had warriors that were leading. Then we reversed that process again. We probably now have gone the other way again. We’re proud to say that a person that may be leading units is a strong combat leader. Maybe not as strong as an administrative or managerially. So I think we went through that creative time.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Well, sir we need to end the interview now. Appreciate your time very, very much.</u>
      <u who="WEITZEL">It was great, and I thank you for what you’ve done.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">It’s our honor.(End of interview)</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
