<?xml-model href="../schemas/ddhi.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Transcript of an Interview with a James Epperson</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>
          <orgName>Vietnam Center and Sam Johnson Vietnam Archive</orgName>
        </authority>
        <date>
          <!--  Date of publication, e.g. for citation purposes  -->
        </date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <recordingStmt>
          <recording xml:id="primary_recording" type="video" dur-iso="00:29:16">
            <!-- https://www.digi.com/resources/documentation/digidocs/90001437-13/reference/r_iso_8601_duration_format.htm -->
            <media url="https://vva.vietnam.ttu.edu/repositories/2/digital_objects/330265" mimeType="video/mp4"/>
          </recording>
        </recordingStmt>
        <bibl xml:id="primary_transcription">
          <respStmt>
            <persName>Mark Steven Varela</persName>
            <orgName>Vietnam Center and Sam Johnson Vietnam Archive</orgName>
            <resp ref="http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/trc.html">Transcriber</resp>
          </respStmt>
          <ref target="https://vva.vietnam.ttu.edu/images.php?img=/OH/OH0500/OH0500.pdf">Primary transcription</ref>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>TThe Oral History Project of the Vietnam Center and Sam Johnson Vietnam Archive</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application ident="DDHIEncoder" version="1.0">
          <desc>Conversion from Word docx to TEI xml.</desc>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en-us">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <particDesc>
        <person xml:id="VERRONE"/>
        <person xml:id="EPPERSON"/>
      </particDesc>
      <settingDesc>
        <setting>
          <date when-iso="2005-11-12"/>
          <locale/>
        </setting>
      </settingDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <u who="VERRONE">This is Dr. <persName>Richard Verrone</persName> conducting a video oral history interview with Mr. <persName>James Epperson</persName>. <date when = "2005-11-12">Today is November 12th, 2005 </date> and we are in <placeName>Washington, D.C.</placeName>, in the <placeName>Crystal City Hilton  </placeName> and this is the 40th anniversary of the reunion of the <name type = "event"> Battles of the Ia Drang Valley</name>, <name type = "event">Falcon</name>, <name type = "event"> X-Ray</name> and <name type = "event">Albany</name> and others. <persName>Jim</persName>, if we could, let’s start with what do you remember about—before trying to walk to <placeName>Albany</placeName>, you all landed and came in at <placeName>X-Ray</placeName> and can you tell me a little bit about that, what <placeName>X-Ray</placeName> looked like and then the decision to walk to <placeName>Albany</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="EPPERSON">Well, we went into <placeName>X-Ray</placeName> to relieve <orgName>the 1st of the 7th</orgName> because they had been shot up pretty bad and they were flying them out on the choppers that we flew in on. Fly in, we would offload a chopper, <orgName>1st of the 7th</orgName>. Two of the companies from <orgName>the 2nd of the 7th</orgName> who had been flown in to reinforce them were lifted out at the same time. I think it was <orgName>Bravo</orgName> and <orgName>Charlie</orgName> companies were on the ground with them, had gone in to reinforce them when they got hit. They essentially dropped us off, picked them up and flew them out.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Right. You came in with <persName>Colonel McDade</persName>?</u>
      <u who="EPPERSON">I came in with <persName>Colonel McDade</persName> because I was his radio operator and everywhere that he went, I went. Everywhere we went by helicopter, mostly by helicopter. Now, prior to this when <persName>Colonel White</persName> was still battalion commander, when <placeName>the Plei Me </placeName> Special Forces camp was hit, they were going to go up there and they left in a convoy from <placeName>An Khe</placeName>, a Eppersonep convoy to go up there and they got ambushed. And they turned around and came back, <date>a couple of days later</date> we flew into there. We were walking on nothing but brass from expended bullets because they had done a lot of shooting and stuff. Then, like I said, we were flown to <placeName>Pleiku</placeName> as a forward area to go into the Ia Drang Valley. We were—I don’t know if we were at <placeName>Pleiku</placeName> as a, I want to say reaction force.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Reserve force?</u>
      <u who="EPPERSON">As a reserve force. To in case something happened like it did happen. They flew us in on the <date when = "1965-11-16">16th of November</date>. The day that they pulled <orgName>the 1st of the 7th</orgName> out and flew them back to <placeName>Pleiku</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE"><date when = "1965-11-16">Tuesday, November 16th</date>.</u>
      <u who="EPPERSON">I don’t remember the day; I know the date. We went in on <date when = "1965-11-16">the 16th</date>.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Did <persName>McDade</persName> go over to <persName>General Moore</persName> or then <persName>Colonel Moore</persName>? Do you remember?</u>
      <u who="EPPERSON">I would assume so, to find out what was going on. <persName>Colonel McDade</persName> had only been our battalion commander a short time. A month or something like that. Probably if it was that long because  <persName>Colonel White</persName> was our battalion commander, <persName>John White</persName> was our commander when we went over there. <persName>Colonel McDade</persName> took over, I guess maybe he had been with us maybe a month. That would be the outside, I think. Because we got in country in September and <placeName>An Khe</placeName> passed and then the mess at <placeName>Plei Me</placeName> and then they flew us into <placeName>Plei Me</placeName>. I was not on the Eppersonep convoy that went out, that was going to go up there. We had a Filipino master sergeant that was killed. He was manning a machine gun on a Eppersonep, then they turned around and came back. But then, <persName>Colonel McDade</persName>, I mean just as a matter of policy would have gone over to talk to <persName>Colonel Moore</persName> and find out what the situation was. Now when—and then we just used, naturally just used the fox holes and stuff that <persName>Colonel Moore’s</persName> men had dug. Then we got notified the next day—I don’t remember receiving any enemy fire that night. But the next day we got notified we were going to have to walk from <placeName>LZ (Landing Zone) X-Ray</placeName> to what was known as <persName>LZ Albany</persName>.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Do you remember anything about that decision and why the decision to walk versus to be lifted?</u>
      <u who="EPPERSON">You know, that really is an interesting question. Because there is a gentleman in this hotel who has asked the same question. My son. Why I almost wasn’t his father. The only reason I wasn’t in the kill zone and I'm using that literally, a kill zone, was because <orgName>Delta Company</orgName> had captured two prisoners.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Right and you went forward.</u>
      <u who="EPPERSON">And we went forward. Because we were in the middle of the column.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Right. In the middle of what became the kill zone. Before we get—tell me about Colonel <persName>McDade</persName>. What do you remember about him?</u>
      <u who="EPPERSON"><persName>Colonel McDade</persName> was and still is a gentleman. In the book, what I say I'll say now, and you’ll have it on tape and know it. <persName>Colonel McDade</persName> was a good officer, I think for what he had—he had been a staff officer ever since he came back from <placeName>Korea</placeName>, I think. He’d been wounded in <placeName>Korea</placeName>. He was probably a good staff. I think that he was sent to us so that he gets six months of combat experience to get his eagle or command a battalion. I don’t really think—like I said, he was in <placeName>Korea</placeName>. So we were stretched out, you can imagine or actually there were, what five companies? </u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Five companies. </u>
      <u who="EPPERSON">Because <orgName>the 5th Battalion</orgName> was attached to us when we marched out because we only had <orgName>Delta</orgName>, <placeName>Alpha</placeName>, and headquarters companies, from <orgName>the 2nd of the 7th</orgName>. They came in and we split, and Bravo, <persName>Charlie</persName> companies—I guess <orgName>Delta Company</orgName> from the <orgName>5th Cav</orgName>. To tell you the truth, I really didn’t even know that they were attached to us until I read the book. But they split off and went to another landing zone, I think <placeName>Columbus</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE"><placeName>Columbus</placeName>. Yes, sir.</u>
      <u who="EPPERSON">And we continued on. Well, it was after they split off at, but we were in a column like you see in <name type="event">the World War II</name> and <name type="event">Korean War</name> movies, where you see the guys walking on the edges of road, so the vehicles could use the middle of the road. Well, we didn’t have any vehicles. So we were just walking. I can remember getting to the landing zone and when the <persName>Colonel</persName> started talking—well, you’re asking about <persName>Colonel McDade</persName>, but <persName>Colonel McDade</persName> hadn’t commanded troops, like I said since <placeName>Korea</placeName>, I don’t think. As a company commander, battalion commander something like that he moved up the ranks as a staff officer. I don’t know, even if we would’ve had an officer like <persName>Colonel Moore</persName>, I don’t know how much of a difference that would’ve made. Other than the fact that I—when we caught the prisoners, everybody stopped. The guys that smoked sat down and started smoking and instead of everybody continuing into the landing zones, where we could have set up a defensive perimeter maybe. But because they stopped, that was why the ambush was so effective. I mean, we had people on the ground that shouldn’t have been there. Chaplain’s assistant, my best friend <persName>Dave Mendoza</persName>, clerk in the S2 S3 tent. Other clerks, they shouldn’t have been on the ground, they should have been at a rear epsilon of subcommand or post where they could do their jobs.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">They were hauling typewriters, weren’t they? Didn’t they have all of their equipment?</u>
      <u who="EPPERSON">I couldn’t tell you that. I know they all had weapons, you know because you all go through basic, you’re all quote, unquote O5 Bravos or infantryman. I was, like I said, I went forward with the <persName>Colonel</persName> along with a guy by the name of <persName>Harold Haas</persName>, who I think lives in <placeName>Florida</placeName> some place and I’ve talked to him once in forty years and that was about five or six years ago, and I think I tried to call him once more and I couldn’t get a hold of him. He was living with his son down there some place.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">What do you remember about that meeting of the company commanders and the prisoners. What did you—</u>
      <u who="EPPERSON">Well, <persName>Colonel</persName>—like I said, when they brought them forward, <persName>Haas</persName> and I took our radios off. We still had our web gear on, but the radios were on their own separate strap. We took the radios off because—</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">They’re heavy.</u>
      <u who="EPPERSON">Walking in that heat, twenty-five pounds of radio on your back, kind of wastes you. We had set our radios down. We had actually walked—<placeName>LZ Albany</placeName> was a small landing zone here where they might have been able to get two choppers into, at the most at a time. Then, there was an area of low vegetation, like bushes and stuff like this. Then, the one that we were eventually lifted out of was a big—I think they could bring in four ships at a time into it, when they lifted us out on <date when = "1965-11-18">the 18th</date>. <persName>Haas</persName> and I had walked away just through this little stand of brush. We’re looking out over this big landing zone that was out there. All of the sudden you hear, “Bzzz, bzz, bzz” And we’re looking around for the bees or the wasps because we had disturbed wasps before. What it sounded like. Smart, right? All of the sudden, we realize those aren’t bees! Somebody’s shooting at us! <persName>Haas</persName> had slipped his web gear off and dropped it on the ground. So we jumped back into the little underbrush area. I don’t even think we had a rifle. I guess we had our rifles with us, I think we did. He says, “I left my ammunition out there, my web gear!” I said, “Go get it!” He says, “I'm not going to go get it, they’re shooting at us!” Again, I'm real smart, I walked out. Not run, I walked out, picked it up and walked back and dropped it in front of him. Said, “Here’s your ammunition.” Why I did that, I don’t have the foggiest idea, but I look at it this way, when that man up there wants me, he’s going take me. I can get ready to walk out of this room, trip and fall and break my neck!</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Did you think that then?</u>
      <u who="EPPERSON">Yeah! It’s just something that I guess I’ve always felt that if, when the good lord wants me to go, I'm going to go! And I don’t have anything to say about it. He’s the one, he knows what day he’s going to take me up there.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">So the company commanders dispersed. <persName>Forrest</persName> runs all the way back to the rear.</u>
      <u who="EPPERSON"><persName>Forrest</persName> ran back, he lost two radio operators.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Right. How do you feel about that as a radio operator?</u>
      <u who="EPPERSON">Try running sometime with a twenty-five pound radio on your back and your web gear and your two canteens of water and what we called a butt pack, the little fanny pack thing that you can carry a couple of days’ worth of stuff in. It ain’t easy.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">And you’re following <persName>George Forrest</persName> who is an incredible athlete too, and he’s going full speed.</u>
      <u who="EPPERSON">So what happened with you all there? You’re in the brush, taking cover.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Let’s put it this way, I was no longer a O5 B20, which is an intermediate speed radio operator. I became an 11 Bravo, which is an infantryman. I could’ve cared less about those radios, somebody was shooting at me, I didn’t want them to kill me. I was going to shoot back at them. It’s interesting, when <persName>Joe Galloway</persName> wrote the book, there was a gentleman from <placeName>San Jose,California</placeName>. Had sent him—got no contact because he’d heard about the book and he’s saying that he was the radio operator in <placeName>LZ Albany</placeName>. When I called <persName>Joe</persName> and told him who I was and he called me back like this was in the middle of the week and he was busy and he called me back on Saturday to talk to me about the thing, that’s how I wound up in the book. This guy kept insisting, I kept saying, “Well no! <persName>Harold Haas</persName> was one radio operator; I was the other radio operator for the battalion commander.” Well, now that I look back on it, since <persName>Haas</persName> and I were playing infantrymen instead of radio operators where we should’ve been, there is a good possibility that somebody just reached out, grabbed this guy and said, “Here! Give them the radios, you’re the new radio operator. We don’t know where the radio operators are.” It was hell and I can remember after the battle and the next day on the <date when = "1965-11-18">18th</date>, when they came in to get us and they flew us to a fire base, an artillery fire base. We provided security that night. Yeah, right. I can remember—we had to call in to brigade every hour. I can remember <persName>Colonel McDade</persName> kicking me in the shoulder telling me to, “Wake up and answer the radio. If you fall asleep again, you’re going to sleep a Spec 4, you’re going to wake up a PFC (Private First Class).” Hour later, brigade is calling you to find out what’s going on. I came out as Spec 4, but we were so exhausted, and it was funny because that first night, I really had trouble going to sleep or no, the next day before they came in and got us, I would try to lay down and go to sleep. I’d lay down and my eyes would pop open like they were on springs. I couldn’t go to sleep, I guess the adrenaline was still running, and the tension and everything, the possibility that we were going to get hit again. It was just one hell of a time.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">What happened the rest of the day and surviving that night? I know I’ve talked to others who said, “I don’t think they’re going make it through that. That night waiting.”</u>
      <u who="EPPERSON">Well, like I say, most of our people, we did manage I think—Major <persName>Henry</persName> was the battalion executive officer. To tell you the truth, I think <persName> Major Henry</persName> was sent, because he was  <persName>General Kinnard </persName>’s pilot, was sent to babysit <persName>McDade</persName>. He managed to get us into a semi quote, unquote “Defensive perimeter” and then that night I understand that B and C Company were back in <placeName>Pleiku</placeName>. They cleaned up all their web gear, they’d cleaned up everything and they’d taken showers and everything. Somebody came in and said, “Saddle up, we’re going back out.” And everybody was bitching about the fact that they were, “We just got in from <placeName>X-Ray</placeName>! <name type = "event">The Battle of X-Ray</name>!” They said, “<orgName>The 2nd of the 7th</orgName> is in trouble, they need us.” And there was no hesitation. None at all. They grabbed their stuff, hit the choppers and came out.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">What was that night like at the LZ?</u>
      <u who="EPPERSON">Scary. Scary as hell. We knew we really didn’t have an adequate number of men until they flew into that larger landing zone.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Do you remember <persName>Rescorla</persName> arriving?</u>
      <u who="EPPERSON">No. I did not, much to my regrets, I did not meet <persName>Rick</persName> until <date when = "1993">1993</date>, when I came to my first reunion here. My wife died <date when = "1993-04">April of ’93</date>. My son—I had belonged to <orgName>the 1st Cav Association</orgName>, so I was getting the saver. I got the one that was advertising this. Just having it and my son said, “Dad, go back.  Mom never wanted to go back because she didn’t know how the wall was going to affect you.” He told me, he says, “Go back. You might run into somebody you know.” At that time, we were at the Hyatt in Rosalind. I sat down, I was sitting at the bar, I had come in a week early because when I was in the service the first time from ’57 to ’60 or actually, from ’58 to ’60, I was stationed at <placeName>Fort Story,Virginia</placeName> which is a subcommand of <placeName>Fort Eustis by North Virginia</placeName>. I wanted to go down to see what the post was like, see how much it had changed. Where my barracks were, it was dependent housing now because we were in the old wooden barracks. They’d torn them all down and they’d built these nice brick apartments and stuff for the enlisted personnel in there. I came back up here, but the night that I flew into <placeName>Reagan</placeName>, I got—I rented a car and I was standing way out on lead road someplace. I decided, I think about 8:30, nine o’clock at night, I'm going to go to the wall. You know, my body is still on <placeName>California</placeName> time, three hours earlier. It’s six o'clock in my body. And I drove, got a map and drove over to the mall. Drove around it three times, third time around it I stopped a gentleman who was walking. Said, “Where’s <placeName>the Vietnam Memorial</placeName> at?” I was expecting something like the others, above ground. He says, “It’s right there.” Of course, the forest service uses that lovely brown board with yellow paint on it and don’t bother to light it, so you can see it.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Well, you can’t see the memorial from the road, if you’re looking at one angle.</u>
      <u who="EPPERSON">Well, no. But there was a sign there if it had been lit, I’d have seen it and known where I was at.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Did you get down there?</u>
      <u who="EPPERSON">Yeah, I walked down by myself. There may be half a dozen of us down there and that’s the time to see the walls, at night. I’d been there at 2:30 in the morning when I’d come back. You go down and it’s just—you see the kids running around during the day up at the top. They started down that walkway. It’s like somebody cut their vocal cords. The noise just—</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">What was it like for you when you went there?</u>
      <u who="EPPERSON">Me?</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Yes.</u>
      <u who="EPPERSON">Scary. Hard. I didn’t have anybody that was there with me. I cried. I came in Wednesday. Went down to the wall Thursday morning with my son, another couple that are here, he didn’t serve in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, he served in <placeName>Korea</placeName>. He retired as a Master Sergeant, lives in <placeName>Massachusetts</placeName>. We went down and there’s a—<persName>Elizabeth</persName> wasn’t with us, <persName>Dr. Hancock</persName>. I don’t think she was with us, but her mom was here. Her grandfather died at <name type = "event">the Bataan Death March</name>. He was with the <orgName>7th Cav</orgName>.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">This is your second visit, this time here that you’re describing. To the wall.</u>
      <u who="EPPERSON">This was <date when = "2005">just this year</date>. First time I see the wall, I cry.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Did you go <date when = "2005-11-11">yesterday</date> on <date when ="2005-11-11" >Veteran’s Day</date>?</u>
      <u who="EPPERSON">We were the honorees, yeah. I was there.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">How was that experience?</u>
      <u who="EPPERSON"> I was very impressed. You guys are going to be at the wall <date>tomorrow</date> morning?</u>
      <u who="VERRONE"> Yes.</u>
      <u who="EPPERSON"> At o dark thirty?</u>
      <u who="VERRONE"> Yes. Yes. In the interest of time, we need to wrap this up. Tell me—</u>
      <u who="EPPERSON"> The one thing that did happen in <placeName>Albany</placeName> and I don’t know why I did it when we left <placeName>X-Ray</placeName>, I reached over, there was a case of ammunition sitting there. Don’t know to this day why I did it. Premunition, what? I grabbed four extra boxes of ammunition, that’s four mags. Twenty rounds to a box and put they in my pack. Why? Did I have a premonition of something was going to happen?</u>
      <u who="VERRONE"> Came in handy.</u>
      <u who="EPPERSON"> Oh yeah.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE"> Well, <persName>Jim</persName>, I want to thank you for sitting and talking with us and recording your memories of <date>those days</date>.</u>
      <u who="EPPERSON"> I look forward to maybe a longer interview with somebody over the phone. Anytime.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE"> Yes, sir.</u>
      <u who="EPPERSON"> I do still work forty hours a week, so it would have to be a Saturday or an evening, something like that.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE"> We’ll work that out.</u>
      <u who="EPPERSON">But I thank you very much for doing this because this friend of mine, <persName>Ken</persName> is getting his father-in-law to talk about <name type="event">World War II</name> and recording it.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE"> How wonderful. It’s important for you all to make sure these memories always stay. Thank you very much sir.</u>
      <u who="EPPERSON"> Thank you.(End of interview)</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
