<?xml-model href="../schemas/ddhi.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Transcript of an Interview with Bill Beck</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>
          <orgName>Vietnam Center and Sam Johnson Vietnam Archive</orgName>
        </authority>
        <date>
          <!--  Date of publication, e.g. for citation purposes  -->
        </date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <recordingStmt>
          <recording xml:id="primary_recording" type="video" dur-iso="00:58:15">
            <!-- https://www.digi.com/resources/documentation/digidocs/90001437-13/reference/r_iso_8601_duration_format.htm -->
            <media url="https://vva.vietnam.ttu.edu/images.php?img=/OH/OH0502/OH0502.mp4" mimeType="video/mp4"/>
          </recording>
        </recordingStmt>
        <bibl xml:id="primary_transcription">
          <respStmt>
            <persName>Mark Steven Varela</persName>
            <orgName>Vietnam Center and Sam Johnson Vietnam Archive</orgName>
            <resp ref="http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/trc.html">Transcriber</resp>
          </respStmt>
          <ref target="https://vva.vietnam.ttu.edu/images.php?img=/OH/OH0502/OH0502.pdf">Primary transcription</ref>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The Oral History Project of the Vietnam Center and Sam Johnson Vietnam Archive</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application ident="DDHIEncoder" version="1.0">
          <desc>Conversion from Word docx to TEI xml.</desc>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en-us">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <particDesc>
        <person xml:id="VERRONE"/>
        <person xml:id="BECK"/>
      </particDesc>
      <settingDesc>
        <setting>
          <date when-iso="2005-11-12"/>
          <locale/>
        </setting>
      </settingDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <u who="VERRONE">I’m Dr. <persName>Richard Verrone</persName> I'm doing an oral history video interview with</u>
      <u who="BECK">We are in <placeName>Washington, D.C.Crystal City Hilton</placeName>. It’s <date when="2005-11-12">November 12th, 2005</date>. About 1:50 PM. We are here commemorating the reunion, the 40th anniversary reunion of the <name type = "event">battles of the Ia Drang Valley</name>, <placeName>X-Ray</placeName>, <placeName>Albany</placeName>, <orgName>Falcon</orgName>, <placeName>Columbus</placeName> and others. <persName>Bill</persName>, tell me a little bit about those days in <date when="1965-10">November</date>, before you all get in. Tell me about <persName>Tony Nadal</persName> and the guys around you, your buddies before you all arrived that Sunday.</u>
      <u who="BECK">Alright. Well, we all trained at <placeName>Fort Benning, Georgia</placeName>. Advanced infantry division is what I was doing down there. We went overseas. We were best buddies back in the <placeName>States</placeName>. We were close knit in <placeName>An Khe</placeName>. We were in country about two months before the <name type="event">battle of the Ia Drang Valley</name>. We worked today, we played together, we shared things together. We were close and we were good friends. Our sergeants were good friends, good buddies. Our officers, we respected. Our lieutenants, our captains, right up to <persName>Colonel Moore</persName> himself. We all knew each other, so we were pretty much a close knit family.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Was that unusual you think for a battalion to be that close?</u>
      <u who="BECK">I didn’t know it at the time, but in hindsight when you look back on things, I think we are a lot closer than other veterans that I’ve talked to.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Tell me about <persName>Tony Nadal</persName>.</u>
      <u who="BECK"><persName>Tony Nadal</persName> was my company commander. He was a fair and honest man. He treated his men like they wanted to be treated. Treated us fairly. We liked him very much and we respected him. We knew he had a prior tour in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, so us being green we had a good tendency to listen to what he had to say. We knew he had been there before. We looked up to him.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">What about the lieutenants in the company?</u>
      <u who="BECK">Our lieutenants were all good guys. My platoon leader was <persName>Lieutenant Taft</persName>. He was a young lieutenant, young 1st Lieutenant. He was a very good officer, he was real nice to us, he treated us great. We respected him very much. He was killed right in front of me, about eight, ten yards in front of me on <placeName>LZ (Landing Zone) X-Ray</placeName> when the firing first started. It was a real shame because he was a bright young lieutenant. Probably out of <placeName>West Point</placeName>, I didn’t know then.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Well, I do want to get your impressions of two individuals, who a lot of people know. <persName>Hal Moore</persName> and <orgName>Sergeant Major Plumley</orgName>. Tell me about <persName>Hal Moore</persName>.</u>
      <u who="BECK">Well, back then I only knew him as an officer, that he was our battalion commander and as you went up in the scale, you know, lieutenants, majors, captains, colonels, the more fear you had for them. The more brass they had on, the more you feared them, the more you respected them.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Was it a fear and a respect?</u>
      <u who="BECK">Well, yeah you didn’t want to do anything wrong because you had to go before them, and you knew you were going to get rained out if you did something wrong. So you wanted to keep that down on a sergeant level where you know, where they just might give you a kick in the ass. But when you went up anything higher, you can get some serious offenses against you. You know, for minor things. They might give you an Article 15 or on KP (Kitchen Patrol) duty for fifteen days or something like that. So you didn’t want to go see those guys. They were very strict, very formal. Down on our level, the grunts down there, we could clown with each other, have a good time and get away with a lot of stuff. But <persName>Colonel Moore</persName>, we had a lot of respect for him and we didn’t see him real often. He wasn’t out on the field with us that often on a small level, little search and destroy missions we would go on every day. But he was there on <placeName>LZ X-Ray</placeName>, he was with us. The entire battle.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE"> What did that mean to you all? To have him right there in the middle of it and refuse evacuation and stay?</u>
      <u who="BECK">Well, had he not better there on sight, I think it would have been a different story. Because I was lost, I lost my lieutenant was killed in front of me. Some of my sergeants were shot, wounded, and killed. <persName>Russell Adams</persName>, the other guy on the machine gun and I, we ended up by ourselves and we needed direction. We needed somebody to tell us what to do, where to go. We were without that for an hour or two.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">What about <persName>Sergeant Major</persName>?</u>
      <u who="BECK"><persName>Sergeant Major</persName>? You really feared <persName>sergeant major</persName> because he had the most stripes on his arms. He was a—we were all young back then, but of course he being older than us, we knew he was a <name type="event">World War II</name> combat veteran, <placeName>Korea</placeName> combat veteran and now were in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, so we really feared him. I mean he was the greatest guy in the world, he was nice to you but there again you didn’t want to do anything wrong and face him because you were going to get really chewed out big time. So we had a lot of respect for all our officers and NCOs (Non-Commissioned Officers). </u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Okay. On Sunday morning, <date when="1965-11-14">November 14th</date>, you all air assault down into <placeName>X-Ray</placeName>. Did you have any idea on your level kind of what you were getting into? Or what you’re—I know you knew what your assignments were going to be once you hit the ground, but what did you know intelligence wise on your level as a system machine gunner?</u>
      <u who="BECK">We knew absolutely nothing about what we were stepping into. We were just out on another mission, another search and destroy mission that day. We left one part in a jungle, got on helicopters and dropped off in another part of the jungle. We did that every day we were looking for an enemy. That day was no different than the rest. But as it turned out, we stepped into a hornet’s nest.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Right. So when you all get down with <persName>Nadal</persName> and <persName>Taft</persName>, tell me what happened to your positions and how soon things started up for you.</u>
      <u who="BECK">Well, we had landed, and we got off the Huey helicopters and my gang, my three man machine gun crew. <persName>Russell Adams</persName> was the gunner that day, obviously assistant gunner and then we had an ammo bearer to carry extra ammunition.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">You all rotated is that right?</u>
      <u who="BECK">Yes, well the assistant gunner did. We rotated the guns from day to day. I mean it was heavy, it was twenty-five pounds and then the ammo. So you’re carrying an extra hundred pounds somewhere along the line with your backpacks and hand grenades and canteens. So to relieve each other, we’d trade off in a gun. It was his day to have the gun. We landed, got off the helicopters, and we actually where we were standing, we were facing away from <placeName>Chu Pong Mountain</placeName> and had no idea that there was a dry creek bed there in the jungle. We were standing there and just looking around, it was a beautiful sunny Sunday afternoon. Figure it’s just another walk through the jungle and find nothing and do this again and again. <persName>Lieutenant Taft</persName> walked by, he got orders obviously from his radio man and he walked right by and said, “Okay boys, let’s go. Follow me.” We turned around and we followed him into the creek bed. That area which is thick jungle there. Our landing zone was fairly flat, so we walked off that flat area, into the thick jungle. I don’t think it went ten steps and all hell broke loose. The firing, the machine guns, the bombs, the grenades. Real scary, real hectic. <persName>Lieutenant Taft</persName> gets shot and killed. The guy right in front of me, <persName>Jerry Kirsch</persName> gets machine gunned right across his stomach. He’s no more than two, three yards in front of me. The guys to the right and left of me, they get shot. One gets killed, the other one I know got shot and wounded. <persName>Jerry</persName> rolls on his back, he’s screaming. He’s looking up and he’s screaming for his mother at the top of his lungs. I see he’s shot in and blood and everything. He’s on his stomach screaming. It freaks you out, this instant thing that’s happening here. <persName>Russell Adams</persName> broke off to the left. I didn’t see my ammo bearer who was behind me. <persName>Russell</persName> broke off to the left and of course I'm going to stay close to <persName>Russell</persName>, I ran after him. We were actually running parallel to the creek bed now, going straight out the mountain, <persName>Chu Pong Mountain</persName>. So we kept escalating, the battle. But that was just the start of it right there. I’d seen instantly, I saw at least two guys killed and maybe three guys wounded all in the matter of five seconds. So that scares the hell out of you. So I'm running, my juices are flowing. I spot <persName>Adams</persName> and I catch up to him. <persName>Russell</persName>’s firing a machine gun.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">And you drop aside him?</u>
      <u who="BECK">We weren’t even there yet at that point. We were going parallel to the creek bed and he just keeps going. From the original setting where we landed, he moved fifty, seventy-five yards up towards the mountain. He came to a resting place there that I guess he felt comfortable with or maybe we couldn’t go any further actually. Because we were under fire the entire time. People were shooting at us, bullets hitting the ground, cracking over your head. So he settles down there, he’s firing a machine gun and I'm beside him. I have my ammo and I'm looking for the ammo bearer and he’s gone. So I figured he got wounded or killed, which wasn’t the case actually. I found out three days later what happened to him. But it was us, we were reduced to a two-man team. Machine gun team. So now were settled in. <persName>Russell</persName> is doing the firing. I’m spotting, I'm looking anything that moves, enemy and stuff. I'm staying over there straight ahead, and <persName>Russell</persName> is doing his thing, he’s doing a good job.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">How loud is that? I mean, what’s happening in the ways of this battle and the machine gun?</u>
      <u who="BECK">It was deafening. It was still deafening. The noise, it just erupted. You know, all of our guys and all of their guys and they’re throwing everything at us. Rockets and RPGs (Rocket Propelled Grenades) and grenades like I said and helicopters above them. I don’t know if we had gunships right then, but later we had gunships. So now they’re firing rockets down in on us and they’re exploding amongst us and stuff. It’s real havoc. Trees are falling down and breaking and leaves and dirt and smoke and fire, you name it. It’s all filled in together, it was very deafening.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Did that surprised you?</u>
      <u who="BECK">Oh yeah, you’re not trained for anything like that. I wasn’t trained to see that the very first five seconds, nobody can train you for what you’re going to see. So it scares the hell out of you. But you move, you can’t stand still, you’re going to die, so you do everything you think you can do. You jump, you dodge, you roll, you crawl. You do what you have to do. But we ended up there where we—seventy-five yards up.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">That’s a long way from the rest of the company, you’re on <persName>Bob Edward’s</persName> right. But did you think, “Wow, we’re really far out.” Or was it more just getting there and getting safe.</u>
      <u who="BECK">No, it just all happened like some things happen in slow motion, some things happen real quick. You don’t know how to go from point A to B. It was very exhausting. I was soaking wet not just right then, but later in the battle, from running around and doing things. I was totally exhausted. It takes a real drain on you. So we ended up here and that’s that. </u>
      <u who="VERRONE">When I asked—I want you to describe what happens right after this. When you guys get down and some of this action. But when I asked <persName>General Moore</persName> on Thursday morning, towards the end of this interview, two and a half hours, I said, “What do you think of when you think of the <placeName>Ia Drang Valley</placeName> and <placeName>X-Ray</placeName>? What comes to your mind’s eye now?” He took about thirty, forty-five seconds silence and he says, “<persName>Bill Beck</persName>.” </u>
      <u who="BECK">Oh.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">I said, “Why?” He said, “Because he kept the gap filled. He saved the whole situation right then when it was so critical. He kept me alive, our headquarters. The <placeName>CP (Command Post)</placeName> where it could stay stable and not be—that gap was huge.” He credited so much to you and <persName>Russell</persName>. So—</u>
      <u who="BECK">He’s a very kind man with his words. At the time, we didn’t know where the <placeName>CP</placeName> was. I didn’t know where the rest of our men were. I didn’t know where <persName>Captain Nadal</persName> was. I didn’t know where the rest of my buddies were. All I know is last time I saw them, they were heading into the jungle. Like I said, I didn’t know the creek bed was there at that time, I found that out a little later. But we ended up there because of <persName>Russell</persName>, that’s where he went, and I stayed with <persName>Russell</persName>. So that happened by fate or blame it on <persName>Russell</persName>, <persName>Russell Adams</persName>. But he got me up there. When we were there, it became a fight for your survival. <persName>Russell</persName> got shot.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">How soon after you guys got down? </u>
      <u who="BECK">There’s some things happen up there. <persName>Russell</persName> was doing his thing. I left <persName>Russell</persName> for more ammunition because we didn’t have an ammo bearer. So I tell <persName>Russell</persName> he’s running low on ammunition. I think I only had one box with me, maybe a bandolier hanging on me, so it’s like three hundred rounds. He probably had a hundred rounds on him. Our ammo bearer was supposed to have two boxes, which would’ve been four hundred rounds. We never got those four hundred rounds. So we’re—we got low on ammo and I tell <persName>Russell</persName> I said, there was like a little break, I said, “I'm going to look for <persName>John</persName>, our ammo bearer.” So I run back to the rear where we originally started from. I eventually find two boxes of ammo lying on the ground. I say, “Well, <persName>John</persName> got shot and killed and they medevac’d him out or something, I don’t know what’s going on.” I get the ammo and then I'm on my way back up, and right there by the creek bed, against the trees turned out to be <persName>Lieutenant Raul Taboada</persName>. He was a Lieutenant of ours. I didn’t know him real well at the time, but all I saw was Lieutenant bar and part of his name. He was severely wounded in his hand and his leg. I patched up his hand and his leg. I took time to do that. He had pictures of his wife and children laying out around him. He got them out of his thing. He told me years later he thought he was going to die. He had his .45 out in his hands and I asked him what that was about. I thought he was going to say it was to shoot the enemy. He said he was going to shoot himself when the North Vietnamese came in to get him. So I took his .45 from him. I had two .45s, I had mine and I had his. I patched his hand and his leg up.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">How did you patch it? With what?</u>
      <u who="BECK">I used his first aid pack and I used mine. I patched his leg up best as I could. I patched his hand up and he must’ve been in terrible pain. As I was wrapping, I wrapped it real soft every time I’d try to tie it a little bit, he’d wince in pain, you know. But his leg was equally bad. I patched him up and I called for medic and I had to take off, I had to leave. My back was to the creek bed actually. He was sitting against the tree on the ground. I did that, I took the ammo heading back up to <persName>Russell Adams</persName>. Somebody threw a hand grenade out, the <orgName>North Vietnamese</orgName> threw a hand grenade out right in front of me, it rolled to the ground, it went off. I was going to jump on the ground and try to get away from it, but it went off right just as I bent down. It was a concussion grenade, thank god. If it was a fragment grenade, I’d have been wounded or killed. Big blast and white flash. So that scared the hell out of me. I thought, what the hell. I look to the right, because it came from the creek bed area. So I spot these two <orgName>North Vietnamese</orgName> against this little mound there. They were actually down in a creek bed and they were coming up on a flat area, there’s a little mound with this bamboo coming out of it and everything else. There’s two of them on this side and there’s an American GI (Government Issue) on the other side. The mounds are only three four feet high. Maybe six feet in diameter. So they are on one side and the GI is on the other side. Now, I don’t know if they could see each other or if they saw each other prior to this or what the hell is going on. But that’s how close they came. So I'm screaming and yelling, I stop and I scream and yell. They are not very far away.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">What were you saying?</u>
      <u who="BECK">I was screaming, I said, “<orgName>North Vietnamese</orgName>! <orgName>Viet Cong</orgName>!” Everything I could say, screaming and trying to point. Nobody could hear me; the noise was very loud. He didn’t look and I don’t think the <orgName>North Vietnamese</orgName> could even see me because it could’ve been another one that threw the grenade at me. I don’t know where that grenade came from.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Are you thinking it’s these two guys? </u>
      <u who="BECK">Pardon?</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Are you thinking it’s these two guys or someone closer?</u>
      <u who="BECK">Well, it’s just two guys I saw. The place is polluted with them. They were everywhere. I looked down into the creek bed and up in trees. So I pull my .45 and took good aim and emptied the thing and they both slumped down. So I felt comfortable with that. I figure, he still didn’t see him. At least they’re taken care of. Went back up to <persName>Russell Adams</persName>. So that’s when I come back to <persName>Russell</persName>.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">You’re still carrying the ammo boxes?</u>
      <u who="BECK">These two ammos, yeah. I picked the ammo boxes up and I take them up. So this all happened, the run from <persName>Russell</persName> initially back to first aid and then back up there, I bet you was within like five to ten minutes. It took me like a minute to wrap him up, <placeName>Taboada</placeName> a minute to do that. But I'm running, the distance is seventy-five and seventy-five, whatever it was and I’m exhausted. All the dodging these bullets and grenades. Extremely emotional and I’m lying on the ground, halfway up. The grounds cracking, the dirt is flying up, bullets cracking by your head and everything. So you have to jump and dodge and you’re trying to weave, not make it an easy target for them. So I'm trying to stay alive. I’m laying down totally exhausted, can’t move anymore. Eventually, got up off my ass to get <persName>Russell</persName>. I finally catch up to <persName>Russell</persName>. Come up and get more ammo. There was another belt of ammo in the gun and off to his left in our rear, just less than ten yards is this GI laying on his back with his arm up in the air with a canteen. It’s like he is trying to drain the canteen. So I see that, from my vantage point on the ground, I see just his arm. I look up and I see this GI. I tell <persName>Russell</persName>, “I'm going to give him first aid.” He’s firing at the enemy, <persName>Russell</persName> is. We’re being shot at the whole time, shit’s hitting the tree and this and that.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">The machine gunners were the prime target.</u>
      <u who="BECK">Well, I guess so, you know. Which I found out later, yes, they were. The radio operators, the machine guns and officers. Anybody that was giving orders like, “Follow me” and stuff, like <persName>lieutenant Taft</persName>, picked them off right away. Radio operators. I guess we were on the list also. Not that the rifle man wasn’t on the list either, we were all targets. Anyway, I run over. This poor guy’s laying there. There’s radios lying beside him. His M16 is laying on the ground. He’s lying there, he’s looking up at the sky. Just some tall thin kid. About my height and weight and everything, but I didn’t know the guy. I didn’t see a name tag or anything. I look and he’s got a hole in his chest. Dead center. I assumed, not being a medic or anything, I assumed it went right through his heart. But he’s still alive. You can see he’s like in shock. I ripped his shirt open and I rolled him over. On his side and I said, “You’re going to be okay.” I’m lying like a son of a bitch. I said, “You’re going to be okay.” I guess they taught us that at first aid school at <placeName>Benning</placeName>, I don't know. Tell a guy he’s going to be alright, give him some moral support. I said, “You’re going to be okay.” Expecting to see half his back blown out. I roll him and it’s the same little hole in the back. So that’s how close we were to high velocity. You know, zipped right through him. But still, it killed him. He was still alive there when I was working, I patched him up with his first aid pack. Took it off and tried to wrap him up best I could. I knew it was going to be like hopeless. But the poor kid, he’s lying there in the sun baking. I called for a medic there and this black medic came up. I knew the guys face but I just don’t know his name. He came pretty quickly, which I was really pleased. I thought, “It’s good somebody heard me”. I'm screaming at the top of my lungs. I'm yelling medic half a dozen times. He comes and when I leave him to go back to <persName>Russell</persName>, it’s only ten yards away. I go back to <persName>Russell</persName> and I think it was—when I got close to <persName>Russell</persName>, where I could see him, I see he was shot.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Where?</u>
      <u who="BECK">In the head. He’s lying there and I get up to <persName>Russell</persName>, I said, “<persName>Russell</persName>!” Jesus. He’s in bad shape. He got shot right through the helmet, creased his head. Head’s laying wide open and all this blood and mess. He’s lying there and he’s looking up in the sky. His mouth is open, but he’s not saying anything. I lied to him! I said, “Oh, you’re going to be okay <persName>Russell</persName>.” I got to get the gun, the gun’s laying on the side. When he got shot, everything went to hell and we’re under attack, the bullets are still hitting, cracking. He’s laying right there. So I upright the gun, take aim out there where we were firing last before I left him. There’s something I wanted to tell you here and I don’t want to lose my thoughts. Anyhow, I start firing right away again. Firing, firing, firing, screamed for medic in between. Screamed for “Medic! Medic! Medic!” Lo and behold, he comes another medic. Some blond hair kid, I didn’t get his name. Only partial of it. I told <persName>General Moore</persName> it was like “Nall”, N-A-L-L, which is probably part of his name. I did years trying to research to find this guy. Could never find anybody by that name. But there again, I can paint a picture of this medic, some blond haired kid, slight build and all that stuff. He came up and took care of <persName>Russ</persName>. We partially dragged him back, I don't know if I helped load him up on this kid or what. But anyhow, he took him out. So I'm on the gun and we’re still under attack.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Are you seeing the enemy coming at you?</u>
      <u who="BECK">Yeah. Yeah.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">How far away?</u>
      <u who="BECK">Well, here’s the story. Let me think if I was going to say something about that—I forgot that one thought already.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Well, what about when you took the gun over and you’re calling for the medic.</u>
      <u who="BECK">Yeah, there was something in there I was going to say with the medic. It’s just too much. </u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Did he say something to you? Did you communicate?</u>
      <u who="BECK">No, this second medic, we prayed. We had like a minute to pray.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Really?</u>
      <u who="BECK"><persName>Russell</persName>’s laying there, he’s a mess. Right up the gun. So here’s there and we’re looking at this. You know, <persName>Russell</persName> and I. I wrote <persName>Russell</persName> off. He’s dead, you know. He’s going to die. It was a horrible thing to see. So somehow this guy and I we’re talking about god and stuff. We started crying. I mean, the fear. The fear. </u>
      <u who="VERRONE">In the middle of this chaos?</u>
      <u who="BECK">Oh yeah, the fear just jumped on you! That’s the scaredest I’ve ever been in my life, you know. Because you knew you were going to die. We’re praying to god, to each other out loud. I remember crying, I'm not ashamed to say it. The tears.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Do you remember what you were saying? The prayers?</u>
      <u who="BECK">Yeah, I was making promises. I was making false promises and stuff. “If you let me out of this, I'll do this.” But anyhow, not proud of that, but I was scared enough to seek him out. But anyhow, they get rid of him and stuff. So now I spot three or four dead center. I was getting fire from the right, which was out of jungle. It was only like twenty to thirty years. It was real bad, it was real nasty there. I knew somebody was directly to the right about twenty, thirty yards in a creek bed and my other buddies from another machine gun crew and that was it. This was all mine out here. The rest of the guys were in the rear, and in the jungle, which I didn’t see for as long as I was up or you know an hour or whatever it was. But anyhow, I got everything straight. I'm trying to get my bearings. What I wanted to interject is, the fear left though, as fast as it can. All this fear came down on you, crying and everything else. When I went back to business, it was like all gone. It’s like the nicest calm that you want to experience. It was like it went from like slow motion and stuff, to serenity or something. I don’t know how to put it into words, but it’s a feeling.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">How did that happened? Do you know?</u>
      <u who="BECK">I don't know, it’s just like—I guess you say to yourself, once you get that out of your system real quick, you say to yourself, “Well, this is the way it’s going to be. I’m going to die. So are you going to die like a man or something?” I don’t know what comes over you. It’s just I made acceptance with this situation at that particular time. All of the sudden, I wasn’t scared anymore. Like, maybe I turned to anger when I think about it. Maybe my fear turned to real anger and I thought, “Alright, let’s get it on. Let’s get business done with here.” If I turn out like <persName>Russ</persName>, so be it, but let’s go. But for real, there I am, and I spot some movement directly in front of me, which is like forty to fifty yards and then off to the left, I had a nice hundred-yard field of fire. So that’s the way we went into the jungle off this mountain, of <placeName>Chu Pong Mountain</placeName>. So I was comfortable with straight ahead to the left, but not in the jungle because they could come up real close there and you couldn’t see. You see stuff moving, just fire in there you know. I spotted two or three four movement in front, so I'm laying down fire and everything else. Bullets smacking, hit and I still don’t know how I didn’t get hit, because I don’t know if they are coming from the front or the side or what. Just thump! You know, dirt kick up and crack. You tried to keep your head down and keep firing. So I'm firing and all of the sudden my gun stops abruptly. Dead stop. And it’s smoking because I’ve been firing the gun for a while, he and I. There’s smoke coming off the gun. So we’re firing the hell out of this machine gun. I don’t know, I wasn’t trained for this stuff. I thought, “What the hell is that?” I'm under attack and my gun ain’t working. I had .45s on me, but this thing isn’t good at all, this isn’t going to go good at all. So I did what I—I don’t think I was trained for this, you do what you have to do. I opened up the feed cover and leaned over and looked down in the gun and I could see a brass round was jammed in there. So I thought the only thing I could do is, I pick the gun up, I'm laying down in a prone position. Picked the gun up, slammed it down on the ground. Picked it back up and looked in there, and it was gone, it knocked out. So I put the belt of ammo back in, I put the feed plate down and the cover. Cocked it and pressed the trigger and it worked. So what I assumed happened was—that’s what an assistant gunner is for. When the gunner is on here, the assistant gunner lays to your left and he feeds you the ammo, you put it in the machine gun, and he keeps the ammo off the ground. Anything that comes as you’re firing, it rolls to his hand. You could clean stuff off. Well, mine was laying in the ground, it was picking up all this grass, dirt, rocks and stones. All this debris and it was taking that into the mechanism, and it jammed my gun. Well, that scene went like slow motion. Everything went deaf. You don’t hear nothing. All these explosions, all of the sudden you’re in your little world. It’s like a macabre dream or something. Everything is slow and stops. Until I start firing again and it’s all real life again. You know that incident, it probably—I bet that didn’t take me five seconds to do what I did there. To knock that round out and start firing again. But at the time, it was like an hour. It seemed like an hour. Anyhow, they stopped coming. You know, I was laying down fire nice and low. Because where they were at, it was just grass and some smaller trees. Wasn’t like off to the right real thick jungle. So I know I had to fire low because that’s the last time I saw them. So they were hiding on the ground too, you know trying to crawl up on you. But they stopped coming. But that was an incident right there that scared the hell out of me too, when the gun stopped.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Yeah, I can imagine. Your vulnerability.</u>
      <u who="BECK">Well, I wasn’t trained for it. You just act on instinct. Then the machine gun crew over here, I hear yelled at <persName>Rivera Rodriguez</persName> was shot. His guts were on the ground, he’s screaming over there, he’s the same hard that we’re all in. I'm screaming to him that <persName>Russell</persName>’s hit. He’s screaming that <persName>Rodriguez </persName>is hit. So now I'm by myself anyhow. So I settle in there for—I have no clue for time or whatever. I saw an A1E Skyraider get shot down right there, which was very important to me because when I was there, this A1E Skyraider was flying around up there. There might have been a couple, I don’t know but this one was flying around up there. I was watching them from time to time when I had a lull here. I'm looking, I’d get up as high as I could without exposing myself too much. I look around and see nothing. Kept looking and looking. He’d be flying in and all of the sudden he’d make these dives. It was a beautiful thing to watch, this old Skyraider prop driven plane. He comes flying down, real straight down and he’s firing his fifty caliber machine guns, with all that noise and everything else. I see where’s he firing, he’s firing over to the right on the other side of the jungle, coming down from the mountain. So I assume, because that’s where I saw most of my action, coming over here to the left a little bit, stopping most of right here. So I'm assuming, “Well, he has a better vantage than me from up there.” So there it comes, I paid particular attention to anything over in this area. Because I knew that from my buddies here, I had this whole field of fire here. I didn’t have a good thing here in the jungle, you know. Like a set thirty yards. Anyhow, one of these bombing runs, and he’s dropping his bombs too, and shooting rockets whatever they had on those planes. But he was doing everything. So he makes a big dive one time and I'm watching and bam! He just bursts into flames. To this day, I don’t know if he got machine gunned from the mountain or from the ground or he was flying so low and dropping his bombs so low for real, that it could’ve been from one of his own bombs. Fragments come up and he got hit in the fuselage. He burst into flames and of course he’s still coming, and the flames are way back there, he’s leaving this big trail of smoke and flames. Well, he dipped down, like I said very low and he dipped down, and he was just above the treetop level. I’m telling you, I bet he wasn’t a football field high. Three hundred feet, right? A football field high off the ground, just above the trees. You know, the trees are like thirty feet or something like that and he was just above it. He came down and he went right down above the creek bed, straight down behind us from the mountain and went down there and he dished down into the jungle and he was killed. I found out it was <persName>Captain McClellan</persName>, <persName>Paul Truman McClellan</persName>. I found out years later who the pilot was. But I tried to tell people this. I told <persName>General Moore</persName>, this gentleman was alive when he got hit because—here’s another thing, I'm lying on the ground and I'm screaming at this pilot at the top of my lungs, “Get out! Get out!” You know, it’s just a reaction. But I still remember and I'm looking out because you can’t believe this, what’s going on before your eyes. Here’s coming down and I’m looking, and he’s up there in the cockpit and I can see this guy, he’s looking down at the ground. Now, he didn’t particularly see me on the ground, but we’ve been at a nice place for him to come in for a belly landing, our LZ if he could. But he didn’t have that choice. So he goes—but he was alive because a lot of people surmised. I am an eyewitness, and I will stick to my guns. I heard a couple of people say over the years, that were up in the helicopters and they saw me and said, “Oh, he was killed instantly.” No, that’s not true. He was alive.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">You saw him looking around?</u>
      <u who="BECK">Yes. I watched him moving around and stuff. He died when he hit the jungle or was captured by North Vietnamese. Because I don’t think they ever found his body actually. But they found the plane and everything you know. But that was an incident when I was up there also. Just frightening, shocking scenes, you know. Out of <placeName>Hollywood</placeName>, you know. </u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Yeah</u>
      <u who="BECK">Yeah, I’ve watched a lot of <name type="event">World War II</name> films and stuff and that was always like a—since I didn’t participate in <name type="event">World War II</name> or <name type="event">Korea</name>, that was always like a movie to a kid growing up.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Yeah, you watched it before <name type="event">Vietnam</name>?</u>
      <u who="BECK">See all these planes and boats and the attacks and you know kamikaze planes. But to see it live right in front of your eyes, I mean man, that never leaves you.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">You’d watch these movies before <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, when you were a kid growing up?</u>
      <u who="BECK">Oh, when I was a kid, yeah. I watched the black and white stuff. Victory at Sea, all those great movies and stuff. To this day, I'm a historian in the sense that I love documentaries. I like watching anything real. I won’t watch a fiction movie. I like the documentaries, the history channel stuff like that. But yeah, when it happens right in front of your face, you take a snapshot of it in your brain and it’s with you for life. You never forget it. But yeah.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">So you make your way over to creek bed, don’t you?</u>
      <u who="BECK">Yeah, finally. Someone came by and said—some officer came by when the guys left, and I was happy to see that. At this time now—</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">That was <persName>Herren</persName>, right? He came up, you and <persName>John Herren</persName>.</u>
      <u who="BECK">Yeah, and I didn’t know him at the time either. But at the time, all I had seen guys killed and wounded and everything, I actually thought we were the last guys alive. Me and the buddies over in the jungle, they were on the other machine gun. Now, I hear all this noise and all this firing and everything else. But hell, I'm seeing these dead guys, couple of medics and stuff. But I figured we’re taking a real ass whipping and we’re going down. Well, <persName>Captain Herren</persName> comes by and taps me on the helmet and says, “Stay put. You’re with so and so.” And I was happy with that because finally we had somebody there you know, oh thank god, I had some friendship up here. Anyhow, stayed there for a bit and then someone came over to me then and said, “Join your company down there in the creek bed, A Company.” I thought hell, I thought they were all wiped out and killed. Well, when I got down there in the creek bed, I saw <persName>Captain Nadal</persName>. I saw several of my other buddies. I was very, very happy to see that.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">What did say to you? Or did they—</u>
      <u who="BECK">Well, no, they’re all busy too, you know. They’ve been doing their thing same as I was. We’re all preoccupied. They’re loading up their guns and making sure they had more ammo and they’re organizing and staying focused.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Because I'm wondering, something that people—I don't know if they know or not. What kind of conversations is going on? Are you all not talking at all except, “Do this, do this, do this”? Or are you going “Oh my god, I can’t believe were in this”? Or—</u>
      <u who="BECK">No, we’re beyond that point. We’re beyond that point right there. We were focused and we’re listening for some leadership, which we had with <persName>Captain Nadal</persName>, thank god. That’s what I mean, I was very happy to see him. Somebody with some rank is telling us what the hell is going on here. What was I involved here, what the hell is going on? I'm out there by myself, I don’t know what’s going on. Other than we are under attack and somebody is trying to kill me, and they shot my buddies. What are we up against? Where are we? What are doing? You know, should we go here? Right? Left? What are we supposed to look for? Anyhow, other than the bad guy, we knew what they looked like. Anyhow, I felt very good and very happy in the creek bed. Plus, we had to shelter. I had to shelter for the first time down in that creek bed. It was like four feet deep, five feet at best. Four, four and a half feet deep and maybe anywhere from four feet to six feet wide at different points. This river came from the mountain and snaked down and zig-zagged. It wasn’t like a straight creek. It zig-zagged with all these little curves and things. Guys were throwing hand grenades, then enemy and our guys were in there. They were throwing hand grenades back and forth in this creek bed at each other. From one side of the creek to the other. One end to the other. But they were down in there. But I felt good about that because I thought, “Oh man, this is nice. I got some cover here and I got some friends.” You know, this is a new game now and I feel good that I got out of that other mess. Hell, this was going to be no better than what I saw.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Right. So what’s <placeName>Nadal</placeName>’s—he’s like “We’re going.”</u>
      <u who="BECK">We’re down there and I don’t know, if I was there for five minutes or one minute. I'm in there and next thing I know, he’s to my right and I'm here and there’s one or two guys to my left and the rest of the guys were down in the creek bed. I don’t know how many there were right then. Ten, twenty guys? Thirty guys? I don't know. He’s yelling, he says, “Alright get ready! Get ready!” He’s yelling, “Let’s go! Fix bayonets!”</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">You still have your machine gun?</u>
      <u who="BECK">Yeah, I had my machine gun, I'm still by myself by the way.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Oh yeah. </u>
      <u who="BECK">I don’t have an assistant or ammo bearer or anything, but I'm here. Now I have very little ammo too, there’s a story I want to interject here. He’s yelling, “Get yourself ready! Let’s go, were going to make an assault.” He tells his guys, “Fixed bayonets!” He’s screaming “Fixed bayonets! Fixed bayonets!” These guys are putting bayonets, the ones that didn’t already have them on. They’re putting bayonets on, I'm thinking, “What am I going to do?” I had a bayonet I carried on me from digging holes and stuff and opening tin cans and stuff. But you can’t put a bayonet on a machine gun. I wanted to at that time because that’s how insecure I felt, you know. I thought, “Oh my god, bayonets? What’s this about?” I knew we were close, but he said we were going to make an assault. I thought, I'm happy where I'm at! You know, it’s the safest I’ve felt all day. Then he said, “Let’s go.” Goes up over the top, I'm to the left of him. I'm four, five yards no more left to <persName>Tony</persName>. Now were going to cross the creek bed into the jungle. Then stuff is coming in. Machine gun fire and the gunships above us are firing in right on us. Things are exploding around us. Our friendly fire and everything else. It’s a 4th of July. We get out about twenty yards; guys are dropping, you know, us. The <orgName>North Vietnamese</orgName> are dropping out of trees and stuff. You’re firing down here and there’s guys dropping out of trees. Everybody is firing at their own targets. Some guys are firing at the same target. It’s whatever you see, whatever you feel comfortable with. I have this machine gun, now the job of the machine gunner is to spread the area. Keep their heads down so we can advance! Well, I see I have like thirty rounds of ammo left on my belt and that’s it! I went through everything else. This is what I had on this first assault. So I thought, hell, you know two pulls of the trigger and this is gone. On initial assault, I had already fire fifty rounds of this belt anyhow. So I'm left with thirty rounds. I'm standing afterwards with <persName>Captain Nadal</persName> about twenty yards out, just guessing. He looks over at me and screams and yells at me, “God dammit! Fire that machine gun! Lay down some fire!” I thought, he doesn’t know I only have couple of rounds of twenty thirty rounds of ammo because he can’t see it. So I leave a little burst off to please him. But I want to use this machine gun as a sniper rifle. I mean, in a roundabout sense because I want to see my target and try to pick them off one or two rounds, but it didn’t work that way because you can’t see them. You know, they’re bobbing up and down and running around and hiding. They’re at your feet, up in trees. I didn’t have enough ammo to do what he wanted but at that instance, this full-scale thing of fire comes in, this enemy fire and the guys beside <persName>Tony</persName> get killed. <persName>Tony</persName> is on the radio. He’s got his M16 down, he’s on the radio or it might be the other hand, but he’s on the radio and he’s calling in supporters, talking to <persName>Colonel Moore</persName>, whatever he’s doing on the phone. Radio man is behind him. Just as I look over, his radio operator gets shot. Gets hit up here and he goes back on his back and just like a ton of rocks. He goes right back, and I'm looking I said, “Wow!” And these other guys, they drop. The only way <persName>Tony</persName> knew it, he was on the phone is when the guy fell, he took the phone out of <persName>Tony</persName>’s hand. So <persName>Tony</persName> turns around and looks for his radio man and he’s not there. Here’s down there at his feet. So that was it, <persName>Tony</persName> said, “Let’s go.” Everybody grabbed a guy and we dragged them back down to the creek bed. Guys are laying there dead, their dying. That’s that deal. Probably five minutes later, ten minutes, I don’t know what is, he says, “Alright, line up, we’re going to make another assault.” I thought, oh my. I get more ammo now because I'm screaming, “I need ammo, I need ammo.” Somebody gives me a box of ammo. So I got more ammo, so I'm good to go now, I feel fairly good. We make another assault to go out there spraying, everybody is doing their thing. We’re dropping again, we get about twenty yards out there, we got to pull back. But it was that type of thing you know. So I don’t know how many assaults they made before I got there. But I remember being on two and the third one we tried to go left into the thick towards the mountain. I didn’t know at the time, but I think that was to try to find <persName>Savage</persName>, <persName>Ernie Savage</persName>. But I remember the trip very well, we didn’t fare any better there either. We only go about twenty, thirty yards and we have to come back. It was that heavy, they were out there. There were fixed positions now. So it was bizarre to say the least, I'll tell you. It was very hectic.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">What are you feeling? What are these emotions happening? Are you just reacting, reacting, reacting? Following orders or are you—</u>
      <u who="BECK">Yeah. Yeah. One good thing about us, like I stated earlier, we were close knit group. We didn’t hesitate when <persName>Lieutenant Taft</persName> said, “Follow me.”</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">You would.</u>
      <u who="BECK">Although when he passed us, he looked white as a ghost. I'm afraid to tell you that. It looked like the color drained out of him. He must’ve gotten orders on the phone from <persName>Captain Nadal</persName>. They pass them down, <persName>Colonel Moore</persName> to <persName>Captain Nadal</persName>. He must’ve got orders, they said there’s enemies and go in.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Expand the perimeter and go out.</u>
      <u who="BECK">Yeah. We followed him. What the hell, we followed him two months prior to that. We followed them at <placeName>Fort Benning</placeName>, you know these guys. That’s what we’re taught to do. <persName>Tony</persName> says, “Let’s go.” We went. We didn’t have to hesitate. That one guy hesitated. That’s our ammo bearer. They call that “combat shock”.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Yeah, he hesitated. He later found out.</u>
      <u who="BECK">I can jump ahead with this story; I don’t mind sharing this with you because it’s important to me. Through the whole two and half, three days there in that battle, I assumed our ammo bearer was killed, shot and killed or wounded and medevac’d back out to a safer place. When we get back to base camp three, four days later, because we went to <placeName>Pleiku</placeName> for a day and then went back to <placeName>An Khe</placeName> to get refitted and resupplied. We went back out there and we’re asking—we’re standing out for count in the morning and you’re seeing all these spaces. Platoon went from thirty guys down to twenty. The company went from this down to this. All these small numbers and squads you know, “Hey where’s so and so? Where’s so and so?” “Well, he was shot, and he was killed.” “Yeah, I saw him get killed. <persName>Russell</persName>, he died.” I told people that <persName>Russell</persName> got killed when we came back. Because that’s where I left him. I didn’t know they got him to <placeName>Japan</placeName> and then to <persName>Walter Reed</persName> and they actually saved his life and fixed him up. I told guys, “<persName>Russell</persName> died. He got killed, I saw him. He got killed and left me.” So we’re sharing stories. I said, “Where’s <persName>John</persName>? Our Ammo Bearer?” They said, “Oh, he’s down in his pup tent.” They had little pup tents there at <placeName>An Khe</placeName> at our <orgName>7th Cavalry</orgName> base camp, which was home to us. I said, “What do you mean, he’s down there? Is he hurt?” They said “No. Combat shock. He left you guys.” I said, “What do you mean he left us?” He says, “When it hit the fan, when it first started, I guess he saw as much as we did too, he was shocked. He just didn’t handle it the way we did. He took off and got on a chopper that was coming in and then leaving. He got a chopper, and they took him out.” There’s been witnesses on the chopper pilots that took him out. Said there was this guy that they took back, and he was babbling. God bless him, I understand the shock of combat, what we saw and everything else. But he didn’t handle it very well. Anyway, they call it combat shock. The mood I was in right then after that thing and all my buddies and everybody else really pissed off about a lot of things, really hurting. So I said, “I’m going down and I'm going to shoot this son of a bitch.” And I did. I didn’t shoot him; I got my .45 out and I went down to my pup tent—not mine, but we were all side by side and I flipped the flap back and—</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Did you have the .45 in your hand?</u>
      <u who="BECK">Yeah! I really think I was going to shoot him. Because that was my intention. I told the guys, “That no good son of a bitch.” I said, “He left us without ammo! <persName>Russell</persName> got hit, I was out of ammo several times!” I wasn’t a happy camper.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">You had to go back and get it yourself.</u>
      <u who="BECK">Yeah, I wasn’t a happy camper. We could have been overrun because of him, you know what I mean? So anyhow, I go down there. Flip that flap, “I’m going to ream him out and if he gives me some lip, I might shoot him.” I look at him in there, he’s sitting in this little pup tent on top of his helmet. He’s sitting on his helmet with his knees and head in his hands. He looked up at me and it was the most pitiful look I ever seen on a man’s face. I wouldn’t know how to describe it. He looked at me it was like a remorse or shame. I don't know what to call it, but it was extremely pitiful look. I cursed him out, I said, “You son of a bitch.” I left and that was the last we saw him. They gave him a medical discharge. There was something I wanted to say with <persName>Russ</persName> and us, and about him. </u>
      <u who="VERRONE">About <persName>Russell</persName>?</u>
      <u who="BECK">It left me again, I had it when I was telling the story, I should’ve stopped but I didn’t want to. Something fairly important.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">That happened in the action?</u>
      <u who="BECK">Yeah, with <persName>Russ</persName> and I and it didn’t have to do with <persName>John</persName>. It was the ammo and stuff. That’s a shame, it’ll come to me afterwards.[Third party speaks to interviewee.]</u>
      <u who="BECK">I had it and it was a fairly important thing I wanted to get off my chest.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Was it something when he was on the gun?</u>
      <u who="BECK">It was before I left. It was up there. It wasn’t the airplane; it was something else and it wasn’t the gun jamming.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Was it the wasps? That was over by the creek bed.</u>
      <u who="BECK">That was at the creek bed, that was another story. That was crazy too, boy. Talk about unexpected things, you know.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Let me ask you this, we need to wrap it up a little bit because we have someone else waiting. </u>
      <u who="BECK">Yeah, I do.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">You’re there, you’re there that night, the next day. What are you physically like? Tell me what’s going on. </u>
      <u who="BECK">Exhausted. No sleep, we didn’t sleep. We only got like two, three hours of sleep the night before because that’s what we used do. We used to pull that duty. One man on for three hours, one off. Well, actually by the time you get to sleep and then you’re up at five in the morning, you only get two or three hours of sleep. So then we went the whole day with all that action without any sleep and the next day, nobody was sleeping. I know I didn’t. We were totally exhausted. It wears down on you and it starts to get like a dream world. It really does. The 16th, it was like shot. We were standing there waiting to get helicoptered out. Artillery shells were coming in close to us. We weren’t even moving. We were numb.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">On the <date when="1965-11-16">16th</date>? When you’re getting ready to leave?</u>
      <u who="BECK">Yeah, yeah. They’re just blowing up over there. Using the standard. Who gives a damn, you know. No fear, just worn out. Who cares?</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Do you remember <persName>Moore</persName> that day, on the <date when="1965-11-16">16th</date>?</u>
      <u who="BECK">I just remember seeing him. Being honest with you, what I remember of <persName>Colonel Moore</persName> when I first saw him after that battle was, I saw a very—I don’t want to say this the wrong way, I saw a very worn out man. I mean, he looked beat. But then we did too. You see, I didn’t have a mirror to look at myself. I know what I looked like. We were all worn out. Besides, I looked at my buddies, they were <persName>Sergeant Robles</persName> and the other guys. I looked at him and he’s just leaning on the rifles. Nobody is talking. Nobody is saying anything. What they saw and what they experienced; it’s all going through your mind. Well, <persName>General Moore</persName> was no different. He looked exactly like us. But I was surprised, I figured he’d be all chipper and clean. He wasn’t, he was as dirty as we were. Filthy. Worn out. Talk about a guy not sleeping, I'm sure he didn’t get any sleep. Because he had to coordinate for the next day. Me, all I could do is just to stay put and hope we didn’t get attacked again. You know, get overrun.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">What about the “Broken Arrow” call? What do you remember about that? This is the morning of the <date when="1965-11-15">15th</date>.</u>
      <u who="BECK">I didn’t know about it, but I remember the day. I mean, all hell broke loose there. I was over by the creek area during those events. That was another macabre scene. Like this is big, this is serious. Actually, into the third day, I was resigned to the fact that we might be there all week. You know, I thought how? How can we? I didn’t know, but thank god the thing was over, I mean for us anyhow. God bless the guys <orgName>2nd of the 7th</orgName>, what they ran into.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">40th Anniversary. Forty years after this, how’s it been for you here at the reunion?</u>
      <u who="BECK">Oh, it’s always good. It’s always good to come down here, I’ve been coming down here since they initiated the wall in <date when="1982">1982</date> or <date when="1983">’83</date>. I’ve been coming every year. Sometimes twice a year. It’s great to see the guys, it’s great to be able to talk to them, to share. You know, the camaraderie down here, everybody that’s here, went through the same thing you did and that’s the calming effect that helps. It’s hard too because we share stories, and we start talking about our friends that didn’t make it and so those memories drift back here to the painful times.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">What about <persName>Russ</persName>? He survived.</u>
      <u who="BECK"><persName>Russ</persName> is one of the strongest men I know, god bless him. He lives a hundred and ten miles from my house. He has a dairy farm, has like fifty black and white cows. He gets up at five in the morning and goes to bed at midnight if he’s lucky. He milks those cows. He got these big silver vats as big as this room that holds all of these gallons and gallons of milk. Big truck comes and gets his milk. So he’s a dairy farmer and he’s successful at it, it’s a lot of hard work. But he was one of the best troopers I ever knew. Tough, not a big guy, five eight, five ten. Just a tough off the farm kid. They come from inner cities and out on the plains and everything else. <persName>Russell</persName> was a farmer. A tough farm boy. He worked on the farm with his dad as a kid and everything. As strong as an ox.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Tell me about the book and the movie, what’s that done for you? How has that affected you?</u>
      <u who="BECK">Well, it’s a nice accolade to us. It’s a nice credit to our battle and the efforts everybody gave forth. Glad it wasn’t swept under the rug, which I'm sure the politicians would’ve loved it swept. Well, they did in a roundabout way, they swept under the rug. They told the American people it was a victory, and it was, but at what cost? The movie was wonderful, they did a great job, there’s a lot of truth in it. More truth than <placeName>Hollywood</placeName>. I'm just happy it’s out there in a book for generations to read, future generations to read. We pray to god somebody read it and change history the way we do things, the way things are done. Find a way, a better way than war.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">You mean war?</u>
      <u who="BECK"> Find a better way than war. Read that book and read other books on horrible battles of our time and the things that are going on today and say, “You know we can’t just keep giving these 58,226 kids and these 2,040 kids to this day, they’re forty-five and constantly give, give, give.” You got to find some other means. Be nice but I don’t know if it will ever happen. There’s got to be some sacrifices. But I'm glad the book is out there for people to read. I hope the younger generations read and learn. Because it’s a good book, it’s a good story that was told.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Alright <persName>Bill</persName>. Well, thank you so much for sitting and doing this.</u>
      <u who="BECK">Thank you guys for your time. Doctor, thank you very much.(End of interview)</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
