<?xml-model href="../schemas/ddhi.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Transcript of an Interview with Camille Geoghegan Olsen</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>
          <orgName>Vietnam Center and Sam Johnson Vietnam Archive</orgName>
        </authority>
        <date>
          <!--  Date of publication, e.g. for citation purposes  -->
        </date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <recordingStmt>
          <recording xml:id="primary_recording" type="video" dur-iso="0:37:19">
            <!-- https://www.digi.com/resources/documentation/digidocs/90001437-13/reference/r_iso_8601_duration_format.htm -->
            <media url="https://vva.vietnam.ttu.edu/images.php?img=/OH/OH0503/OH0503.mp4" mimeType="video/mp4"/>
          </recording>
        </recordingStmt>
        <bibl xml:id="primary_transcription">
          <respStmt>
            <persName>Mark Steven Varela</persName>
            <orgName>Vietnam Center and Sam Johnson Vietnam Archive</orgName>
            <resp ref="http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/trc.html">Transcriber</resp>
          </respStmt>
          <ref target="https://vva.vietnam.ttu.edu/images.php?img=/OH/OH0503/OH0503.pdf">Primary transcription</ref>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The Oral History Project of the Vietnam Center and Sam Johnson Vietnam Archive</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application ident="DDHIEncoder" version="1.0">
          <desc>Conversion from Word docx to TEI xml.</desc>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en-us">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <particDesc>
        <person xml:id="VERRONE"/>
        <person xml:id="OLSEN"/>
      </particDesc>
      <settingDesc>
        <setting>
          <date when-iso="2005-11-12"/>
          <locale/>
        </setting>
      </settingDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <u who="VERRONE">This is Dr. <persName>Richard Verrone</persName>, I am doing a video oral history interview with <persName>Camille Olsen</persName>. Today is <date when="2005-11-12">November 12th, 2005</date>. It is around 2:30 pm eastern standard time and we’re in <placeName>Washington, D.C.</placeName>, at the <placeName>Crystal City Hilton</placeName>. We are here for the 40th anniversary of the battles of <name type="event">Ia Drang</name>, <name type="event">Plekiu</name>, <name type="event">LZ (Landing Zone) Albany</name>, <name type="event">X-Ray</name>, <name type="event">Falcon</name> and the rest. <persName>Camille</persName>, thank you for doing this. I want to ask you, we’re here obviously for the connection with your father, <persName>Jack Geoghegan</persName> and what he did and how he served the country and his sacrifices there on the second day of the battle at <placeName>LZ X-Ray</placeName>. Tell me, now in <date when="2005">2005</date> before we look into the past, what have you learned about your father separate from his military service, separate from that identity of him. Tell me about him as a person from what your mother has told you and the rest of the extended family and his parents.</u>
      <u who="OLSEN">Well, for as long as I can remember, I don’t even remember a time where I didn’t know about him. There was never this moment in my life where you know, “Your dad died in <name type="event">Vietnam</name>.” It was never like that. And I also grew up very close to his parents and he was an only child. In fact, when my mom remarried, we remained very close with his parents until they died. Which is unusual in today’s world. You know, when people hear that story, we’d have holidays together and all. My stepdad—you know is dad, I mean it’s been dad since I was four years old. It was just so natural; it was just a part of our lives. So there was never a time where he wasn’t a part of our lives. His life and just who he was, it really didn’t register so much for me or I didn’t search for more information until I had my own children, which was—gosh, eight and a half years ago, when <persName>Stephanie</persName>, my oldest was born. I just didn’t understand that whole connection, that whole parent. Those feelings you have. That’s when I wanted to learn more about him and what he was like outside of the things I had learned. I knew he was a wonderful giving person. He was very religious, very into his faith, Catholic. I think an idealist in many ways, just wanted to serve people and really devote his life to that. He—I know you know this story, he deferred going into the <orgName>army</orgName> to get his master’s degree and you know sometimes I think, well if he hadn’t done that and served that time, how different things would be. But what’s interesting even more in the last few years is trying to figure out myself and maybe because I never knew him, how much alike I am to him. You know, it’s funny. People meet me at these reunions and immediately say, the similarities we look so much alike. One man who hadn’t been to any of these before, we met him last year and he served with my dad and he just couldn’t get over it, how much I look like him. But having a brother and sister from the second marriage and how different I am from them. They are very much alike but very different, as all siblings are. But I am so different in so many ways. It’s just it’s starting to really click and kind of hit home that that’s the genetic stuff. That’s all, that’s you’re wiring that’s just there! So I thought about that a lot more recently.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">What have you thought? I mean there are similarities but tell me what it is that you find about yourself and your father, that connection.</u>
      <u who="OLSEN">Well, it’s funny I’ve really been thinking about this so much lately just with relationships. Right now, I'm married, married the love of my life really. You’ll get to meet him tonight, it’s just an amazing man. Two beautiful children and I'm so fortunate in that and also fortunate that we’re in position right now where I can be home with the kids. So in that role, kind of that being home and then having to develop friendships and relationships with people, other women or in the neighborhood. I'm much more involved in that than I was when I was working. Of course, I couldn’t. It’s hard to be involved in all that. But I find myself just—so much wanting to nourish those friendships and those relationships and it’s always been a big part of me. Having good friends and keeping those contacts and doing things for others. I don’t want to sound corny because I don’t mean it like that.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">It’s not coming across that way.</u>
      <u who="OLSEN">Okay. I just—for example, my husband is having back surgery on Wednesday. So we have a lot going on, were thinking about that and I also have a couple a friends who—a friend who has to have something removed from her breast, it’s a concern a cancer thing and another friend who is dealing with some other issues. I just want to make sure I do a little something for them. You know, put a card in the mail or just something a little different than just a phone call that makes them know I'm thinking about them and that’s so important to me to do those kinds of things. The more I hear of my dad, the more I mean he’s so much like that. I think—and my mom is too, so much like that which is interesting that they were such a perfect match. So I'm sure that comes from both of them. But I have thought about that a lot lately that is so important. I'm not doing it for that reaction you know, those people or whatever. To be grateful or thankful or any of that. Just something to kind of brighten your day.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">This is how your mother described <persName>Jack</persName>. She described him as a very selfless person. Someone who wanted to really do for others in a simple way and in a complicated way, like going to <placeName>Africa</placeName> and taking on this huge responsibility and this huge undertaking but also in the smallest ways, being kind to people. She gave an example of how he treated his and cared about his men in his platoon as an officer and how they looked to him and have a relationship with him and the trust with him and how he died speaks to that very clearly. Trying to say that one of his troopers, one of his men.</u>
      <u who="OLSEN">Right.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Let me ask you a couple of things about when you realized he had been killed in this war. How old were you? I mean, five, six, seven years old? Somewhere in there?</u>
      <u who="OLSEN">Yeah, but I mean I don’t even remember there being a realization. It was just always there. It was always a part of our lives, my life.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">When did it become, don’t take this wrong, significant? The realization of, “Okay, <name type="event">the Vietnam War</name>.” You kind of see the <name type="event">war</name> in a context and, “My father was part of that, he never came home.” When did that start to happen?</u>
      <u who="OLSEN">Well, I remember very vivid memories of being—I was probably fifth or sixth grade, my dad was stationed at <placeName>Fort Riley, Kansas</placeName>. So I remember the home and all of that. I remember going through a series of nightmares where he was in my mind running and getting shot—</u>
      <u who="VERRONE"><persName>Jack</persName>?</u>
      <u who="OLSEN"><persName>Jack</persName>. Over and over again. I couldn’t shake it, you know. I was afraid to go to sleep. I vividly picture the room and everything during that time.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Is that because your mother had said, “This is how he died”?</u>
      <u who="OLSEN">Right. And I knew. There had to have been something. I just really remember that dream. I don’t remember what may have triggered that or why I was dreaming that. I'm sure along the way, I mean just throughout my life there’s been times, moments where it is sad or there’s a memory or when my grandparents were alive. Their memories, although they were trying to be very happy or positive. They didn’t want to dwell on the sadness. They wanted the joy and all in your lives. I remember that and once again, different periods of my life. When I was here living in this area, soon after the book, I had joined this organization, <orgName>Sons and Daughters in Touch</orgName> which is—you’re familiar with that group?</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Yes.</u>
      <u who="OLSEN">You know, wow there’s actually people out there like me because you didn’t encounter people that lost their dads or anybody that they even knew in <name type="event">Vietnam</name> really. Very few.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">It wasn’t until really the mid ‘80s when talking about <name type="event">Vietnam</name> and trying to understand <name type="event">Vietnam</name> became something—</u>
      <u who="OLSEN">That was okay.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Yes! An okay part of conversation and an okay analysis to have.</u>
      <u who="OLSEN">And what’s funny is that I have friends from this group, <orgName>Sons and Daughters</orgName>, who vividly they remember that time period when you couldn’t talk about and it was embarrassing or shameful that you had a relative or father serve there. But I didn’t have that experience. I don’t know if that was my mom who sheltered that somewhat, I don't know. But I never had that feeling, like an embarrassed feeling that he had been there. I never, never. </u>
      <u who="VERRONE">What kind of feeling was it and is it?</u>
      <u who="OLSEN">It’s sad to me. I just feel like—I don’t even know how to describe; I don't even really know how to answer that. It’s sad, when I think about him and being there, he was there for such a short time and that— it’s very sad. It’s more of, I guess it’s kind of that, “What if” feeling. Cause there’s nothing—if things didn’t happen the way they did, if he’d been in R&amp;R (Rest and Recuperation) that day or whatever, how things would’ve been different. So I don’t know, just surrounding that whole thing there was just a lot of confusion in my own mind or questions that will never be answered. Not that I would want to change. I think about my life and my children and all that. They’re such an impact that my mom and her remarriage and <persName>John</persName> who she’s married to, wonderful man. None of that would be. So it’s kind of just this convoluted, strange feeling.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">No, I can only imagine. Tell me about your father. <persName>John Johns</persName> and tell me, how has he treated this issue over your life?</u>
      <u who="OLSEN">He’s amazing. Honestly, he just—it wasn’t until I was older and even with the movie, even more so because there was more talk of him, of my father, my first father. It’s hard for him—sometimes I have to say to distinguish the two I'll say, “My stepfather.” And I don’t mean that, but he has a hard time with that. And I do too, I don’t like to say that because he’s not my stepfather, I mean he is technically. But he’s my father, he raised me.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">You were what? Four and a half years old?</u>
      <u who="OLSEN">Four and a half. I think they met when I was—I was three. Yeah, because they were married in April and my birthday is in June, so I was almost four when they married. So I don’t know anything different, I don’t remember anything different. But he has been just amazing. So incredibly supportive. With that book, he encouraged my mom to do that, to write that. He is so proud of all that’s come of it. I mean, he’ll be telling people the story. He’ll be bringing it up and we’re like, “Oh jeez, bringing it up again.” It’s cute. He’s just that excited about it. To this day, encourages us to be as involved with the movie as we could be, every aspect of it. When I said I wanted to go to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, I mean he’s helping me—I mean paying my way to go. I got some veterans’ donations, but they paid the rest of that.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Right.</u>
      <u who="OLSEN">That was so important to keep my father’s memory alive. But really because I didn’t have so much of that sadness that so many children that lost their dads in war had, I was very fortunate, and I know that. When I am around this group, <orgName>Sons and Daughters</orgName>, and listen to some of their experiences even when their mothers did remarry and a lot of them are just horrific stories. I mean just—and it just makes me realize again how fortunate I am. There was just not that sadness associated. I just didn’t. So lucky, I feel so at peace with it all, always have, really. I mean there’s been points in my life where I’ve gone through some turmoil trying to understand it or understand my feelings. One thing I was going to say earlier that kind of slipped my mind, I transgressed on something else, but the <orgName>Sons and Daughters</orgName> group that I joined way back when this book was done, and they had their first Father’s Day banquet. I went and I brought my mom with me and all I did was go to the banquet, didn’t go to anything else associated with it. It just scared me to death. I sat there and listened to <persName>Tony Cordera</persName>, who’s the president of the group then, still is. Very involved and he’s done phenomenal things for the organization, started describing the feelings of having this father that was lost in the war and just kind of synopsis of everybody’s feelings, all the children. I sat there and I cried. I couldn’t stop crying. You know that heaving crying, it was awful!</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">From your gut.</u>
      <u who="OLSEN">Oh, I could not! My poor mom she just didn’t know what to do. She just sat there not knowing how to handle that because the speakers are going on and we’re sitting banquet room and a veteran next to me, who I didn’t know. We just wound up sat next to these people. He just took my hand and held my hand through the whole thing. That experience scared me to where I didn’t want any part of that group.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Really?</u>
      <u who="OLSEN">Uh-huh. It had such a huge impact. I was just afraid of that and afraid of that emotion that it brought out.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Did it surprise you?</u>
      <u who="OLSEN">Oh, yeah. I shocked me. It just—(Chuckles) I think about it now and it was overwhelming and that tends to be how the emotional calm. Because I really do feel at peace with it all but there will be times that just different things will trigger an emotion and I never know, it’s unexpected.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Is there regret?</u>
      <u who="OLSEN">Regret from?</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Fill in the blank, for not—you kind of touched on that because you’ve been very blessed in your life. But what about not knowing your first father.</u>
      <u who="OLSEN">Oh, that’s the hardest part. I don't know, I talk to people who knew their father and how they felt, and I think maybe that’s harder.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Yeah, because they are very tangible.</u>
      <u who="OLSEN">Very tangible, exactly. In my mind it’s like—I describe it, I describe it frankly because it’s the only way I can kind of have a word to put to it but almost a ghost like figure in my mind he is. It’s like I know he existed and there’s all these tangible things to know that, me being predominantly one of them but to actually think of him as a person, you know, and what you’re doing <date when="2005-11-12">today</date> is so amazing because you’re going to have audio and video and something to relate to so much better. We don’t even have audio, I have nothing. Nothing! To know how he spoke, his voice.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Right. You have this one picture, is that correct?</u>
      <u who="OLSEN">That’s it! I’ve got a few, there’s a few pictures of he and I. There’s that picture from the book, and there’s a few right after I was born where’s he’s holding me. Then of course there’s some military pictures, but you know back then people just don’t take pictures like they do now. And I don’t have anything. I’ve contacted <orgName>Widener University</orgName>, “Do you have any footage of him just on the military, on the field, <orgName>ROTC (Reserve Officer Training Corps)</orgName>? Doing something.”</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">And they don’t?</u>
      <u who="OLSEN">No!</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">That’s amazing.</u>
      <u who="OLSEN">They’re telling me they don’t! I mean it’s so frustrating. I have pictures of you know that time too when he was at school, very few. It’s funny because the ones that I do have generally of him are, you know he’s in uniform and very straight and rigid and the whole thing and I happen to—I can’t remember, somebody showed me a picture from the college days where he was at a party and there were all this group of guys and they were all making these goofy smiles and it was the first time I ever saw a picture like that, just this other side of him. But that to me is the hardest part. I don’t have anything to—I just don’t have anything. Mannerisms, I’ve said before just how he walked! I mean just the little things that make a person a person.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Your mother commented on you, that you look like him, you act like him in a lot of ways. So maybe you have yourself in that sense.</u>
      <u who="OLSEN">That’s a good way to put it, I’d never thought of it that way.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Do you get tired of talking about this? This subject?</u>
      <u who="OLSEN">No, no.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">People kind of identifying you with him versus identifying you with you and your life now or since, I guess?  </u>
      <u who="OLSEN">I’ve never felt that way. I don't know if because—you know, you just think of all the different aspects of your life and the different kind of roles you play and whether I'm <persName>Stephanie</persName>’s mom or <persName>Ray</persName>’s wife or <persName>Jack Geoghegan</persName>’s daughter, it’s just who I am at that moment. Like when I'm here, it just feels so good to have people come. These men are just amazing. They just, they embrace you and they make you a part of it all.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Do you all sit with them? Stay with them? How do you interact with them?</u>
      <u who="OLSEN">We do. The last few dinners we’ve been sitting with his whole company, <orgName>C Company</orgName> and the different folks there that remember him, which is really neat. His radio operator, my dad’s radio operator came to—I want to say it was three dinners ago. It must’ve been—I think it was when <persName>Randy Wallace</persName> was speaking about the movie. I think that was the one it was. It was that one or the one after, but I believe it was that one. And I had never met this man, I didn’t even know he existed. Somebody that was with my dad when he died, with him, heard the shots. To meet him was so amazing.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">You learn more about that incident.</u>
      <u who="OLSEN">Yeah! It’s just that experience, that incident. He tells me every time I see him and I'm sure he’ll be here tonight—I’ve only seen him at these reunions three times now, but just the night before he died, how much they were in the foxhole and they were talking, and they just stayed up. I mean they were up all night! Talking about how much, he’s like, “How much your dad loves you and your mother.” He said they kind of promised each other, like I think so many do in situations, if something happens to me, you know one of the two, make sure word gets back and take care of my family and all that. He had a really hard time doing that. He couldn’t—I'm sure that was just such an awful experience to go through.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">The burden I guess too.</u>
      <u who="OLSEN">Right. So when he finally came to one of these dinners he just hugged me and hugged me. It’s got to be so hard for those guys too.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">I’ve heard, and you can corroborate this, that someone else wanted to go get <persName>Willie Godboldt</persName> and he said, “No, I'll go.”</u>
      <u who="OLSEN">Yes. I’ve heard that too.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">How do you feel about that? I mean that’s a huge question, sorry to put that to you.</u>
      <u who="OLSEN">No, no.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">And have you met the Godbolts? Have you had any contact with this family?</u>
      <u who="OLSEN">No, I have not met them. Which is sad, I would love to meet them. You know, I don’t really think of it—of course it crosses my mind what if he hadn’t gone? What would’ve happened? Would he be here now? And honestly, the more I hear about the type of person he was, I don’t think he would’ve made it back. I don’t think—if it hadn’t been that incident, it would’ve been another incident. It was such a massacre. Not just <name type="event">LZ X-Ray</name> but—</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Oh, <name type="event">Albany</name>. Yes.</u>
      <u who="OLSEN">I don’t know if he would’ve made it out regardless of that.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Tell me about <persName>Hal Moore</persName> and the role he’s played for you and your mother in your life.</u>
      <u who="OLSEN">I’ve really gotten to know him through these reunions. You know the story where mom was in touch with him and when he came back from <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, he wanted to go to my dad’s grave. So he and <persName>Julie</persName> have always been a part of my mom’s life. To a certain degree, you know kind of fading in and out, I guess depending on what’s going on at that time in their lives. What’s interesting is he also knows <persName>John</persName>, my dad.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Yes, they worked together.</u>
      <u who="OLSEN">Yeah, it’s just amazing. So we have that connection too. But it wasn’t really until these dinners and I remember when we first started coming and it was in conjunction with the book being released and <persName>General Moore</persName> did a special tribute to the wives and the children. We all got medals and you know it was just a ceremony that he wanted to do, and he continued to do that for every dinner whenever there was a child or spouse, he would do that. So I got to know him through that and of course you know with the movie and having much more interaction with him there. He’s been amazing.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Tell me about the book and how that affected you back in the early nineties and you’ve touched on that already. But also, the movie. You guys, that relationship between <persName>Jack</persName>, your dad, and your mom was one of the big parts of that film. One of the huge emotional ties of that film. Tell me about the book and the movie and how that’s affected you.</u>
      <u who="OLSEN">Well, the book—I was so proud when that came out, just so excited. Everybody was. Everybody associated with that. So that just carried. I was working here in <placeName>D.C.</placeName> when that came out, I was actually working at a bank that no longer exists (Chuckles). All these banks that—</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">The mergers—</u>
      <u who="OLSEN">Yes, yes. But I vividly remember all that and sharing all that with the people I worked with. Just being so proud of it and all. And then wanting to get a little more involved, that’s when I kind of reached out to the <orgName>Sons and Daughters</orgName>. But it really wasn’t until the movie, which of course at that point when the movie was starting to be made, I had one child.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">How did you feel about it?</u>
      <u who="OLSEN">The movie? </u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="OLSEN">So excited.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">About it being made?</u>
      <u who="OLSEN">Oh yes. Didn’t have any problem with that. Well, we had thought initially—well, for a long part actually until filming, that there wasn’t going to be a part for my dad. That there was actually our name going to be used or any of that. That they would probably just take a combination of people and create a character. I had no idea that it would be what it is. I actually saw <persName>Randy Wallace</persName> last night and we were talking about it and he just goes back to that chapter that she wrote, and he said, “How can I do anything but represent your mom and you.” He said it was just the way it was written, and he really wanted to do that. So that was remarkable to find out yes, there was a character. Just amazing, and <persName>Keri Russell</persName>. I don't know if mom told you all the coincidences and strange things that seemed to happen. All these little things sometimes and then bigger things other times, but one of the so called “coincidences” that happened in association with this that I think is really fun is that when we found out there were roles for my parents and <persName>Chris Klein</persName>. So we were able to, I could show mom pictures of <persName>Chris Klein</persName> or we got some movies and directed her to go see this movie. Some of them no.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Don’t do American Pie but—</u>
      <u who="OLSEN">Right? Exactly! (Laughs) She’s so funny, she said, “My children are sheltering me from movies.” When we found out <persName>Keri Russell</persName> and she didn’t know who <persName>Keri Russell</persName> was. At the same time, they were in <placeName>Fort Benning</placeName> filming and <persName>Keri Russell</persName> was struggling with wanting to call my mom and was afraid to call her. She said for three days, she’d pick up the phone and put it down because she didn’t know how my mom would react or how she’d react, the whole thing. So this is in conjunction with my mom now finding out there’s this person <persName>Keri Russell</persName> playing with her. I’m on the phone with my mom and she has one of those dial-up computer networks, so I had to get off the phone for her to then get on the computer to look up a picture of <persName>Keri Russell</persName>. So I had found one on mine. I said, “Okay mom, go to such and such site and you’ll see <persName>Keri</persName>.” So we hang up the phone. Mom types in the address you know, <persName>Keri</persName>’s picture is coming up on the screen and the phone rings and it’s Keri. I mean just at the exact same time.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Wow.</u>
      <u who="OLSEN">Things like that just happened! You know to me that’s not a coincidence. There’s more to that. Emails would cross, <persName>Randy</persName> and my mom would send an email with the exact same time. They hadn’t corresponded in months and then an email would cross, and you would know that they each sent it.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">That’s neat.</u>
      <u who="OLSEN">Just really cool things like that. Unbelievable. All throughout the whole process of the movie.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">You’re glad that this movie happened, glad the book happened?</u>
      <u who="OLSEN">Oh yes, yes.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Has it brought your father more alive to you?</u>
      <u who="OLSEN">Uh-huh. Oh, it has and in so many ways. It’s funny because I said with <persName>Chris Klein</persName> I said, “I’d just would love to be able to stay in touch with him in some way. Not in any regular basis. But because my girls are going to think you’re their granddad in a certain way that’s how they’re going to connect and just to have that for them would be wonderful.”</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">What did he say?</u>
      <u who="OLSEN">Oh, he was fine with it. “Oh yes, yes!” You know, we’ll see, and <persName>Keri Russell</persName> has been very good about, she’ll keep in touch with my mom, my mom will send her an email every so often and she’ll get back so that’s really nice that we have that connection. But the movie itself, everything about was just a good experience for us. They just treated the story just so beautifully.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Tell me about the role of your husband, <persName>Greg</persName> and this whole thing. Has he been?</u>
      <u who="OLSEN">Oh <persName>Greg</persName>, yeah. He still can’t believe it’s all happened. He’s just in awe over it still. So supportive, when I went to the filming at <placeName>Fort Benning</placeName> and it left him with, at that time <persName>Julia</persName> our youngest was five six months old. So he was left with her and I was gone for four nights, but he was, “You got to do it, just go do!” Same thing with <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, when I went to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> and that was an eighteen-day trip.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Tell me about that, going back to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. Where did you go? What did you do?</u>
      <u who="OLSEN">Well, we went—I was with this group, <orgName>Sons and Daughters</orgName> and of course the whole purpose of this trip, it was the first trip to go as a group. <orgName>Sons and daughters</orgName> kind of retracing our fathers footsteps. We went into <placeName>Saigon</placeName>, <placeName>Ho Chi Minh City</placeName>. We were there as a group for several days and then from there we broke off in teams to go to the different areas where our dads were. So we were with people whose dads died in the same area. So we can into the south, <placeName>Ho Chi Minh City</placeName> and them went off in these teams and we were in central highlands. What was kind of neat about our particular experience, that team I was on was that we were able to see more <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> than other folks. Some people whose dads were in <placeName>Saigon</placeName>, they stayed there. So we got to do the central area. That was just amazing. We had guides that were very knowledgeable on military history and the man that was in our group, poor man he was with all women, (Laughs) one guy.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">I'm sure he didn’t mind so much.</u>
      <u who="OLSEN">Oh geez, he was funny, he just kept laughing at us, shaking his head at the whole thing. But would give us the military history as we went and all these different places. When we got to <placeName>Pleiku</placeName>, we knew we couldn’t go and I knew even going into this trip, I couldn’t get to the valley. I knew that.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">You couldn’t go to <placeName>X-Ray</placeName>, yeah.</u>
      <u who="OLSEN">They’d asked, “Do you still want to go? Do you still want to do this?” “Oh absolutely.” I want to be in this country. I just want to experience it. Scared to death to do it but wanted to do it, I was committed, and really kind of committed myself when this movie came out, I was like, “I'm going to do this.” I heard about the trip and the trip we heard about it in conjunction when this movie came out. Certainly, totally unrelated it just worked out that it was the timing of it. When I started getting the materials on it, I said, “I'm going, I got to go.” Kind of committed way back. So we went, when we were in <placeName>Pleiku</placeName>, we went around. It’s a very remote area still. Difficult to see, it’s just the poverty people live in. We were able to go as far as kind of being over a hilltop. On a hill, looking into the valley, you still couldn’t see much but we were in <placeName>Plei Me</placeName> and driving around in these dusty dirt roads. You’d see the oxen and the whole thing! It was just so remote. That was amazing. I would still love to go back and go into the valley. I think it would just have even more meaning of course to be there. Find kind of the location of where they all were. Maybe one day. I’d love to do that one day. Not right away, a little more break between that trip and another one.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Right, when was it that you went?</u>
      <u who="OLSEN">It was a year after the movie came out. So it was <date when="2003">2003</date>. Because when we were coming back, that was actually the same time that SARS was breaking out, didn’t even have a name for it then and war, we were right at the brink of war. It was March. But in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, we did central highlands and then we got back together as a group, as a whole, <orgName>Sons and Daughters</orgName>, and went and did—we were in <placeName>Da Nang</placeName> kind of in the coast. After everybody came back from their individual excursions, they kind of rewarded us with a beautiful hotel there.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE"><placeName>Furama</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="OLSEN">Yes. You’ve been there?</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">No, I just know of it very well. I almost went there when I was there.</u>
      <u who="OLSEN">It was so beautiful. So we did that and from there we went to <placeName>Hanoi</placeName> and spent some time there. So it was an amazing trip but tough.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">I can imagine the emotions of the whole group.</u>
      <u who="OLSEN">Yeah, just different. People would say, “Did you go for closure? Did you go to kind of put it all to rest?” I said, “No, not at all.” That wasn’t even a thought in my mind. It was just one more piece of the puzzle. Putting it together.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">When people look at this, years into the future, what would you like them to know about your father, <persName>Jack</persName> and what he did for this country in this kind of larger context and personally with you?</u>
      <u who="OLSEN">Wow, a hundred years from now?</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Or five-hundred, or fifty?</u>
      <u who="OLSEN">Oh geez.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">You know, your great-grandchildren watching this. Which they will.</u>
      <u who="OLSEN">That’s hard to imagine. It’s hard to even fathom. I guess the impact of one person’s life. The kind of life he lived and the people that he touched even forty years later and however many years later, that impact in how it can come back in his spirits alive again. Hopefully people will see that. To lose a love one in a similar situation hopefully that many years from now where we’re away from all this crazy barbaric war that we go through, but that people’s spirits can live on and can continue to impact hopefully generation after generation. You just hope people learn from, you thought people learned from <name type="event">the Vietnam War</name> and now in another one, but just that pride for your country and going to serve your country and in somewhat that idealistic attitude to serve the greater good in other people and that continues and hopefully continues to be an inspiration to people. It’s hard to imagine that far out. They’d probably laugh at us that this is our equipment and what we have now, we’re so—it’s amazing.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">We’re doing what we can.</u>
      <u who="OLSEN">Right?</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Thank you so much <persName>Cammie</persName> for being here and doing this, so we can honor the service of your father and his sacrifice and your whole family. To celebrate them now. So thank you very much.</u>
      <u who="OLSEN">Thank you.(End of interview)</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
