<?xml-model href="../schemas/ddhi.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Transcript of an Interview with a Hal Moore</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>
          <orgName>Dartmouth Digital History Initiative</orgName>
        </authority>
        <date>
          <!--  Date of publication, e.g. for citation purposes  -->
        </date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <recordingStmt>
          <recording xml:id="primary_recording" type="audio" dur-iso="9">
            <!-- https://www.digi.com/resources/documentation/digidocs/90001437-13/reference/r_iso_8601_duration_format.htm -->
            <media url="//rcweb.dartmouth.edu/DDHI/histories/moore_hal/moore_hal.mp3" mimeType="MIMEaudio/wav"/>
          </recording>
        </recordingStmt>
        <bibl xml:id="primary_transcription">
          <respStmt>
            <persName>Mimi Eisenberg</persName>
            <orgName>Wordcraft</orgName>
            <resp ref="http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/trc.html">Transcriber</resp>
          </respStmt>
          <ref target="path_to_file">Primary transcription</ref>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The Dartmouth Vietnam Project</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application ident="DDHIEncoder" version="1.0">
          <desc>Conversion from Word docx to TEI xml.</desc>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en-us">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <particDesc>
        <person xml:id="VERRONE"/>
        <person xml:id="MOORE"/>
      </particDesc>
      <settingDesc>
        <setting>
          <date when-iso="2005-11-10"/>
          <locale/>
        </setting>
      </settingDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <u who="VERRONE"><persName>General Moore</persName>, thank you for being with us <date when="2005-11-10">today</date>. I am <persName>Dr.Richard Verrone</persName> conducting this oral history interview with <persName>Lieutenant General Harold G. Moore</persName>. <date when="2005-11-10">Today</date> is <date when="2005-11-10">November 10th, 2005</date>. We’re in <placeName>Washington D.C.</placeName>, at the 40th anniversary reunion of the battles of the <placeName>Ia Drang</placeName> and <placeName>Pleiku</placeName> veterans. Sir, there’s a lot we need to discuss. I would like to ask you something in general before we get to <placeName>X-Ray</placeName> and the events that surround that. Could you talk to me about yourself and your training and what you brought with you to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> in <date when="1965">1965</date>. In your principles of leadership, how you saw your men. What you wanted to do with them and how trained them up for that job.</u>
      <u who="MOORE">Well, this will take about an hour. I’ll cut it back to a few minutes. I was a paratrooper soon after I was commissioned out of <placeName>West Point</placeName>. <orgName>Airborne Division</orgName> in <placeName>Japan</placeName>, <orgName>82nd Airborne</orgName>, <placeName>Fort Bragg</placeName>. Jump tested parachutes. <orgName>Associated Airborne</orgName> equipment for the <orgName>Army</orgName>, the <orgName>Air Force</orgName>, <orgName>CIA</orgName> for two and a half years. Had a few sporting events which were life threatening, which taught me the primary lesson of always keep focused when you’re in a tough situation. Don’t panic, don’t do things spontaneously unless every instinct in your body tells you to. I served in the <placeName>pentagon</placeName> as a one-man airborne research and development officer. Developing airborne techniques, airborne equipment. <orgName>Army</orgName>’s interest and requirements for <orgName>Air Force</orgName> and aircraft. I was requested by then  <persName>Harry Kinnard</persName>, commanding general of the  <orgName>11th Major General Air Assault Division</orgName> to be one of his infantry battalion commanders in the <orgName>11th Air Assault Division</orgName>, which was a test division testing air mobility, air assault concepts. So I did that at <placeName>Fort Benning</placeName> for fourteen months and I had great troops, many of whom had trained together in basic and advanced infantry training. We trained in a lot of tough exercises in the <placeName>Carolinas</placeName>, <placeName>Georgia</placeName>. We became bonded as a family team of fighting men. Also, in such a situation you learn to love your fellow soldiers. Which is a phenomenon that many civilians cannot understand. You love your fellow soldiers as if they were your brothers. And if you're the leader, you’re responsible for their total welfare. Not only the food, the mail, the hot chow, a place to sleep when you’re in the arson, but most importantly to discipline them. I don’t mean punishment. I mean to discipline them, to perform as perfectly as they can when in battle, be perfectly trained in the use of their weapons. Perfectly trained on their duties within the team that they are in, their squad, or platoon. All that discipline and I'm going to stress, no punishment involved. It will help them to stay alive on the battlefield.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Did they understand this?</u>
      <u who="MOORE">Oh yeah. I think that’s the primary duty of a commander, whether it’s a staff team or a combat team in the air or on the ground. Your duty is to lead them to be a beautifully disciplined team, a fighting team, fighting family team of men and women! I stress the ladder word of women because now in the contemporary military, where the role of women have been expanded so broadly. They are a full member of the fighting team, just like the men. I’ve always believed, since my time at West Point where I was in grave danger of being kicked out because of being so dumb in all the mathematically based on bizarre subjects. But I had a positive attitude, never quit. I studied in the toilet outside the room door, in the hall, 40-watt lightbulb until one or two o’clock in the morning. I learned how to sleep fast, I got four, five hours of sleep. Got eight hours and four, five hours of sleep. I am proud to say that I graduated at the top of the bottom fifteen percent of my class. I learned and I'm glad I couldn’t coast easily through <placeName>West Point</placeName>. Otherwise, I would never have had those two principles sledgehammered into my head. Attitude. Positive attitude always. I never quit. And I hammered those principles into my troopers. Which resulted in them being very tough fighting men in the grave test at <placeName>Landing Zone X-Ray</placeName> and other battles in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. I have three or four principles of leadership, which I think are applicable in any endeavor. On the athletic field, on the boxing ring, in business, in the military, with what you do. The first principle is, with the game of baseball, three strikes and you’re out! Not so in the game of life. In other endeavors, in the game of life. Three strikes and you’re not out. Number two, there’s always one more thing you can do to influence any situation in your favor. After that, one more thing and after that, one more thing. The more one more things you do, the more opportunities open up. In that connection, whenever I was in a tight spot on the battlefield or in a time critical decision environment in the <placeName>Pentagon</placeName> and involved with tens of thousands of people, millions of dollars on occasion, personnel chief of the <orgName>Army</orgName> for two and a half years—I would think, “What am I doing that I should not be doing?” And “What am I not doing that I should be doing to influence the situation in my favor.” Associated with that principle of one more thing, I’ve learned in life, in any endeavor, family, battle, and business. After I retired, I was vice president of a major ski area in <placeName>Colorado</placeName> for four and a half years. When there’s nothing going wrong, often there’s nothing going wrong except there’s nothing is going wrong. That’s when you got to be most alert. Finally, I learned early in my life to trust my instincts. Your instincts are the product of your education, your training, your work, your personality. In a tight time critical situation, especially in those types of situations, if my head tells me one thing and my gut tells me another, I go with my gut. Often times there’s no time for a reasoned analysis of the situation. You can’t take out a notebook that says, “Pros and cons, option one and two.” In seconds, and in this work on the battlefield <placeName>Landing Zone X-Ray</placeName>, about which that book was written, we were being assaulted by hundreds and hundreds of men and I guess just a handful of us. I went with my instincts every time. I turned out to be right. So those are just a few of the basic principles that I’ve attempted to live by and one of the principal things I learned at <placeName>West Point</placeName>, which I’ve applied throughout my life and tried to teach my five children. Always choose the harder right instead of the easier role. Over the years also and I'm proud to say this, years ago in my youth, I concluded that none of us know when we’re going to go out of the game. Our life here on this earth is a tryout. We’re proving life and eternity. I think a lot of people get focused on day-to-day earthly activities without paying attention to the fact that their time on this earth is like a snap of the fingers compared to an eternity. So I’ve always tried to conduct myself so I as to qualify. The older I get, the more vulnerable I get to going out of the game. I'm doing my best to make the cut.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">What role has your spiritual life played for you in the military? How do you blend those two things, a strong spiritual belief and warfare?</u>
      <u who="MOORE">Well, as strange as it may seem, when I was sent to battle by my president, and swore an oath at <placeName>West Point</placeName>, on the plane at <placeName>West Point</placeName> to follow the orders of the president of <placeName>United States</placeName>. I trusted my president and I trusted that the orders that I was receiving were honest orders which had to be followed. No one ever likes taking the life of another person if they’re in their right mind. I know that there’s many criminals who take delight in killing other people. But I did my duty. At <placeName>X-Ray</placeName>, when we had that terrible three-day shootout, at the end, when we walked across those enemy bodies, I was proud of what my men did but a lot of them could be walked across. I lost seventy-nine men killed, twenty-one wounded. But as I looked at all those dead North Vietnamese soldiers, the thought struck me that they had mothers too. We did what we had to do.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">The diary you found that you all recovered off the North Vietnamese soldier. Tell me about that. The personalizing of your enemy.</u>
      <u who="MOORE">The North Vietnamese soldier—when I fought in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, not only in the <placeName>Ia Drang Valley</placeName> but in other very tough battles, he was a well-trained soldier. Highly motivated, was not afraid to die. I think part of his motivation may have been that they were determined to drive the round-eyed Russian foreigner out of their country. The thought struck me often in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> that we look just like the French. White, black, we were brown. We were in their country! Killing them! Dropping bombs on their cities. I don’t think it was a very tough job for the leaders in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> to imbue a very tough fighting spirit into their soldiers to get this round-eye foreigner out of our country, which had been enslaved by the French for a hundred years. Pillaged. I think they identified us almost like we were French.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">When did this thought and this belief hit you?</u>
      <u who="MOORE">We’re good to go?</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Yes, sir.</u>
      <u who="MOORE">Okay.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">So your enemy, you’re discussing his determination. Is this a characteristic of <orgName>the People’s Army of Vietnam</orgName> and the <orgName>Viet Cong</orgName> fighters or did you see a difference? </u>
      <u who="MOORE">Oh, I think they’re about the same. Same motivation. Probably a similar motivation to some of the Iraqi terrorists. The goal that the British occupation in the countries in the middle east for years, for decades. Here comes another bunch of white guys, want to take over our country, get our oil. But let’s not get off on <placeName>Iraq</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">When did you come to this understanding about that, the American forces were similar to the French forces in the eyes of the Vietnamese?</u>
      <u who="MOORE">Oh, in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. Yeah, I have studied history of <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> and some military history for years. I visited <placeName>Di An, Binh Duong</placeName> for three days. I’ve been back to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> seven times since <date when="1990">1990</date>. I’ve talked to <persName>General Giap</persName>, twice. <persName>General Dũng</persName>, the historian for hours. I talked to <persName>Lieutenant General An</persName> who was my opponent on the battlefield in the <placeName>Ia Drang</placeName> as a <persName>Lieutenant Colonel</persName>, we were trying to kill each other. Went back to the battlefield with him. You’ve probably seen that documentary. </u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Yes, sir. </u>
      <u who="MOORE"><persName>Joe Galloway</persName> and I visited his widow and his family in <placeName>Hanoi</placeName> three four years after his death. I have found the military history of <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> just fascinating. Of course, the French were not only in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, they were in <placeName>Laos</placeName> and <placeName>Cambodia</placeName> as well. Colonizing the whole place. I never have fully understood it, perhaps you can enlighten me on why <persName>President Truman</persName> did not strongly object to the French recolonizing <placeName>Southeast Asia</placeName> after <name type="event">World War II</name>. When they threatened the Dutch, that they were going to cut off marshal aid if they didn’t get out of Indonesian and they did! Why did we tolerate the French giving birth to another war in <placeName>Southeast Asia</placeName>? Which became the siege of American involvement in our tragedy in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. <persName>General An</persName> and I, when we met in <placeName>Hanoi</placeName>, we talked for several hours. Went to dinner together with some of his officers. <persName>General Dũng</persName>, the historian, <persName>General Minh</persName> his boss, now four-star. He was a very good general during the battle. Commanded the hound forces and the hounds. As strange as it may seem, <persName>General An</persName> and I became friends. We were in a van together for several days. In a hotel together, ate together, good interpreter. He was sick with a respiratory infection and I was too, and I gave him some of my medicine, he got better, and I got better. We resolved after that trip back to the battlefield in <date when="1993">1993</date> in <date when="1993-10">October</date>, to attempt to get the Vietnamese government to erect an obelisk on the clearing at <placeName>Landing Zone X-Ray</placeName> which would say only, “On this field in <date when="1965-10">November 1965</date>, the <orgName>US Army</orgName> forces, and <orgName>the People’s Army of Vietnam</orgName> fought the first major battle of the <name type="event">American War in Vietnam</name> .” Nothing else. Not who kicked who’s ass. Just the fact of the battle. He was attempting to get this authorized with a road out there. When he died, the whole project collapsed. I’ve been back to the <placeName>X-Ray</placeName> battlefield one other time after the <date when="1993">1993</date>, I went back with twelve of my veterans. You can take a truck from <placeName>Pleiku</placeName>—you’ve been to the central highlands?</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Yes, sir.</u>
      <u who="MOORE">You take a truck from <placeName>Plei Me</placeName> to the west until the road runs out. Then, you got to start walking. First place you hit is  <placeName>LZ (Landing Zone) Albany</placeName>. Then you walk another mile and a half north and you hit <placeName>LZ X-Ray</placeName>. It’s still scrub jungle, high elephant grass, a few Montagnards. There has been some logging out there, by the Japanese primarily. But I think all that stopped. When we were there in <date when="1993">1993</date> and <date when="1997">’97</date>, there was the remains of a logging road which have been all grown over. So as you well know, the tours of veterans of <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, they’re taken to <placeName>Hanoi</placeName>, to the museum, <placeName>Da Nang</placeName>, <placeName>Hue</placeName>, the palaces, the tunnels of <placeName>Củ Chi</placeName>, <placeName>Saigon</placeName>, the roof on <placeName>Caravelle</placeName>, the outdoor roof on that hotel right across the street, I forget the name of it. But they don’t take them to—sometimes to <placeName>Plei Me</placeName>, which is pretty handy to <placeName>Pleiku</placeName>. You’ve probably been to <placeName>Plei Me</placeName>. You got to really be careful when you walk around there with all the unexploded ordinates, but if you push them, they’ll let a group go to <placeName>Plei Me</placeName>. But they don’t let anybody out into the <placeName>Ia Drang Valley</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Do you think there’s another reason instead of the lack of access?</u>
      <u who="MOORE">Well, I have always puzzled over this. I think there may be other reasons, including the presence of <orgName>Khmer Rouge</orgName>. <placeName>X-Ray</placeName> is only six miles from the <placeName>Cambodian</placeName> border. And the <placeName>Ia Drang River</placeName> runs into <placeName>Cambodia</placeName>. So I think <orgName>Khmer Rouge</orgName>, although that threat may have been diminished in recent years, it’s certainly was present when we went back there in <date when="1993">1993</date>. Spent the night on that battlefield. That was pretty sporty. Then there was also the <orgName>Montagnard</orgName> situation, where unfortunately the <placeName>Hanoi</placeName> government is almost weaponed out the <orgName>Montagnard</orgName> tribes. Sending them away from their ancestral villages into what are called new economic zones to the east or just killing them. It’s a real national tragedy, which is really not too well understood in the western world. I'm sure you are very familiar with all that.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Yes, sir. There were <orgName>Montagnard</orgName> tribespeople there on the morning you came in on the 14th?</u>
      <u who="MOORE">Oh indeed, there were, yeah.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">They quickly dispersed?</u>
      <u who="MOORE">I never personally saw any Montagnards, but there were <persName>Montagnard</persName> villages to the north of us along the river. That’s primarily the Montagnards were. When we went back in <date when="1993">’93</date>, some days a few <orgName>Montagnards</orgName> materialized. Also, when we went back in <date when="1997">1997</date>, we saw a few Montagnards along the river. Got to have water, that’s where they settled. </u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Could you describe <persName>Sergeant Major Basil Plumley</persName>? </u>
      <u who="MOORE">I believe in destiny. I believe in faith and I think it was my destiny to get linked up with <orgName>Sergeant Major Plumley</orgName>. When I took command of my battalion at <placeName>Fort Benning</placeName>, <placeName>Georgia</placeName> in <date when="1964-06">June of 1964</date>, and I met up with <persName>Sergeant Major Plumley</persName>, 6’2”, about my age. Master parachuter like me. He had five combat jumps. Four in <name type="event">World War II</name>, one in <placeName>Korea</placeName>. He and I believe the exactly the same principles. Tough training, fair and square to all your men. Tough discipline. If somebody screwed up, take the necessary action but don’t overreact because what you want to do is retrain them so that won’t happen again. <persName>Sergeant Major Plumley</persName> and I were a team. I told <persName>Sergeant Major Plumley</persName> that he had unlimited access to me at any time. That he could accompany me anywhere I went if he wanted to, if he didn’t have something else to do. I wanted his principal duties to be to improve the professionalism of the non-commissioned officers of the battalion. Promotions of soldiers in the ranks in those days was determined by quotas, which came down from higher headquarters. Like I might get a quota for two soldiers to be promoted to three stripe buck sergeant and two soldiers to be promoted to staff sergeant. I turn it all over to <persName>Sergeant Major Plumley</persName> and he organized a committee of all the 1st sergeants. The five 1st sergeants in the battalion, and whenever we would get those quotas to come down, they would meet. They knew the soldiers better than I did, better than the officers. They would meet and determine which soldiers would get those stripes. He would come in to me with a recommendation and I would always approve anything he recommended. I trust him totally. In battle, he could accompany me anywhere he wanted if he felt that’s where he needed to be. I had dinner with him recently and he and I sort of laughed a little bit over why we weren’t killed! </u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Those three days? During those three days?</u>
      <u who="MOORE">The whole tour in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. </u>
      <u who="VERRONE">In previous or just <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>?</u>
      <u who="MOORE">Just in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. Of course, you can get killed in a helicopter crash in the <placeName> United States</placeName>, but the chances of getting killed in battle are a hell of a lot better. <persName>Sergeant Major Plumley</persName> is a national treasure. We went into <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> together and we flew out together on the freedom bird, on the same day. Ironically, we were in a battler near <placeName>Nha Trang</placeName> special forces camp. My replacement, the colonel had arrived two weeks earlier. I really didn’t want to take—I didn’t want to lose command of my brigade. I knew how to fight that enemy, I knew the terrain, I knew the dos and don’ts. Here is a guy fresh out of <placeName>America</placeName>, socks were still clean. Hell, he didn’t know nothing about that enemy. I refused to let him take command of the brigade! I got by with it for a while. Then a company got surrounded down there in <placeName>Nha Trang</placeName> special forces camp, <orgName>101st Airborne Division</orgName>. I heard about this and I asked the assistant division commanded for operations, “Why don’t you send my brigade down there to take the pressure off those couple companies and save them from being wiped out.” So we went down, they were sent down and this was my last battle in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. It lasted for about—took us about a week or so. Finally, the division commander, <persName>General Norton</persName>, he showed up and he said, “Hal, you got to turn over your brigade. Your replacements been here now for over two weeks.” So I turned over the brigade and flew back up to <placeName>An Khe</placeName>. Me and <persName>Sergeant Major</persName>, we packed up our duffle bag. Flew down to <placeName>Saigon</placeName>, spent a night in <placeName>Saigon</placeName> and the next day we were put in a <orgName>Jeep</orgName> and headed out to <placeName>Tan Son Nhut Airport</placeName> to get on the freedom bird, and go back to <placeName>America</placeName>. We got to <placeName>Tan Son Nhut</placeName> and it ended up being mortared. </u>
      <u who="VERRONE">It’s a good send off.</u>
      <u who="MOORE">After all we’d been through, we thought this is really ironic to maybe get wounded or killed in a mortar attack in <placeName>Saigon</placeName>. So they sent us back to <placeName>Saigon</placeName> and we were delayed on the airplane for two days and we got on the airplane the next day. Came home together. <persName>Plumley</persName> is a piece of work.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">What do you mean?</u>
      <u who="MOORE">Unique. Iconic. He can be an armory. He doesn’t give interviews. He avoids the press. But he and I are dead loyal to one another. He lives just right outside of <placeName>Fort Benning</placeName>. My home in <placeName>Alabama</placeName> is in <placeName>Auburn</placeName>, forty miles from <placeName>Fort Benning, Georgia</placeName>. Over the years, long gone by, my wife and I would go over to <placeName>Fort Benning</placeName> on occasion to visit my troopers in the cemetery. Her parents were buried, daughter of a colonel. On occasion, we’d visit <persName>Sergeant Major</persName>. Sit down in his kitchen with him and his wife. She’d always have a pumpkin pie, hot coffee. We’d sit there and talk about old times. Tell war stories. Some of them were true. We’d visit the cemetery. I lost my wife a year and a half ago. That’s where she is. So if you want to interview <persName>Sergeant Major Plumley</persName>, I don’t think you would succeed. You’re going to have to learn about Plumley from guys like me and <persName>Joe Galloway</persName> and others. Because he refuses all interviews.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">That’s why I’m asking, one of the reasons I'm asking.</u>
      <u who="MOORE">Yeah, he won’t agree to an interview. <persName>Joe Galloway</persName> and I are in the process of writing a sequel to our book and we wanted to have a chapter in there on <persName>Sergeant Major Plumley</persName>. He told <persName>Joe</persName> flat out, “<persName>Joe</persName> you are welcome in my home at any time, but I’m not going to give you an interview.” If he won’t interview with <persName>Joe Galloway</persName> or me, he’s not going to talk to nobody.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Tell me about <persName>Joe Galloway</persName>.</u>
      <u who="MOORE"><persName>Joe Galloway</persName> is another person whom I was destined by a higher power to meet. I first met <persName>Joe</persName> on the night of <date when="1965">November 1965</date>, when my battalion was ordered to join the <placeName>Pleiku</placeName> campaign being fought by the <orgName>1st Cav Division</orgName> and some <orgName>South Vietnamese units</orgName> in the central highlands, after the attacks of the <placeName>Plei Me</placeName> special forces camp. So my battalion was sent down to patrol to the east of Plei Me special forces camp, to attempt to engage contact with any enemy that was in the area. I thought that was kind of stupid because the enemy had been defeated in a siege of the <placeName>Plei Me</placeName> special forces camp and obviously they had retreated to the west. I couldn’t understand why we were being ordered to patrol to the east. <persName>Joe</persName> joined us and he and I were marching with A Company, some troops of A Company that day. During which we crossed a stream up to our necks in the central highlands, three thousand feet cold stream. We’d been wet for the night, all soaking wet and <persName>Joe</persName> stayed on the ground with us instead of hopping back on a Huey and going back to <placeName>Pleiku</placeName> for a hot shower and hot chow.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">That was unusual for the press?</u>
      <u who="MOORE">For a reporter? Hell yeah. He rolled up on the ground in his poncho with the rest of us and I liked that. We patrolled around for another couple three days around a <placeName>Plei Me</placeName> camp. Made little to no contact. On the night of the—late afternoon of the <date when="1964-11-13">13th of November</date>, I got a telephone radio message from the brigade commander, <persName>Colonel Tim Brown</persName>, to prepare to assault into the Ia Drang Valley the next morning with a mission of finding and killing the enemy. So I went back to my field command post which was outside the gates of <placeName>Plei Me</placeName>. If you’ve been in <placeName>Plei Me</placeName>, you’ve probably seen the old French fort remains with the revetements. We had a couple of three ops tents pitched in the revetements of that old French fort. I issued the ops order, warning order and the next morning we assaulted into <placeName>X-Ray</placeName>. We had a terrible fight all that day. My operations officer, <persName>Matt Dillion</persName>, whom I think you’ve interviewed.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Yes, sir.</u>
      <u who="MOORE">He was overhead in my command chopper. I landed; I was the first guy on the ground, I landed with the assault company. Which was my practice in training and in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> to join in the battle beginning. Not to be a hero, not to be hunting for a medal, but if you’re in the lead helicopter, if you have to divert to an alternate landing zone because of a hot LZ, you’re right there and you can make the decision and I had one selected. Also, you can make a quick arial reconnaissance going in, get an idea on the terrain. If it’s a hot LZ, you’re on the ground to take care of it. If it’s a cold LZ, you have time to walk around and make a reconnaissance of the terrain, you get an idea of the battlefield where you might make contact.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Right. Did <persName>Bruce Crandall</persName> fly you in that first flight?</u>
      <u who="MOORE"><persName>Bruce</persName> was a pilot in the first.  <persName>Lieutenant John Mills</persName> was his co-pilot and me and the <persName>Sergeant Major</persName>, my two radio operators and my intelligence officer  <persName>Captain Metsker</persName>, who was killed within two hours. Three hours, actually. And <persName>Mr. Nick</persName>, a Vietnamese interpreter, we were in the lead helicopter of <orgName>B Company</orgName>, which was the assault company. As you know form reading the book and so forth, we had a hell of a fight that first day, it was a cliffhanger. Probably only had about two-hundred of my four-hundred-fifty or so men on the ground. We were attacked by two battalions of enemy, eight hundred to a thousand enemy. I'll go into the details of that a little later if you want me to, but it was a cliffhanger all that afternoon. My men fought magnificently; we lost a lot of troopers. Finally, things quieted down a little bit and we established a command post behind an anthill which was about the size of a small pickup truck. Six-feet high, six-seven feet high termite hill. That’s where I established my field aid station, my ammo point and where I gathered my dead. About seven o’clock, I had <persName>Dillion</persName> overhead in my command chopper along with my forward air controller, <persName>Charlie Hastings</persName>, <persName>Lieutenant Hastings</persName>—my fire support coordinator. With a back of radios, they relayed back to brigade commander, helicopter liaison officer, they could control all that movement. Had <persName>Dillion</persName> not been on the ground with me, I would’ve been penalized because who would have done all that stuff. Anyhow, I told Dillion late in the day, “I want you to come on in, I want you bring <persName>Charlie Hastings</persName> and bring my fire support coordinator, <persName>Jerry Whiteside</persName>, captain artillery.” He said, “Come on in.” He said on the radio, “That reporter, <persName>Galloway</persName> wants to come in.” I remember <persName>Joe</persName> from <placeName>Plei Me</placeName> and I said, “Well, if you got room on that last chopper coming in and if he’s crazy enough to want to come in here, bring him in.” So he did. <persName>Joe</persName>, you get from him the story of him coming into <placeName>X-Ray</placeName>. Like I said earlier, I think we were destined to meet, fate. Twenty-three year old kid reporter, half my age, he landed and he stayed with us for the rest of the fight. I was—in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, in <placeName>Korea</placeName> we didn’t have many reporters. I fought the stabilize night warfare, the outpost warfare in <placeName>Korea</placeName> for fourteen months. We didn’t have many reporters joining us but in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, hell they were everywhere. I was a strong believer in freedom of the press. I told my public information officer when I was a brigade commander—when I was a battalion commander, I didn’t have a public information officer. I let it be known that I welcomed news media to join me and my troopers in the field. I gave them only two instructions. Do not interfere with operations and do not put out any public information which would help the enemy. In other words, don’t reveal my plans, where I'm going to be moving. I never had any reason in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> to regret that. I told my troops that if a news media person or TV, photographer or journalist like <persName>Joe</persName> or photographer, if they want to talk to you or take your picture, it’s up to you. My only guidance is two things. Number one, tell the truth as you see the truth from your level. Number two, do not speak above your level. If you’re a squad leader, don’t talk like you’re the platoon leader. If you’re a rifleman in the ranks, don’t talk like you're the squad leader. If you’re <persName>Hal Moore</persName>, the brigade commander, don’t talk like you’re the division commander. I felt so strongly that the American people deserved to know what the hell is going in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. What their sons and their brothers and their husbands were doing over there. I’ll tell you what, every time we had an operation, we were surrounded by the news media. I like that too because my men got publicity back home.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Did you have any rules about not photographing your dead troopers?</u>
      <u who="MOORE">Not photographing dead troopers?</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Yes.</u>
      <u who="MOORE">I can’t recall putting out any specific orders on that. But I also cannot recall any incidents that occurred where while I was in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, I was questioned about photographers taking photographs of dead troopers. I can’t recall of any—we had an army movie team in X-Ray, they came in early the second day. Maybe you’ve seen that battlefield footage. I'm sure they’ve captured some sequences of some of my dead being carried into the clearing station. But I can’t think of any such photographs that were publicized. That’s the first time I’ve ever been asked that question, but I'm trying to think back, and I got a lot of stuff sent to me from the <placeName>US</placeName> after we had battles, newspaper clippings. I'm trying hard to think of it.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">There are some pictures from <placeName>X-Ray</placeName> by <persName>Peter Arnett</persName>.</u>
      <u who="MOORE"><persName>Peter Arnett</persName>, yeah.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Who did photograph—</u>
      <u who="MOORE"><persName>Peter</persName> was there with us. <persName>Peter</persName> gave me the picture of Rescorla on the cover of that book. He’s credited with that photograph. Peter gave me a couple of other pictures of me, one of me standing over a dead North Vietnamese with my rifle and my bayonet on the third day when we had counterattack. He didn’t give to me any pictures of just a dead American trooper, that’s the first I’ve heard of that. But to answer your question, no, I didn’t put out any instructions on that. I think a lot of that is common sense on the part of the photographer.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">You would think so?</u>
      <u who="MOORE">I would think that if a photographer who would take—a newsman photographer who would take a still photograph of a dead trooper with a nametag, I think that’s bad for them, considering people back home.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Was your attitude towards the press in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, was it different from most other kind of news?</u>
      <u who="MOORE">I don't know, but I’ll tell you this. The army of public affairs officer years ago asked me for permission to publish in his instructions when he briefed commanders to be the tank commanders or brigade or division, he took an excerpt from my book and I’ll show it to you if you want to open it up. If I can find it.[Editor’s note: Audio cuts and resumes here.]</u>
      <u who="MOORE">What the hell is going on. <persName>Joe Galloway</persName> and I were really in on the birth of the embedded reporters in the <name type="event">Iraq War</name>.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Yes, you were.</u>
      <u who="MOORE">When you talk to <persName>Joe</persName>, he’ll tell you about that.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Well in the book and in the movie, you instructed him to let the American people to know this. To tell the truth to the American people.</u>
      <u who="MOORE">Exactly. Well, I’ll have to find it.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">What is the passage discussing?</u>
      <u who="MOORE">What I just told you. I can’t find it.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">We can look and perhaps we can check the index. Do you speak of <persName>Galloway</persName> in this passage?</u>
      <u who="MOORE">No, in general, yeah.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Perhaps we can look in the index and look for media or the press. I’d be glad to help you with that.</u>
      <u who="MOORE">It’s probably early in the book.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">While I'm looking, what made <persName>Joe Galloway</persName> different? Or was he different as a reporter?</u>
      <u who="MOORE">First, he stayed on the ground with us. He was in the battle of <placeName>X-Ray</placeName> until we were pulled out of there. He didn’t go back to <placeName>Pleiku</placeName> to file his reports. He spent the night; he was the only reporter that spent the nights with us. <persName>Peter Arnett</persName>, <persName>Neil Sheehan</persName>— <persName>Neil</persName> is a dear friend of mine for whom I have high respect, but he and a flock of other journalists who came in at the end of the battle, they milled around interviewing troopers and then they got on the bird and went out. <persName>Joe</persName> went out also, but the battle was over. He had to get his copy to <orgName>UPI (United Press International)</orgName> . You’ll find that somewhere, I’ll try to look it up for you during the break.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">What is it like to be interviewed in the middle of a battle? Or a lull in the battle?</u>
      <u who="MOORE">If it’s an honest to god lull and I didn’t have any of the immediate pressing situation to consider, I would grant a brief interview. When I became a brigade commander, when we went out on operations, I told the division public affairs officer to notify the news media in <placeName>Saigon</placeName> that the elements of the <orgName>1st Cav Division</orgName> will be taking the field. In my brigade, I had a reputation of finding the enemy. Consequently, the news media flocked because they wanted to put out the information. So every night, like when I was in “Operation Masher White Wing” on the <placeName>Bong Son plain</placeName> in <date when="1966-01">January</date>, <date when="1966-04">March of ’66</date>. Every night around five o’clock I would brief the press. I’d have maybe ten, fifteen journalists in the press tent and I’d brief the press on what went on that day and the results and then I told them of my plans for the next day, so that they could determine if they wanted to go with this unit or that unit. Then, I’d caution, “Don’t put out information that would help the enemy.”</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Right.</u>
      <u who="MOORE">I said, “You can fly in a helicopter anywhere you want, but don’t interfere if there is no room on that bird, don’t push a soldier off, don’t crowd somebody. If you want to get in the middle of the fight, that’s your call. Don’t interfere with operations.” Which meant also do not go up to a company commander during a firefight and ask for an interview. I never had that happen. I think the freedom of the press is one of the great freedoms of a democracy. Absolute great freedom, along with freedom of speech. We’re blessed in this country to have those two freedoms. Of course, they have to be exercised judiciously. I am delighted that the <placeName>Pentagon</placeName> embedded journalists in the <name type="event">Iraq War</name> that has been going on for the last couple of years. I don’t know if you know this or not but at the <placeName>Pentagon</placeName>, before the <name type="event">Iraq War</name> jumped off, offered American journalists the opportunity to go to <placeName>Fort Benning</placeName> and I believe <placeName>Fort Sill</placeName>, <placeName>Fort Knox</placeName>, maybe other military bases air and ground and marine, to be briefed on battlefield maneuver activities and battlefield activities. When I was at <placeName>Fort Benning</placeName> making a talk before the <name type="event">Iraq War</name> jumped off, they were having one of those gathering where the journalists for a week were at <placeName>Fort Benning</placeName>. They learned about infantry tactics and they learned about firing maneuver and fire support and they were much more qualified to report to the American people what they were seeing in <placeName>Iraq</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">I remember seeing that on the news and reading about this training.</u>
      <u who="MOORE">Whereas in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> as I understand, <persName>Joe</persName> six packed right off the streets of <placeName>Chicago</placeName> can show up in <placeName>Saigon</placeName> and get a press card. He wouldn’t know the difference between a squad and a battalion or a M16 rifle and a mortar. If I were asked today to cover a rugby football match in the <placeName>Redskins’ Stadium</placeName>, I wouldn’t know what the hell I was looking at! That was the same with a lot of the journalist at <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, they didn’t know what the hell they were looking at. So consequently, they took these pictures of dead soldiers and they reported graphic stuff which they never should’ve reported. Some of which helped the enemy.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Sir, I’d like to talk about <placeName>X-Ray</placeName> in a little bit of detail. Would you like to take maybe five minute break?</u>
      <u who="MOORE">Let’s do that.[Editor’s Note: Audio cuts in.]</u>
      <u who="MOORE">That’s what the <placeName>Pentagon</placeName> people wanted to put out to their periodic briefings of battalion, brigade, and division commanders that were recently selected to command.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">From all the interview that I’ve done and all the reading that I’ve done, both as a history student and then since teaching, that attitude towards that is unique.</u>
      <u who="MOORE">It’s what?</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">It’s unique.</u>
      <u who="MOORE">Unique?</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Yes, sir. That commanders did welcome and understand the need for press coverage. But after the fact, as the more negative reports were coming out from the media, they then tried to turn the volume down a bit. Really did not like what was coming out and your basic rules here, it seems that they followed those, there was no problem. But after the fact, I think people were starting to have a problem with the way that the war was being reported.</u>
      <u who="MOORE">I realize that every now and then a report would come out that would not be accurate or that would maybe damage my reputation or the reputation of my troopers. But I felt like it was appropriate to take that chance for the American people. The American people who send their sons and daughters off to war and their husbands, they deserve what the hell is going on. I think the <placeName>pentagon</placeName> wised up recently when they embedded reporters, some of whom unfortunately have been killed and wounded.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Let’s go back to that faithful day, Sunday the 14th. Tell me about—in the interest of time, let’s cut to the first day. You were the first on the field, is that correct?</u>
      <u who="MOORE">That’s correct.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">And this is one of your principles, to be the first on and last off?</u>
      <u who="MOORE">That’s right.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">What was the situation there? You all landed, this at <orgName>B Company</orgName>, the assault company. You get out and the other principle you mentioned here is that when there’s nothing wrong, then something’s wrong that there’s nothing wrong and there was no immediate resistance when you all took the field. Describe what you were thinking and feeling.</u>
      <u who="MOORE">Well, early in the morning before the assault as described in the book, I gathered a group of my key officers into two helicopters and we did an air recon at a high altitude of the objective area south of the <placeName>Ia Drang Valley</placeName> and the <placeName>Chu Pong Mountain Complex</placeName>. We flew from south to north over the <placeName>Chu Pong Mountain Complex</placeName> and the <placeName>Ia Drang River</placeName>. Up as far as the <placeName>Duc Co Special Forces camp</placeName>, which was probably six, seven miles north of the mountains. Just to get an idea of the terrain and the clearings.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE"><persName>Matt Dillion</persName> was with you?</u>
      <u who="MOORE">Oh, yeah. I had—it’s described in my book who I had in the helicopter, the key people who needed to give me advice and to see the terrain to perform their duties better. So we came back and consulted and tentatively decided on the clearing which <orgName>Dillion</orgName> called “X”, which was <placeName>X-Ray</placeName>. They go by alphabet. I ordered H-13 scout section two man helicopters to make a last minute quick right above the tree recon of the <placeName>Ia Drang Valley</placeName> area. Not just <placeName>X-Ray</placeName>, but I didn’t want to tell the enemy where we were going to land. <placeName>X-Ray</placeName> and <orgName>Tango</orgName>, another clearing which was a well-type clearing. I rejected that because we could only take a couple of helicopters at a time. <placeName>Yankee</placeName> was another clearing on the side of the mountain. So they recon very quickly and they saw commo wire coming across this clearing we called <placeName>X-Ray</placeName>. It could hold obviously maybe eight helicopters, four to eight helicopters at a time. So I selected that as the assault clearing. Came back to <placeName>Plei Me</placeName>. Had the artillery positioned to fire the artillery prep and then I gathered together on the <placeName>Plei Me</placeName> airstrip and you’ve seen the remains of it on the western end of the <placeName>Plei Me</placeName> airstrip. I gathered all the helicopter pilots and crews. All my company commanders and any troops in the vicinity. Probably fifty people. And I issued my ops order. Orally, nothing right. Why did I gather all these people? Because I wanted them all to know my concept. My plan of maneuver, my plan of fire support, which companies would land when, in succession. Why did I do that? If I went out the of the game, then somebody knew what to do. There wouldn’t have to be any confusion. I did that every time I went into battle in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. We had the artillery prep, and I made a mistake which I’ve always regretted. I take full responsibility for that mistake. I should have put closer air on the mountain.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Did you think about it?</u>
      <u who="MOORE">Never crossed my mind! And I had my forward air controller, <persName>Lieutenant Hastings</persName> right there! <persName>Matt Dillion</persName>, experienced operations officer right there. I don’t criticize them, but they didn’t suggest air support.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">But you didn’t know that mountain was the base camp.</u>
      <u who="MOORE">I had information, my intelligence information was that three battalions of North Vietnamese in the <placeName>Valley</placeName> when I was giving a set of coordinates which was about a mile and a half north, northwest of <placeName>X-Ray</placeName> on the <placeName>Ia Drang River</placeName>. Another set of coordinates of a battalion, another battalion in the southeast part of the mountainous complex about two miles from the clearing we called <placeName>X-Ray</placeName>. The third set of coordinates that I had were the six digit coordinates right in the middle of <placeName>LZ X-Ray</placeName>. For an enemy battalion.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">You’re going to land on top of them.</u>
      <u who="MOORE">And I should’ve realized that the enemy would have an observation post on the mountain!</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">On the higher ground, looking field.</u>
      <u who="MOORE">But my head was up my ass and I never thought of it. I should’ve put in air support, smoke, white phosphorus, firebomb, they were available! So I must confess that I made that mistake. Probably, had I not made that mistake, some of the enemy that came balling down off that mountain might have been taken out of the game. But we landed without incident and I ran into the—I fired my rifle during landing as was my practice, bushes and trees where there might be enemy. I ran, me and the sergeant major, my two radio operators, and my interpreter ran across the clearing, ran across the dry creek bed. Me and Captain <persName>Metsker</persName> were firing our rifles into possible enemy locations. We ran into the trees maybe a hundred yards. Made no contact. Not very happy about that because I looked up that mountain and I got on that ground and thought, “Oh boy. We are under observation.” Later in <placeName>Hanoi</placeName>, talking to <persName>General An</persName>, he did indeed have a command post on that mountain where he could observe the valley below. I could’ve taken him out! But anyhow, we made no contact. I came back and being the first on the ground, I was able to make a ground reconnaissance of the clearing and the fringes of it. It quickly became apparent to me that the dry creek beds to the west of the clearing, the edge of it into the trees maybe fifteen, twenty-five yards, that the creek bed and a ridge line coming down from the mountain and a draw beside that ridge line, those were the key terrain features. I realized I had to hold the creek bed because whoever owned that creek bed, owned the landing zone. I realized that the ridge line and the draw beside of it were key avenues of approach down the mountain and up the mountain. My mission was to find and kill the enemy. I had given my three-rifle company specific orders. There was not practicing in the two wars I fought as a part of my ops order, always instructed all of my maneuver commanders to be prepared to take over the mission of another company or another platoon if the situation requires that. So all three of my company commanders although they had specific areas that they were going to patrol, they knew that they could get other orders of other commanders. Which was why when I gave orders, initial orders, the company could readily respond because they had made the map recon and they briefed our platoon leaders.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Could you tell me about the <persName>Herrick</persName> platoon and what happened there?</u>
      <u who="MOORE">Who? <persName>Herrick</persName>?</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Yeah, <persName>Herrick</persName>’s platoon. We know what happened from the movie and from the book. The decisions that went into that and how that played out.</u>
      <u who="MOORE">Well, once we captured that prisoner who told us that there were three North Vietnamese battalions on the mountain that wanted to kill Americans and haven’t found any, I immediately ordered my <orgName>B Company</orgName> commander,  <persName>Captain Herrick</persName> to reconnoiter that ridge line and that draw. He was prepared to do that, he took it on and within a short while, he got hit on with a large group of enemy blowing off that mountain down that ridge line. Probably a couple hundred enemy. My companies were all under strength due to <persName>Lydon Johnson</persName>’s order that no man with sixty days or less to serve on departure from <placeName>Fort Benning</placeName> would not go. So I lost about a hundred seventy-five men I’d trained. Then, once in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, Malaria, tropical diseases and after sixty days, again I’d be losing men going back home before the battle. So I went into that fight not with seven-hundred-fifty men which was authorized for my battalion, but about four-hundred and fifty. So that meant that officers would have to do their jobs and sometimes NCO (Non-Commissioned Officer) jobs. NCOs and platoon sergeants would often have to be a squad leader. So I incurred a lot of causalities because of that. When the fire fight broke out, I had my rifle company, <orgName>B Company</orgName> up that ridge line to protect that creek bed. In the process of the initial fire fight, <persName>Lieutenant Herrick</persName> spotted a group of enemy, I don't know how many, maybe three, maybe six who were running to the north down to another creek bed which was to the west of the creek bed bordering the LZ. He radioed back to <persName>Herren</persName>, his company commander that he was pursuing these enemy. It was an impulsive act on his part and by so doing, he deprived his company commander of three maneuver, a maneuver element. Got three rifle platoons and support platoon with machine guns and mortar. There’re three maneuver elements in a company, there’re three maneuver elements in a platoon, there’re three maneuver elements in a battalion, had three rifle companies. When <persName>Herrick</persName> took off, he deprived his company commander of protecting the right flank of one of his platoons and it deprived <persName>Herren</persName> of a maneuver element. <persName>Herren</persName> said, “Okay, but don’t get surrounded.” In retrospect, <persName>Herren</persName> should’ve stopped him from pursing those three or four enemy, but I don't know what went through <persName>John Herren</persName>’s mind. He was superb company commander. Superb. We all make mistakes. Like I did on a close air support on the assault. Possibly, he had gone too far to be recalled. But anyhow, he was quickly surrounded and gathered his men on a little knoll. Formed a circle and within minutes, he was shot and killed. Within minutes, his platoon sergeant was killed. Machine gunner was killed, and <persName>Sergeant Savage</persName> took command.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Tell me about <persName>Ernie Savage</persName>.</u>
      <u who="MOORE">Three stripe buck sergeant. Superb soldier, superb leader. He took him in.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Did you know that going into this?</u>
      <u who="MOORE"><persName>Savage</persName>? Well, I knew my NCOs, most of them very well, yeah. Expect the recently assigned ones. I knew <persName>Savage</persName> was a good man. I commanded that battalion fourteen months back in <placeName>Fort Benning</placeName>. They were my troopers, and they knew me. They knew my principles. He quickly got to the radio and was able to call in fire support and deploy his troops. He did a great job. In retrospect and I’ve talked to <persName>Ernie Savage</persName> and to others and we agreed that although it was bad for the platoon to be surrounded out there away from the rest of the company and the battalion, and it formed a problem for me because I promised all my troopers that I would bring them all home, that none of them would be left on the field. So I was in a hell of a problem when that platoon got surrounded and I was in a hell of a firefight with a couple of battalions coming down the mountain for that landing zone. It was very sporty. In retrospect however, <persName>Sergeant Savage</persName> and I have talked about this. We agreed that although it was bad for the platoon to be surrounded and cut off from the rest of the battalion, it may have been well good for the battalion because it probably confused the enemy that we were stretched out! It may have prevented that enemy from circling around to the northeast and coming at me from two directions. So in retrospect it was probably good for the battalion, bad for the platoon. Do you follow me?</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Absolutely follow you.</u>
      <u who="MOORE">Had you thought of that?</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">It crossed my mind on the plane reading it again that—and it’s depicted in the movie somewhat. They occupy the attention of quite a few of the enemy. Those were enemy that weren’t even in your limits.</u>
      <u who="MOORE">Exactly.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Again, in the interest of time, I want to ask a couple other of questions and I’d like to ask you again about an individual, <persName>Jack Geoghegan</persName>. He’s portrayed in the movie as playing a large role. We are going to be interviewing <persName>Barbara</persName> today at two o’clock and Camile as well on Saturday. I know that you value so much the lives and humanity of your troopers. Tell me about <persName>Jack Geoghegan</persName> a little bit.</u>
      <u who="MOORE">Well, as <persName>Barbara</persName> will tell you and maybe you already know, <persName>Jack Geoghegan</persName> was the late in life only child of elderly parents. He was a remarkable young man. He was the brigade commander 1st captain of the cadets at the <orgName>Pennsylvania Military College</orgName>. In his senior year and the year before that I think he was the brigade sergeant major. He was a natural leader and I’ve talked to some of the men who were in school with him at <orgName>Pennsylvania Military College</orgName>, which is no longer a military college as you know. He was commissioned 2nd lieutenant; I believe into the regular army. But he and his wife <persName>Barbara</persName> chose to spend a year in <placeName>Africa</placeName> as missionaries, which was very unusual. I believe that they were Catholic, but I'm not sure. Never really thought of what religion my troopers had. But I had quickly marked <persName>Geoghegan</persName> as a really fine young 2nd lieutenant. Eager to learn, loved his troopers. At <placeName>An Khe</placeName> before we went into the Ia Drang Valley, we were at <placeName>An Khe</placeName> from mid-September to mid-November. We went out on a couple of operations which amounted to nothing, but I specifically remember one event where Lieutenant <persName>Geoghegan</persName>’s platoon was fording a stream and he lost one of his men drowned. He was terribly upset about that. It was his fault and all that.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Did he come talk to you about that?</u>
      <u who="MOORE">Oh, I went to him. I tried to calm him down and tell him that he got to face up to the fact that this happened. I don't know whose fault it was, you might look into it, maybe do better the next time you cross the stream, but pray he’s going to heaven and don’t let your attitude contaminate the rest of your platoon. You got to have a positive attitude. Although you can be grieving, you still have to have a positive attitude. Can’t let that contaminate your leadership.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">What was his reaction?</u>
      <u who="MOORE">Quiet. Then later on when we were defending the base camp in a perimeter, I would go out and visit my troops on the defensive perimeter which were spotted at the mountains around <placeName>An Khe</placeName> base camp. I distinctly remember a couple of days before we went out to Plei Me I was sitting down with <persName>Geoghegan</persName> at his foxhole CP (Command Post) where his platoon was online outpost around <placeName>An Khe</placeName>, having a cup of coffee. Canteen cup, just talking to him. I knew that he was suffering mentally from losing his soldier, so I tried to pay a little special attention to bring him back online so to speak. The morning that he was killed, my <orgName>Charlie company</orgName> had a hundred and twelve men instead of his authorized company over two hundred. That company and it was reinforced by a platoon from the <orgName>2nd of 7th Cav</orgName> that came in the night before, that company and my <orgName>Delta Company</orgName> mortar position was heavily attacked at daybreak early the next morning. Early the next morning, I’d stay awake most of the night and maybe I’d grab a little sleep, not much. During that night, I was thinking of how are we going to get that cut off platoon back? I decided to make an attack with all three of my companies out from the landing zone. I had instructed my company commanders to meet me at the <orgName> Charlie Company</orgName> command post which had a good view of the area to receive my ops order. But then I noticed that everything was deathly quiet. The birds weren’t singing. Quiet like this room and boy my antennas were up. What the hell is going on? I immediately ordered all of my companies to send out patrols to the front, all around the perimeter and <orgName>Charlie Company</orgName> patrols ran smack into this large attacking force. They were able to give the alert back to Charlie Company<orgName></orgName>, <orgName>Delta Company</orgName> positions and to me, the rest of battalion. I didn’t know if this was going to be attacking there only or all around my perimeter. But that’s why it was so damn quiet, and my instincts told me something was going wrong here. If there’s nothing wrong, somethings going wrong.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Right and trust your instincts.</u>
      <u who="MOORE">Trust your instincts. So the patrols that were out made it back under fire to the <orgName>Charlie Company</orgName>’s position. They were heavily attacked. All five of my officers in that company were wounded. Two of the lieutenants were killed. <persName>Lieutenant Geoghegan</persName> and <persName>Lieutenant Kroger</persName>.  <orgName>Lieutenant Kroger</orgName>’s brother is going to be at this reunion, <persName>Jeffrey</persName> who’ve I’ve met. That’s when <persName>Charlie Hastings</persName>, my <orgName>Air Force</orgName> forward air controller on the ground, I didn’t know that there was such an order, but he called into the radio, “Broken Arrow”, not like in the movie. I didn’t know he had done this. When he put that “Broken Arrow” call out, that was an alert to every available fighter bomber in <placeName>South Vietnam</placeName> had to come to the assistance of an American unit about to be overrun. Within ten minutes or so, we had fighter bombers stacked up over the <placeName>Ia Drang Valley</placeName>. Thousand-foot intervals up to thirty-seven thousand feet waiting to deliver their ordinance. The smoke and the dust and the noise! Screams on the men hollering for “Mom” or “Medic.” It was just unbelievable. It was the damndest situation I’d ever been in. During that battle, which was a climactic battle really of X-Ray, we could well have been overrun.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Did you have any doubt?</u>
      <u who="MOORE">Never once did it cross my mind that we would go down. I was too damn busy thinking about negative thoughts. Obviously, what can I do to influence this situation that I haven’t done. Well, the first thing I did after—<orgName>Charlie</orgName> thank god called “Broken Arrow”, then I ordered my <orgName>A Company</orgName> on the other side of the perimeter, send a platoon to <orgName>Charlie Company</orgName>’s assistance. A couple of those guys were killed getting across the clearing, but they helped a lot. My <orgName>D Company</orgName> people at the mortar positions had machine guns and they had cut down a lot of them. Only one enemy that I know of staggered through the perimeter defensives and that was a black pajama <orgName>Viet Cong</orgName>. We were attacked by a regular North Vietnamese battalion and a battalion of black pajama <orgName>Viet Cong</orgName>. Probably eight-hundred men. This enemy in black pajamas, wounded badly staggered through the perimeter and we brought him in to the CP and aid station and he couldn’t even talk. My interpreter had gone to ground. We treated his wounds, but he died rather quickly. We buried him right there. His remains are still right there I suppose, shallow grave. But anyhow, <orgName>Charlie Company</orgName> held their ground. They lost so many men, killed and wounded. Destroyed the combat effectiveness of the company. After things quieted down around 9:30 in the morning, me and the Sergeant Major—before it had entirely quieted down, I had committed my recon platoon, my reserve which helped hold off that enemy and caused alarm and when they retreated boy, we brought down fire power on them and there were enemy bodies all over that place. Weapons littering the ground. Mortars, they came to stay. Maps, officers with packs with maps, those guys came to stay. So me and the sergeant major ended up helping to clear the situation and we walked, we walked up part of the line and I say Lieutenant <persName>Geoghegan</persName>’s body on the ground beside PFC (Private First Class) <persName>Willie Godboldts</persName>’s body. I later learn from <persName>Sergeant Jemison</persName>, the platoon sergeant who was shot three times, stomach neck and arm, that Godboldt had been wounded and he was hollering, “Somebody help me.” Then <persName>Sergeant Jemison</persName> in the foxhole with <persName>Geoghegan</persName> said, “I’ll go get him.” And <persName>Geoghegan</persName> said, “No, I will.” <persName>Geoghegan</persName> got up and got to Godboldt and about that time he was shot in the head. Being a sergeant major and walking the line, we carried <persName>Lieutenant Geoghegan</persName>’s body back to the evacuation point. We then went back to check on the troopers and I found <persName>Sergeant Gilreath</persName>, <persName>Platoon Sergeant Gilreath</persName>, who’s platoon sergeant of 2nd <persName>Lieutenant Kroger</persName>’s platoon and <orgName>Kroger</orgName> was dead. <persName>Platoon Sergeant Gilreath</persName> was dead. I knew <persName>Gilreath</persName> probably a little better than some of my NCOs. I knew most of them very well. Because <persName>Gilreath</persName> was a paratrooper like me and we had made some jumps at <placeName>Fort Benning</placeName> together. So we carried <persName>Sergeant Gilreath</persName> back. We adjusted the situation best we could, we had a reinforcing company come in and took over the land, that was <persName>Diduryk</persName>’s company with <persName>Rescorla</persName>. <persName>Diduryk</persName> was a superb commander, he was killed in action on his second tour in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. Superb commander. Russian parents were immigrants and he spoke with a heavy Slavic accent. <persName>Rescorla</persName> with the British accent, almost like a foreign accent.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">They made quite a pair.</u>
      <u who="MOORE">Oh yeah, but in the ensuing battle whenever being attack and all that air support came in, I can’t describe to you really that hell we were in. The smoke, the dust, the explosions, the white phosphorus, machine guns, field artillery. We had four batteries of field artillery firing around us. That enemy, he was walking through hell. During this maelstrom of thunderous activity, four batteries six tubes each, firing artillery. Fighter bombers laying down five-hundred pound bombs. Rockets, helicopter gunships. It was hell on earth. During that furious activity, I recall kneeling on one knee in my command post area surrounded by wounded and my radio operator was right beside of me.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE"><persName>Ouellette</persName>?</u>
      <u who="MOORE"><persName>Ouellette</persName> suddenly slumped over. I thought well, he had been shot. Still had my radio stretched to his radio on his back.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">The bullets are flying around you here?</u>
      <u who="MOORE">Oh yeah. The small arms fire, the enemy machine gun fire coming through my command post was clipping the leaves off the trees. Shot <persName>Ouellette</persName>, shot and killed <persName>Tom Burlile</persName>, a medic. The round that hit Ouellette in the head, he was right here. I’ve been under fire in <placeName>Korea</placeName> and I knew the snapping sounds of a small arms fire, but you can’t let that bother you. If you’re going to get shot, you’re going to get shot. It’s a crapshoot! Any soldier on the battlefield that worries about whether or not he’s going to get shot, he’s a nuisance! Soldiers got to do their job. But I looked up and there were two fighter bombers coming straight at the command post from the west. As I looked up, the one on the right was ahead of the guy on the left and it was about four times as high as this ceiling and he had cut loose two eight foot long cylindrical napalm containers. Frozen in my mind. And they were going to hit my command post area. My ammo dump, my engineer demo team, some of my medics, but if that second fighter had dropped his too, he was aimed straight at <persName>Hal Moore</persName>, <persName>Joe Galloway</persName>, <orgName>Sergeant Major Plumley</orgName>, <persName>Captain Dillon</persName>, my medical officer, my medical team. It would have taken out the whole command post in the middle of the battle for survival. Probably, had that happened, I don't know what would’ve happened to my companies in this furious battle without a commander and without—we had taken out <persName>Charlie Hastings</persName>, my captain calling in artillery. It might have turned out to be another Little Bighorn with the <orgName>7th Cav</orgName>. But fortunately, and I hollered at <persName>Charlie Hastings</persName>, above the dead loud, “Call that son of a bitch off!” I think it’s in the movie. I don't know what <persName>Hasting</persName> did but, he did not drop. Faithful moment. I went on to command the battle. Ten minutes later, my medic platoon sergeant looked over at <persName>Ouellette</persName> on the ground and he was kind of moving. He took his foot, “Get up <orgName>Ouellette</orgName>!” <persName>Ouellette</persName> sat up kind of shaking his head. He took off his head, there is a hole in the helmet. An AK-47 round had penetrated his helmet but did not penetrate the helmet liner, but it knocked him unconscious. And he’s got that bullet in his pocket today.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Yeah, he does.</u>
      <u who="MOORE">At that point, two napalm bombs were dropped and engulfed my ammunition supply point, the engineer team. The movie is very accurate on <persName>Joe Galloway</persName>’s actions in trying to save <persName>Jimmy Nakayama</persName>, who got on the helicopter still alive, but he was burned so badly that he died of his burns. That battle went on for probably—probably for three hours. Finally, we defeated the enemy and captured several. Treated them for their wounds, evacuated them. We evacuated our dead and wounded. Reconstituted and carried on. <persName>Diduryk</persName>, he had arrived the night before and I put him in command of the <orgName>Charlie Company</orgName> position, and he was a superb company commander. He had his men dig deep foxholes, fresh batteries in the radios, replacement batteries. Cleaned all the weapons. He had all of his men go forward of the position, reconnoiter and look at the position as if the enemy were going to look at it. That night we were attacked again very heavily. Two or three times during the night but <placeName>Diduryk</placeName> held his position and I think he only had six men lightly wounded. That’s when <persName>Rescorla</persName>, to settle down his men, he would sign to them during the night. British battles songs, choir songs. But a full script to that story, after the book came out, I had a phone call from a retired air force colonel in <placeName>California</placeName> who called me up to tell me he was the leader of that section and he was flying the second aircraft.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Wow.</u>
      <u who="MOORE">He apologized, he said, “I’m sorry, General.” He was a retired colonel and he kind of got a little cheerful on the phone. I said, “Colonel, I don’t even need to forgive you, but I will. I don’t know how you fighter bomber pilots saw any of the targets you were dropping on with the smoke and the dust. You did a great job; you saved our ass! If we hadn’t had that fighter bomber support during that fight to augment the artillery we may well have gone down. So I forgot his name but he’s retired and living in <placeName>California</placeName>. Still pored heavily on his mind.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Let me ask you about another incident. When that one North Vietnamese solider penetrated into headquarters—</u>
      <u who="MOORE">He penetrated the perimeter where he was captured immediately. He was wounded badly.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Was there a <orgName>PAVN (People’s Army of Vietnam)</orgName> soldier who came at you personally, as depicted in the movie?</u>
      <u who="MOORE">No.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">I didn’t think so.</u>
      <u who="MOORE">No, the enemy never penetrated as far as my command post. That was <placeName>Hollywood</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Okay. Just wanted to strengthen that out.</u>
      <u who="MOORE">In that movie, at the end of the movie when they showed that attack, we did—early the next morning, after we had defeated this enemy attack that night before with <persName>Diduryk</persName>’s company, like I was taught at <placeName>West Point</placeName>, when you defeat the enemy, you pursue them to the death. Like we should’ve been allowed to pursue the North Vietnamese into Cambodian but were not by <placeName>Washington</placeName>. But I ordered <persName>Diduryk</persName> to have his men fix bayonets after this successful night attack and I would join them. We would have a massive fire support, artillery and air and then we would jump off in the attack and the signal to jump off would be one final five-hundred pound bomb being dropped right in front of your command post where I’ll be with you. That happened and we killed twenty-eight more men. But it was not at all like the movie depicted, with one helicopter gunship providing fire support and all that dramatic crap that <placeName>Hollywood</placeName> introduced and that really pissed me off. I told <persName>Randy Wallace</persName>, I said, “It didn’t happen that way, <persName>Randy</persName>.”</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">What did he say?</u>
      <u who="MOORE">He said, “<persName>Hal</persName>, this is not the history channel. It’s a movie.”</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">(Laughs)</u>
      <u who="MOORE">So that really angered me. That and the command post scene where it showed this one enemy guy going across the clearing you know hidden from me, that never happened! The enemy never penetrated my position! The enemy did before we could defeat all of them—some of them were looting and killing my wounded and did. Had they not stopped to do that; they may have caused me some more problems. As for <persName>Julie</persName>, when <persName>Joe Galloway</persName> wrote his story and it came out on press all across the country, it stunned the people back in <placeName>Columbus, Georgia</placeName>. That’s where the 11th <orgName>Air Assault Division</orgName> was stationed, which became the <orgName>1st Cav</orgName> and when we were ordered to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, all of the army families including my wife and my five children, they were all ordered out of the government family housing out of <placeName>Fort Benning</placeName>. Thirty days. Get off the post. I’ve never understood why such a heartless order was given. Later on, in that <name type="event">Vietnam War</name> as it drug out, I understand that several air bases were opened which would have been closed used or to accommodate families whose fathers were fighting a war in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. But <persName>Julie</persName> and others were given thirty days to get off the post. Get out of the <orgName>Army</orgName> quarters. I was off fighting a war, I’m deployed. We deployed on the <date when="1964-08-19">16th of August</date> and she had the until middle of <date when="1964-09">September</date> to get out of there. Kids that go to school you know, her situation was repeated by the hundreds! So a lot of those families went all across the country. But numerous others resettled in <placeName>Columbus, Georgia</placeName>. <persName>Julie</persName> rented a small house in <placeName>Columbus, Georgia</placeName>. Three bedrooms, five kids, every night she had to put up a couple of cots. Her father and mother retired military were living in Auburn thirty miles away, retired colonel of artillery. Fought in <name type="event">World War I</name> and <name type="event">World War II</name>. So she had her parents nearby and she also was in the company of numerous of the wives and families of my troopers. They would meet regularly and compare letters and information from overseas. But when word came out that we were in that terrible battle and she saw me being interviewed on TV on the battlefield, after the battle by <orgName>ABC Television</orgName>, the whole place was stunned.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">By the severity of the battle?</u>
      <u who="MOORE">About the battle and the news that was coming out about it. Of course, they were all apprehensive now, “Did my husband make it?” Sergeant’s wives. Then within five to eight days, the dead started coming back and the first dead solider was returned for burial at <placeName>Fort Benning</placeName> was <persName>Sergeant Gell</persName>, <persName>Captain Nadal</persName>’s radio operator. I was with <persName>Sergeant Gell</persName>, he was caught in the machine gun fire in the attack in his first afternoon. <persName>Gell</persName> was shot.  <persName>Captain Nadal</persName>’s artillery forward observer was shot and killed. His radio operator was shot and killed by this machine gun fire and <persName>Captain Nadal</persName> was untouched. <persName>Gell</persName> was carried back into my command post and I was right there when he died right there. I think he had five daughters. Three stripe buck sergeant. By the way, some of his daughters are going to be here, <persName>Carole Crowley</persName> is one of them. So he was sent back for burial and the way the families were notified were by cab drivers. <persName>Julie</persName> found out about <persName>Sergeant Gell</persName> and the cab drivers, and the cab driver knocked at her door. That’s correct in the movie. In the midst of all this, she thought, “Well if I don’t open the door, he will go away.” But then she told me that she told herself, “No, face up to it <persName>Julie</persName>.” And she opened the door and there was this cab driver with this telegram wanting directions to another address and she collapsed in tears. She raised hell with the <orgName>Army</orgName>. The commanding general at <placeName>Fort Benning</placeName>, she raised a fuss all the way up to stop that inhuman practice and it took a while to get the <orgName>Army</orgName> and the other services to send a chaplain and another officer in uniform to the bereaved, to deliver this shattering news. And she attended the funerals. Twelve, fourteen of my men and the <orgName>2nd of the 7th Cav</orgName> at <placeName>Albany</placeName>. She visited the homes of the bereaved, the widows and most of them were black. There was one Hispanic girl from <placeName>Puerto Rico</placeName> whose husband was killed, living in a one room motel room. Eight months pregnant. <persName>Julie</persName> could speak Spanish. She visited, knocked on the door and, “Oh señora.” And she was so calmed down when <persName>Julie</persName> could speak to her in Spanish and she and the other wives arranged a layout and then shipped back to <placeName>Puerto Rico</placeName>. But <persName>Julie</persName> visited one room walk ups, trailer courts, shacks with dogs underneath the front porch and dirt all around. Not like it was displayed in movie where sergeants and lieutenants were living in <orgName>Army</orgName> quarters it took me twenty-one years to qualify to get into. She watched this scene being filmed on this beautiful, shaded street at Fort Benning and she broke into tears. She told <persName>Randy</persName> that it didn’t happen like this. “Why don’t you tell the truth! It would be much more profound! Just didn’t happen like this. I didn’t personally delivered telegrams but every day I got information from the <orgName>Army</orgName> post on who was going to get those telegrams and I followed those tabs, and I was the first person after the cab driver delivered the telegram. I had my five kids, a couple of them in school, I had babysitters and I did this all the time my husband was in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. Not just after the Ia Drang Battle, but all the battles that he was in ’66.”</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">What did <persName>Randy Wallace</persName> say to this?</u>
      <u who="MOORE">He shook his head and said, “Well, we just can’t arrange that. It would cost a lot of money. We just can’t arrange that” I was really angered, and <persName>Julie</persName> was grieved. It wasn’t the truth! It was <placeName>Hollywood</placeName>, just like that last attack where he had <persName>Crandall</persName> in the Huey and he had <persName>Geoghegan</persName> in that attack, I think.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">He was killed, but not before. Had Plumley with you?</u>
      <u who="MOORE">Had Plumley with me and I'm out there with bayonet. That was bullshit. I was in that attack and my bayonet wasn’t fixed. I was firing my rifle. There were good targets out there, but I didn’t personally stab anybody with a bayonet or do a but stroke. I think one of <persName>Peter Arnett</persName>’s pictures has me standing over a dead North Vietnamese. But you do what you have to do and it’s—soldiers have to do these horrible things and the enemy had mothers too. But you do what you have to do.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">General, when you see—when you think about <placeName>LZ X-Ray</placeName> in those three days, what do you see in your mind’s eye? What are the memories for you that are more pertinent and more acute in your memory?</u>
      <u who="MOORE">One of memories that is very vivid is the first afternoon when there were only probably a hundred fifty, almost two hundred of my soldiers in the ground and we were hit by two battalions. But the night before, this had been my practice. Me and the Sergeant Major sat up against the log at midnight and thinking through the, “What ifs?” And my biggest what-if concern was, what if it takes me four, five hours to get my battalion shuttled in.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Right, it was thirty minutes in, right?</u>
      <u who="MOORE">Yeah. I was concerned that we were going to get into a hell of a fight before I got my troops on the ground and deployed. I decided if that happened, I would call in max fire support and counterattack. Stiff arm the enemy away from that landing zone. That’s exactly what happened the next day, when we were attacked. But what really helped was the actions of one man, Spec 4 <persName>Bill Beck</persName>. He was out on the left flank; nobody was on his left. At that time, it was <orgName>A and B company</orgName> on the ground. When <persName>Beck</persName> was out there, he was an assistant gunner and his gunner <persName>Russell Adams</persName> was shot in the head, flopped on the group and <persName>Beck</persName> picked his helmet and he said it look like half his brain fell out. <persName>Beck</persName> too over that machine gun. He was alone on that gun probably for an hour and a half. He said, “Somebody brought me up some ammo and that made me very happy.” But he said that he said, “I was firing at the enemy and they were thirty forty yards out! I could feel the bullets cracking all around my head!” This is a twenty-two year old draftee out of <placeName>Pennsylvania</placeName>—<placeName>Steelton, Pennsylvania</placeName>. At a critical time and a critical place, he was the critical person on the battlefield for my battalion! And what he had done was nothing less than save it! Had he not been there with his courage and his professionalism and will to win, never quit, the enemy could well have delt me on my left, come up behind me and I would be speaking to you from the grave. I hope <persName>Bill Beck</persName> is at this reunion.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">He is here, we will talk to him.</u>
      <u who="MOORE">When we went back to the battlefield, he went unerringly to his position and found the helmet with the hole in it, he’s got that helmet now. And when we were in—<persName>Bill Beck</persName> when back to the battlefield with us in <date when="1993-10">October ’93</date>. When we had a big dinner at <placeName>Hanoi</placeName> on a houseboat on one of those lakes, <persName>Beck</persName> was sitting next to a Vietnamese Colonel and an interpreter. They got to talking about where they were in the battle and <persName>Beck</persName> drew the symbol of a machine gun and a creek bed and the North Vietnamese Colonel turned white and he said, “You killed my battalion! You killed my best friend!” That really happened. That same afternoon, instincts. When we were in this terrible action and this was a critical point. Had they overrun that creek bed or flanked us; we’d have been in a hell of a fix. Hundred fifty, hundred seventy-five were taking casualties and we were up against seven to eight hundred, nine hundred enemy! Of course, I had all kinds of fire support, which helped but <persName>Bill Beck</persName> on that ground, on that flank, he was a savior. But then I got word that my <orgName>Charlie Company</orgName> was coming in, my third rifle company. My whole rear was open, the north was open. Open to the south, we were fighting out to the southwest. And when <orgName>Charlie Company</orgName> came in, I thought, “Where am I going to send them?” And every instinct in my body told me, “To the left. Towards the mountain where <persName>Bill Beck</persName> was.” And when my head tells me one thing, and my gut tells me, I go with my gut. I ran out to the middle of the landing zone, under fire. Machine gun fire around over our head like a swarm of bees and I ran up to <persName>Captain Bob Edwards</persName> and I hollered at him above the noise. I said, “Grab your men and run them right over there and tie in with <orgName>A Company</orgName> and be prepared to be attacked.” He jumped three feet in the air and started running, hollering for his men. He got them into position twenty minutes before a whole fresh battalion attacked. I’ve interviewed those men, <persName>Bob Edwards</persName>, he said it was just like shooting ducks out there. They didn’t expect us to be there. Instincts. Of course, that morning they paid a heavy price. The next morning. But we beat off that attack, we made a couple of counter attacks that afternoon trying to get out to that cut off platoon, neither one of which succeeded. But it did succeed in stopping the enemy from attacking us. Things went quiet. I was able to visit my troopers on the perimeter, talk to them. We formed a good perimeter that night. It was a hell of a fight and reflecting back on it—</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Forty years later, right now.</u>
      <u who="MOORE">You asked me what I think about, primarily I think about that first afternoon. Where we had very few men on the ground and we were hit by two battalions of enemy wanting to kill us. I keep thinking how fortunate I was to have such great soldiers. Great non-commissioned officers. Great fire supports. The <persName>Bill Becks</persName>. The <persName>Bob Edwards</persName>. I had ordered my medical platoon in and they were under fire, treating the wounded. But you know, never once during that fight that first afternoon or the next morning or after, never once did it cross my mind that we would go down. Not once. And I have concluded that in any endeavor, in an athletic contest, in a business situation, in a military, the business battlefield, if you think you might lose, you’ve already lost. Can't let it get to your head. I don't know who else you’re going to interview, but you might interview <persName>Bill Beck</persName> on going back to the battlefield and that afternoon.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">We will. <persName>Bob Edwards</persName> this afternoon, we’ll talk to him.</u>
      <u who="MOORE">Oh, talk to <persName>Bob</persName>. He was gravely wounded but he still commanded his company!</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Yes.</u>
      <u who="MOORE">And one of his platoon sergeants, <persName>Platoon Sergeant Glenn Kennedy</persName> shot and killed a sniper that had shot <persName>Bob Edwards</persName> and shot his XO (Executive Officer), <persName>Lieutenant Harrington</persName>. <persName>Sergeant Kennedy</persName> was killed later on in the <placeName>Bong Son Plain</placeName> in <date when="1966-05">May of 1966</date>, and it just broke my heart. When I came back from <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, <persName>Julie</persName> and I visited the widows and their families. For several days, we were remaining in <placeName>Columbus, Georgia</placeName>. A number of them moved elsewhere. Like <persName>Barbara Geoghegan</persName> went to <placeName>Redding, Connecticut</placeName> with her in-laws. I often think of those days. It was the critical time of my life. That was a battle which changed the war in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. The <name type="event"> American War</name> in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. And I knew at the offset when we were hit heavily by those two enemy battalions, I knew that however the outcome of this battle, major decisions were going to be made in <placeName>Saigon</placeName> and <placeName>Hanoi</placeName> and <placeName>Washington</placeName>. And I knew that we had to win, and I knew we would. <persName>General Kinnard</persName> wrote me a letter in recent years saying that we had a lot of good battalions in the <orgName>1st Cav Division</orgName> but I'm glad that it was your battalion that ran into that Hornet’s nest. It was a pretty good compliment from the commanding general.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Yes sir, it was.</u>
      <u who="MOORE">But I’ve gone back to the battlefield twice. Once with <persName>Joe</persName> and I wanted to spend a night on the battlefield, catch the vibes. The helicopter that took us in there, a Russian helicopter flown by two Vietnamese pilots, they took the first lift out but then the second lift we were stranded by monsoon rain which pounded us for two hours and we spent the night there. I was able to walk over to my command post and I visualized in memory some of the dead that we were unable to get out that night and it’s depicted accurately in the movie. I could see them in my mind, boots sticking out in crazy angles from the ponchos, laces tied last time by their fingers. I visited part of my perimeter, <orgName>Charlie Company</orgName> perimeter. Specifically, I found myself at <persName>Geoghegan</persName>’s foxhole, what was left of it and I remember again him and others as I walked the line said, “Count on me, Colonel. We’ll get through this. Carry on, sir.” And I knew then that night in <date>October ’93</date>, I grieved because I knew who was going to get killed the next morning. And when I looked at all those dead bodies under the ponchos, I knew within thirty hours, thirty-six hours that a lot of lives would be shattered through telegram. But to end up that night, after we were pounded in this rain, we built a campfire that is shown in the documentary to dry out and on the ground was me and <persName>Larry Gwin</persName> and <persName>George Forrest</persName>, <persName>Forrest Sawyer</persName> and the <orgName>ABC</orgName> crew, <persName>Joe Galloway</persName>. I can't think of who else, just a few of us. We were drying out and the night birds, roar of a tiger, clicking of the gecko frogs, shouting of the monkeys and we were just sitting there in the dead quiet. If you’re ever in an area like down in a canyon where there’s no ambient light, there’s millions of stars up there. Millions of galaxies. Makes you think, it has to be a supreme being who created all this. It just didn’t happen. Suddenly, we were showered by hundreds of meteorites. What do you call it?</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Shooting stars?</u>
      <u who="MOORE">Shooting stars! Showers of them. I had seen and we had seen every now and then one or two shooting stars, but they were hundreds of them! It went on for thirty, thirty-five, forty minutes. It had to be a supernatural event. We were dead silent looking at this magnificent display in this thunder of silence. It sort of quieted down, stopped and we were stunned. I don’t know who said it, it may have been <persName>Joe Galloway</persName>, but it had occurred to us all that those may well have been the spirits of the men on both sides that died in that place. In <placeName>X-Ray</placeName>, in <placeName>Albany</placeName> and the other battles of the <placeName>Ia Drang</placeName>. Spirits of those enemy and friendly who died by the hundreds. Saying to us, “Farewell, you’ve told our story. We can rest in peace; we can go now.” Who knows, it may have been. But that is an event which has never occurred before or after in any of our lives. I have been in dark canyons, I’ve been back to the battlefield, I’ve been in other battles in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> where it was quiet at night on occasion, but never have I read about or seen such an event. So I don't know who you’re going to interview but I hope they follow my guidance of telling the truth as they saw the truth.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">I'm sure they will.</u>
      <u who="MOORE">Good or bad. Good or bad.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Well, this will be a good place to stop. Yes, sir.</u>
      <u who="MOORE">Made mistakes, like I told you about mistakes I made. This is history!</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Yes sir, that’s why we’re doing this.</u>
      <u who="MOORE">Yeah. I don't know who is going to watch or listen to all these oral histories, but I do hope—</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">You’re speaking to the future right now. People will be listening and watching for generations.</u>
      <u who="MOORE">That’s good, I wish I could listen to what happened at Little Bighorn, <placeName>Valley Forge, Petersburg</placeName>.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">What do you want to say to these people that will be listening a hundred years from now?</u>
      <u who="MOORE">My message to any viewers or listeners or both to these oral history tapes which the <orgName>Vietnam Center</orgName> is accruing, I hope that the major lesson that you remember in whatever walk of life you’re in, military, civilian world, political world—hate war, but love the American warrior. That’s my message down range. I got to go.</u>
      <u who="VERRONE">Thank you, sir.[End of Interview]</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
