<?xml-model href="../schemas/ddhi.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Transcript of an Interview with Willard Bennette</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>
          <orgName>Vietnam Center and Sam Johnson Vietnam Archive</orgName>
        </authority>
        <date>
          <!--  Date of publication, e.g. for citation purposes  -->
        </date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <recordingStmt>
          <recording xml:id="primary_recording" type="video" dur-iso= "00:23:39">
            <!-- https://www.digi.com/resources/documentation/digidocs/90001437-13/reference/r_iso_8601_duration_format.htm -->
            <media url="" mimeType="video/mp4"/>
          </recording>
        </recordingStmt>
        <bibl xml:id="primary_transcription">
          <respStmt>
            <persName>Mark Varela</persName>
            <orgName>Vietnam Center and Sam Johnson Vietnam Archive</orgName>
            <resp ref="http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/trc.html">Transcriber</resp>
          </respStmt>
          <ref target="path_to_file">Primary transcription</ref>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The Oral History Project of Vietnam Center and Sam Johnson Vietnam Archive</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application ident="DDHIEncoder" version="1.0">
          <desc>Conversion from Word docx to TEI xml.</desc>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en-us">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <particDesc>
        <person xml:id="BENNETTE"/>
        <person xml:id="NAPOLI"/>
      </particDesc>
      <settingDesc>
        <setting>
          <date when-iso="2005-11-12"/>
          <locale/>
        </setting>
      </settingDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <u who="NAPOLI">I am Professor <persName>Phil Napoli</persName>, <date when = "2005-11-12">today</date> is <date when = "2005-11-12">the 12th of November 2005</date>. I am with Mr.—listen to me, if this were television I’d be in trouble—with Mr. <persName>Will Bennette</persName> and we’ll talk a little bit about your memories of <name type="event">the Vietnam War era</name>. The first thing I’d like you to do is just introduce yourself to us. Give us your age, where you live and that kind of stuff.</u>
      <u who="BENNETTE">Well my full name is <persName>Willard M. Bennette</persName>. I go by <persName>Will</persName> ever since high school days. My father was <persName>Willard</persName>, and I was a Junior. I'm hree months away from being age seventy-five. I entered the service out of a <orgName>ROTC (Reserve Officer Training Corps)</orgName> program at <placeName>Colorado State University</placeName> in <placeName>Fort Collins, Colorado</placeName>, which is my hometown. Went in as a reserve officer. Signed up for flight school because a fraternity brother of mine was at <placeName>Fort Sill</placeName> and at flight school. He said, “This is a pretty good deal, you know? You get a hundred bucks.” I signed up for it. Eventually, went regular <orgName>Army</orgName> and decided to make it a career, and twenty-eight years later I got out as a full colonel and that was <date when = "1980">1980</date> when I got out of the service. I started back in <date when = "1941-01">January of ’54</date> . So I went to flight school. I was an artilleryman in the <orgName>Army</orgName> but once you entered the aviation program, you pretty well stayed in aviation assignments although they were supposed to rotate you back into your basic branch once every six years or something. I got rotated once and I commended a 105 artillery battery at <placeName>Fort Sill, Oklahoma</placeName>, and that was the last time I ever saw a piece of artillery. So I was in aviation specialty really. That was <date>the days</date> before the <orgName>Army</orgName> created an aviation branch. We just had aviators, but we also had your basic branch. So to pick up—where I got introduced to <orgName>the 1st Cav</orgName> in <placeName>Fort Benning,Georgia</placeName>, was—I came out of <placeName>Alaska</placeName>. I was up in <placeName>Alaska</placeName> for three years, basically flying the de Havilland fixed wing aircraft but I also transitioned into the Huey. In <date when = "1994-07">July of ’64</date>  I got a set of orders saying go to the <orgName> 11th Air Assault division </orgName> at <placeName> Fort Benning, Georgia</placeName>, and then the fun began. We joined the division; it was very hectic. I was operations officer for <orgName>A Company 229th</orgName>. We went through the Carolina maneuvers. I don’t know if you know much about that, but it was about a three-month exercise, we went all through the <placeName>Carolinas</placeName>. Finishing up with a big air assault at <placeName>Fort Bragg</placeName> where we conquered the whole city and, you know, we went back victorious. From then on, we just worked local training at <placeName>Fort Benning</placeName>. I was fortunate enough to be given command of <orgName>Charlie Company of the 229th </orgName>  in <date when = "1995-03" >March of ’65 </date> . And in <date when = "1995-07">July of ’65 </date> we deployed for <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. My helicopters of my company and almost all the officers and enlisted people went down to <placeName>Mobile, Alabama</placeName>, I believe where they boarded an aircraft carrier. I never went there, never saw it. I was with <persName>General Wright</persName>, one of the assistant division commanders and my operations officer <persName>Ken Jayne</persName>, who you’ll probably interview later. We went on the C130 with the advanced party. I was on the very first party of the advanced party. The idea for sending company commanders on the advanced party was that they assigned us up to join in-country helicopter companies that had been there, and I went to <placeName>Pleiku</placeName> and I was attached—whatever word, to <orgName>the 119th Assault Helicopter Company</orgName>. I stayed there for about two weeks, flew a few missions with them. Didn’t learn a thing because I think we knew it better than they did, even though they were in-country. Then we got the word to come back to <placeName> An Khe</placeName> and all of us were given an entrenching tool and we were told to go out and clear the weeds and prepare our pads for our helicopters, which were due in about two weeks. So being an aviator with an entrenching tool wasn’t all that exciting but we cleared the entire Golf Course, as they called the helicopter area. I remember  <persName>General Wright</persName> putting out the word that he wanted absolutely no bulldozers, no blades, no heavy equipment because he was afraid that we would destroy the grass and we’d have a dustbowl. Well, we destroyed the grass anyway and we had a dustbowl. When you put about, what? Four-hundred helicopters in this area. I was also given my plot of land where we staked out where we would establish our basecamp for <orgName>Charlie Company</orgName>. And worked until the helicopter showed up. They finally showed up. From that point on, the division assigned missions and we flew some assault missions into Bong Son area. Never had any fatalities, never had anyone wounded to speak of—maybe a graze of a bullet or something like that. Then, I guess all heck broke out over there in the <placeName>Plei Me</placeName> area, which was outside of the <placeName> Ia Drang Valley</placeName> area. I don’t know the history any better than probably you do, but when the scouts found it, did this and did that. Things started getting heated up, I think probably like on the 14th of November. <orgName>Charlie Company</orgName> and my company was habitually attached to the 2nd of the 7th, commanded by <orgName>Colonel McDade</orgName>,  <persName>Lieutenant Colonel McDade</persName>. For example, A Company commanded by <persName>Bruce Crandall</persName> was habitually associated and attached. That word “attached” doesn’t mean that—we were just habitually associated and supporting these infantry battalions and <persName>Bruce</persName> was doing his attachment with <persName>General Moore</persName>, <persName>Colonel Moore</persName> in the 1st of the 7th. The assault into <placeName>X-Ray</placeName> was a normal mission that I can remember. As a matter of fact, <orgName>Charlie Company</orgName> was not involved other than I think I had to provide a flight of four, which was a very common thing we did. Some company—like I would have a mission and other companies of the battalion would come over and be attached to me for that certain mission. I think I had a flight of four that went into <placeName>X-Ray</placeName>. So I was not on the ground and I was not involved in those flights. Of course, all hell broke out in <placeName>X-Ray</placeName>. People went in and out. I did not go into <placeName>X-Ray</placeName> until—I guess it was either the third morning or the second morning. I went in there at early dawn with the visibility pretty bad with fog and all. We brought in a lot of ammunition and we took out a lot of dead and wounded. So many that we had to pile dead and wounded in the same hole of our helicopter. It was not the most pleasant thing to do. My involvement in <placeName>X-Ray</placeName> was only that maybe one or two approaches in there doing what I just said. Then in the meantime, 2nd of the 7th, who I was attached to as far as supporting, marched overland from <placeName>X-Ray</placeName> to what was become <placeName>Albany</placeName>. Of course, they got ambushed severely. They lost something like two-hundred and sixty people. One of my officers, <persName>Ken Weitzel</persName>, who I'm sure you’ve interviewed, or I hope you do, was on the ground. Not to be derogatory toward <persName>Lieutenant Colonel McDade</persName>, but <persName>McDade</persName> seemed to always be behind the power curve as far as what was going on and what was needed. I just couldn’t stay ahead of his lack of planning, so I picked out <persName>Ken Weitzel</persName> who was a 1st lieutenant infantry officer. Good, smart mind and I said, “You’re going to go down there and become my liaison officer.” Which meant I was short a helicopter pilot, but it was more important to have him on the ground. He had the radio, and we communicated all the time on my company’s frequencies. He would give me warning orders as to what they were brewing up and gave me a chance to plan to respond to what <persName> Colonel McDade</persName> wanted to do. But I was getting advanced notice, it didn’t have to go through the channels, I knew about it. They marched overland. I was talking to <persName>Ken Weitzel</persName> <date when = "2005-11-11">last night</date>. First time I’d seen him was <date when = "2005-11-10">two nights ago</date> for the first time in forty years. He said he was going to ask this question and I’ll ask this question and then maybe you guys can figure it out. Why did they march the 2nd of the 7th overland from <placeName>X-Ray</placeName> to <placeName>Albany</placeName> instead of letting us fly them from <placeName>X-Ray</placeName> to <placeName>Albany</placeName>? And no one has been able to ever tell <persName>Ken Weitzel</persName> that. Why didn’t they fly them? Why did they march? But they did march, and I can remember <persName>Ken Weitzel</persName> telling me that the troops were very wounded, tired, exhausted, lack of security, being on the guard was just lax. It wasn’t happening. Of course, they got whammed. We flew in reinforcements about dusk. I can’t remember what unit it was, but we flew in reinforcements. Then through the night, there was a couple of missions that went in and brought in some ammunition. My hairy experience with them—I mean it was hairy going into there, but I was always “Yellow 1”, which was the first aircraft in that I insisted on. I was the company commander and I insisted on being the first aircraft to led. I was leading the flight to go in for that reinforcements, I think around 1700 hours. The fire was so intense, that if I had to break off—I thought it was wise to break off and some other aircraft— the fire was suppressed and they got in and I came in tail-end <orgName>Charlie</orgName>, you know, big deal. So I wasn’t the first one in <placeName> LZ (Landing Zone) Albany</placeName>. I was supposed to be, but I broke off and went around because of the enemy fire. I am leading up to the fact that I was involved in that. It’s interesting as exciting that was it was sort of routine. Fire and getting pinged at, stuff like that. Then we got a call, I was at <placeName>Pleiku</placeName> in our bivouac area. My operations sergeant woke me up about 12:30 to one o’clock and he said, “They’re crying for more help down there.” Not to bad mouth medevac, but I do believe— all these years later, I do believe that he said that medevac had turned the mission down because the intensity of the situation. That sound like a slam to medevac, but I know it happened on several occasions. You know, they were unfamiliar with the place. I took the mission, I asked for a second helicopter and that was <persName>Ken Jayne</persName>, who flew number two, and we took off somewhere like one o’clock, 1:15. Of course, we’d been in that LZ four and five times that prior twelve hours. We entered to the area and I always describe the landing the air space was total chaotic mess. There were tracers going off everywhere. People dropping flares above. I don’t know who was doing that, <orgName>Air Force</orgName>, somebody was dropping flares. There were A-1s buzzing through the area, dropping napalm. This was at one o’clock, pitch black. It wasn’t black, it was just—we couldn’t find the landing zone. I couldn’t find landing zone LZ. Talking on the radio with <persName>Ken Weitzel</persName>. Talking on the radio with <persName>Frank Henry</persName> who was executive officer down there. “Where are you? Where are you?” Our fuel warning lights started flickering. Once they come on, you got about twenty minutes of fuel left in the Huey. Just about that first flicker we caught—I think <persName>Ken James</persName> said, “I’ve got a beam of light.” Because we’ve told him to get in the LZ or give us a beam. They could see us; we couldn’t find them. Little pocket flashlight they beamed that light at us, we talked on the radio, beeped three times. We didn’t want to go down on Charlie’s flashlight. We made sure—we were convinced it was our own people’s flashlight. I asked <persName>Ken Weitzel</persName> the other day, “Was it you in that LZ with that light?” He said, “Well, we all shared that.” <persName>Jim Spires</persName>, who was the 3 of the battalion was out there in the landing zone. <persName>Sergeant Major</persName>—we evacuated that night. I can’t think of his name right now. They all claimed that they were out there flashing lights at us. And I thought that was pretty neat because we finally found it and we just flew that light beam just like we would fly an ILS (Instrument Landing System) on an instrument approach. Came in there with the tracers were just going “zing, zang” everywhere. Why we didn’t get hit, lord only knows. We touched down. Our crew chief and our gunners got out of the helicopters to help. Of course, push the ammunition out and bring the wounded in. We started getting some mortar fire at some part of the landing zone, to the point to where I said, “Let’s pick up and move.” We move maybe about thirty yards, forty yards in some direction, which made our gunners, and our crew chiefs hump the wounded a little further. I know that they returned fire with their weapons, they had their M-16s, so they were either dragging the wounded and firing—I don't know what they were doing because I was standing at the controls. They were fighting for their lives and helping bring in the wounded. We finally got everybody aboard that we thought we needed to get on board. We were quite overloaded, but we took off. Whether we had dead aboard, I don't know, they might’ve been. I hope they weren’t any dead. I think they used all the room just for wounded. We got out of there. That fuel warning light was blaring in our face and we B-lined it back for <placeName>Pleiku</placeName>. The medical station as I remember was sort of next to the main airstrip at <placeName>Pleiku</placeName>. We touchdown there and I shutdown. I told <persName>Ken Jayne</persName>, I said, “Let’s shut these suckers down. We’re not going to hover from there to our company area because we’re going to run out of fuel.” So we decided to shut them down and bring the fuel trucks to us. The next day we would resume missions. I really can’t pinpoint missions specifically other than that one. I was awarded the Silver Star, as well as <persName>Ken Jayne</persName> for that two o’clock in the night mission. Did I earn it? Yes, I did. Should others have been given awards? Probably so. The heat of battle, you know, everything was hard to document as to who was doing what. I know that was being written up by <persName>Colonel Winkel</persName>, who’s done a lot of research on helicopter operations in the Ia Drang. The infantry would always say, “Well, that helicopter crew, they were just so heroic. They came in there.” “Well, who was it?” “Well, that helicopter.” Well, you know, you got four souls on that helicopter, but nobody knows who they were. And nobody looked at the tail numbers, so it was “the helicopter crew.” To give awards to “the helicopter crew”, you had to find out who was it. And <persName>Winkel’s</persName> done a lot of research trying to pinpoint things. Whether he’s accurate on his information—I mean, it’s so long ago I can’t remember who was my co-pilot. Things like that have left me. But I do remember that night. Like I said, I think the <placeName>Ia Drang Valley</placeName>—that would’ve been the night of the Silver Star Award and all of that would’ve been about two o’clock in the morning on the 18th of November. I would assume that everything calmed down. I think we were back and out of there by the 19th or 20th of November.  I don’t know what happened in <placeName>Ia Drang after</placeName> that. The <orgName>229th</orgName> I think were told to go back to <placeName>An Khe</placeName> and the <orgName>227th</orgName>, which is our sister battalion, I think they may have come in. I don’t really know what took place in the <placeName>Ia Drang</placeName> after the 18th. You’re going to have to ask me a question, I’ll go on. I commanded the battalion, I commanded the battery—the company, I’m sorry. I’m an artilleryman, so they’re called batteries. I commanded the helicopter company <orgName>Charlie 229th</orgName> for nineteen months, which I was very proud of. Total twelve months over there and the other eight months or whatever I said in <placeName>Fort Benning</placeName> before we left. I don’t think after that people got command of anything in over six months. They tried to rotate and let everybody enjoy a command, but it was six months. I went back later, two years later, and commanded <orgName>the 227th</orgName> Assault Helicopter Battalion. Which was fun but nothing compared to being a company commander. Because I got to fly all the time.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">Did you learn anything about flying those missions in those months that you hadn’t learn at Benning?</u>
      <u who="BENNETTE"> Well, I learn that we couldn’t fly low level without either assistance from someone higher up—either the battalion commander to give us some steers. Steer right, steer left. Start the flair. Because it all was a jungle. The maps we were going by were certainly not the greatest or the most accurate maps. So we flew low level. We did a lot of low level in <placeName>Fort Benning</placeName> exercises, and we tried it over there and we basically—I can remember we just got lost. I did do a lot of reconnaissance before a mission and maybe that was not smart. Maybe that was—I knew where we were going if I got advanced notice. Now, whether the enemy knew that and watched me, I don’t know. Because, for example, we would go out and I knew which area that they were wanting to land. I was just going to check out terrain features and all that. I also had the aerial artillery rockets people with me. They would accompany on this reconnaissance because every time we went in on mission, we would have them firing our rockets for us to prep the area. But let’s say we had our landing zone, but we also did the low-level reconnaissance to four areas. So hopefully Charlie, the enemy, would know which one of those four was going to be for real. Whether we faked them out or not, I don’t know. You know, they probably would monitor—we didn’t have secure radio on those days  either. My second tour we had secure radios where hopefully they weren’t breaking in and listening, but I don’t know. I always said this about <placeName>Fort Benning</placeName> and <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. I thought the exercises in <placeName>Fort Benning</placeName> and the <placeName>Carolinas</placeName> was probably just as tough or tougher, except we didn’t get fired on. But I thought the training—I would like to mention the training. I thought those that developed the training of <orgName>General Seneff</orgName>, <persName> Colonel Seneff</persName> then, commanded the group. A fellow by the name of <persName>Leo Sucheck</persName> who later made General, they developed—and battalion commander of the <orgName>229th</orgName> was <persName>Earl Buchane</persName>. They did one great job in developing a training program. I thought when we went over there, there couldn’t have been a better trained unit. I compared that when I went over there early to learn some lessons from the 119th. I didn’t learn anything!</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">Yeah.</u>
      <u who="BENNETTE">I didn’t like the way they conducted their missions. I'm not going to criticize the company commander and tell him what’s he’s doing wrong, it wasn’t my business. I didn’t learn anything from them because I thought we came over much better trained from my experiences at <placeName>Fort Benning</placeName>. So I don’t know what else to tell you.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI"> I'm afraid that given our time, I have stop. There’s much more I would personally would like to ask.</u>
      <u who="BENNETTE"> All right.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">So I apologize. But these guys are running me, effectively.</u>
      <u who="BENNETTE">Okay.</u>
      <u who="NAPOLI">But I wanted to say—(Interview audio ends)</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
